Stanford University.
Okay,
let's begin.
Let's begin tonight.
I want to just go through
a very quick review of some equations,
then I want to move on.
Tonight I hope to get to
some physics and to discuss gravity,
if nothing else,
in a uniform gravitational field.
We've already talked,
of course,
about a uniform gravitational field.
That's just the,
well,
you all know what that is,
just near the surface of the Earth.
But the question is,
how would you describe that
uniform gravitational field in general relativity?
Okay,
we want to get there.
We want to understand what kind of metric it describes,
or describes it.
But let's just write down some,
just to remember some equations,
just to have some,
some review.
First of all,
we talked about covariantly differentiating.
The idea,
covariant derivatives act on tensors,
in particular on vectors.
And we worked out the covariant
derivative as it applies to particular tensors.
In particular,
first of all,
the covariant derivative,
let's call it dm.
The covariant derivative of the
metric itself is always zero.
Oh,
let me say one more thing about the covariant derivative.
The point of the covariant derivative
is to write a tensor such that,
can I get this straight,
such that in Gaussian normal
coordinates it is just the derivative.
In Gaussian normal coordinates,
the coordinates which are closest to Cartesian
coordinates at a particular point in the space,
the covariant derivative is just the derivative.
But in other coordinates,
it takes on a more complicated form,
if we want it to be a tensor.
Alright,
so the,
so the covariant derivative...
Question about Gaussian normal coordinates.
So,
I was searching on the web and found
things that said they're the same as synchronous coordinates,
and showed that,
basically the spatial coordinates aren't coupled
with time in the metric tensor.
And that's what they said about it.
Is that...
You know,
I may be using Gaussian normal
coordinates in too restricted a sense.
What I mean by Gaussian normal coordinates,
I may be using the term too restricted a way.
The only trouble is it's the only term I know.
Let's call them the flattest possible,
the most Cartesian coordinates at a point.
Can you make a,
can somebody make a,
you know,
a series of letters out of that?
The most Cartesian coordinates at a point.
What does the most Cartesian mean?
Alright,
it means,
it means exactly what we said before,
that the metric at that point,
at that point is a Kronecker delta,
and its first derivatives are zero.
Okay?
That's what I mean by the
most Cartesian coordinates at a point.
I may be misusing the term Gaussian normal coordinates.
My education was not,
was left something to be desired,
and I sometimes use terms inappropriately.
Uh,
okay,
we'll just call them the best coordinates.
They are the best coordinates at a point.
The best coordinates at a point
have derivatives equal to zero in,
uh,
sorry,
have the metric having derivatives equal to zero,
and the problem of finding a tensor
which in the best coordinates at a point,
reduced to nothing but the ordinary derivative,
is the covariant derivative.
Alright,
so here's the covariant derivative.
It acts on any component of the metric,
and always gives zero.
Why?
Because in the best coordinates,
the derivative of the metric is zero.
Okay.
Now,
next,
we considered the covariant derivative of a vector.
Question.
dRVs,
and I chose to study a vector with covariant components.
It's a covariant derivative of the covariant vector.
Alright,
and here's what we found it is.
It starts out as just the derivative of Vs,
and then has a term which would be zero
in the best coordinates at a point.
Alright,
what is it?
It's plus gamma R S,
let's call it P,
Vp.
Remember the summation convention was summing over P here.
Oh,
yes,
is it plus or minus?
I believe it's minus.
It's minus.
And the minus is a convention.
And we worked out what these symbols are.
The gamma P R S,
they are not tensors.
They're made up out of derivatives of the metric.
That means in the best coordinates,
they're zero.
They are zero at a point in the best coordinates,
because the derivatives of the metric are equal to zero.
But if they were a tensor,
then they would have to be zero in every coordinate,
and they're not.
Alright,
so these gammas,
let's write them down.
Gamma P R S is equal to G P N.
Remember,
G P N is the inverse metric,
the metric except with upper components,
times partial of G N R,
with respect to X S,
plus partial of G N S,
with respect to X R,
minus partial of G,
oh,
there's a factor of two,
excuse me,
a factor of two,
minus partial of G R S,
with respect to X P.
Shouldn't take you too,
this should be memorized.
It doesn't take too long to memorize it.
If G P N,
okay,
that's just to raise some index here,
but now you look at it,
it has G N R,
it has G N S,
and it has G R S.
Wait,
did I do this right?
No,
um,
G R S with respect to P,
no,
with respect to N.
N,
N.
There it is.
Now I have it right.
It has all three combinations of G blah blah
with respect to X,
blah blah,
and they come in three combinations,
two of them positive,
one of them negative,
and a half here.
That's the Christoffel symbol,
with one upper index and one lower index.
And that just goes right into here.
That tends to make
covariant derivatives rather complicated objects.
You know,
if I wrote down a metric for you,
that's a nuisance to write all these things down,
but this is what it means.
All right,
next,
let's talk about covariant derivatives
of vectors with contravariant components.
Let's,
uh,
let's call it DMVN.
DMVN.
All right?
As always,
it starts out with a simple derivative.
But I'm not going to work it out for you.
I'm not going to work it out.
You work it out the
same way you worked it out
for covariant derivatives,
of covariant tensors.
But there's a simple trick.
You can do it yourself.
Do it at home.
I'll tell you what the trick is.
You begin by writing VN,
with upper index,
as equal to GN,
now give me another letter,
P,
VP.
Okay?
And now you say,
I want to construct a covariant derivative
of VN.
And since the covariant derivative
is a derivative,
it's a derivative in the best frame.
It is a derivative.
It will satisfy,
here.
This is a product.
This is a product of two things.
And it will satisfy
covariant derivative of GNP
times VP
plus GNP
times covariant derivative
of VP.
Let's put a,
um,
an index down here,
M,
and a bracket around here.
What this says is simply that
the derivative of a product
is the sum of two terms,
the derivative of the first term,
that's this one,
times VP,
plus the derivative of the second one,
times G.
This holds for covariant derivatives.
It holds for just about every kind of derivative
you can ever think of.
And now,
what do we know about the derivative
of the metric?
Now,
this is the metric,
the covariant derivative of the metric.
Remember that the metric
in the best coordinates
has no derivatives.
Right?
So,
in the best coordinates,
the metric itself with lower indices
is constant at least to first order,
at least to,
uh,
to first derivatives.
That means the inverse,
the inverse matrix,
is also constant to first derivatives.
And so one can also argue
that the covariant derivative
of the metric tensor with two
contravariant indices
is also zero.
We know how to differentiate a thing
with lower indices.
That's this formula
over here.
If you just plug that in here,
and manipulate it a little bit,
you'll find out how to differentiate,
how to covariantly differentiate
a tensor with upper indices.
I'll write the formula for you.
Here it is.
It's the same kind of thing
as up here.
Derivative with respect to m
of vn,
derivative with respect to xm
they always start out that way,
and then,
now,
plus,
this you'll work out by doing
this little exercise here.
It's a simple little exercise,
takes a few minutes.
And now it's plus
gamma m
n,
let's call it,
p,
I guess,
what did I call it?
I'd like to keep my notation consistent.
nmr,
no,
yeah,
r,
vr.
Okay,
let's look at it for a minute.
As before,
it begins with just a simple derivative.
Then it has a term
which would be zero in the best coordinates,
because in the best coordinates,
the gammas are all zero.
This would be zero,
but it's not zero
in general coordinates.
This has one lower index,
one lower index here.
It has one upper index,
has the same upper index here.
Here it has a lower index,
contracted with an upper index.
So the formula makes sense.
It satisfies the rules.
Upper indices contracted with lower indices,
summed over,
and indices generally in place.
It's plus.
That's the little peculiarity
that you get by doing this exercise.
It's plus.
That's all you really have to remember,
that when you go from covariant to contravariant,
the way the indices fit together,
you can't mistake it.
A lower index and an upper index.
That same lower index has to appear on this side.
There's nothing else it can be
but the lower index of the Christoffel symbol.
The upper index has to appear here,
and then there has to be a contraction.
Okay,
that's the covariant derivative
of the contravariant components of a tensor.
Good.
Now we come to an idea called parallel transport.
We've already more or less spoken about it,
but let's spell it out in detail.
Supposing you have a curved space.
Oh,
I should write down one more thing,
just to write it down for now.
The curvature tensor.
I think I won't.
We won't need it too much tonight.
All right.
And now we have some vector field.
Let it be a vector field living on the space.
And I'm interested in knowing whether I,
when I move along here,
whether the field stays parallel to itself,
whether the vector field stays parallel to itself.
All right,
so I have some vector at each point here.
At each point,
I have a vector.
At each point along the curve,
and I want to know whether
the field stays parallel to itself.
All right.
Parallel to itself means that the covariant derivative
is zero along that direction.
That's what it means.
Covariant derivative is the difference between the vectors
except written in the best coordinates.
If the derivative of a vector
from one point to another is zero,
that vector is maintaining a relationship
of being parallel to itself
and the vector field is not.
So that's actually a definition.
But let's see.
We have written down,
I'm going to write down again the covariant derivative
because we're going to use it.
DMVN.
Let's write that down for the moment.
Is equal to partial of VN with respect to XM.
I'm going to write it down again.
Plus gamma N MR VR.
Okay.
That's the covariant derivative.
Now,
I want to consider the derivative
along the trajectory here,
or along this curve.
How the vector changes from point to point.
That simply corresponds to taking the covariant derivative,
VN,
and multiplying it between these two points by DX.
Let's see.
DXM.
If I differentiate with respect to XM
and then multiply by DXM,
that can just be called
the small change in the
vector going from point to point
from DX,
except keeping track of the fact
that the coordinates themselves may bend
as you go from point to point.
And that's why you have to use the covariant derivative.
This is the change in the vector,
V,
in going from one point to its neighbor.
What is it equal to?
Let's just call it,
let's just give it a name.
DVN.
It's a small change in the vector
going from one point to a neighboring point.
More precisely,
it's the small change in
the vector in the best coordinates.
Okay.
That's it.
Now,
what is that equal to?
It's equal to
DVN by DXM,
times DXM.
I'm simply multiplying this equation
by DXM,
and then plus
gamma MRN
VR DXM.
I did nothing here except multiply this by DXM
and then sum over M.
So let's erase the middle expression here.
This is the covariant change
in a vector going from one point to another.
Now,
this thing here,
that's simple.
That's just the derivative of something with respect to X
times DX.
That can just be called
the differential change
in V.
That's the differential change in V.
So look at this equation.
The covariant differential change in V
is the ordinary change in V
plus this Christoffel symbol,
multiplied by DX.
This is the formula which tells you
how a vector changes from point to point.
Now,
supposing I'm interested
in defining
a vector which is parallel to itself
as I move along this curve.
Parallel to itself means it doesn't change
as you move along here.
At each point,
you erect some best coordinates,
in those coordinates,
you test whether the vector is changing.
If not,
you say,
all right,
good,
the vector is constant along a little segment there.
Go to the next segment.
Erect best coordinates at that point.
Do the same thing.
If at every point,
the change in the vector is zero,
if this equals zero,
the vector is said to be
parallel to itself along that curve.
As you move along that specific curve,
the vector maintains a relationship
of being parallel to itself.
The best coordinates are always parallel to themselves?
Are always what?
Parallel to themselves?
No,
not necessarily.
Once you find the best set of coordinates,
you can rotate it.
No,
they don't have to be parallel to the curve,
but they have to be fixed and well-defined.
But they could be parallel to the curve.
The best coordinates are not unique.
Just like an ordinary flat space,
the Cartesian coordinates are not unique
because you can always rotate them.
You can also rotate the best coordinates
at a point.
And that's not important.
That won't change
whether your vector stays parallel to itself.
All right.
Moving a vector from one point to another
such that this covariant differential change
is zero is called parallel transport of the vector.
If you move a vector along a curve
in such a way that the differential change
in its contravariant component
plus the Christoffel symbol multiplying v times dx
along that trajectory,
that being zero,
is called
parallelly transporting a vector along a certain curve.
Now,
the funny thing about curved spaces
is if you take two points
and you start a vector over here
and parallelly transport it along this curve here,
you'll get some other vector here.
But if you choose some other curve
and parallelly transport it,
in general,
it will come out different.
So the notion of parallel transport
is relative to a particular curve.
This is what I showed you about cones.
When we talked about having a cone
with a round top or something like that,
if we parallelly transport a vector from here to here
versus transporting it around the back of the cone,
you will get a different final result.
So parallelly transport...
I've got one question.
Yeah.
That's...
And of course,
when that happens,
it's because there's curvature in between.
So I know I'm misunderstanding,
but tell me where I'm wrong.
I figured this V,
this vector,
is a vector field.
Okay.
What I said was for a vector field,
but now just imagine that...
You could imagine that there was a vector field,
or you could just imagine that the vector field
was only defined along the curve.
In fact,
we don't even have to...
We can even ask,
how do we construct a vector
along this curve
such that it's everywhere parallel to itself
along the curve?
What we do is we solve this equation.
We solve the equation that when we move the vector,
we move it in such
a way that this cancels this.
So my question is,
if it were a vector field,
then it would be independent of the path.
Yeah.
Sure.
The vector field would be independent of the path,
but there might be one path
along which this vanishes everywhere,
and another path along which it doesn't.
But still,
when you get to the end...
When you get to the end,
you have a unique answer,
but one transport of the vector...
You would say that the vector was
covariantly constant along one curve
and not covariantly constant along another curve.
Now,
you're right.
We're defining something slightly different.
Instead of saying there's a vector field,
let's just suppose we start with a vector over here.
And now I'm going to fill this vector field,
this curve up with vectors.
Let's imagine it's been filled up.
So roughly speaking,
there's a vector field now along this curve.
Let's not worry about what it's doing over here.
And then just require of
this vector field along the curve
that it's covariantly constant.
And this is the equation that says that.
Question.
Yeah.
This isn't the main focus,
but are you also preserving the length of that vector?
Yeah.
That's right.
Covariant,
yes.
Then you can prove that this equation
conserves the length of the vector.
I didn't assume it,
but one could prove it from here.
Yeah.
That's right.
The reason why you chose...
You chose the sharp edges
because maintain the differentiability,
is it?
Say it again.
The cone.
You didn't make it very sharp.
It's because maintain differentiability?
Yeah.
But it wouldn't have mattered
even if I made a sharp cone.
If I want to specify
what the curvature is in here,
then I better make it nice and rounded
so that it has a finite curvature.
The curvature at the tip of
a sharp cone would be infinite,
so I wanted to avoid that.
Question.
Yeah.
Is it...
The tangent vector of that curve...
Yes.
Is it always parallel?
No.
But when it is,
the curve is a geodesic.
That's exactly what we're coming to now.
All right.
So we've defined...
Yeah,
let's see what's going on here.
Let's take the cone,
slice it,
and open it up on the blackboard.
Okay,
so it's...
Slice it and open it up
so it looks something like this.
It's empty out here.
All right.
Now,
let's take a curve
that just goes around like that.
That corresponds to exactly the kind of curve
that I drew over here,
right?
Goes around and comes back
to the same point over here.
This point and this point are the same point.
Okay,
now let's take a tangent vector,
as you said.
It's pretty clear that this tangent vector is changing.
What would a vector which didn't change look like?
A vector which didn't change would look like this,
like this,
and would come back to here.
Would come back to this direction over here.
So the answer is no.
In general,
the tangent vector to a curve
is not covariantly constant.
But in fact,
this is not a geodesic.
This is not a geodesic of a cone.
In fact,
you can see.
Just flatten everything out.
This is a circle.
It's not a geodesic.
It's not the shortest distance between these two points.
Shortest distance between those two points is that.
Drawing back on the cone,
it would look something like this.
The shortest distance between those two points.
Okay,
so now we want to
get right to what you said.
Question of the tangent vector
and the non-tangent vector.
The notion of a geodesic.
And just to say it since you already said it,
or since I already said it.
The notion of a geodesic.
A geodesic is a curve.
One can define it in two ways.
You can define it as being the shortest distance,
the shortest curve between two points.
Better yet,
a curve whose distance is stationary.
It could be the longest distance between two points.
If the distance is stationary,
then we will say that the curve is a geodesic.
But a better,
not necessarily a better definition,
in fact I think it is a better definition though.
A better definition is to look locally along the curve.
And require that the curve be as straight as possible.
Okay,
now what does that mean?
I'll give you some intuitions
and I'll give you a precise statement.
If at each point along the curve,
the derivative of the tangent vector is zero,
then that curve is as straight as possible.
But let's think what this means.
I'll give you an intuition.
I'll try to give you an intuition for it.
Suppose you have a curved terrain.
Now,
this is a two-dimensional example,
but there's nothing particularly two-dimensional
about the notion of a geodesic.
Now,
let's suppose you have a car
that you drive on this terrain.
Okay.
Also assume that the size of the car,
in particular the distance between its wheels,
is small by comparison with any curvature.
In other words,
the car is very small
compared to the hills and the valleys and so forth.
And now,
take your steering wheel
and point it absolutely dead ahead,
straight.
Okay.
And start driving.
Don't turn the wheel.
Make sure in advance that it was pointing,
you know,
go to your mechanic,
don't just set it straight ahead,
and don't deviate.
Just go straight ahead.
The curve that you will execute on this space
will be a geodesic.
Another way to say it,
the same thing is that the tangent vector
along the curve is constant.
The tangent vector along the curve is constant,
so let's define the tangent vector.
Here we have...
Here we have a curve.
And now go to a point.
We're going to construct a tangent vector
right at this point,
and take a neighboring point.
It's separated by a little interval called dxm.
Okay.
A small interval.
And now draw a vector through those two points.
Make that vector be a unit vector.
And then take the limit
in which the second point approaches the first point.
That's called the tangent vector.
Now,
I need one more equation here.
Remember that ds...
Well,
okay.
No,
let's...
Let's...
No.
Okay.
The way that you construct the tangent vector
is very simple.
tm is equal to dxm divided by something,
divided by the distance between those two points.
Just divide by the distance between those two points,
and that's what we call ds.
Remember what ds is?
ds squared is the square of the distance
gmn dxm dxn.
Just divide it by ds.
That's what we call ds.
So that defines a unit vector.
You can prove that it's a unit vector.
I'll allow you to do that.
It's a unit vector at every point along the space...
along the curve.
That's called the tangent vector.
And it points in the
direction between two neighboring points,
the direction specified by two neighboring points,
and its length is 1.
Okay.
So that's the notion of a tangent vector.
And now what about the notion
that the tangent vector
is constant?
That's the statement that if I
plug in the tangent vector for v,
the right-hand side or the left-hand
side of this equation should be 0.
So let's write that equation down.
Okay.
Plugging in t into that equation,
it says that dtm...
Let's call it tn.
Plus gamma m r in tr dxm.
Let's see what I did.
All I did was plug in for v t.
You have a dv and a v.
Here you have a dt and a t.
And set that equal to 0.
Go along each point and check
whether as you move along this curve,
this quantity is 0,
everywhere is along the curve.
If it is,
the curve is a geodesic.
It corresponds to setting your steering wheel dead ahead
and moving in as straight a line as you can.
That's the notion of a geodesic.
And we can write it in a little neater form.
We can write it in a slightly neater form.
Let's divide both sides of the equation by ds,
by the little distance between neighboring points here.
We're differentiating,
which means we've taken a little interval here,
dx.
And now we're going to divide it by ds.
That says that the derivative of t,
tn,
with respect to distance along the curve,
this is the derivative of the tangent
vector with respect to distance along the curve,
plus,
well let's write it equal to minus,
is equal to minus gamma nmr,
tr,
but then dxm by ds.
What is dxm by ds?
tm.
So I have a little equation
here that only involves the tangent vector.
It also,
of course,
involves the Christoffel symbol,
but let's suppose we're given that.
Let's suppose we're given the Christoffel symbol.
Then the equation of motion of
a geodesic is just this equation.
Gammas are made up out of the metric.
So if we know the metric,
we know what to put on the right-hand side.
And we can say one more thing.
Since t itself is a derivative,
we can write this as a second derivative.
d second xn by ds squared.
I've written now that tn is dxm by ds,
and then differentiated it again,
ds squared.
The second derivative of xn along the curve
is equal to minus gamma nmr,
tr,
tm.
Does this look like anything familiar?
Probably not.
But it is,
actually.
If we were to think of
s as time along the curve,
some measure of time as we move along the curve,
then this thing would be acceleration.
Second derivative of the position with respect to time,
if we imagine that s is like time.
We'll come back to that.
So if s were like time,
or if s were increasing uniformly with time,
then this would be the acceleration.
Acceleration is equal to something
that depends on the metric.
And t,
and some more t's here.
We'll deal with them later.
This has the look of a Newton equation.
Acceleration is equal to something
that depends on the gravitational field.
The metric is the gravitational field.
So this is the equation that replaces Newton's equation,
as we'll see,
for the motion of a particle in a gravitational field.
In other words,
in some sense,
a particle in a gravitational field
moves in the straightest possible trajectory.
Now,
it moves through the greatest pos-
the straightest possible trajectory through space-time,
not just through space.
So now we have to come to space-time.
So far,
we've just been studying the mathematics of curved spaces.
Curved spaces as Riemann would have understood them.
The mathematician Riemann was the
one who invented most of this,
most of this mathematics.
And one of the main aspects for curved spaces.
These are ordinary curved spaces
in which distance was governed by the Pythagorean theorem.
Alright?
And always the square of the distance was always positive.
Minkowski space is a space
which also has a natural
measure of space-time distance along curves.
So,
space-time distance between neighboring points,
or even distant points.
Minkowski space
is a space with a
notion of distance between neighboring points,
in fact a
notion of the square of distance.
Distance is usually defined in Riemannian
geometry in terms of its square.
Okay,
in Minkowski geometry,
again we have a
notion of square of distance between
neighboring points and what is it called?
The proper time between the points.
The proper time.
The proper time between the
points and it's also a notion of neighboring distance,
sort of.
Given two
points in spacetime,
Tx,
the space-time distance between them,
and now let's not
call it the space-time distance,
let's call it the proper time,
is equal to
dt.
t squared,
not plus the x squared,
but minus the x squared,
and if there are
more coordinates,
let's say y and z,
it would also have minus dy squared minus
dz squared.
That's called the tau squared.
Tau is the proper time and it's
conventional to rewrite this as minus ds squared.
Sometimes you use s,
sometimes tau.
I'm not going to use s,
I'm going to use tau,
but according to convention,
this is equal to minus g mu nu,
dx mu dx nu.
Now what does that mean?
g mu nu is the metric of spacetime,
dx mu stands for
x mu,
stands for t,
x,
y,
and z,
and according to standard convention,
t is called x zero
and x is x one,
y is x two,
and z is equal to x three.
That's convention.
Alright,
so mu and nu run from zero to three.
This has exactly the same value as the x and
y.
It's the same form,
exactly the same form.
I'm using mu and nu because it's conventional
when talking about spacetime to use mu and nu.
The only new thing is the metric tensor.
Let's write down the metric tensor.
The metric tensor now has a minus one that corresponds
to the dt squared.
Notice there's an extra minus sign here.
Zero,
zero,
plus
one,
zero,
zero.
Zero,
zero,
one.
That's the matrix or the metric tensor g mu nu.
Alright,
how does this read?
It reads minus dt squared
plus dx squared plus dy squared
plus dz squared.
And what are all these zeros doing here?
The zeros are doing,
telling you
that there are no cross terms dt dx,
dt dy,
or anything like that.
These are special coordinates.
These are Minkowski coordinates and
they play the role in relativity
of Cartesian coordinates.
In special relativity,
this is all there is to it.
Okay.
In general relativity,
g mu nu becomes a function of space and time.
Let's just call
it g of x.
It becomes a function of space and time.
Not just a function of space,
but
a function of spacetime.
But one thing.
What can you say,
in what way does this work?
Well,
in what way is this
matrix different than delta mu nu,
one,
one?
The answer
is it has a minus one in one place.
But there's also an invariant concept here.
The invariant
concept is this one has one
negative eigenvalue and three positive eigenvalues.
The metric
of spacetime always has one
negative eigenvalue and three positive eigenvalues.
We're not
going to spend much time dealing with that.
We're going to spend a lot of time dealing
with that.
The equations always take care of all of that.
But what does it mean that
there's one negative eigenvalue and three positive?
It means there's one dimension of
time and three dimensions of space.
I could write a metric that looked like this,
with
two minus signs here.
That would have dt squared,
let's say,
excuse me,
that would have two
positives and two negatives.
That would be unallowed in relativity.
It would correspond to a crazy space with two
time directions and two space directions.
Einstein realized that the metric of spacetime
should have one negative and three positive eigenvalues.
But this is,
we don't need to
worry too much about that.
Other than that,
all of the equations are the same as we've
done up till now.
Yeah?
Can mathematicians explore spaces like this?
You know,
I don't think so.
Not to my knowledge.
You'd have to ask
somebody who knows a little
bit about the history of geometry.
But to my knowledge,
no.
So I think Minkowski and Einstein were,
as far as I know,
the first one to explore
these.
The equation you wrote for d
tau has three minuses and one negative.
But one positive.
Yeah.
So it's minus the metric zu tell by z,
right?
Did I get this wrong?
No,
I got it right.
There's minus .
There's two minus signs.
These are both conventional.
Oh.
Minus GPU nu.
Yeah.
There are two minus signs…
y object.
…Y just in order to keep
my notation consistent with everybody else's.
so.
Radiospin.
Right.
Okay,
other than that,
as I said,
everything is exactly the same.
You just,
if you want to know whether the space is flat,
now what does flat mean?
Flat does not mean that there's a coordinate
system in which the metric is a Kronecker
delta.
It means that there's a coordinate system
in which the metric looks like this.
It's the Kronecker delta except with one negative sign.
That's the notion of a flat spacetime.
A flat spacetime is one
with one negative and three positive,
but in which there do
exist coordinates in which the metric can
be brought to this very simple form.
That's the notion of a flat spacetime,
and if the spacetime cannot be brought to this
form,
then it's curved.
How do you check whether it's curved?
You do all exactly the same things.
Could you have three negative and one positive?
Yeah.
What's that?
Could you have three negative and one positive?
You could.
Actually would be basically the same thing,
but uh...
Is there a special symbol like the
Kronecker delta but it has the one negative?
Yeah.
It's called eta mu nu.
And so one,
yeah,
that's a good point.
When we write this,
if we were dealing with these coordinates,
we would write this as
eta mu nu dx mu dx nu.
The general equation,
sorry,
the general equation is to put
a g mu nu of x here.
The special case in which you're
dealing with these special flat coordinates,
I told you
before don't use the term flat coordinates,
in which you're dealing with these special
Minkowski coordinates,
which are like Cartesian coordinates,
is that this is called eta mu
nu times dx mu dx nu.
Okay.
So that's what we inherit from special relativity.
This is all inherited from special relativity.
Okay.
Are we okay?
Everybody clear?
There's a minus sign missing somewhere there.
Hm?
There's a minus sign missing on one of the etas.
On one of the what?
Oh.
Good.
Thank you.
Minus.
Yeah.
Right.
Okay.
So that's what we inherit from special relativity.
That's correct.
All right.
So for a while now
we're going to do special relativity.
In other words,
we're going to deal with a flat space.
We're going to deal with a flat space,
and we're going to wind
up looking at it in polar
coordinates.
Not polar coordinates as Euclid would have used them,
but polar coordinates as Minkowski.
Okay.
So for a while now we're going to
deal with a flat space with a flat space.
All right.
Mm-hmm.
Okay.
So for a while now we're going to
deal with a flat space with a flat space.
So let's get rid of space.
Can we go to the big picture in here,
Janice?
So for our next problem
and this is an exercise um,
huge time,
okay,
this will be a big
No problem.
But this is one of the issues that
accepts both yeah and this is a problem.
Okay.
These practice what?
This is T natural
If they're going to accelerate with uniform acceleration,
then they will maintain the
distance between them,
but distances are supposed to
transform when you accelerate something.
So if we were to just start
these points moving with a uniform acceleration,
we would actually
discover that in the rest frame of the points,
the distance between them was what,
getting
larger and larger?
I think larger and larger.
That would mean,
for example,
if there were
strings between them,
that as they start moving,
in an attempt to keep their distance uniform,
the string would stretch and eventually break.
That's not what normally would be thought
of as a uniformly accelerated reference frame.
What's nice about a uniformly accelerated
reference frame is not only do
the distance between points stay the same,
but they're
connected.
But if you had strings connecting the points,
they wouldn't get stretched,
all
sorts of things like that.
Another thing about a
uniformly accelerated reference frame in
special relativity,
if you wait long enough,
uniform acceleration will lead to moving with
greater than the speed of light.
So uniform acceleration,
to the extent that it exists
and makes good physical sense,
is not as simple as just
moving these points all with the same
acceleration.
I'm going to tell you how to construct
what a relativist would call a uniformly accelerated
reference frame.
But to do so,
I want to go back a step.
I want to go back to Euclidean
space and talk about polar coordinates.
Because the uniformly accelerated coordinate system
is the analog of polar coordinates.
Okay,
so let's start with ordinary space,
y and
x.
And I want to introduce polar coordinates.
Polar coordinates mean an angle and a radius.
Here's a point.
It's characterized by a radius,
and an angle,
and here's some equations
which you're all familiar with.
Okay,
you know those equations,
you know that cosine squared plus
plus sine squared theta is equal to one,
which is the same as saying that x
squared plus y squared is equal to r squared.
Finally,
two other equations.
Cosine of theta is equal to e to the i
theta plus e to the minus i theta over two,
and sine theta equals e to the i theta
minus e to the minus i theta over two.
You can check that cosine squared
plus sine squared is equal to one,
just theta,
simple identity for all possible theta.
These are the basic equations governing polar coordinates.
Oh yes,
in this one.
Thank you.
An i in that one,
very good.
Okay,
now,
what's the equation of a circle?
The equation of a circle is just
that r is equal to a constant,
and there's a circle.
Imagine a point moving around with uniform velocity.
Uniform angular velocity.
With uniform angular velocity,
the acceleration of that point is uniform on the circle.
It's uniform,
the acceleration is uniform on the circle.
What direction is the acceleration point?
Toward the center.
But the magnitude of the acceleration is constant.
Okay,
now what does this have to do with relativity?
Relativity,
we write basically the same equations.
To define a uniform accelerated point.
That's the light cone.
What is a uniformly accelerated point in special relativity?
It's a point moving on a hyperbola.
It is accelerated,
it's not moving with constant velocity.
Constant velocity would mean that
it's moving on a hyperbola.
It would mean that it's direction would be fixed.
It has no velocity over here.
It's moving straight upward.
This is time.
Time.
This is x.
At this point the velocity is zero.
At this point it's moving forward.
As it moves up and up and up,
it gets closer and closer to the speed of light,
but never exceeds it.
Okay.
And the question is,
what is the equation?
How do we,
what's the analogous equations for hyperbolas,
basically?
This is a hyperbola.
Alright,
so let me just write them down.
Cosine and sine theta
are replaced by the hyperbolic versions.
Hyperbolic cosine.
And let's call the hyperbolic angle omega.
Omega is what increases as you move along the hyperbola.
It's a kind of angle,
and it plays the role of
the angle in Euclidean space here.
It's measured off along the curve here,
along the hyperbola.
This is hyperbolic sine of omega.
The definition of hyperbolic cosine
and sine is very similar.
This is equal to E to the omega
plus E to the minus omega all over 2.
Very similar to this,
sorry,
to that one.
And this one here is E to the
omega minus E to the minus omega over 2.
The symbol over here means that,
you know,
it's a constant.
E to the minus omega means divided by 2.
No I in this one.
No I in hyperbola,
in hyperbolic geometry.
You can check,
very easy,
that
cosh squared omega minus sinh squared omega is what?
Sinh.
It's called sinh.
Analogous to this equation.
And now define x.
It's the analog of this equation over here.
x is equal to r.
cosh omega and t.
And t,
the vertical coordinate,
is equal to r sinh omega.
This is,
these actually define r and omega.
These are the definition of r and omega,
if you like.
It's a coordinate transformation.
It's a coordinate transformation from ordinary x and t,
flat space x and t,
or just,
Minkowski coordinates x and t.
It's a coordinate transformation to r and omega.
Which one do you think is like time?
Omega or r?
Can you tell?
Well,
if you're on this horizontal axis,
where cosh omega is just 1,
on the horizontal axis,
cosh omega is just 1,
if you increase r,
you're just going out along this axis.
So r is like a space coordinate.
You're just going out along this axis.
If you increase omega from this point,
you're traveling upward in analogy
with traveling around the circle.
Traveling around the circle,
the analogy is moving upward along the hyperbola.
So omega is like time.
There's a time-like coordinate.
And r is like time.
It's a space-like coordinate.
Now,
just as
there's a uniformity to the circle,
at any point you can define r,
and it's constant on circles,
you can define r,
in this case,
is constant on hyperbolas.
So here's the hyperbola r equals 2.
Here's the hyperbola r equals 1.
Here's the hyperbola r equals 3.
Here's the hyperbola r equals 4.
And finally,
if I take x squared minus t squared,
along one of these hyperbolas,
it's just given by r squared
times cosh squared minus sin squared,
but that's just 1.
So a hyperbola is,
this is,
this hyperbola is just fixed r,
constant r,
let omega vary,
let the angle vary,
and that defines the hyperbola
x squared minus t squared equals r squared.
So that defines coordinates.
Those coordinates in special relativity
are the closest thing that exists
to uniformly accelerated coordinates.
Okay.
This point here
moves in an accelerated trajectory.
This point moves in an accelerated trajectory.
The distance between here and here
is the same
as the distance between here and here.
That you can check.
Is the same as the distance between here and here.
That means
that as the frame,
as the,
as the
Lorentz frame of reference rotates,
not rotates,
but accelerates,
as the Lorentz frame of reference accelerates,
the distance between neighboring,
neighboring particles,
let's think of these as a sequence of particles,
the neighboring particles stay the same.
What's unusual here,
and different than an ordinary,
an ordinary accelerated frame of reference,
is that the acceleration
along these trajectories is different.
Let's look,
let's look at a trajectory which comes in very,
very close in here.
Very small r.
It makes a sudden,
a sudden change of direction.
A sudden change of direction.
That indicates that this trajectory
has a much larger acceleration.
Incidentally,
the accelerations,
the proper acceleration,
the actual acceleration
that an observer would feel
everywheres along this trajectory is uniform.
Same acceleration here,
as here,
as here.
Just in the same way
that a particle moving in a curve here
feels the same acceleration inward as here,
as here.
The acceleration along the trajectory is uniform.
The proper acceleration,
the proper acceleration,
what does the proper acceleration mean?
It means the acceleration felt by somebody over here.
You know,
how much of a push
she feels being accelerated over here.
It's uniform along these things,
along these hyperbolas.
Everywhere is the same,
but the acceleration is different here,
here,
and here.
The message is this,
that if you want to define uniform acceleration,
you have to have,
acceleration which is constant in time is okay,
but,
you're necessarily going to have different accelerations
at different points of space,
at different r.
This never exceeds the speed of light,
and the proper distance,
the proper distance between points stays fixed.
Remember,
proper distance is,
yeah?
If you make it here,
it's not an angle,
it goes from x to y.
That's right,
it's called a hyperbolic angle.
It's called a hyperbolic angle,
and,
it is not an angle.
It's not an angle,
it doesn't go from zero to two pi.
That's exactly right.
It goes from minus infinity to infinity.
Yeah.
Yeah,
I'll tell you what proper acceleration is.
it's the derivative with respect to proper time.
Yeah.
Proper acceleration would be d second x mu,
not by dt squared,
but by ds squared,
where s would be,
or d tau squared,
excuse me,
d tau squared.
All right.
That's the notion of proper acceleration.
You measure the acceleration,
not with respect to ordinary time,
but with respect to proper time.
Okay.
It's the rate of change of the,
of the proper velocity,
which is dx by d tau,
with itself with respect to tau.
And it's everywhere is the same along these curves,
but differs from one point to another.
The further out you are,
the further out you are,
the smaller the acceleration,
the straighter,
the less curved the trajectory.
In fact,
you can write an equation for the acceleration,
for the proper acceleration.
The proper acceleration,
a,
along such a trajectory depends on only one thing.
It depends only on r.
Okay.
In units
in which c is equal to one,
the acceleration,
let's take a particular curve here
and call it capital.
Let's call it capital r.
Capital r represents its distance along here.
Call it capital r,
not little r,
but little capital r is just
a particular value of little r.
Then along that hyperbola,
the acceleration is given by one over capital r.
The smaller capital r,
it's,
it's actually the same thing as going on here.
The smaller little r for a,
the bigger the acceleration needed to hold it in place.
Okay.
So the acceleration is one over r.
Now this doesn't make good unit sense.
What's the units of acceleration?
Length divided by time squared,
right?
Okay.
Let's write that as length squared divided
by time squared times one over length.
Okay.
So acceleration has units of one over r.
So it's one over length times velocity squared.
Okay.
All right.
If we work in general units,
not set the speed of light equal to one,
the acceleration here is equal to c squared over r.
Okay.
That means that for a fixed r,
the acceleration is very,
very large.
You have to go to very,
very large r
before,
before you're talking about a moderate acceleration.
Okay.
Because of the square of the speed of light here.
Yeah.
Question?
No.
Okay.
Is r the x intercept of the curve?
Yeah.
r is the x intercept of the curve.
That's exactly right.
And this acceleration is exactly the acceleration,
ordinary acceleration that you
would experience at this point
moving on that curved space-time trajectory.
Yeah.
The more curved it is
over here versus here and here,
the more acceleration.
Okay.
So I'll use c equals one generally,
but keep in mind that this acceleration is very big
unless r itself is very big.
Okay.
Let's go a little further.
Question?
Yeah.
It looks like what curves you're going to get
is very dependent on where you put the order.
That is correct.
A uniformly accelerated reference frame is defined relative
to a particular origin.
Okay.
This,
uh,
that's right.
Hmm?
I mean,
nothing should be relative to the origin.
Well,
you better find it.
No real physics depends on the...
I'll tell you what we're going to do.
We're introducing a somewhat arbitrary set of coordinates.
And in that arbitrary coordinates,
we're going to write the
equation of motion of a geodesic.
And we're going to see that
the equation of motion of a geodesic
looks like a particle falling
in a uniform gravitational field.
But only if we,
you know,
really work it out in detail.
Okay.
So I'll show you what we're doing.
We'll get there.
Yes,
you're right.
This is one of many possible coordinate systems
where you could put the origin any place you like.
And for that particular coordinate system,
we have a well-defined R and omega.
But we could move the origin if we liked.
But let's not.
Let's not.
Let's keep the origin fixed.
Okay.
So here is the acceleration.
Uh,
and now let's talk about the metric.
Let's talk about the metric.
First,
the metric in ordinary polar coordinates.
Metric in polar coordinates,
ordinary distance squared,
that's equal to the R squared plus what?
Anybody remember?
Something involving d theta squared.
R cosine theta.
No,
no,
no.
This is not a sphere.
This is just a plane.
You're thinking about the sphere,
right?
It's just R squared.
R squared d theta squared plus
the R squared on the plane.
This just says that for a fixed separation theta,
the actual distance along here increases linearly with R.
So for a given d theta,
the distance associated with d
theta increases linearly with R.
Therefore,
the square of the distance increases,
the distance increases quadratically.
This is the metric of
the flat plane in polar coordinates.
Now notice,
first of all,
that the metric is not the Kronecker delta.
It has the R squared.
That's one.
But it has R squared d theta squared,
so that's R squared.
If we were to write the
metric and a two-dimensional metric for this,
this would look like this.
It wouldn't be the Kronecker delta.
It has this R squared here,
position dependence.
Why?
Because the coordinates are curved.
Space is not curved.
Completely flat space,
curved coordinates.
The analog here is d tau squared is equal
to R squared d omega squared minus d R squared.
Now,
I've taken only two dimensions.
For the moment,
I'm going to ignore y and z.
We don't need y and z now.
We're going to be thinking about
a particle falling in a gravitational field
along what is the vertical axis will be the x-axis,
and y and z will be the other coordinates,
and they won't matter for
the problem we're going to discuss.
So the problem we're going to
discuss is just R and omega,
time and distance from the origin.
Time and distance from the origin.
That's the metric.
And we want to see what
that metric has to do with gravitation.
Gravitation is supposed to have
something to do with the metric.
So here's what we're going to do.
Remember,
as we move outward here,
the acceleration is changing.
If we go very,
very far away,
yeah,
let's think about a place far enough away
that the acceleration is,
pick an acceleration.
What's a good acceleration?
How about 10 meters per second per second?
Okay.
Let's go out far enough out
here that the acceleration is g,
10 meters per second per second.
It's accelerating to the right.
Okay.
So where was our formula?
Our formula was that the acceleration,
acceleration is equal to 1 over R times c squared.
And we're going to set that equal to g.
So that means R is
equal to c squared over g.
We have to go very,
very far away.
Measured in meters,
what is c?
C is 180,
no,
not 186,000,
but 3 times 10 to the,
3 times 10 to the eighth meters per,
and 3 times 10 to the eighth,
so 3 times 3 is 10 times,
times 10 to the 16th.
This number here is 10 to the 17th.
This is only 10,
so this whole thing is 10 to the 16th.
We have to go out 10 to the 16th meters
before we find a place which is accelerating
with the gravitational,
ordinary gravitational acceleration.
對
But let's go out there.
Moreover,
if we don't move too much along the r direction,
this acceleration won't change much.
So let's introduce,
let's imagine we fix on a certain distance r,
given by this.
If we set c equal to 1,
of course,
then this is just 1 over g.
But we have to keep in mind
that 1 over g corresponds to a very,
very large distance.
The 1 is the thing which is big.
It's really c squared.
Let's go out to a distance r,
where the acceleration is g,
and then think about a region.
A region of r which is close to r.
This corresponds to being near the surface of the earth,
not allowing things to change.
So we're going to move a
little bit away from that r,
and we're going to call the distance along there y.
I guess I called it y,
not x.
So the distance from this hyperbola,
the space-like distance from this hyperbola,
is y to the specific hyperbola at that place.
In other words,
I'm writing that r,
little r,
is just equal to big R,
which I'm going to keep fixed.
Okay?
So I'm going to write this as big R,
plus y,
making new coordinates.
These coordinates are sort of
tailored to be around this point,
which is moving with the gravitational acceleration g,
the neighborhood of that point.
And now I'm going to rewrite the metric.
I'm going to rewrite the metric.
Rewrite the metric.
Let's see.
Where can we rewrite that?
Let's erase this.
Just rewrite it.
d tau squared is equal to r squared.
That's this little r squared,
but that's big R squared,
plus 2ry plus little y squared,
right?
All times d omega squared minus the r squared.
So that's big R squared.
So now I have an even more complicated-looking metric here.
Well,
it's a little more complicated,
not much,
and here it is.
But we're going to focus about the region of r.
So let's divide out r from this.
Let's write it in this form.
1 plus 2y over r,
plus y squared.
Is it over r squared?
Yes,
r squared.
I'm factoring r squared out of here,
and now I'm going to multiply.
I'm going to multiply this.
r squared d omega squared minus the r squared.
One last step.
I'm going to call r times omega,
big R,
times omega.
I'm going to give it a new name.
I'm going to call it little t.
I've called the original time here big T.
I'm going to call this thing little t.
Where is it?
This is little t.
And now I get a metric that looks like this.
1 plus 2y over r.
What about this?
This is much smaller than this.
Remember that r is enormously big.
r was how big?
10 to the 16th meters.
10 to the 16th.
OK.
And y,
I'm assuming that y is a
couple of hundred feet or something.
We're talking about falling in a gravitational field.
So y is a small number compared to r.
y squared over r squared is much,
much smaller.
y over r is small.
y is 10 feet or 100 meters
or how far did that guy fall?
24 miles.
That's tiny compared to 10 to the 16th meters,
right?
And y squared over r squared is even much smaller.
So I'm going to drop this.
So we did a whole bunch of stuff.
And at the end of the day,
we get a metric that apart from this,
which is small,
just looks like good old metric.
dt squared minus dr squared.
It just looks like space and time
in the more or less ordinary way.
d space squared minus d,
sorry,
d time squared minus d space squared,
but with a little correction.
A little correction.
And that little correction is what accounts
for gravitation in this accelerated reference frame.
Now,
first of all,
keep in mind that we're really talking about flat space.
So far,
we have not introduced any curvature.
This is really flat.
This is flat space.
So any gravitation that we find here is,
in a sense,
the same fake gravitation that
we find in the accelerated elevator.
We're studying physics in an accelerated coordinate system.
It's the elevator being pulled in this direction here.
And what do we expect to find?
We expect to find that in that elevator,
there is an effective gravitational field.
The effective gravitational field is
associated with this over here.
It's associated with this over here.
And let me tell you what the connection is now.
And then we're going to,
well,
you know,
maybe instead of,
yeah,
maybe instead of telling you,
what we'll do is work out the equation of
motion of a particle in a metric like this.
All right,
here we have a metric.
And that's all there is to it.
It's really simple.
Oh,
what does R again,
R is related to the acceleration.
Where do we write that?
We write it down.
We said that the acceleration is C squared over R.
If I set C equal to 1,
let's set C equal to 1,
then,
oh,
sorry,
G.
G is C squared over R,
the gravitational acceleration.
We chose R so that it was
accelerating with 10 meters per second per second.
That gave us this equation.
In C equals 1 units,
this is just 1 over R.
So 1 over R.
1 over R is G.
And look what we have.
We have just 2Y times G.
Have you ever seen the expression Y times
G in studying gravitation in a uniform field?
The potential energy.
Y times G.
Actually,
it's not quite the potential energy.
It's the potential energy divided by the mass,
but it's just called the gravitational potential,
right?
This is 1 over R.
Y times G is the gravitational potential.
And this is 1 plus twice the gravitational potential.
That's extremely general.
In any kind of gravitational field,
as long as the gravitational field
is more or less constant with time,
not doing anything too radically relativistic,
this coefficient multiplying dt squared is
always 1 plus twice the gravitational potential.
All right.
But why do I call this the gravitational potential
other than that it just looks like the gravitational potential?
Because if I work out the equation
of motion of a particle in this metric,
I will find that the equation of motion is
essentially as long as the particle is moving slowly,
as long as the particle is moving slowly,
as long as it's a good Newtonian approximation,
as long as things are not too relativistic,
then we'll see that that particle falls along the Y-axis,
like a particle in a uniform gravitational field.
So here's our basic metric,
and we want to find out
how particles move in that metric.
What's the rule for how a particle moves?
Anybody know?
Yeah.
Yes,
sorry,
it's either R,
it could be R or Y.
You're absolutely right,
we could set this equal to Y now.
Now,
why is that?
Because dr is equal to dy.
That's a good point.
Okay,
dy squared.
Right,
so we're writing the metric in the yt coordinates.
This is only good for the vicinity.
We made some approximation here.
We threw away a term.
We said it was very small.
It's only good in the vicinity
of this distance from the center.
In other words,
it's only good in the region
where the acceleration is reduced.
It's really g.
So question about big R.
It seems like,
I mean,
you picked that
so that the constant acceleration curve
would approach the asymptote t equals x,
basically.
I mean,
that's what you did.
This is sort of a computational trick or whatever device.
To do what?
I mean,
you could have constant acceleration
beginning at any point along x.
That's correct.
You could.
There will always be hyperbolas,
but they won't asymptote to the same.
That's right.
That's correct.
Yeah.
So there's-
That's right.
So there's a uniformly accelerated frame everywhere.
But that's the same.
That's exactly the same as ordinary physics.
There's a uniformly accelerated frame
with an origin over here.
In other words,
it's just a bunch of different
elevators whose floors are at different height
at a particular instant.
Right.
That's all that's going on here.
And we can think of this curve
here as being the floor of the elevator.
The elevator is being pulled in that direction now.
So it's an elevator on its side.
Elevator is being pulled this way.
And somebody's experiencing a gravitational
field and being held down.
I'm sorry.
You need some arms.
Right.
So elevator is being pulled that way.
We can take this coordinate r to be the
bottom of the elevator and the height above the floor
of the elevator.
We're calling it the elevator.
We're calling y.
Okay.
y is the height above the elevator.
And here's the metric.
What do I do with it?
Here's the metric of space-time in the elevator,
in the uniformly accelerated elevator.
All right.
We had to do a little
bit of work to get there.
But that's what it is.
The metric tensor in the vicinity of
a point accelerating with the speed of gravity.
Sorry.
With the acceleration of gravity near the Earth's field.
That's it.
Okay.
Now,
what are the rules about particle motion?
Most of you probably know them.
The rule about particle motion
is that particles move on geodesics.
Not geodesics of space,
but geodesics of space-time.
In other words,
we take the metric of space-time,
whatever it is,
and we go through exactly
these same operations.
And here is the equation of motion of a particle.
This is the equation of motion,
was the equation of motion which says geodesic.
Go straight ahead.
But not straight ahead in space now,
but straight ahead in space-time.
But otherwise,
the equations are the same.
Let's write them out.
I want to write them slightly differently.
d second x in by.
Now.
And I don't want to...
Yeah.
Okay.
d tau squared.
This is called the proper acceleration.
As long as the elevator is moving slowly,
in other words,
down here,
if it hasn't been
accelerating long enough to get
up near the speed of light,
then the proper time and the
ordinary time are essentially the same.
And this is just the ordinary acceleration.
This could be,
what would we choose?
X.
We would choose X to be Y.
We want the Y component
of acceleration along that direction.
So,
this would be the Y component of acceleration.
That's the left-hand side,
and the right-hand side is minus gamma.
Now,
the N component stands for Y.
This is the Y component of motion.
So,
we have minus gamma Y for the Y direction.
MR,
and what is T?
T is dxR by dS dxM by dS.
Okay,
now fortunately,
there's a whole bunch of these now.
M and R can run over all the possible coordinates,
one through four.
So,
it looks like,
well,
there's basically ten such contributions,
but most of them are extremely small.
As long as the elevator is moving slowly,
and as long as the object that we're interested in,
namely the object,
the particle,
whose coordinate is one,
as long as all of the motion is slow,
then only one of these combinations is significant.
How big is dt by dS for slow motion?
Remember?
It's essentially one,
because S and T,
or dT tau,
excuse me,
this should be tau.
Tau for the relativistic case.
These are the components of four velocity,
but the components of four velocity for a particle,
which is moving slowly,
the only component that's important is the time component.
The time component of velocity,
what does that mean?
Who ever heard of the time component of velocity?
Well,
it's just one.
It's just one.
It's derivative of time with respect to time.
In this case,
derivative of time with respect to proper time,
but proper time and time are almost the same.
So,
the two entries here,
with R and M standing for time,
those are big,
and they're just a fraction.
So,
that's about one.
They're both equal to one.
What about a space component divided by dT tau?
Well,
that's proportional to the actual ordinary spatial velocity.
We're assuming the spatial velocity is small,
small compared to the speed of light.
So,
the only important contribution here comes
when R and M are time components,
and that's minus gamma Y time time.
d second Y by d tau
squared is equal to minus gamma Yt.
That must be the gravitational force.
The Christoffel symbol must be the gravitational force.
Must be the derivative
of the gravitational potential energy.
So,
let's go back to the definition now.
Here it is up here.
Here's the Christoffel symbol that we're interested in.
And what do we need?
We need the one with two
time components and one Y component.
So,
let's see what we get.
What did I have here a minute ago?
P.
What was this,
P?
And what's down here?
M and R?
N and R,
right?
No.
R and S.
Yeah.
Okay.
And we're going to throw away some small things.
Okay,
so G,
P,
N.
What is this P here?
This P here is supposed to be Y.
So,
there's a GY something.
A GY something.
But the only GY something is GYY.
And that's one.
Or maybe minus one.
I'm going to lose the signs because I'm getting tired.
No.
The GYY is equal to plus one.
So,
the only G that appears here is GYY.
It's the only component of the
metric that has a Y index.
So,
this one is just one.
GYY.
And what do we get here?
We get partial of GY something R with respect to,
what is this?
These are supposed to be time components.
And this is supposed to be Y component.
GYR with respect to time.
This one is the same thing.
GYR,
that's zero.
There is no YR component here.
That's just zero.
There's only one component.
There's only one term and it's this one.
And if you work it out,
it gives you minus derivative of G.
Now,
let's see.
R and S are supposed to be time components.
So,
this is time,
time divided.
And what is N?
N is supposed to be Y.
This whole Christoffel symbol is nothing but the derivative
or minus the derivative,
one half.
There is a one half there.
One half minus.
Derivative of the time component with respect
to Y with a factor of one half.
That's what's on the right-hand side over here.
I think this should be plus.
Plus derivative of G time,
time with respect to Y.
Does this look at all familiar that the right-hand side of
an equation of motion contains a derivative with respect to Y?
Potential energy,
right?
Force is equal derivative of potential energy.
Yeah.
So,
somehow,
G must be the potential energy.
But look at this.
Here's G right here.
Here is G .
This term is constant.
It doesn't have a derivative.
But this term does have
a derivative with respect to Y.
The derivative of this term with
respect to Y is just 2G.
So,
this is just equal to...
Oh,
is it 2?
A minus or plus?
There's a minus.
Yeah.
There's a minus that cancels.
There's a...
There's a minus.
There was a half here.
Yeah.
The half is canceled,
and there is a minus sign.
I'm too tired to remember where the...
Ah,
yeah.
The minus sign came from the
fact that the tau squared is...
This is minus GTT.
All right.
The derivative of GTT with
respect to Y is just 2G.
Get rid of this half.
And what does that do?
It does this all equal to...
It's equal to minus G.
That's the equation of motion of
a particle in a uniform gravitational field.
Okay?
So,
we went through...
We went through what is a rather complicated derivation.
But what we learned is the following.
That,
first of all,
space-time has a metric.
And the metric can have
fairly complicated structure in arbitrary coordinates.
In uniformly accelerated coordinates,
it has this extra term there.
And the equation of motion for a geodesic,
at least as long as things are going slowly
and along the Newtonian approximation,
the equation of motion for a geodesic is just
Newton's equation in a uniform gravitational field.
Uniform gravitational field,
constant acceleration,
it's what we expected.
But to do it properly using metric...
And using Christoffel symbols and all these things,
you know,
it's a fairly complicated
procedure.
Einstein,
of course,
guessed this.
He guessed all of this in the opposite direction.
He didn't know about Christoffel symbols.
He didn't know about...
He knew about uniform accelerated coordinate systems.
And somewhere along here is
somehow the place where we started.
I don't know exactly how we started.
But somehow along here.
This was the observation that motion is geodesics.
Geodesics in a particular metric.
And the metric of uniform acceleration just looks like this.
So we've come back.
We've come around sort of full circle from
the first lecture where we talked about accelerated
elevators giving rise to gravitation.
And we've come around full circle.
But so far,
we haven't gotten to really the answer.
So we're going to look at the real gravitational fields.
These are not real gravitational fields because
they really correspond to flat space up there.
If we were to take this
metric and calculate the curvature tensor,
it would be exactly
zero,
indicating that there do exist coordinates where
the metric has the simple form like
this.
So this gravitation that we're experiencing
here is really exactly the gravitation due
to an accelerated frame of reference.
Not due to real gravitating matter.
Now we can sort of guess what
the effect of real gravitating matter would be.
Instead of putting 2y times little g,
what's the gravitational potential in a,
let's say
we have a gravitating object.
And again,
we can use a y coordinate over here.
Yeah,
that's 1 over y.
Right.
And so we can expect that when we
study an actual gravitational field of a gravitating
object,
we're going to get Newton's constant here divided by y.
And that's the Schwarzschild metric,
but not quite.
We're going to work out the Schwarzschild metric.
No.
You made a mistake.
What's the potential energy of a,
in a,
of a gravitating object?
Try it again.
What did you say?
You got the sign wrong.
Hm?
Right.
So,
we get this.
Oh,
but that's weird,
because that means that the time,
that means when y is large,
this is small.
Okay,
that's good,
because this is positive.
But something crazy happens at the point where,
sorry,
this is not 2g,
this is 2gm,
the mass
of the gravitating object.
Something happens when y is equal to 2gm.
This coefficient is just 0,
something very peculiar there,
right?
This has to do with
the horizon of the black hole.
Right,
so I plugged in,
I plugged in the gravitational potential here,
guessing,
guessing that the
same kind of thing would happen,
that the same kind of thing would happen,
and it does.
This gtt,
this gtt by the y,
that is just the derivative of the gravitational potential.
So if we want our equations to work out
and look like a falling mass in a gravitational
field,
we want to plug in the gravitational potential here,
gm over y,
but then we find
something really odd.
This coefficient vanishes somewheres.
Okay?
That vanishing is the horizon of the black hole.
So next time we're going to get
into the subject of the Schwarzschild metric.
We're not going to derive it now.
We need field equations to derive it.
We don't,
we haven't discussed field equations yet.
We've only discussed the geometry,
and we've discussed the motion
of a geodesic in a gravitational
field,
and so this is just a little demonstration
of how geodesics give rise to Newton's equations,
and then we jumped ahead and said,
okay,
let's guess that that's more general and
see something like this.
Immediately,
we discover something odd,
and that oddness is the oddness of the black hole
metric.
Good.
Okay.
I think we're finished for tonight.
Yeah?
Technically,
that white board,
the Christoffel symbol,
should have been a white
circle,
and this is going to be
the edge of the black hole metric.
now,
you say,
but wait a minute
the original metric,
the original flat space metric was just eta
and that's correct,
if you were to have done this calculation
in the original flat space coordinates
you would have found no force
that's because the eta is constant
and it has no derivative,
it has no Christoffel symbol
so if you were to work in the original coordinates
you would find no gravitational force
that's not surprising,
if you're in outer space
and you have an elevator and
the elevator is not being accelerated
no force,
things move on straight lines in that frame
in the accelerated frame of reference
particles move on curved trajectories
and those curved trajectories are the
they're not really curved trajectories
but they look like curved
trajectories in the new coordinates
and their motion is
is governed by Newton's equations with the right hand side
you see,
the fact
that the Christoffel symbols
are not a tensor,
that's important
if they were a tensor
then they,
if they were zero in one frame,
they would be zero in every frame
and since the derivative is the gravitational force
it would tell you that if
gravitational force is zero in one frame
it's zero in every frame
but that's not true
the gravitational force in a
non-accelerated frame is zero
the gravitational force in an accelerated frame is not zero
that's the equivalence principle,
equivalence of gravitation and acceleration
so it's important that this thing on
the right hand side is not a tensor
if it were a tensor
and it was zero in one frame,
it would be zero in every frame
okay,
that's the idea of
of
the value of the force in Newton's equation
depending on what frame of reference it is,
okay?
depending on what you're in,
okay
can you give a little bit more feel
for why we need to have a huge R
to make this
make the acceleration
to make the acceleration modest
that's,
it was only in order to
be working in a reasonable non-relativistic framework
um
yeah,
it was in order to compare with non-relativistic framework
we don't want the acceleration to
be in a reasonable non-relativistic framework
we want the acceleration to be so big
that in a small amount of time
we get up near the speed of light
we want the acceleration,
but I chose,
I decided just to put
in the ordinary gravitational acceleration here
so that's c squared over R
well,
that's just the way it is,
if you,
in these coordinates here,
the place where the acceleration
is modest
is very far away
okay
so
after all,
the gravitational field of the Earth is pretty modest
you can think of a lot stronger
gravitational fields and we will talk about them
okay
for more,
please visit us at stanford.edu