Stanford University.
Okay,
let's begin.
We were in the midst of discussing
the properties of the Schwarzschild black hole.
We really barely began.
So,
let me just review quickly.
The Schwarzschild solution,
first of all,
is an idealized solution.
It's idealized in the sense that the Newtonian force law,
F,
where are we?
This is broken.
I'm sorry.
F equals MMG over R squared.
That's an idealization.
It's an idealization under the assumption
that the mass creating the gravitational field
is a point at the center.
A point mass creates a gravitational field like that.
If the mass is spread out.
Then,
of course,
we don't really believe this to be
the case in the interior of where
there's mass,
in the interior of the earth.
This is not correct.
But it is true in the exterior.
It is true out beyond the surface of the earth,
at least if we ignore the atmosphere and other
forms of gravitating mass.
And so it's an idealization for a point mass.
In Newtonian mechanics.
You never really know.
You never really ever reach a point mass.
Real materials have a certain stiffness.
You can squeeze on them,
but you can never squeeze them to infinitely small radius.
They just have a certain resistance to being squeezed.
And gravity is only so strong.
Gravity is only so strong.
Even though.
The gravitational field.
The gravitational field has to get very,
very large at short distances.
The nature of materials is always such that
if you squeezed it down to arbitrarily small
distances,
it would spring back.
Not so in the general theory of relativity.
We're going to see an example tonight
of a way in which that's true.
That if matter gets too close to the singularity,
it gets sucked in in a way that doesn't happen
in Newtonian gravity.
Okay.
So,
Newtonian gravity.
For example,
in Newtonian gravity,
or Newtonian physics in general,
if you have a force center
like this,
and you put,
let's say an idealized force center,
right at the center there,
and
you put in a particle which
is moving straight toward the force center,
and with infinite
precision.
Yes,
indeed.
It will hit the center.
But even if you have the littlest
deviation away from ideal perfect perfection in the
trajectory of this particle,
it will not hit the center.
And it'll swing around it.
Effectively there's a kind of
force repelling it from the center.
You know what that force is called?
Centrifugal force.
If your aim is not perfect,
the particle will have a little bit of angular momentum.
And because of that angular momentum,
there will effectively be centrifugal force,
and
the centrifugal force will keep
it from going through the center.
So in Newtonian mechanics,
even though,
in Newtonian gravity,
even though the center
pulls very hard when you get close to it.
Nevertheless,
it is infinitely unlikely for an
infalling point particle to actually hit
the center.
Not so in the general theory of relativity.
In general theory of relativity,
gravity is even stronger.
It's so strong that it overwhelms the
centrifugal barrier and pulls anything into the center.
You know what's good?
Yes.
I have a question.
In Newtonian mechanics,
wouldn't that also be because
the particle is infinitely small,
it would be almost impossible to hit it?
No.
Well,
this is true.
This is true.
But in the general theory of relativity,
you do hit it.
Yeah.
You do hit it.
Okay.
Let's write down the Schwarzschild metric.
The Schwarzschild metric is the
Schwarzschild metric we did not derive.
I just wrote it.
And we're going to analyze it.
Then later we're going to come back and
I'll tell you what equations the Schwarzschild metric
is a solution to.
It's a solution to Einstein's field equations.
But let's take it as a target.
This is something later we will want to derive.
For now,
it's a specific metric,
a specific geometry whose properties we're going to analyze.
All right.
So it's described by a proper time,
a proper time interval.
And I've written it down before.
It's 1 minus 2m,
the mass of the object,
times the gravitational constant,
divided by the
radial coordinate.
Okay.
So this is just twice the potential energy
of a unit mass particle moving at distance
r.
That's times dt squared.
And minus 1 over the same thing,
1 minus 2mg over r,
dr squared.
And notice that...
Okay.
So when you pass r equals 2mg,
as you come in toward the center,
this changes sign.
But so does this.
So there will always be one coordinate with
a positive sign here and three other coordinates
with a negative sign.
Let's write in the other three coordinates.
The other three coordinates would be r squared.
And I've expressed this as d omega squared.
The omega squared...
Let's write it over here.
The omega squared is just
the metric of a unit sphere.
It's just the metric of a
sphere in azimuthal and polar angle.
So it's just d theta squared plus
cosine of theta squared d phi squared.
We'll just call it that.
Sometimes we may only be
interested in one of these angles.
For example,
we're going to be interested in
the problem of an orbiting particle.
If the orbiting is around the equator like that,
then we can forget phi altogether.
No,
we can forget...
Sorry.
We can forget...
We only need one angle.
We don't need two angles.
And we can just call it d phi squared.
Incidentally,
cosine theta at the equator is just one.
And so at the equator,
this would just be d phi squared.
Okay,
so that's this metric here.
Let's draw a picture of it.
First,
let's draw the time axis.
The time axis I will draw vertically.
There's the time axis.
Horizontal is space.
We only have two directions
of space that I can draw.
So you have to think of
a flat plane intersecting time equals zero.
But of course,
it's really a three-dimensional plane,
but I'm not going to try to draw that.
And then at r equals 2mg,
something is happening.
This,
of course,
the center here could be
thought of as r equals zero.
So this is r equals zero.
r equals zero at the center.
And we would do exactly the same thing
if we were talking about a Newtonian point particle.
We would just place the particle at the center.
Then,
somewhere as r at r equals 2mg,
there's something happening.
Or not happening.
Some funniness in any case
in the mathematical structure of it.
It's like a cylinder.
And it's a cylinder surrounding r equals zero.
It's called the Schwarzschild radius.
And it's called the horizon of the black hole.
We'll understand why as we go along.
Alright,
this is the horizon of the black hole,
or it's the Schwarzschild radius.
Out beyond that,
very far away,
let's look at what's going on very far away.
Very far away,
1 over 2mg,
that's negligible.
If we go to very large distances,
1 over r becomes very small.
So this just becomes dt squared.
This just becomes minus dr squared,
minus r squared,
the omega squared.
That's just flat space.
That's just flat space in polar coordinates.
Flat space time.
So far away,
it's just flat space time.
But as we move in toward r equals 2mg,
something happens.
And the geometry is characteristically different.
Now,
it is true that something
looks bad at r equals 2mg.
First of all,
the coefficient of dt.
becomes zero.
But even worse,
the coefficient of dr squared becomes infinite.
So something is blowing up.
But we're going to see that nothing of
any real physical significance is happening at that point.
On the other hand,
at r equals zero,
the denominator here becomes zero.
1 minus 2mg over r becomes zero.
And that becomes infinite.
And you might ask,
is something real going on at r equals 2mg?
No,
sorry,
at r equals zero.
Indeed,
something real is going on at r equals zero.
And what's going on at r equals
zero is the curvature is becoming infinite.
That's the thing that's going on.
Nothing special.
No large curvature is happening.
No enormous deviation from flat space
is happening at r equals 2mg.
But at r equals zero,
all hell is breaking loose.
If we were to have calculated the curvature tensor,
to find out just how curved this geometry is,
we would find all of its components
become infinite right at r equals zero.
There's another way to describe that.
Curvature means tidal forces.
Anything falling in when it would hit r equals zero
would experience infinitely strong tidal forces.
And be torn to pieces.
It would be stretched radially,
squeezed in the angular direction an infinite amount.
So r equals zero is a real place.
In other words,
a real serious disaster.
r equals 2mg,
nothing special.
Okay,
we talked a little bit about radial infalling.
The radial infall is the
And there's a lot of things I'll
just remind you of what the conclusion was.
I don't need to derive this again because we're going
to see exactly how it works in terms of pictures.
We're not going to need the equations to see how it works that
it takes an infinite time for something falling in to pass r equals 2mg.
That means in the coordinates that I've drawn here,
time,
surfaces of constant time are horizontal.
The time axis is vertical.
If something were falling in,
it would look like this.
It would fall in and in.
It would start far away,
fall toward the black hole or
the horizon or whatever it is,
and it would accelerate for a while.
I won't try to draw it accelerating.
I'm not good enough for that.
But as it got closer and closer to the horizon,
it would asymptote.
Getting closer.
Closer and closer,
but never quite getting there.
If this object had a length,
let's say it was a meter
stick falling in the long way.
If it were a meter
stick falling in the long way,
the front end of the
meter stick might look like that.
The back end of the meter
stick would do exactly the same thing.
It would fall in.
And it,
too,
would never cross the horizon.
And so the only way to make
sense out of this is to say,
at least,
that what happens is
that that thoughts just keep coming in,
admit that they're holding on for you.
Every time a moment a various it will
turn your appearance upside down to a way
the idea that the ball nowhere
fell after a figure disappears .
The fact is that not all ruthless
things will be dropped into the bow.
Let's say since the stars have worried about the stars,
the most likely story,
the scivious one that we already saw,
is that
just a meter stick,
but it was a clock.
How could you build a
clock out of a meter stick?
Well,
you could put two mirrors at either end
of the meter stick and allow a light beam
to go back and forth and back and forth,
and you simply count the number of pulses of light
beam that go back and forth.
That would be one way of
making a clock out of this,
but
clocks,
as they move,
however they are moving,
they don't tick off this kind of time.
They tick off proper time.
That's the meaning of the proper time.
The proper time is the
ticking of a moving clock,
how many ticks the moving clock makes from some starting
point.
This time over here,
that's called coordinate time.
It's just the
coordinate time.
It's the coordinate that we're
using to describe the entire system.
Notice that if r is very
far away,
supposing we're way out here,
not moving at all,
not moving in,
not moving out,
then d tau is equal to dt,
at least to a high approximation,
because 1 minus 2mg over r is
just 1.
So very far away proper time
and ordinary time are the same.
Very far away
this factor is just basically 1.
And d tau and dt are the same thing.
If we're not
moving
so that dr and the omega are zero,
then a clock moving very far away will really
just measure
dt.
But as we get closer and closer in,
for a given amount of dt,
d tau gets smaller and smaller.
So for example,
here's a given amount of time transpiring,
now time I mean little t,
a given amount of ordinary time,
coordinate time,
transpires between this surface and that surface over here.
How much proper time?
As you get closer and closer,
the proper time that transpires along
this trajectory here gets smaller and smaller.
So,
while it appears that the amount of t that it
takes to fall in through the black hole is infinite,
we could ask how much tau evolves
in the black hole.
By the time an infalling
object eventually arrives at the horizon.
And that is finite.
Again,
we're going to see this in pictures,
we're going to see this without doing any mathematics,
without doing any calculation.
We'll see it just from simple diagrams.
But here we can see why this might be true.
Even though the time dt,
or the time interval t is getting longer and longer,
because tau is shrunken,
by comparison with t,
there's a chance,
in any case,
that the amount of time along
one of these trajectories here is finite
until you cross the boundary.
Now,
somebody falling in with a clock,
do they,
with or without a clock,
an ordinary human being,
do they experience,
and by experience I mean experience in the usual sense,
do they experience an infinite amount of time
before they get to the horizon,
or a finite amount?
The answer is,
they experience the proper time.
Your heart is a clock,
your brain is a clock,
every timekeeper that you have
will experience the same shift or relative size scale
for the beating of the clock,
the tau,
and we can say the beating of clocks very,
very far away.
All right,
so it would be interesting to know
whether the amount of proper time that it
takes to fall in is finite or infinite,
and we could solve equations,
we could,
um,
we solve equations,
we can calculate,
we can do integrals,
but fortunately we don't really have to.
The pictures will take care of it.
Before I get
to those pictures,
I want to show you how to solve another problem
that does not have to fall,
have to do
with somebody falling into the black hole,
but has to do with another question,
orbiting the black hole.
Orbiting the black hole means,
well,
it's a little hard to draw,
orbiting the black hole means
corkscrew going around as time goes forward,
but let's take the case of a circular orbit.
A circular orbit means that if
we projected the orbit onto a,
onto just a,
onto space without worrying about time,
that the orbit would just be a circular orbit.
So if we were looking down at this thing,
if we were looking from the future down
at the center,
we would see r equals zero,
we would see some sort of
circle corresponding to the Schwarzschild radius,
r equals 2mg,
r equals 2mg over here,
and we would see an orbiting particle.
Going around,
and I'll take the case of a circular orbit.
Circular orbits are of course particularly simple.
Can we figure out what the circular orbits are?
Yes we can,
but I'm going to show you
just one specific kind of circular orbit.
The particular kind of circular orbit
we're going to talk about is
the orbit of a light ray.
As you might expect,
and as you probably know,
that a light ray,
here's again,
let's draw,
let's draw another picture of this,
but now let's draw it
so that the horizon is small.
I haven't changed the size of the horizon,
I'm just looking at it from a larger distance.
A light ray goes by.
We know from Einstein,
from a number of different places,
that the light ray will bend when it goes by,
by the massive object.
I did show you at
one point that the equivalence principle,
the accelerating elevator,
does tell you that a light ray
moving across the elevator,
as the elevator is accelerating,
will bend its trajectory.
It's the same thing here.
Gravity bends trajectories,
and in fact,
obviously,
as you move in closer and closer,
that light ray will get closer.
It will get bent more and more.
Why?
Because gravity becomes stronger.
As you move in toward the Schwarzschild radius,
it really whips around there,
and at some point,
it's not the horizon,
it's further out than the horizon,
there exists a,
there exist trajectories
which just go right around,
circular trajectories,
which just go right around the gravitating object.
Now this can only happen,
this will not happen near the surface of the Earth.
You'd have to squeeze the Earth down
to practically become a black hole.
You'd have to squeeze it way,
way down,
past the Schwarzschild radius.
Incidentally,
an object with the mass of the Earth
would have a Schwarzschild radius of about a centimeter.
So in other words,
the Earth would not do anything like this
unless it was squeezed down
to the diameter of a peanut.
So,
not to worry,
you're not going to see
light rays circling around the Earth.
But nevertheless,
it's very interesting to try to see
if we can understand the orbiting light rays.
Now this is a little bit calculationally intensive here,
and I'm going to show you
the set of things that you do
to calculate the circular orbits.
We're going to do it by
using the rules of classical mechanics,
things that we've already set up in previous quarters.
And part of the reason I'm doing it this way,
the reason I'm doing it this way is
because it's the only easy way to do it,
and even it is not so easy.
But it is worth the point
that the things we learned before
about classical mechanics,
for example,
are not disconnected from what we're doing now.
We're going to use classical
mechanics and some conservation laws,
not much more than conservation laws,
just a little bit more,
the basic principle of stability,
the basic principle of equilibrium,
that equilibrium happens at extremal points
or at stationary points of potential energy.
We're going to use that,
and we're going to use the mechanics
of an object orbiting,
but not an object,
a Newtonian object,
but an object moving with this metric over here.
Okay,
so we talked about this last time.
I'm going to go back over it,
but not at great length,
and then show you the calculation.
We start with the action.
Whenever you're working out
equations of motion for anything,
it is almost always easiest
to start with the action principle.
The action principle,
from the action principle,
derive a Lagrangian,
and from the Lagrangian,
derive the Euler-Lagrange equations of motion,
or some other trick.
And we're not going to do quite that.
We're going to use conservation laws.
All right,
so again,
we start with this metric here,
and the rule for the action
is the action of a moving particle.
The action of a moving particle is...
got a parameter in front of it.
The parameter is,
of course,
the mass of a particle.
This is necessary to give action.
What are the units of action?
Anybody know?
What's the units of Lagrangian?
Units of the Lagrangian are energy.
Units of action are energy times time.
All right,
so there's a...
In order to give it the right units,
there's got to be a mass out in front.
It's got to be energy times time.
Mass is energy.
I'm not going to fool
around with the speed of light.
We'll leave the speed of light equal to one tonight.
Units of action are mass times time.
Energy times time.
So here's your energy,
and what's the rest of it?
The rest of it is
the proper time of the orbit
between one point and another point.
In other words,
the integral dt,
d tau,
along the trajectory from an
initial point to a final point.
Okay,
d tau is the square root of what appears here.
So let's rewrite d tau,
square root of...
I'm going to give...
In order to not keep
writing this thing over and over
and this thing over and over,
I'm going to give them some new names.
We're going to call this object F,
called script F,
and one over it I will call script G.
The reason I'm using script is because
in order to not write this thing equal this thing,
I didn't want to use just ordinary G.
So I called this one script G,
but then I said,
well,
I better call this one script F.
Okay,
so this is script F and script G.
It's script F times dt squared
minus script G times dr squared,
and then finally minus r squared,
and then I'll call this one script G.
Now,
for d omega squared,
we're talking about a particle moving on a trajectory.
Let's assume that the trajectory is a circle
parameterized by a single angle.
It could be the angle around the equator.
Okay,
and so I'll just call it
minus r squared d theta squared.
Maybe it's d phi squared.
It doesn't matter either way.
It doesn't matter whether it's the polar angle
or the azimuthal angle.
I'll just call it d theta squared.
That's for a trajectory moving around,
let's call it the equator of the sphere.
So in other words,
this angle here is theta,
r squared d theta squared.
Now,
what we do with this,
always the same thing,
divide by dt squared inside the square root,
and then multiply by dt outside the square root.
Same thing.
So we're going to get
rid of the dt squared here.
This dr squared is going
to become dr by dt squared.
So that's just called r dot squared,
the radial component of the velocity squared.
This becomes d theta by dt squared,
which is just theta dot squared.
The angular velocity,
this is the angular velocity,
but now I have to put back
dt.
I removed dt squared,
but from under the square root,
and so I make that
up by multiplying by dt here.
f and g are functions of r.
For the moment,
I won't specify them,
but let's just write them down.
And do remember that g is one over f.
As it happens,
g is one over f.
Okay.
For a circular orbit,
r dot is equal to zero.
this will get a little bit simpler,
because for a circular orbit,
r dot is equal to zero,
but we don't want to quite go there yet.
All right,
so what do we read off the Lagrangian?
The Lagrangian is just the thing inside,
is the thing inside the integral.
The Lagrangian,
let's call it script L,
is minus m,
contains the factor minus m,
times this script L,
which is minus m,
square root f minus g,
whoops,
not s,
but g,
r dot squared minus r squared theta dot squared.
Now,
what do I want from this?
I want two things.
There are two conservation laws for this problem.
The conservation laws are energy.
Energy is always a conservation law.
Any other conservation law that you can think of
for orbiting systems?
Satellite?
Angular momentum.
Angular momentum is just the momentum conjugate to theta.
Remember the definition of
a momentum in Lagrangian mechanics.
If we have a coordinate called q,
any coordinate called q,
the momentum associated with q
is just equal to the derivative
of the Lagrangian,
with respect to q dot.
We've seen that over and over again.
Here it is again.
Alright,
so the angular momentum,
and unfortunately angular momentum is also called L,
but I'll call it not script L.
The angular momentum is just equal
to the derivative of the Lagrangian,
with respect to theta dot.
We're just applying this equation,
when q is equal to theta,
and that is equal to m over the square root.
Now I'm not going to continuously write
this square root over and over again.
I'm just going to call it square root,
without writing anything in here.
But when I write square root,
you keep in mind that it's
the square root of what's in here,
times the derivative of what's inside,
with respect to theta dot,
and that just gives us an r squared theta dot.
That's the angular momentum,
and the importance of the
angular momentum is that it's constant.
The importance of the angular
momentum is that it's constant.
It's also proportional to the mass.
I'm going to write it as the
mass times something I'll call Greek L,
or lambda.
I'm going to factor out the mass,
and what's left over I will just call lambda.
What is lambda?
Lambda is everything in here,
with the exception of the mass.
Alright,
so we could write this,
I'll just divide by L over,
I'll divide by m,
remove m from here,
and remove m from here.
Alright,
so here we have an expression
for a quantity which is conserved,
it's conserved because the angular momentum is conserved,
and it's a function of theta dot and r dot.
For a circular orbit,
it simplifies a little bit,
because r dot is equal to zero,
but let's not do the circular orbit yet.
Let's calculate the,
this is the,
this is,
well okay,
this L is the momentum associated with angle.
There's another momentum,
and the other momentum is associated with r,
the other co- there are two coordinates in this problem,
r and theta,
and to find P r,
we have to differentiate the
Lagrangian with respect to r dot.
That's also equal to some,
let's see,
what is that?
That's m script g r dot,
I think divided by the same square root.
Same square root,
I think that's right.
Yeah.
So we have r dot,
but r dot is not conserved.
r dot is not conserved,
there are forces,
radial forces,
and when there are radial forces,
there are accelerations along the radial axis.
If there are accelerations along the radial axis,
P r is not conserved,
but what is conserved is the energy.
So I'm going to write over
here the general expression for the energy,
the general expression for the
energy is the good old Hamiltonian,
the classical Hamiltonian.
I'll remind you what it is.
It's given by the sum over the various coordinates
of
the momentum
times the velocity associated with that coordinate,
in other words,
the time derivative,
sum over the coordinates,
in this case there are only two coordinates,
and then you subtract off the Lagrangian.
I bet you all remember that.
But the point is,
there is always an energy,
it's always given by a certain construction,
you can go back in your notes later
and check that this is the definition of the energy,
and it is always conserved.
It's conserved as long as the
Lagrangian does not explicitly depend on it,
it does not explicitly depend on time,
there is no explicit time dependence in here,
and so the energy is conserved.
All you have to do now is take his,
where is p?
Here's p r,
multiply it by r dot,
p theta is just l,
multiply it by theta dot,
add them together and subtract the Lagrangian.
It sounds like a horror,
but it's not so bad.
What you get is pretty simple,
h is the energy,
h is script f of r,
times the mass,
divided by good old square root.
We will not need p r any further,
we only needed it to calculate the energy,
and this of course is equal to the energy,
and it is conserved,
it does not change with time.
Alright,
so let's just put it under here,
where I really want it.
The energy is script f of r,
m,
and then square root,
and now I'll actually write in
what goes into the square root here.
But,
I'm now at the stage now
where I'm going to use the fact
that we're interested in circular orbits.
For circular orbits,
r dot is equal to zero,
and so for a circular orbit,
the energy is,
f minus,
no,
no minus g,
r dot,
no r dot,
minus r squared theta dot squared.
Alright,
so this is an expression for
the energy that involves theta dot squared.
The,
the,
it's partly kinetic energy,
partly kinetic energy due to the motion of theta.
There's no kinetic energy due to the motion of r,
because r is not changing for a circular orbit.
No r velocity,
just theta velocity.
This is a combination of potential energy,
it has r dependence,
and it has theta,
and it has velocity dependence.
And it's conserved.
Uh,
that's the energy,
and what about the angular momentum here?
The angular momentum is also conserved,
and it has the same denominator,
f minus r squared theta dot squared.
Okay,
what do you do with this?
I'll tell you what you do with it,
I'll tell you what the prescription is.
The first thing you do,
is you solve this equation,
and I'll let you do it,
at home.
You solve this equation for theta dot,
and you find theta dot as a function of r,
and,
this is usually called the reduced angular momentum,
the angular momentum divided by the mass.
You find,
the angular velocity,
as a function of angular,
sorry,
yes,
you find the angular velocity
as a function of the reduced angular momentum.
And that's not hard to do,
but there's no point in doing it,
it's very easy to do.
I won't do it,
but then you,
when you get it,
you plug it back into this equation,
into the energy equation.
And the result is that you have the energy
as a function of r,
and the reduced angular momentum.
So,
I'll tell you what you get.
Now,
physics always consists of this alternation
between principles,
and having fun figuring out the principles,
and what you should do,
and then the boring work of doing little calculations.
And then back to principles again.
And,
uh,
I will sort of shortcut
the boring calculational part.
We solve for theta dot here,
and then we plug into the energy.
And...
I'll write down what we get.
The energy is equal
to the square root
of f
times another square root,
and the other square root is r squared,
lambda squared,
reduced angular momentum squared,
plus r to the fourth,
all divided by r squared,
uh,
times m.
Times m.
You always have m there.
And that's it.
That's it.
There's nothing,
uh,
there's nothing too interesting about it.
How do you find a circular orbit?
What you do is,
this does not depend on r dot.
We're now interested only on the radial,
uh,
the radial aspects of the motion.
We want to know at what radius
the equilibrium position for the,
uh,
for the circular orbit is.
The equilibrium position depends on the angular momentum.
Okay.
For ordinary,
okay,
good.
For an ordinary Newtonian problem,
is the angular momentum bigger or smaller
the further away you go for an orbit?
It's not obvious.
I'm going to leave it to you to work out,
whether it's bigger or smaller as you go further away.
Constant,
uh,
angular frequency,
let's say,
right?
No,
no,
no.
The further away you go,
the slower the angular frequency.
But,
remember,
and the smaller the velocity,
but remember that when you construct angular momentum,
you have to multiply by r,
so it's not clear which way it goes.
All right,
if you know a little about the hydrogen atom,
you can guess,
but,
uh,
yeah?
Would that be simpler if
the r squared in the denominator
was factored into the squared?
Yeah,
it probably would be.
No doubt.
Do I have r squared?
Yeah,
yeah,
it would certainly be,
but I'm going to leave it that way anyway.
Okay.
I'm going to leave it that way for the moment,
because,
uh,
I want this way.
But now I want to go
to the limit of a photon.
I'm interested in the limit of a photon.
I'm interested now in the bizarre question
of whether a photon can orbit the geometry.
Can a photon ever get in close enough
that the speed of light
is not enough to eject it from the circular orbit?
So we're going to look for a circular orbit,
and the rule is to minimize the energy
as a function of r.
For fixed angular momentum.
Okay,
but now there's something going on.
Photons have zero mass.
So we've got a bit of a funny problem here.
Let's go back.
Let's remember the angular momentum
was m times lambda.
Photons have zero mass,
so it looks like they have zero energy,
but they don't have zero energy.
A moving photon,
a high-energy photon,
will knock your teeth out if it hits you.
Why?
Because it has momentum and energy.
Okay,
so photons do have energy.
As m goes to zero,
something had better get big
to cancel that m.
But they also have angular momentum.
Or momentum.
Momentum and angular momentum.
A photon,
if it's moving around in orbit,
or even if it's just going past a star,
does have angular momentum.
So what happens as m goes to zero?
The answer is that the thing that you hold fixed
is the angular momentum.
If you're interested in a photon
of a given angular momentum,
you hold the angular momentum fixed,
you let the mass go to zero,
but obviously that's going to make lambda get infinite.
In other words,
the right way to take the limit
for studying a photon of a fixed energy
and a fixed angular momentum
is to take the limit
that the mass goes to zero
lambda becomes infinite
in such a way that the product
of m times lambda
stays fixed.
The angular momentum stays fixed.
Alright,
now let's just look at this formula.
What does happen when lambda gets very big?
Another way to say it
is lambda is the angular momentum per unit mass.
If the mass goes to zero,
lambda will get big
if we keep the angular momentum fixed.
Alright,
so here's an expression.
Lambda is going to be the biggest thing in sight.
m is going to go to zero.
So let's analyze it.
If lambda is going to infinity,
for any value of r,
lambda squared times r squared
will be eventually bigger than r to the fourth.
And much bigger.
Eventually,
r squared times lambda squared
will be bigger than r to the fourth
and much bigger.
So we can,
simplify this,
and just say,
what's under the square root here
is just r squared lambda squared.
And forget the r to the fourth
because it's negligible
when lambda gets very big.
Well that's just r times lambda.
I don't need to write such a fancy expression.
It's just r times lambda
times m.
But lambda times m
is just the angular momentum.
Alright,
so what's in the numerator here,
what's in the square root in any case,
times m,
the square root times m
is just
the radial distance
times the angular momentum.
In the limit,
in the limit that we pass to a photon,
to a massless particle,
holding the angular momentum fixed,
this just becomes lambda times m,
which is l,
all times square root of r squared.
Then we have this thing over here.
And we have this thing,
square root of f,
we're going to put that back in in a minute
and figure out what that is.
And finally,
we have a one over r squared
downstairs,
which means altogether,
one over r.
One over r,
l,
and that's the energy.
What was this?
What were we calculating?
We were calculating the energy of the,
of the orbit.
It's a function only,
it contains l,
but it only contains l as a multiplicative factor.
All of the interesting stuff is a function of r.
It's a function of r.
And where is the equilibrium?
Where is the equilibrium?
The equilibrium
is when the energy is stationary.
You can think of this as a kind of
potential energy.
It doesn't depend on any velocities.
All the velocities have been eliminated out of this problem.
The radial velocity has been eliminated out
because it has no radial velocity.
The angular velocity was eliminated
by substituting for the,
by solving for the angular velocity
in terms of the angular momentum.
Here we have the angular momentum
and we have a function of r.
Where is the orbit?
The orbit,
the photon orbit will be
where the function of r
is stationary,
either maximum or minimum.
So that's all we have to find.
We have to find where
and what value of r
the combination square root of f
over r
achieves
either a maximum or a minimum value.
Okay,
let's now go back
and remember
what f is.
f is just the Schwarzschild factor here,
just this one minus two mg over r.
So,
it's square root
of one minus two mg over r
all divided by r.
Let's imagine plotting this function.
Let's imagine plotting the function
and trying to see what the minimum,
what it looks like.
Where its minimum is
and,
sorry,
it is not a minimum
as we will see,
it is not a minimum.
Okay,
first go very far away.
When you go very far away,
two mg over r is much smaller than one.
It's negligible compared to one.
And so when you're very far away,
this is just approximately one over r.
In other words,
it just falls off like one over r.
But what happens as you move inward?
As you move inward,
what are we moving into?
We're going to move inward to r,
the origin here is not r equals zero.
It's r equals two mg.
The horizon.
We're moving in toward the horizon.
And at r equals two mg,
what happens to the numerator here?
It becomes zero.
The denominator is not zero at that point.
And so the whole energy function
becomes zero at the horizon.
So it must look like this.
And that is what it looks like.
Now,
how do you find the point at which,
at which it's maximum?
How do you find the point at which it's maximum?
You differentiate this thing,
and you set it equal to zero.
I will tell you the answer.
The answer is,
and notice that the,
notice the,
did I leave out l?
I left out l,
didn't I?
Yeah,
but l just multiplies it.
The properties of the maximum or minimum
or whatever it is,
will not depend on l.
Okay,
so here we are.
Differentiate the square root thing
divided by r.
Set the derivative equal to zero.
Where is it?
It's right over here.
And that's the point r equals three mg.
At three mg,
there's a maximum to the energy.
Now,
if you have a potential energy
that has a maximum,
does that correspond to an equilibrium position?
Yes.
It corresponds to an equilibrium position,
but an unstable equilibrium.
An unstable equilibrium means
that if you put an
object right at the equilibrium position,
it will stay there,
but if you give it the slightest tap,
it'll fall off.
The smaller the tap you give it,
or the smaller the imprecision
in putting it right up at the top,
the longer it will last at the top,
or near the top,
but eventually,
it will rise up.
It'll roll down,
pick up some speed,
and fall off the top.
We're talking about a circular orbit.
We're talking about a circular orbit
of a massless particle.
We sent m to zero.
So,
what we found
is right at r equals three mg,
a massless particle,
a photon,
can orbit the black hole.
It's not at the Schwarzschild radius,
it's one and a half times the Schwarzschild radius.
That radius is called the photosphere,
or sometimes the photon sphere,
for obvious reasons.
It's the sphere on which a photon can orbit.
You might expect that if you had a black hole,
and you went and you looked at that distance,
you would find all kinds of photons orbiting around it.
After all,
any photon that gets started in that orbit
will stay in that orbit.
But of course,
if the photon starts slightly away from the top here,
just infinitesimally away,
if it starts out a little bit too far,
it'll go back out.
That corresponds to the orbits of photons
which are out beyond the photon sphere,
and which are just the orbits which get pulled in...
Whoops.
I hit the photon sphere.
I didn't want to hit the photon sphere.
I wanted to be outside the photon sphere.
If you're outside the photon sphere,
but just outside the photon sphere,
the photon will go...
whip around,
and then come out,
not necessarily exactly in the opposite direction.
The closer you get to the photon sphere,
the more angle the photon will sweep out,
before it eventually goes back out.
So in particular,
if you're very,
very close to the photon sphere,
a photon coming in can go around many,
many times,
but then go back out.
That corresponds to just being
slightly off to the right here,
and slowly going outward.
Well,
you can imagine coming in,
not quite getting there,
and then going back out.
What happens,
however,
if the photon is on that side?
If the photon is on that side,
it gets pulled right in.
It can't withstand the gravitation
if it's just slightly inward
of the photon sphere.
Instead of orbiting,
it may orbit a few times,
but it will spiral right in
to the horizon,
and then,
of course,
eventually,
it will spiral into the singularity.
Okay,
so that's what we see
from this little calculation.
Yeah?
Why did you keep angular momentum constant?
Oh!
What else should I do?
I'm interested in a photon with a given angular momentum.
That was the problem,
wasn't it?
Yeah.
Well,
every photon has some angular momentum,
so I might as well set it
equal to what its angular momentum is.
Angular momentum is conserved,
so whatever it is,
it will stay that way.
And notice the orbit does
not depend on the angular momentum.
The angular momentum factored out.
The orbit of the unstable equilibrium orbit
is right at r equals 3 mg,
and it doesn't matter what the angular momentum is.
So we ended up thinking classically,
but...
So here comes a photon,
and it has a certain linear momentum
that's determined by the frequency,
basically.
Yeah.
And depending on which radius it comes in,
it's going to have different angular momentum
about the center,
right?
About the black hole.
Right,
but it could be...
No,
no,
no.
It could be at a fixed...
We could be talking about
a thing at a definite radius,
and it can have different angular momentum at that radius.
The different angular momentum
will correspond...
Some of them will be orbits,
and some of them won't orbit.
Some of them will just go off.
But we can fix both the radius
and the angular momentum independently.
Not if we want to have a circular orbit.
All right?
If we want to have a circular orbit,
then the radius and the angular momentum are connected,
but not at the photon sphere.
At the photon sphere,
all circular orbits...
All the circular orbits can have any angular momentum.
That's what's curious.
So not for photons,
it seems like...
You don't have that freedom.
You don't have what?
The freedom to fix angular momentum in the radius...
Well,
you do.
You do.
Well,
no.
The only circular orbit...
Wait a minute.
For the photon,
there's only one circular orbit.
I mean,
even if there's none circular...
Yeah.
No.
You have the freedom
if you don't worry about circular orbits,
but for a photon,
the only kind of circular orbit
is the one at 3mg here.
That's basically what we derived.
The only kind of circular orbit.
And it's an order.
It's an unstable circular orbit.
Okay.
Anything that's inside...
Any photon that is moving,
let's say,
along...
You know,
in an angular direction
that's inside the photon sphere
gets swept in by gravity.
And of course,
anything that's moving slower than a photon
has even more trouble staying outside.
So...
Anything which is inside the photon sphere
moving in an angular direction,
whether it's got a mass
or it doesn't have a mass,
will always wind up falling in.
Question?
Yeah.
Why is it that the photon sphere occurs
where the energy is at maximum?
That's where you will find the stable orbit.
That's just...
That's just the analog of saying that...
Not a stable orbit,
an equilibrium.
If you're looking...
We're talking about a kind of equilibrium.
What kind of equilibrium?
An equilibrium with respect to the radial coordinate.
All right?
So the equations of motion
of the radial coordinate
for fixed angular momentum
have a solution
which is just to extremalize the energy.
It's the same operation as when you say
a equilibrium position
corresponds to a
minimum or maximum of the potential energy.
Potential energy is the part of the energy
which doesn't depend on velocity.
Here we're talking only about the radial motion,
so we're talking about the part of the energy
which doesn't depend on the radial motion.
It doesn't depend on the radial velocity.
Okay.
Think about it.
Dwell on it a little bit.
Compare the corresponding energy
with the corresponding Newtonian calculation.
You'll see all the pieces are the same
as the Newtonian calculation of calculating...
But the outcome is quite different.
The outcome is quite different that...
that in particular there are
no circular orbits for anything,
photons or otherwise.
There are no circular orbits inside the photon sphere.
There are circular orbits for massive things
outside the photon sphere,
but for massless particles,
only the photon sphere.
So that's just an example...
an example of working out a specific motion
in the Schwarzschild geometry.
Yeah.
So what does this mean
for what it would look like around the black hole?
I mean,
we talked about things looking like
they're all plastered onto the event horizon,
but you couldn't actually see anything like that,
could you?
Well...
I mean,
looking at the black hole
from a distance?
Let's talk about looking at
the black hole from a distance.
Okay.
There's a black hole.
You're out here looking at the black hole.
Light that passes out here
bends a little bit.
So you think about what you see in the backdrop.
You think about the backdrop,
what's behind the black hole.
That's what you see.
You don't see the black hole.
The black hole emits no light.
So what you see is the backdrop,
the stars or whatever it is.
The Picasso painting behind whatever it is,
you see it.
And of course,
now what you see is...
It appears that everything in the painting is shifted.
You look and you see this point
as if the light were coming from here.
So everything gets shifted out a little bit
away from the center.
But it gets worse than that.
As you look in,
for example,
there will be a light ray
that goes from here to here
and another light ray that goes from here to here.
There may be a light ray
that goes from there to there.
And you'll see this point double.
If it isn't this point that you see double,
it will be this point that you see double.
Some point along here you will see double.
In fact,
it's not even that you'll see it double.
You'll see it split in half.
You'll see a mess map.
It's worse than that.
No,
no.
The light ray can go this way.
It can go this way.
It can go behind the black hole.
And so what you actually
see is a kind of ring
around the black hole.
You see a ring around the black hole.
And it's even worse.
There are light rays that can go around
that can start over here and go like that.
A black hole is a very bad thing
to try to hide from your enemy.
Well,
not the black hole.
It's very hard to hide from your enemy
by hiding behind the black hole.
If your enemy is over here and you're over here,
you may think you're hiding,
but you're not because there are light rays
which go around like that.
But,
of course,
what you see is very,
very complicated
as your line of sight moves closer and closer
to the horizon because you'll see light rays
which go around many,
many times,
and it will fragment the background
into just an impossibly complicated thing.
Yeah,
Einstein rings are experimentally
or observationally verified things.
Yeah?
Is that the photon sphere or the horizon?
Well,
I was thinking about the horizon over here.
A light ray which is pointed
outward can get out from just above the horizon.
It's the ones which are pointing tangentially this way
which will fall in if they're inside.
A light ray...
Oh,
not here.
Here.
Here's the photon sphere over here.
A light ray which is moving in the angular direction
will not be able to escape from the photon sphere,
but a light ray which is radially outward will escape.
And in particular,
light rays which are sort of partly radially,
partly angular,
and those will swing all the ways around
and come out,
for example,
over here.
Okay?
Right.
So that makes looking at a black hole very disifying.
You'll see a very complicated pattern.
If we use the Euler-Lagrange equations
to solve the equation of motion for a photon...
to try to calculate this image...
I'm sure it works,
but how big a mess is it?
For the circular orbit?
No,
just for the more general case of calculating this,
the Einstein range,
for example.
I've never done it.
It's a mess.
Well,
you know,
with modern computers,
you just throw the equation on the computer
and it'll spit out answers.
Yeah,
right.
Right.
You know,
as I said...
Euler-Lagrange for this particular circular motion,
is that substantially harder than the...
For which motion?
For the circular orbit.
No,
it's not...
It probably takes more steps than what I did.
What would you do?
I suppose what you would do...
Yeah,
well...
No,
no,
I realize.
I know that.
No,
no,
it's a fair question.
You write down Euler-Lagrange equations
and then you stare at them and you say,
how the devil am I going to solve them?
Oh,
I use the conservation laws.
Sometimes I have enough conservation laws
that it completely determines the answer.
Then you don't have to solve any differential equation.
And that's all we really did here.
I could have written down the equations of motion
and then observed that there were some conserved quantities
and just used them.
But the trick of starting with the action
is always the most efficient way to do things.
Well,
is it always?
I think it is always.
Maybe there's a case here and there
where there's something easier,
but not usually.
Okay,
now we want to understand better
what it is that's happening at this curious point.
It's not a point.
It's kind of a shell around the black hole.
Let's draw it again.
Here's r equals zero.
I don't know.
What do you like?
Green horizons or red horizons?
Red.
Good.
I do,
too.
So there's a kind of shell around the black hole,
the horizon,
and something curious is going on there.
Among other things,
the sine of the coefficient of dt squared changes,
as does the sine of the coefficient of dr squared.
They both change.
They keep fixed the number of negative signs
and positive signs,
but still something curious is going on.
We know that clocks,
when viewed from far away,
a clock falling in seems to go slower and slower.
That's that relationship between dt and d tau.
So something is happening here.
But on the other hand,
I've also told you
that in some sense nothing is happening.
So how do we reconcile nothing with something?
With something.
that happen in gravity can be understood
by first understanding them for accelerated coordinate frames.
That's the equivalence principle.
As I've said,
gravity is not really exactly the
same as a uniformly accelerated coordinate system,
but it's often a very good thing to see if we
can see what's going on for a uniformly accelerated coordinate system.
So let's go back to that problem.
The problem,
the uniform acceleration in relativity is a little more
complicated than it is in good old Newtonian physics.
We've already talked about it.
And it corresponds to a coordinate system,
which is the analog of,
polar coordinates,
but polar coordinates in hyperbolic geometry.
Well,
hyperbolic geometry just means
circles are replaced by hyperbolas.
Okay,
so I'll just very quickly remind you.
Let's introduce,
this is flat space now.
This is plain old flat space.
It's not a black hole.
It's just ordinary flat space time.
There may be some coordinates coming out of the blackboard,
for the moment I'm not
going to be interested in them.
What I am interested in is this coordinate,
which I'll call capital X,
and this coordinate here,
which I will call capital T.
Time and space.
And there may be two more coordinates which you
can think of as coming out of the blackboard,
but they're not going to play any big role
in what I'm going to say for the moment.
Okay.
Now,
what is the metric of this,
what is,
oh,
sorry.
Next.
We introduce hyperbolic coordinates,
or we introduce polar coordinates.
Let me write them down for you.
The definition is that X is
equal to something which I'll call rho.
Rho is distance away from this point over here,
horizontally.
Rho times hyperbolic cosine of omega.
And omega is a kind of
time variable that varies along a hyperbola.
Along each hyperbola,
omega varies.
It's a kind of angle,
but it's not really an angle.
It's not periodic.
It's a hyperbolic angle.
It goes from minus infinity down
here to plus infinity up here.
But this is the analog of X
equals rho cosine theta for ordinary polar coordinates.
What about T?
T is equal to zero.
T is equal to rho hyperbolic sine of omega.
What about X squared minus T squared?
X squared minus T squared is equal to
rho squared times cos squared minus sin squared.
Cos squared minus sin squared is one.
So each one of these hyperbolas is,
a trajectory on which X
squared minus T squared is constant.
And that is what we call
uniformly accelerated coordinates in special relativity.
It's really just special relativity.
The metric,
the metric of ordinary flat space is
given by d tau squared equals rho squared,
the omega squared minus d rho squared.
And then,
we have the equation.
And that's the analog of r
squared d theta squared plus dr squared.
This would be,
the metric would be,
let's continue to call it rho squared.
Rho squared d theta squared plus
d rho squared would be the metric
and polar coordinates for an ordinary geometry.
Here it is for,
for Minkowski space,
for special relativity.
d tau squared is a special relativity.
So,
this is rho squared,
the omega squared minus d rho squared.
Okay.
Now I'm going to change some coordinates.
Just boring,
very,
very boring coordinate changes for a moment.
I'm going to invent a new coordinate called xi.
I hate,
I hate making new notations.
But we have no real choice.
We have to,
we have to study this theory in different coordinates.
And I'm going to change coordinates a little bit.
I'm going to take this rho squared here.
And I'm going to call it
four times the Greek letter xi.
Xi.
Rho squared is four times xi.
I'm going to call,
let's write that down.
Rho squared is equal to four times xi.
Similarly,
well not similarly,
but all the other coordinates,
but also we're going to write
that omega is just t over two.
No big deal there.
It's just convenient to,
to replace omega by t over two.
And now redo the metric.
The omega squared,
what's the omega squared?
The omega squared is dt squared over four.
Okay.
So,
this is dt squared over four.
That's the omega squared.
dt squared over four.
And now we have to multiply that by rho squared.
I'm talking about the first term here.
And that's just four times xi.
Big deal.
Xi times dt squared.
Okay.
Now,
what about minus d rho squared?
Let's take minus d rho squared.
Here's rho squared.
Let's calculate.
d rho squared.
The differential of rho squared.
Let's differentiate this equation.
Two rho d rho is equal to four d xi.
Okay.
That means that d rho is equal to,
I think it's two d xi over rho.
Did I have that right?
Mm-hmm.
Let me have it right.
Okay.
So,
d rho squared is four
d xi squared over rho squared.
But now,
rho squared is four xi.
So,
let's put that in here.
Four xi.
Four is cancel.
And now,
maybe yes,
maybe no,
you'll notice a similarity with the Schwarzschild metric.
In the Schwarzschild metric,
you have a coefficient function here times dt squared.
And you have the inverse
coefficient function here times dr squared.
If you think of xi as being like r,
then this has some family resemblance to this.
Notice another thing,
that this changes sign when r gets in too close.
Xi changes sign when it becomes negative.
Does xi being negative mean something?
Yes,
we will see that xi being negative does mean something.
So,
there is a similarity,
but the basic similarity is a coefficient and another
coefficient,
which are inverses of each other,
which we will see can meaningfully change sign
as xi becomes negative.
Okay,
let's flesh this out a little more.
Let's flesh this out a little more.
What's that?
Does it matter at all?
That we're missing the third term?
We're going to put it back.
We'll put it back.
It doesn't matter,
but for the moment,
we're just concentrating on
the radial and time-like directions.
And then we'll put back the other one also.
But for the moment,
let's just concentrate on these two guys over here.
Okay,
here's what I want to do.
I want to focus and sort of zoom in,
zoom in on the place near r equals 2mg.
Sort of blow it up,
focus in on it,
which is just another way of saying we're going
to study this metric in the region
where r is almost equal to 2mg,
just to sort of blow
it up and see what's going on there.
Take a microscope and blow it up.
Okay,
let me first write it this way.
r minus 2mg over r.
I haven't done anything.
I've just written it as a numerator over a denominator.
Now,
I have a question.
I have to be careful.
We're only going to be interested.
Here's the horizon.
And I'm interested in the vicinity very,
very close to the horizon.
I want to explore that region very close to it,
which means I'm not going
to let r change very much.
If I don't let r change very much,
you would think I could
just set it equal to 2mg.
But then I would have a bit
of a problem with the numerator here.
I would have zero.
I don't want to do it with the numerator.
But in the denominator,
the denominator does not change much.
It doesn't become zero at r equals 2mg.
Nothing special happens to r
when it becomes equal to 2mg.
Implication is that in an approximation
where you just hover near the horizon,
you can set r equal to
2mg without losing any accuracy very,
very close to the horizon.
It's like in Newton's
equations or Newton's gravitational theory.
If you're near the surface of the Earth,
for many purposes,
you can set r equal
to the radius of the Earth.
You have to be a little bit careful about things which
go to zero and also things which can go to infinity.
And this is something which
can go to infinity over here.
So let's look at this.
This is r minus 2mg dt squared.
And this is the inverse.
2mg over r minus 2mg dr squared.
You know what I'm going
to do just to simplify this?
I don't want to carry along too much baggage.
I'm going to set the mass of
the black hole to be a specific number.
I'm going to set it equal to a
number so that 2mg is just equal to 1.
That will simplify our lives a lot here.
I can always do that.
That's a choice of units.
What are the units of 2mg?
Units of length.
2mg is the Schwarzschild radius.
There's units of length.
For a particular black hole,
I can choose units of length where
the Schwarzschild radius is just equal to 1.
I can't do it for all black holes simultaneously.
But if I'm interested in a particular black hole,
I can do that.
And that makes this formula much simpler.
Let's just do that.
Let's set 2mg equal to 1.
That's r minus 1 dt squared.
1 over r minus 1 dr squared.
What's the next step?
What?
The next step is to redefine
r minus 1 and call it xi.
Just a change of variables.
It's a change of variables which
measures r relative to the horizon.
Now the horizon is at r equals 1.
r equals 1 equals horizon.
So what we're going to do
is we're going to change coordinates again
so that our new coordinate is
just measuring distance from the horizon.
It's just measuring the deviation
of r from its horizon value.
Let's call r minus 1 xi.
This one becomes 1 over xi dr squared,
but dr and d xi are the same thing.
Let's see,
what was the definition?
xi is equal to r minus 1.
d xi is just equal to dr.
So this becomes d xi squared.
Exactly what...
No,
yes,
yes indeed.
Exactly what we have here.
What's going on?
What this is telling us is
that the vicinity of the horizon
is in some mysterious way just flat space.
Or approximately flat space.
Nothing dramatic is happening there.
Because by a coordinate transformation,
if by a coordinate transformation,
I can change the metric
so that it looks like this.
It's saying that to an approximation,
a good approximation,
the vicinity of the horizon is locally flat.
Nothing very dramatic going on.
No large curvature.
More or less flat space.
Now that's surprising,
but it's true.
Okay.
Is that the case?
You said that the hyperbolic coordinate system was flat,
but uniformly accelerated?
The uniformly accelerated coordinates,
yes.
But that doesn't mean that the space isn't flat.
Where is it next to the flat?
It's flat space in which there is a coordinate system
which is moving with uniform acceleration.
Why would we be interested in a coordinate system
for a gravitating object
which is mimicking uniform acceleration?
Well,
me standing here,
I am experiencing an acceleration
of 10 meters per second per second.
I feel exactly the same things that I would
if I were in free space
and the floor under me was accelerating upward
with 10 meters per second per second.
In studying a gravity system,
if you have a gravitating object
from the perspective of somebody standing still,
being supported,
let's say,
above the horizon
or wherever it is,
you're effectively doing physics
in a uniformly accelerated reference frame.
What does physics feel like there?
What does it do there?
It does whatever the
uniformly accelerated reference frame does.
And here we see,
we're just seeing exactly that.
We're seeing the vicinity of
the horizon of a black hole
is simply a uniformly accelerated coordinate system,
but the space itself,
the space-time itself is effectively flat.
Not much different than that.
In fact,
hardly different from that.
Now,
let's talk about
let's talk about this
inversion of space to time and time to space.
Alright?
C,
whoop,
C was equal to r minus 1.
Or,
if I put back mg,
it would be related to r minus 2mg.
I set 2mg equal to 1,
but what C is,
is it's really proportional to r minus 2mg.
C can change sign.
How does it change sign?
By going from outside the horizon
to inside the horizon.
So,
as I said before,
yes,
it makes sense,
at least in the black hole context here,
to say that C can change sign.
Does it make any sense in this flat space?
And if so,
what the,
where is negative C on this diagram?
So,
to answer that,
we go back and we say,
look,
here's what rho,
here's what C was.
C
was equal to rho squared over 4.
The 4 is not so interesting.
That's not the point here.
Forget the 4,
it's not important.
C is rho squared over 4.
Does it mean anything for,
for,
for rho squared to change sign?
How can rho squared change sign?
Rho squared is a,
rho is a positive number,
and rho squared,
or rho is a,
a real number,
its square is positive.
No,
that's not quite right.
The way you think about rho
is it's the rho squared
on the right-hand side of this equation.
Positive rho squared here
means a hyperbola
in this quadrant.
A hyperbola in this quadrant over here
has a positive rho squared.
It means that x squared is bigger than t squared.
x squared is certainly bigger than t squared
all along in,
in this entire quadrant.
x,
magnitude of x is bigger than the magnitude of t
in this whole quadrant here.
That's why rho squared is positive.
What does rho squared being negative mean?
It means that t squared is bigger than x squared.
It means you're up here,
let's forget the bottom and the left-hand side,
let's just concentrate on the,
on this quadrant and this quadrant for a moment.
Rho squared being negative
simply corresponds to the point
in the upper quadrant here.
That's what it means,
rho squared being negative.
So in going from c positive to c negative,
you're simply passing from here to here.
Imagine now that we wanted to
follow our way in,
yeah,
we wanted to follow our way in
till we got to c equals zero.
And then where would we go from there?
Here's what we're doing.
Yeah.
Here's omega equals zero.
And we're following rho,
we're following rho into the origin here,
at which point c changes sign.
So we're following rho,
where do we go from here
as if we're following omega equals zero
and letting c vary?
We don't go here.
We go here.
We jump into the upper plane.
So omega equals zero along here,
and omega equals zero here.
Here,
c is greater than zero.
c is less than zero.
So what has happened is,
yes,
a space-like coordinate,
namely c,
has jumped and become a time-like coordinate.
Omega,
which was this angular coordinate here,
what happens to it?
What happens if we vary omega in this quadrant?
We're moving along here.
Also a hyperboloid.
What's that?
Is it faster than light?
Yes.
But nothing,
it's just,
yes,
but they're just coordinates.
Coordinates can do anything you want.
No physical system is moving
faster than the speed of light.
Whether a system is moving
faster than the speed of light
is quite separate from whether a coordinate
is moving faster than the speed of light.
Right?
So these are just funny coordinates.
These are funny coordinates where rho goes,
or not rho,
sorry,
where c,
where c goes from being a space coordinate
to being a time coordinate,
and omega goes from being time-like in here
to being space-like in here.
However,
remember,
all this was just flat space.
There was nothing going on in the space.
Somebody who jumps through here,
sees nothing special.
There's nothing happening.
It's just peculiar coordinates
that have some funny behavior as
you go from one side to another.
The same is true of the Schwarzschild coordinates.
c is r minus 1 or r minus 2mg.
When this changes sign,
when you go from here to here,
you're doing exactly the same thing that
you do going from here to here.
Okay,
let's...
Let's go on a little bit
and think about the black hole now.
c is r minus 1.
Varying r means varying r until you get to 1.
That's the horizon,
or 2mg.
And then continuing to vary r,
you move up here.
That's the nature of these coordinates.
But eventually you'll get to r equals 0.
Here r is decreasing,
decreasing,
till it gets to 2mg.
And then it keeps decreasing
until you get to some point
where r is equal to 0.
Okay.
When r is equal to 0,
something nasty does happen.
something else is happening.
Where is r equals 0?
r equals 0 is over here.
Here's the horizon.
Inside,
interior to the horizon.
This thing has changed sign.
And guess what?
The singularity at r equals 0
is not a place.
It's a time.
It's not a place.
It's not a single place.
There are many different places,
all at the same...
all at...
Well,
they're not the same.
They're not all at the same time.
But this surface r equals 0
is not what you thought it was.
It wasn't a vertical line like this.
It was more horizontal and more space-like than time-like.
So there's r equals 0.
Pretty confusing,
right?
Very confusing.
But this is the way the black hole really is.
You'll get used to it.
If you think about it and you play with it...
You doubt it?
Well,
let me...
Some simple questions.
What if r becomes...
On that chart,
r could be negative
just by going past the...
geometrically just past that curve.
And you have two empty coordinates that...
I don't know what their physical significance would be.
The question is physically,
what happens to a system?
You say you can.
You said you can go.
You meant me.
You didn't know where.
Behind...
Negative r.
Where would you be if you went behind...
No,
maybe you'd be up here,
okay?
Right.
Maybe you'd be up here.
But the problem is you have to go through this.
Is r equals 0 still
the center of the black hole?
It is what it is.
You can think of it as
the center of the black hole.
But it's not.
But obviously it's a funny kind of center.
It would be a time,
not a place.
Yeah,
it's a time,
not a place.
If you like.
That's why you can't avoid it.
You can't avoid the future.
There's no way to escape from the future.
Here's a place.
This thing is a place.
I can avoid it.
I can go around it.
What I can't avoid is the future.
Okay?
That's why you can't avoid the singularity.
When you get in here.
Because no matter what you do,
it's always in your future.
And you will hit it.
Just like the clock will run down,
you'll hit it.
So the singularity is not avoidable the
way it would be in Newtonian physics
in which the center of coordinates is a place.
You can go around a place.
You can't go around a time.
So there we are.
That's the nature of the black hole singularity.
What about the horizon?
Well,
the horizon is over here.
But we're going to think about
it a little bit differently eventually.
We're going to think about this
whole line as being a horizon.
But let's erase some of this.
And,
yeah.
On your diagram there,
when you first drew it,
you drew those two axes
that actually aren't quite perpendicular.
Wait,
this and this?
No,
those are the ones you draw through second.
The two that are out there that make an X.
What are those exactly?
Those are light cones.
Those are light-like directions.
Oh,
okay.
Got it.
Thanks.
Those are light-like directions.
So the particles come in at
a W equal or minus some number?
Yeah.
A particle might start out over here,
come in,
and pass through there.
All right,
now this figure explains something to us.
This figure allows us to understand much better this
idea that it takes an infinite amount of time
for a thing to fall through the horizon,
at least an infinite amount of coordinate time,
but still it falls through in its own timekeeping.
It falls through in a finite time.
So let's redraw it and
see if we can understand that.
Same picture.
And now let's draw what the time slices look like.
These are the different times.
Omega is like time.
What was the relation between,
where did I write it down?
Yeah.
In comparing this over here,
yeah,
what was the relation?
The t,
t was omega over 2 or?
Omega is t over 2.
Right.
So time is simply this angular coordinate.
Position is constant along these hyperbolas.
Now let's imagine somebody throws in,
I don't know,
Alice throws Bob into the black hole.
Alice stays outside.
Bob goes in.
Alice has coordinates which are
just these polar type coordinates,
omega.
Where?
Here's omega equals 0.
Here's omega equals 1.
Here's omega equals 2.
Here's omega equals 3.
Here's omega equals 4.
Oops,
not very good.
Omega equals 4.
Omega asymptotically goes to infinity when you
get up to this light-like direction here.
So Alice,
she says,
infinitely late time corresponds to this surface over here.
In fact,
if she's looking back and watching Bob,
she looks back,
she looks back.
and it's not until an infinite amount
of her time has transpired that she
actually sees Bob go through the horizon.
In other words,
she never sees Bob go
through the horizon.
According to her reckoning,
it takes an infinite amount of
omega before Bob falls through the horizon.
That translates to an infinite
amount of t in these coordinates.
On the other hand,
just looking at the diagram,
you can see immediately that the amount
of proper time between here and here is
finite.
Just an ordinary trajectory,
nothing special happening to it.
It's
ticking off time,
there it is,
a finite amount of time in order for this object
to fall through the horizon,
to fall through this surface here.
It is the
horizon but we'll come back to that.
So it's a
quite,
quite unorthodox,
but this is a very well-known metric.
I can show you the
coordinate property,
a funny coordinate property,
that Alice's reckoning is that Bob takes an
infinite amount of time to fall through the horizon.
Not so,
says Bob.
It only took a finite amount of time.
I watched it in my clock.
But the reason for the discrepancy is
this discrepancy between proper time and coordinate time.
Alice uses coordinate time.
Bob uses proper time.
Alice is undergoing uniform acceleration.
Yeah.
Alice is staying outside the black hole.
She's,
like I am now,
undergoing uniform acceleration.
She's standing on the floor above
the horizon of the black hole,
and so she's moving like this.
If she were actually to watch,
let's just imagine her looking back.
She looks back,
and at this instant over here,
where does she see Bob?
She sees Bob back over here.
She sees Bob over here.
In other words,
she has to look back in
time simply because it takes time,
like some time to get to her.
A little bit later,
she sees Bob over here.
She can wait forever,
and she will not see Bob cross that line.
Okay.
On the other hand,
Bob crosses the line as far as he's concerned.
He doesn't see anything peculiar.
Bob sees Alice?
Hmm?
How will Bob see Alice?
Ah.
Okay,
let's look at it.
Let's see how Bob sees Alice.
Well,
before I answer that,
let's just say one more thing.
Alice obviously sees Bob slow down.
Why does he slow down?
Because it takes an infinite amount of time,
or a very large amount of time from her perspective,
to go from here to there.
To go from here to there,
it takes a huge amount of time.
Each heartbeat of Bob takes longer
and longer from her point of view.
So Alice sees Bob slow down.
What does Bob see?
Sorry,
what is that?
Bob,
what does Bob see?
All right,
so let's draw that.
Here's Bob.
He just does that.
He has Alice out here,
and Bob looks back.
He sees Alice over here.
He looks back.
He looks back right at this point where he crosses.
He sees nothing special.
Even after he passes through,
Alice can never see Bob at that point,
but Bob has no trouble seeing Alice.
So Bob sees nothing special.
He doesn't see Alice speed up.
He doesn't see Alice
shrink.
He sees,
he does see Alice accelerating away from him.
That's true.
He sees Alice accelerating away from him,
but that's all.
He sees Alice,
but at any point,
he sees Alice
perfectly normal,
except accelerating away from him.
What was her motion?
Alice,
she's moving with uniform acceleration.
She's moving with uniform acceleration.
That's because she's standing on the floor.
She's standing on the floor at a fixed R.
Remember,
here we have,
um...
She's in orbit.
She could be in orbit.
Yeah.
Or she could just be standing on
a platform that's built above the black hole.
Imagine a platform,
or suspended.
Suspended from a very,
very distant object.
Or suspended from a very,
Whatever way is required to keep her just
at a fixed height above the black hole.
A fixed height above the black
hole corresponds to a trajectory like that.
Bob looks back.
Nothing special happens to Alice
when Bob crosses this point.
On the other hand,
from Alice's perspective,
she never sees Bob cross that point.
It takes forever from her perspective.
So it's very asymmetric,
and it is asymmetric.
It's bizarre.
I'm going to...
When does Bob hit the...
The singularity.
All right.
So up here is the
singularity someplace at R equals zero.
Bob hits the singularity right over here.
By that point,
the...
The tidal forces will have become so large
that Bob will no longer be with us.
I mean,
Bob will have been destroyed by
the time he gets to here.
That's why we don't think about...
We don't think about trying to answer the question,
what does Bob see when he gets,
let's say,
to negative R.
By the time he gets to negative R,
he has experienced infinitely strong tidal forces,
and there is no more Bob.
His proper time is small t?
No,
his proper time is tau.
Tau is proper time.
Okay.
That's what Bob measures along here.
He's going parallel to t too.
He's going parallel to t.
Oh,
oh,
in here,
inside.
Yeah,
inside,
in this quadrant here,
Bob would probably use R for time.
Or something like R for time.
Yeah.
Inside here.
R is varying from here to here from,
uh,
from,
from here to here.
From R equals 2mg here to R equals 0 here.
So his clocks would,
uh,
have more to do with R than T.
And T would be more like position in here.
Okay?
But as I said,
he doesn't feel any funny thing
happening with space where his clock starts,
becomes a meter stick,
and his meter stick becomes a clock.
Nothing like that.
He just sails through happily.
Now,
I think it's...
apparent that this line over here is rather special.
It's rather special in
that anything that crosses behind here,
anything that crosses behind here,
cannot
escape.
We'll eventually remember in
the coordinates that we're using,
light moves
with a 45 degree angles in here.
Light moves with 45 degree angles in these
in these coordinates,
and so light cannot escape out here,
it cannot escape out to
here.
All it can do is eventually hit the singularity,
and anything that's moving
slower than the speed of
light will also hit the singularity.
So anybody who finds
himself in this quadrant in here,
is doomed.
Somebody out here has the possibility of escaping.
Well let's talk about light
rays.
If a light ray is moving radially outward here,
it will escape.
It'll simply just
keep going.
If it's pointing radially inward,
it of course will,
it's also doomed,
it
will hit the singularity,
and there's everything in between.
If the light ray is
pointing outward it may fall in,
depending on whether it's beyond the
photon radius or not.
But this is the picture that
you want to get used to.
If you want to understand and you want to be able
to resolve funny paradoxes about who sees what in a black hole,
go back to
this picture.
Remember that Alice's time on
the outside...Alice who was far away,
or
Alice who is far away,
Moving with Uniform Acceleration-heracks policies
record this hyperbolic angle as time.
Bob's clocks record proper time and it's
that mismatch,
it's that mismatch which is
governing all of the peculiarities of
motion near a black hole.
Okay I think we are through no yeah.
So with a black hole
forms,
supernova or whatever it is.
So what happens to all the matter from our perspective
outside the black hole?
I mean is some of it trapped
inside and some of it on the surface?
Let's talk about what Alice sees
who stays outside the black hole.
Alice,
now we are
speaking about classical black holes,
we're not doing quantum mechanics,
Alice sees all
of the matter.
So what happens to all the matter that
forms a black hole not falling into the horizon
but sort of a kind of sedimentary
motion with everything just asymptotically getting closer
and closer to the horizon,
closer and closer and closer,
flattening out and forming a kind
of a sedimentary structure,
a layered structure which
just asymptotically migrates closer
and closer to the horizon.
And this is the matter that formed the black hole?
Yeah.
That's the matter that formed the black hole?
Now.
All this information is like mirrored in the world.
That way.
All the information is smearing on the radius.
So does this mean that that person
can now view the history of everything that
has ever happened in terms of objects falling
into the black hole?
So.
.
How does James,
James is that him?
I'm not sure what happened to Charlie.
Can we do Charlie?
Charlie is okay?
Okay.
Charlie comes late and what does he see?
Alright,
so the first statement is to see anything,
light has to come from it.
If Charlie can see Bob,
it's because Bob is emitting light.
Now,
um,
Charlie sees Bob's clocks slow down.
As far as he's concerned,
all of Bob's clocks are
moving slower and slower and slower.
But that also means that Bob's light sources
are emitting,
let's suppose for the moment,
that Bob is sending out pulsed signals.
One signal per microsecond.
And what Charlie sees is at first he
sees signals coming out roughly at one per microsecond.
And a little bit later it's one per second.
And somewhat later it's one every ten seconds.
They get stretched out more and more and more.
Why is that?
Because again,
that ratio of factors there.
And as Bob gets closer and closer to the horizon,
there's a bigger and
bigger stretch between neighboring pulses.
If we translate that into frequency of light,
it's saying that the frequency of light is getting,
the frequency of light emitted by Bob.
Bob thinks he has a flashlight that sends light
at a particular frequency.
He thinks his frequency is whatever is 10
to the blah blah blah cycles per second.
But the light is redshifted
as far as Alice is concerned,
or as far as Charlie is concerned.
The light is getting more
and more and more progressively redshifted.
So what Bob sends out as
conventional optical light will arrive
at either Alice or Charlie
first as conventional light,
then as infrared,
then as microwaves,
then as radio waves,
then longer and longer radio waves.
And of course,
a given number of photons in radio
waves is a weaker and weaker signal,
less and less energy.
So the fact is that Charlie,
after a long,
long period of time,
simply will not in any practical way see Bob.
He'll see Bob's light having been shifted into the very,
very,
very far radio,
which becomes harder and harder to detect.
So the answer is that Charlie will see nothing.
But if he's capable of keeping track of these very,
very faint,
long,
long wavelength radio waves,
then he will just see Bob slow down.
What does it mean to you
when you say something becomes a time,
like the singularity becomes a time?
You've studied black holes.
How do you interpret that?
No more and no less than this picture.
What it means is that every trajectory in here,
that is moving with slower than the speed of light,
will hit it.
Will get terminated at some point.
That's what it means.
That's all it means is
that any trajectory starting from here
cannot avoid it and will eventually hit it
in some specified amount of time along the trajectory.
That's all.
So I'm back to the formation of a black hole.
Well,
let me say one other thing.
There's a technical thing.
It says that this surface is space-like.
It says that the surface is space-like,
that all directions within the surface,
within the surface,
all those directions are space-like,
and there is no time-like direction within that surface.
So I asked this question last time,
but from Alice's perspective,
she'll never see anything get into a black hole.
Right.
So from Alice's perspective,
it's clear that from Alice's perspective,
a black hole can't get bigger or ever even form.
Well,
it can get bigger.
How?
If something goes into it,
how can it get bigger?
As a massive object moves toward the horizon,
the horizon comes out to meet it.
Why?
For that,
you have to solve Einstein's equations.
But in fact,
that's what happens.
The horizon comes out to meet it,
meets it at some point,
it blends in with the horizon,
or it...
And then this bulge in the horizon
spreads over the whole thing
and increases the size of it,
but still,
with the points of this thing coming in here
always being on the outside.
Yeah.
Suppose we have to...
This huge mass in the middle
of an extremely large dust cloud.
Mm-hmm.
And the dust is slowly collapsing in on the mass.
Right.
The mass isn't big enough
to form a black hole yet,
but at some point it would reach that mass
and begin to collapse.
So it seems like,
from our perspective,
there is definitely mass inside the black hole
going all the way to the center,
right?
Somebody watching it from the outside.
From the outside.
From the outside,
we'll not see any of
the mass pass through the horizon.
No,
maybe it was there before the horizon formed,
is what I'm saying.
Yeah,
there's no Schwarzschild radius when it starts.
When it starts,
yeah.
Right.
So we've got this big mass
in the middle of all this dust,
and finally enough mass accumulates
to undergo the gravitational collapse,
right?
Right.
And you'll get a Schwarzschild radius out there.
But we've seen,
we know the mass is at the center,
so how do we now all of
a sudden see it on the surface?
We're going to do the
problem of creating a black hole
by an infalling shell of material,
and we're going to see
exactly what happens with the horizon.
Let me not try to
get ahead of you right now.
I think next time we will work out
the picture that goes with an infalling shell of matter,
no black hole to start with.
When the infalling shell passes its Schwarzschild radius,
there will be a black hole there.
The horizon actually begins before that.
The horizon begins at the center,
grows out to meet the infalling shell.
What happens,
you know...
All right,
so here you have r equals zero
with no black hole yet,
okay?
Somebody throws in an infalling shell of matter.
It would come in.
It would look like this.
Here's the...
Can you see the shell of matter falling in?
Okay,
the shell of matter is falling in.
It gets to r equals zero right over there.
Okay?
But before it gets to the origin,
at some earlier time,
a horizon starts growing from here,
and that horizon looks something like this.
Something like that.
No light can ever escape
from inside the horizon to outside,
because to do so,
it would have to go
faster than the speed of light.
So that means that Alice,
looking back,
will see a light ray coming from here,
from here,
and if she tracks it all the way back,
it will come from here.
She will never see...
She will never see this shell
passing through the horizon over here.
She'll look back and she'll see the shell...
As she gets later and later,
she'll look back and she'll see that shell
getting closer and closer to the horizon,
but never passing it.
But we're going to do that problem.
We're going to do that problem in detail.
Fortunately,
we don't have to do any equations,
just pictures for that.
Any light we see between 2g and 2g?
Any light that we see that
is coming from between 2g and 3g?
Must be...
Coming from where?
Some region...
If you see a light which is...
appears to be between 2g and 3g,
then it must be...
2g...
2gm and 3gm,
yes.
Then the source must be there within that radius,
right?
The source of the light...
Who has to be there?
The source of the light
must be between those two regions.
The source of the light,
yes.
Well,
if we see the source of the light in there,
yes.
I mean,
it cannot be something which is from the background
and then causing that region and coming out.
If we see a source
of light between 2gm and 3gm,
we see a source of light.
No,
we can't,
can we?
Didn't you say light can't escape if it's inside 3gm?
No,
it can escape if it's moving radially outward.
No.
Here's 2gm,
that's the horizon,
here's 3gm.
If we discover a light ray over here
that happens to be moving...
Let's say in that direction,
we can be sure that it's going to fall in.
If we see a light ray in that direction,
no problem,
that light ray will escape.
If we see a light ray in that direction,
we know it won't escape.
So at any given...
Yeah,
at any given distance,
you can divide the different directions
into those which fall in
and those which don't fall in.
If you're at this point here
and you consider a tangential light ray,
in other words,
one moving with fixed radial distance,
that one will fall in.
Not so if it's out beyond the photon sphere.
If it's out beyond the photon sphere,
it'll move out.
If it's inside the photon sphere,
it'll fall in.
But as long as you're outside 2gm,
then a radially outgoing light ray will get out.
Okay?
Yeah.
Does that also mean that any light ray
which comes out through that photon sphere
has to originate in between that photon sphere
and the horizon
and can't have come from outside the photon sphere?
Can light cut through the photon sphere?
Um,
no.
No,
I see what you're asking.
Okay,
so let's...
I think you're asking...
I think.
Here's the horizon,
here's the photon sphere.
And I think you're asking whether a light ray
can go in and come back out?
No.
Because if it went in and came back out,
there would be some point
at which it was moving tangentially.
And once it's moving tangentially,
it'll fall in.
So no,
a light ray cannot...
come in and go out of the photon sphere.
It's another property of the photon sphere.
But,
if...
On the other hand,
if somebody,
it doesn't have to...
Somebody who...
Some poor unhappy person
who has fallen through,
his motion is such that he knows that he's doomed,
he can still send out a light ray
radially outward that will get out.
Yeah.
Not so when he passes the horizon.
Once past the horizon,
no way to communicate with the outside.
The only limitation is that
he will have to send the
light ray pretty close to radially out,
or at least not too...
not too shallow an angle here.
Question.
Yeah.
If Bob and Alice were suspended
just outside of...
Mm-hmm.
What hole could they communicate?
Any idea?
If Bob and Alice were suspended...
Right.
...at some constant elevation...
Yeah.
...could they communicate with each other?
走
Even inside the light?
Ah,
ah,
that's an interesting question.
Um,
okay.
Yeah,
I think if they're a little bit,
just a little bit inside,
and they're suspended,
as you say,
suspended,
just a little bit inside,
a light ray which is just a little bit inside,
and which is moving in a tangential direction,
will go around many times before it falls in.
So,
yes,
they can communicate.
Now,
um,
okay,
so there's an interesting question
to which I'm not exactly sure what the answer is.
Supposing they were in diametrically
opposed positions at some r,
what are the limits on whether they can communicate?
I think,
I suspect there must be a distance
beyond which they can communicate.
I'll work that out.
It's not hard to work out.
Um,
but I don't know the answer offhand.
But as long as they're
sufficiently close to this point here,
yeah,
they can,
uh...
But even in that case,
they could always send out radially out,
which would then turn in and come back,
right?
Yeah,
that's right.
That's correct.
They could have,
they could have,
um,
uh,
Charlie out here.
Alice can send the message to Charlie.
Charlie can take that message
move around to here perfectly nicely in orbit
and then send the message into Charlie.
So they can communicate.
Even in the,
in the sphere,
they could actually just get an angle where...
Yeah,
yeah.
but there's clearly no ultimate limitation on them,
um,
on them,
uh,
communicating.
It's just the range goes down.
There's only one special angle that can do it.
Yeah,
as they move closer and closer to the horizon,
they,
yeah,
I think they can still communicate.
The way they communicate is Alice can send out
almost radially outward,
almost directly radially outward,
and it doesn't even have to be a light ray.
It could be,
you know,
a rock.
She throws out a rock
with enough velocity to almost escape,
and it comes back and whack.
Yeah,
so,
yeah,
so they can,
they can communicate.
All right.
Okay,
good.
Till next week.
For more,
please visit us at stanford.edu.