Stanford University.
We want to come now,
we're not going to get
deep into solving Einstein's field equations.
They're awfully damn complicated.
If you were to sit down,
even to write them down explicitly is complicated.
If you really wanted to write them down.
As I said before,
the principles of general relativity are pretty simple,
but it's computationally nasty.
Almost everything you try to do gets complicated fast.
There's a lot of Christoffel symbols.
I forget how many,
but a lot of them,
independent ones,
even more elements of the curvature tensor.
Each Christoffel symbol has a bunch of derivatives.
The curvature tensor has more derivatives.
The equations get complicated.
Hard to write on a single piece of paper.
The best way to solve them,
in fact,
the best way to even write them down
is just to feed them into your computer and Mathematica.
Mathematica will spit out answers whenever it can.
But on the other hand,
as I said,
basic principles are simple,
but going anywhere past the basic things
tends to be computationally intensive.
So we won't do much computation.
We'll just concentrate on the meaning of the symbols.
And then I'll tell you what happens when
you try to solve them in various circumstances.
We may get a chance to
do a little bit of solving.
But I can't provide the next 10 or 20 minutes,
so I don't think I'm going to
do a whole lot of work crazy.
Think about it like,
in physics.
If we take a material,
a certain material,
let's say this is based on Set
sail and whether you're thinking about gravity,
concept of field equations,
but nevertheless there are field equations
which are equivalent to Newton.
Okay so first of all it's always a sort of
two-way street that masses affect
the gravitational field and the gravitational
field affects the way masses move.
John Wheeler had some way to say it which was
very clever,
I can't remember what it was.
Something like that.
Always these two-way things,
so let's talk about the two-way street in the
context of Newton.
First of all,
field affects particles.
That's just a
statement of F force on a particle,
gravitational force
on a particle,
and it's a constant.
It's a constant.
So if the force on a particle is
on a particle,
can be written as minus m
times the gradient of the gravitational potential.
The gradient of the gravitational potential,
the gravitational potential
I usually write as phi,
and phi is a function of position.
Okay so everywhere is in space due
to whatever,
to whatever reason,
everywhere is in space there
is a gravitational potential called
phi of x,
and it varies from place to place.
You multiply it by m,
the mass of the object,
and you take the gradient and that
tells you the force on the object.
That's one aspect of field phi
of x tells particles how to move,
and in this case
by telling them what their accelerations are.
So if you look at
the gravitational potential of a particle,
you can see that the acceleration
should be,
if we write that this is equal to ma,
and the m's cancel,
and we just have the rule
that acceleration is equal to minus
the gradient of the gravitational potential.
Okay so that's
field tells particles how to move,
and on the other hand masses in space
are all the same.
The equation that tells the gravitational field what to be
is the equation,
Poisson's equation,
does everybody know what del squared phi means?
Del squared phi means the second partial of phi
with respect to x squared plus the second partial
of phi with respect to y
squared plus the same thing with z.
It's called del squared phi
Is equal
To something which on the right
hand side has the distribution of masses
Which are the things which are
causing the field to be there
All right,
so what is on the right hand side?
4 pi
That's a convention.
Well,
it's it's not completely a convention,
but there's a 4 pi
That yeah,
it is a convention because
another factor here is Newton's constant
And if you don't like 4 pi's
you can absorb them into Newton's constant
They'll reappear in other places
So don't think you're getting away with it
by not putting the 4 pi here Newton's constant
6.7 times 10 to the
minus 11 meters per blah blah,
whatever it is
Times one other thing the density of mass
The density of mass is a function of position
It's also a function of time masses can move
around so on the right hand side we have
mass densities
Sources on the left hand side.
We have the gravitational field 5
All right,
so we have these two aspects field
tells particles how to move and mass
Particles in other words mass tells particles how to move
field how to curve,
well how to do whatever it is that it does.
You can solve
this equation in particular in a special case,
in the special case where rho,
first of all
what does rho mean?
Rho means the amount of mass per unit volume,
mass per volume
in the case where rho of x is concentrated,
let's call it a star,
doesn't have to be a star,
it could be a planet,
it could be a bowling ball,
but let's say a spherically symmetric object,
a completely spherically symmetric object of total mass m,
and it does not matter whether
the mass is uniformly distributed in there,
meaning to say it has to
be symmetric with respect to rotation,
but it could be more dense
in the inside than the outside,
doesn't matter.
Once you get on the outside
of where there is any mass,
once you get out beyond
the region where there is mass,
you can solve the equation uniquely
and the solution of the equation is
phi is equal to minus the total mass
times g,
the g is there because there's
a g in the source equation here,
mass,
that's the integrated amount of total mass,
divided by r.
That solves this equation.
If you take this phi,
which depends on position,
and you calculate del squared,
you will find that it's
zero everywhere outside of the equation.
So this is the solution outside.
This is the outside solution.
I don't care about anything but the outside solution,
so I might as well shrink this to a point.
If I shrunk it down to a point,
then this solution would be
valid everywhere except at that point.
The point has a total mass m.
So that would then be Newton's equations.
If I then plug this in,
Excuse me,
question?
Yeah.
So in this case,
rho is constant on the inside of that mass and
No,
not necessarily constant,
just
Symmetric,
yeah.
And zero outside.
So it's discontinuous at the boundary.
Not necessarily.
The mass density could go to zero.
Right.
But it doesn't matter.
That doesn't matter.
Okay.
The point is that if
I take phi written this way,
and then I take its gradient,
it just puts another r downstairs,
differentiating one over r with respect to radius,
which is what del does,
makes it one over r squared,
and winds up giving you
f is equal to little m,
the mass of the particle,
big M,
Newton's constant,
divided by the mass of the particle.
And then I divide it by r squared.
So it's all there.
And this is a field way,
a field,
kind of primitive field theoretic
way to think about gravitation.
Instead of action at a distance,
we have a gravitational field.
It's still really action at
a distance because in Newton's theory,
if you move around the mass,
phi instantly reacts to it and changes.
But it's a way of writing the theory,
making it look like a field theory.
Okay.
This is the thing that we want to replace.
Right here,
we want to replace by
something which makes sense relativistically,
which makes sense in general relativity.
Just to get a little bit
of a handle to get started,
let's remember something about the Schwarzschild geometry.
We pulled the Schwarzschild geometry out of a hat.
Of course,
the point is that it's a solution of Einstein's equations.
This is Newton's equation.
It's a solution of Einstein's equations.
But let's just remember what we wrote down.
We wrote down a metric.
I'm not going to write the whole thing.
I'm just going to remind you what g00 was.
The time-time component of the metric
was 1 minus 2mg over r.
Oh,
I erased what the solution was,
didn't I?
Let me put back the solution for a minute.
Phi equals minus mg over r.
Okay.
Now let's write Schwarzschild over here.
The only part of it that I'm interested in right now
is just to remind you g00 is 1 minus 2mg over r.
I've set the speed of light
everywhere as equal to 1 as usual.
c is equal to 1.
I don't need this equation.
And now I see that...
To the extent that this can be identified,
that 1 minus 2mg over r
can be identified with anything over here,
we could think of this
then as something like del squared...
Let's see,
I want to get the sign right.
I always have trouble with the sign here.
I think it's del squared g00.
Is it minus or plus?
I have written down plus,
but I think I mean minus because of this sign,
because of that sign here.
Del squared of g00...
g00 is just 1 minus...
Oh,
it's 1 plus 2 phi.
It's equal to 1 plus 2 phi.
1 plus 2 phi.
So del squared g00 is just twice del squared phi.
The 1...
That has no derivatives.
Derivative of 1 is 0.
Del squared g00 is just twice del squared of phi.
So del squared g00 is equal not
to 4pi but to 8pi g rho.
Now this should be taken with a grain of salt.
This is just a mnemonic.
A mnemonic device to remember the relationship
between some aspects of general relativity and matter.
So already this begins to sound like
matter or mass is affecting the geometry.
When we make this correspondence between
Newton's phi and Einstein's or Schwarzschild's...
metric,
we see that roughly it looks like...
I use the word roughly because
we're going to be more precise,
but it has the rough texture of del
squared of g00 is equal to 8pi g rho.
Matter telling geometry how to curve,
so to speak.
Okay.
All right.
But of course this is not Einstein's equations here.
Einstein's equations are a good
deal more complicated than that.
Oh,
the other half of the story,
of course,
is that in general relativity,
this equation over here is replaced by
the statement that once you know the geometry,
once you know g00,
the rule is particles move on spacetime geodesics.
So this equation becomes,
is replaced by the geodesic rule.
And...
the Newtonian field equation...
is replaced by something...
which I'm...
kind of naively just writing in this form.
We're going to do better.
We're going to figure out exactly...
Well,
Einstein figured out exactly what goes there.
Okay.
Before we do and before
we write down the field equations...
we need to understand more about the right-hand side.
The right-hand side is the density of matter,
density of mass.
Mass really means energy.
E equals mc squared.
If we...
forget about c and set it equal to one,
then energy and mass are the same thing.
And so really what goes on
the right-hand side is energy density.
We need to understand more what kind
of quantity in relativity energy density is.
It's part of a complex of things...
which includes more than just the energy density.
It's part of a complex.
In other words,
it's part of some kind of tensor...
whose other components...
have other meanings.
So let's go back and review quickly...
a little bit about the notion of...
conservation.
In this case,
conservation of energy and momentum.
In a simpler case that we're
going to discuss in a moment,
conservation of charge.
Conservation...
densities...
flows of...
things like charge and mass.
And let's just review a little
bit that we've gone through before.
But let's do it again.
Let me start with electric charge.
Electric charge is simpler than energy
for reasons we will come to.
Electric charge,
the total electric charge of
a system we can call Q.
That's a standard notation for electric charge,
Q.
I don't know where it comes from.
Charge density...
In many situations,
charge density is called rho.
But I don't want to confuse it with
the energy density or the mass density over here.
So I'm going to give it another name.
I'm going to call the charge density sigma.
And what is charge density?
Charge density is you take a small volume...
a differential small volume.
You take the total amount of charge in there,
divide it by the volume.
So it's charge per unit volume.
Uh...
In the limit of small volume.
Differential volume.
Okay,
and we'll call that sigma.
Sigma equals schematically...
Q divided by volume.
At least it has units of charge divided by volume.
We could draw this in another way.
Here's...
if we draw time this way...
and space this way...
and draw a little element of space over here.
Now that little element of space...
a little volume of space...
in this picture is two-dimensional.
Why is it two-dimensional,
that little element of space?
Because I didn't draw the third dimension,
that's all.
Alright,
it's really three-dimensional,
but it's too hard to draw it on a blackboard.
And now we have some charge which is moving around...
and passes into that little region there.
There's other charges...
out here which don't pass through it.
When I want to count the
charge in a volume of space...
at a given instant of time...
it's almost like asking...
for the charges which pass through...
a little cubic area here...
which is now being represented as a little square area.
Alright,
so it's charge per unit volume.
And you can draw it like this.
Now,
next concept.
This is sigma.
The next concept is the flow of charge...
also called current.
Now what we do is we take a little window...
Let's forget this picture for a moment.
We take a little window in space...
This is a window in space now.
It's a window...
You know,
like a window...
Our room doesn't have windows.
But I mean literally a small window.
It's not necessarily where the window is.
It's any place I want to put it.
It can orient itself in any direction.
The window is characterized by an area...
which I'll take to be infinitely small...
infinitesimal.
An orientation...
and a sense of direction through the window.
A window pointing that way...
is the opposite of a window pointing that way.
Alright,
so this window is characterized...
by a little area...
and an orientation,
an angle...
and a sense along it.
The current has to do with the amount of charge...
passing through that window...
per unit time,
per unit area.
Windows have areas,
they don't have volumes.
Alright?
But we also have to have a clock...
and allow the clock to proceed...
for a small amount of time...
in order to ask how much charge...
flows through that window...
per unit time.
Charge...
J...
And in particular,
if the window is oriented...
along the XM axis...
X1,
X2,
X3...
or X,
Y,
and Z...
If the window...
is oriented along the XM axis...
then JM...
is a vector...
which is equal to the charge...
through that window...
per unit area...
per unit time.
Now,
in this case here...
sigma was a charge divided by...
a product of three lengths...
of volume.
Here it's a charge...
divided by a product of two lengths...
times a time.
But in relativity...
time and space are nice and symmetric...
to each other.
So this dividing by area...
times time is again dividing by three...
three lengths.
One happens to be time-like...
two happen to be space-like.
But it has the same units as sigma...
if C is set equal to one.
If C is set equal to one...
then space and time...
have the same units.
And both of these can be thought of...
as charge through a window.
In this case the window is completely...
three space dimensions.
In this case the window is...
two space dimensions...
and one time dimension.
But they're similar creatures.
Sigma,
the charge density...
and the current of charge...
this is called current...
space current of charge...
those four things together...
form a four vector.
They form a four vector...
in the sense of relativity.
Sigma and J sub M together...
form a four vector...
J sub mu...
or super mu.
With...
J zero...
being the charge density...
and J one,
J two,
and J three...
being the three components...
of the current.
All right?
Good.
One more thing...
conservation of charge.
Conservation of charge...
is a local idea.
What do I mean by saying it's local?
Well,
conservation of charge...
could allow...
just sheer conservation...
could allow a charge...
this blackboard eraser...
may have a little bit of charge on it...
might allow it to disappear over here...
and instantaneously appear over here.
In fact...
it could disappear over here...
and reappear at Alpha Centauri.
I always use Alpha Centauri...
as some place which is so far away...
that it doesn't matter.
And once we would...
and that would mean...
that if that were possible...
you would say,
well,
charge is conserved...
but I would say,
who cares if charge is conserved...
if it can just disappear?
If it can just disappear arbitrarily...
to some very distant place...
it's...
it's just as good as saying...
it didn't...
wasn't conserved.
In my laboratory...
it just disappears.
Charge doesn't disappear that way.
If it leaves the laboratory...
it passes through the walls of the laboratory.
That means...
it passes through windows.
That means it cannot leave the laboratory...
without a current flowing...
and that current has to flow out of the walls.
That idea...
is called continuity...
and there's an equation that goes with it.
The equation is the continuity...
equation.
If I take a little box...
and I look at all the charges...
passing out through the walls...
all the flow of charges...
if I...
I'm interested in the charge per unit time...
that disappears out of the box...
let's say it's a unit box...
then the amount of charge in that unit box...
is just sigma...
if the volume is equal to one...
in some units...
the charge per unit time...
that is leaving the box...
is minus...
sigma dot.
Why minus?
Because it's leaving the box.
If it's leaving the box...
sigma is getting smaller.
That has to be equal
to the sum of the currents...
passing out through the box...
and by...
some Gauss theorem or something...
that's just equal to the divergence...
of the current.
The same current here.
The divergence of the current...
is simply the total amount of current...
passing out of that small box...
the divergence of the current...
inside...
in the vicinity of the box...
that's the current passing out...
and this says...
that sigma dot...
is minus the divergence of the current.
We can also write this of course...
as...
well first of all we can write it as...
sigma dot plus...
the divergence of the current is equal to zero.
Sigma dot...
means...
the derivative of sigma with respect...
to time...
and this means...
the various components of the...
derivative of the current...
with respect...
to the corresponding...
direction of space.
So that current is...
a three vector current.
It's a three vector current.
Is equal to zero.
And now...
if I write that sigma...
is J naught...
this just becomes...
a nice elegant...
and that T...
is X naught...
sigma is J naught...
this just becomes a nice equation...
that...
derivative of Jm...
J mu...
space time index...
not just space index...
space time index J mu...
with respect to X mu...
is equal to zero.
Incidentally,
I suppose if I wanted...
to be really systematic...
I would put a sum over M here.
Sigma dot...
the sigma by DT...
plus sum on M...
the J1...
by the X1...
the J2 by the X2...
the J3 by the X3...
and that becomes...
the derivative of J mu with respect to X mu...
where I have now used the summation convention.
Here...
summation convention implied...
or implicit...
same thing...
is equal to zero.
So it becomes a nice tensor type equation...
J is a four vector...
X...
four components of space...
and...
this has the nice look of a...
good equation...
the derivative of a tensor...
with respect to position.
In curved coordinates...
in general if you had a thing like this...
in curved coordinates...
this would be correct in ordinary coordinates...
you might replace this...
by...
the covariant derivative.
Remember about covariant derivatives of tensors...
It turns out...
in this case it doesn't matter...
for charge currents it doesn't matter...
but in general it would matter...
when you go to curved coordinates...
you should replace all derivatives...
by covariant derivatives.
Otherwise...
the equations are not good...
tensor equations.
Why do you want tensor equations?
You want tensor equations because...
you want them to be
true in any set of coordinates.
Alright,
so anyway that's the theory of...
electric charge...
flow...
current...
and the continuity equation.
This is called the continuity equation...
and the physics of it
is that when charge either reappears...
sorry...
appears or disappears in a small volume...
it is always traceable to...
currents flowing into or out...
through the boundaries of that region.
Now let's come...
to energy and momentum.
Energy and momentum are also conserved...
quantities.
They can be described...
in terms of density of energy...
density of momentum...
density of each component...
of momentum.
You can ask how much...
energy...
is in the form of particles
or whatever it happens to be...
including the...
mc squared part of the energy.
You can ask how much energy is in a volume...
You can ask how much...
momentum is in a volume...
Just look at all the particles within a volume...
and count up their momentum.
Photons or electromagnetic radiation...
has both energy and momentum...
and that energy and momentum...
can be regarded as...
the integral...
of a density.
So in that sense...
each one of them...
each...
the energy...
and each component...
of the momentum...
are like the charge.
They're conserved...
they can flow...
If an object or a thing is moving...
then the momentum and energy...
may be flowing...
and the question is how do
we represent the same set of ideas...
for energy and momentum.
Now...
there's a difference...
between charge...
and energy and momentum.
Electric charge...
is an invariant.
No matter how the charge...
is moving...
the charge of an electron...
is always the same.
The charge of an electron...
does not depend on its...
state of motion.
Therefore charge itself...
is an invariant.
Charge is invariant...
the...
density of charge...
and the current of charge...
are not invariants.
For example...
if I have a given charge...
and I look at it in a...
different frame of reference...
here's my charge...
but I walk by it...
I have trouble doing it...
I walk by it with a certain velocity...
I think I did that pretty well,
didn't I?
Yeah...
okay...
I'll try it again...
Yeah...
good...
And because of...
Lorentz contraction...
I say that the volume of that...
charge is one thing...
You sitting still assign a different...
volume to it...
One of us assigns a smaller volume...
Let's say you assign a bigger volume...
I assign a smaller volume because I see it...
Lorentz contracted...
If we take the charge and we divide it by...
the volume,
we will not agree...
about the value of the...
of the charge density...
But that's okay...
Charge density is the component...
of a four vector...
It's not an invariant...
Charge density is a component...
of a four vector...
Similarly...
You see charges...
Well,
let's say...
You see charges standing still...
And you say there is no current...
Why?
The charges are at rest...
All of them...
I'm moving and I see
a wind of charges passing me...
I say there's current...
Right?
So,
yes...
Charge density and charge current...
are not invariants...
They form together a four vector...
Now...
Energy and momentum are more complicated...
The total energy and momentum...
Not the density of them...
But the total energy and momentum...
are not invariant...
I see a particle standing still...
The whole particle...
Not the density...
I see a particle standing still...
And I say there's some...
energy there of a certain magnitude...
You're walking past it...
And you see...
Not just the E equals mc squared...
part of the energy...
But you also see kinetic energy of motion...
You walking past the particle...
Or the object...
Sees more energy...
Not because of any Lorentz contraction
of the volume that it's in...
But just because...
The same object...
Has more energy than when I look at it...
The same is true of the total momentum...
Not the flow...
Not the...
Not the density of it...
The same is true of momentum...
You see an object in motion...
You say there's momentum there...
I see the object at rest...
I say there's no momentum...
So,
energy and momentum...
Unlike charge...
Are not invariant...
They together form the components of a four vector...
So...
And that four vector...
P mu...
Includes...
The energy...
And the components of...
Momentum...
Pm...
Where m labels the directions of space...
Alright,
so each one of these...
Is like a q...
It's a conserved quantity...
Each one of them is like a q...
Now,
energy can be in motion...
And we can ask...
Why is it in motion?
Energy has a density associated with it...
Energy has a density...
Oh,
incidentally...
E is also...
P0...
Good...
Alright...
Come over to here for a minute...
Density...
Was the time component of j...
Because it's a density...
We'll assign it...
A component zero...
Zero for time...
It's the time component...
Of a density...
Let's think about the time component...
Of the energy...
P0 is the energy...
But...
Let's think about the time component...
Of its density...
Not the total energy...
But the time component of the density...
In other words,
how much energy is...
In a small volume...
But energy within a small volume...
We're going to call that...
T0...
Now,
where the notation T came from...
I don't know...
Oh,
yes...
At some point in time...
It was tension...
But it's a long historical...
Long historical evolution...
T0...
Now,
what are the two indices 0,
0?
The first 0...
Indicates that we're talking about...
Energy...
The second 0 indicates that we're talking...
About its density...
So you can think of this then...
As the...
Time component...
Meaning the density...
Of a thing which is itself a time component...
Namely the...
Energy...
T0,
0...
And it's a function of position...
If you integrate it over position...
It tells you how much total energy you have...
But energy can also move...
Energy can move from place to place...
And like momentum...
Sorry,
like charge...
When energy disappears out of a region...
It does so because it passes out...
Through the...
Through the walls of the region...
And so...
Energy also has a flow...
It's the amount of...
It's exactly the same idea...
The amount of energy...
Passing through a window...
Per unit time...
Is the amount of energy...
Is the current of energy...
If you like...
We don't call it the current of energy...
We call it T0,
1...
I don't want to...
T0,
0...
Is density of energy...
And again I'll...
Emphasize...
The fact that it's density is one of these zeros...
I think it's this one...
And the fact that it's energy...
Is the first entry here...
The flow of energy...
Along the direction...
Along...
The direction...
X1...
The amount of energy...
Passing through a window...
Oriented along the X1 axis...
That's called...
T0...
0 because it's energy...
But then 1 because it's a flow along the...
X1 direction...
Likewise...
There's a T0,
2...
And a T0,
3...
These three together...
Form...
The flow of energy...
And this is the density of energy...
Exactly the same way...
As the continuity equation is derived...
The continuity equation...
For energy is derived...
And what does it say...
For the moment the first index here is just passive...
It tells us what we're talking about...
We're talking about energy...
It's the 0,
1,
2 and 3 here...
Which are like the components of the current here...
Alright...
So what it tells us...
Is that the covariant derivative...
With respect to...
X mu...
Of...
T0 mu...
Is equal to 0...
This is the analogous continuity equation for energy...
But everything that I said about energy...
We could now say...
For any one of the components...
Of the momentum...
So let's go to the components of the momentum now...
Let's say the component...
Pm...
The component Pm...
Also has a density...
Put it up here...
Component...
M...
Of momentum...
It also has a density...
And that density is called T1...
Well M...
Tm0...
The 0 here indicates that it's a density...
The m here indicates that we're talking
about the mth component of the momentum...
So we read this...
The density of the mth component of the momentum...
It's also a function of x...
And likewise...
We can consider...
The flow...
Of the mth component of momentum...
Mth component of momentum...
Flow along direction n...
Of x...
Momentum is a conserved quantity...
It can flow...
Each of its components can flow along some direction...
Let me give you an example...
Of a...
Some examples...
Yeah...
You say x is really the mth...
Component of x...
Correct?
Here...
In here...
That just means a function of position...
Any position...
It means a function of position...
Yeah...
It means x,
y,
and z...
All of them...
Function of position...
Right...
And this is true...
Even if we replace energy...
By a component of momentum...
In other words...
We could replace...
Not by n...
But now we have an equation like this...
For all four possibilities...
We can just call this...
T nu mu...
For each nu...
In other words...
Nu could be time...
In which case we're talking about energy...
Or...
T could be space...
In which case we're talking about...
Uh...
Right...
So we have...
Basically what it comes down to...
Is that the flow...
And densities of energy and momentum...
Form a tensor...
With two indices...
One index tells us...
Who we're talking about...
Energy or momentum...
The other index tells us...
What we're talking about...
And that's what...
And that is called...
The energy-momentum tensor...
Whoops...
Let's see...
Um...
The energy-momentum tensor...
Has an interesting property...
Which I have not proved...
But for example...
Take T m nought...
That is the density of...
The mth component of momentum...
Compare it with...
T nought m...
That's...
That's the flow...
This is flow of energy...
This is density of momentum...
It's a general property...
Of relativistic systems...
Which I'm not going to prove now...
Which tells you...
That this matrix is symmetric...
T m nought is equal to...
T nought m...
We're not going to prove it...
Um...
It takes a little bit of work to prove it...
It's proved...
Relativistic invariance allows you to...
Connect this with this...
And it is a theorem...
Of relativistic mechanics...
That are relativistic field theory essentially...
All relativistic field theories...
The energy-momentum tensor...
Is symmetric...
So let's add that in...
And then we have...
The energy-momentum tensor...
Big square matrix...
T nought one...
T nought two...
Blah blah blah...
T nought three...
That's all...
And so forth and so on...
We'll come back to the meaning...
Of these elements in a little while...
This one is clear...
This is energy density...
These are fairly clear...
They're flow of energy...
This one is momentum density...
The flow of momentum...
So they're pretty clear what they mean...
But we're going to find out that
some of these elements have another meaning...
Connected with pressure...
Things like pressure...
Things of that nature...
We'll come back to that in a while...
But...
The important idea...
Is that the flow...
And density of energy and momentum...
Are...
Combined into an energy-momentum tensor...
And each component of the energy...
Well...
The energy-momentum tensor...
Ah...
Satisfies a continuity equation...
Four continuity equations...
One for each type of stuff that we're talking about...
Okay,
we'll come back to pressure...
In a little while...
Is essentially the second rank or index...
Of the tensor...
Just because...
It's not invariant...
The total energy and momentum is not invariant?
Like total charge?
Total energy and momentum is not invariant...
That's the first index...
I'm comparing it to the charge and current equation...
Yeah...
You got...
The extra index essentially came out of that...
Two...
You don't have the extra...
This mu here...
Does not tell us what quantity we're talking about...
We know we're talking about electric charge...
Okay...
So we could write this in another way...
We could say this is J...
Charge mu...
Okay...
I just put the Q up here...
To remind us what stuff we're talking about...
The mu over here...
Tells us about the direction of flow...
When it's time-like...
It's density...
When it's space-like...
It's flow...
So the second index is the thing which distinguishes flow...
Along which axis...
The first index here tells us...
What quantity we're talking about...
Same here...
T naught...
Tells us we're talking about energy...
This M...
Tells us we're talking about the flow of it...
Along the axis M...
How much of it is flowing out through a window...
Orient along the M axis...
But fortunately we don't have to remember...
T naught M and T naught...
They're equal...
That's the symmetry...
It's easy enough to remember that...
One of these must be...
One of these must correspond
to the fact that it's energy...
And the other...
That it's flow...
But it's not important to remember which is which...
Because they're interchangeable...
Okay,
so now let's...
Let's return...
Excuse me...
That entire matrix is symmetric,
is that correct?
Yes it is...
No,
that's right,
the entire matrix is symmetric...
Right...
That's correct...
We'll come back to its structure...
In a little while...
Maybe not tonight,
but...
And some of the meaning of its elements...
But for the moment...
What we've learned now...
Is that the notion of...
Energy density...
Is...
Incomplete...
It's part of a...
Multiplet of things...
It's part of a tensor...
So the right hand side of this equation...
Is part of a tensor...
The left hand side must
also be part of a tensor...
But whenever you have a tensor equation...
You can't have a tensor equation...
That says...
Some particular component...
Of a tensor...
Is equal to some other...
The same component of some other tensor...
Let's say that...
That is an example...
Let's take some particular...
Component...
Of a four vector A...
Let's say A3...
It's a four vector...
And this is the third component of it...
And I assert that...
There's a law of physics...
That says that A3 is equal to B3...
Three being the Z...
Z direction...
Does that make sense as a law of physics?
Well...
It only makes sense as a law of physics...
If it is also true...
That A2 equals B2...
And A1...
Equals B1...
Why is that?
Why can't you just have a law that says that...
The third component of a vector...
Of the Z axis...
Is equal to the third component of some other vector...
And not have...
That the other two components are equal...
And the answer is simple...
That if...
If it is always true...
In every frame of reference...
That the third component of A...
Is equal to the third component of B...
If it's true in every frame of reference...
Then by rotating the frame of reference...
We can rotate A3...
We can rotate the third axis...
And then...
Until it becomes the second axis...
And so...
If it's true in every frame of reference...
That A3 is equal to B3...
Then A2 must be equal to B2...
And A1 must be equal to B1...
If it's to be true...
In every frame of reference...
That's an example...
Of why equations need to be...
Tensor equations...
Of the form...
A sub M equals B sub M...
Or...
Vector equations...
Okay...
When you go to relativity...
The same thing is true...
Even concluding the time component...
Of equations...
If it were true for example...
In some frame of reference...
No...
In every frame of reference...
That a certain four vector...
Now this is a four vector...
This is the time component of it...
Is always equal to B0...
And B1...
In every frame of reference...
Then the only way that can be true...
Is if...
All components are equal...
In every frame of reference...
A mu...
Is equal to B mu...
For the same reason...
Lorentz transformations are not so different...
From rotations...
And unless...
All the components are equal...
You'll always be able to find...
A frame of reference...
In which A0 will not be equal to B0...
Unless all four components are equal...
So good laws of physics...
Must be tensor laws of physics...
In particular if they're to be true...
In every frame of reference...
Now here we have an equation...
That involves a right hand side...
Which is a particular component...
Of some tensor...
It's a component...
A 0 0 component of the...
Of the...
Of the energy momentum tensor...
Let's not worry too much...
About whether this left hand side...
Was just a guess of what...
The left hand side might look like...
But the right hand side...
Is the energy density...
And it's what you expect to
be on the right hand side...
Of Newton's equations...
But...
The right hand side of Newton's equations...
But the right hand side...
Of Einstein's equations...
Must involve...
Not a particular component of a tensor...
But it must generalize...
To something that involves all components...
Of the tensor...
So that means Einstein's generalization...
Of Newton must read something like this...
The right hand side...
Must be...
8 pi g...
Same 8 pi g...
Times t mu nu...
A special case being...
When mu and nu...
Are both equal to time...
And then that becomes the energy density...
But if the equation is to be true...
In every frame...
It has to be a tensor equation...
What has to be on the left hand side?
What has to be on the left hand side...
Must also be a tensor...
With two components...
A rank two tensor...
Otherwise the equation doesn't make sense...
So on the left hand side...
Must be some tensor...
With the same kind of tensor structure...
It must be symmetric...
Because the right hand side is symmetric...
And have whatever properties the right hand side has...
But it's not something...
Which is made up out of matter...
It's made up out of the metric...
It's something...
Which is made up out of the metric...
It has to do with geometry...
And not with masses and sources...
So the left hand side...
We will just say...
We'll call it capital G mu nu...
The only thing...
We know about it...
Is it's made up out of the metric...
It probably has two derivatives in it...
To compare it with this here...
It's...
It will involve the metric...
In some form...
And very likely two derivatives of the metric...
That's the kind of thing we would like to find...
To put on the left hand side...
And when we find a good candidate for it...
We can then ask...
If we're in a situation where...
Non-relativistic physics...
Should be a good approximation...
Does this G mu nu...
Reduce...
To just del squared G naught naught...
Perhaps it does...
Perhaps it doesn't...
If it doesn't...
Then we throw it away and
try to find a different rule...
Alright,
so we need to know what kind of thing...
G mu nu can be...
Alright,
so let's...
Explore the...
Possibilities...
G mu nu...
Is a tensor made up out of...
Uh...
Out of the metric...
It has two derivatives...
Or at least...
It must have some terms...
Which have two derivatives to make it look like that...
So it's not just a metric by itself...
It has to be a thing with two derivatives...
What kind of tensor...
Can we make out of the metric...
And...
It's a thing with two derivatives...
Alright,
so...
We've already talked about one...
It was the curvature tensor...
Let me remind you about the curvature tensor...
The curvature tensor was made up out of the...
Christoffel symbols...
For our purposes tonight...
I'm just writing down these equations as reminders...
Uh...
You start with the Christoffel symbols...
And I'll just remind you what they look like...
This is equal to 1 half...
G sigma delta...
Times...
D tau...
D tau means D by dx tau...
G...
Delta...
Nu...
Plus...
Derivative with respect to...
Nu...
Of G...
Delta tau...
The first two terms are gotten by...
Interchanging tau and nu...
And then the last one is minus...
Derivative of...
With respect to...
Delta,
I believe...
Of G...
Nu tau...
Now,
what's...
The only important thing...
Right now...
Is this involves the derivative of a G...
It involves...
The first derivative of a G...
One derivative...
Alright...
Next...
What about the curvature tensor...
Down...
But the only important part of it...
Is that it involves another derivative...
So here it is...
The curvature tensor...
On all its glory...
Mu nu tau sigma...
And this is the thing...
Which tells us that there's real curvature...
If any component of this is non-zero...
Anywhere in a region of space...
The space is curved...
Okay...
So...
Uh...
I think...
D mu...
Gamma nu...
Sigma tau...
Minus D nu...
Gamma sigma mu tau...
And then there's another term...
With gamma nu lambda...
Sigma...
Gamma mu...
Tau lambda...
Gamma nu lambda...
I'm rewriting this down...
It's just the general overall structure...
Which is interesting...
For reasons...
Mu lambda...
Sigma gamma nu tau...
Lambda...
Summation convention...
Assumed...
Main point is...
The Christoffel symbol...
Which is not a tensor...
Has first derivatives of the metric...
And the curvature tensor...
Has first derivatives of the Christoffel symbol...
It also has things...
Which are quadratic...
In the Christoffel symbol...
It's okay...
This means these terms here...
Have second derivatives of the metric...
The derivatives of derivatives...
This term here has...
Also two derivatives...
Squares of first derivatives...
So this is the kind
of thing we like to see...
We like to see an R...
We like to see a tensor...
Which involves two...
Two derivatives of the metric...
And that's it...
Two derivatives of components of the metric...
That's a candidate...
Or components of this...
Various components of it...
Are candidates to appear on the left hand side...
Of this equation...
But wait...
R has four components...
The curvature tensor...
The Riemann curvature tensor...
Has four components...
The left hand side of this equation...
Has two components...
Why?
Because the right hand side has two components...
So...
This can't be the left
hand side of the equation itself...
What can you do to it...
To make a thing with two components?
You can make a thing with two components...
By contraction...
By contraction of components...
Remember the rule...
If you set sigma for example...
I'll tell you what happens...
You could set sigma equal to tau in sum...
You would get zero...
And you would get...
If you actually plug in...
What the curvature tensor is...
If you set sigma equal to tau...
In sum...
You would get zero...
If you set sigma equal to nu in sum...
You won't get sigma...
You won't get zero...
You'll get something that we can call...
The tensor R mu tau...
I have a question...
You're going to run into a problem contracting this...
Because you get a covariant...
Tensor where you need a contravariant tensor...
We can all...
That's exactly what I was coming to next...
Okay...
We can build a tensor...
From a tensor with four components...
You can build a tensor with two components...
By contracting indices...
But you have to be
careful that you don't get zero...
You will get zero...
Some of the symmetries of this thing...
The various minus signs that appear here...
In fact...
Will wind up giving you zero...
When you contract sigma with tau...
They will not be...
They will not give you zero...
When you contract sigma with mu...
Or sigma with mu...
But the two tensors you get by contracting...
Sigma with mu and sigma with mu...
Happen to be the same tensor apart...
From a sign...
So there's really only one thing you can build...
It's a theorem...
It's a well known theorem...
There's only one tensor...
That you can build out of two derivatives...
Acting on the metric...
Which has only two indices...
It's called the Ricci tensor...
And it's a contraction of the Riemann tensor...
It has less information...
The Riemann tensor has a lot more components...
Than the Ricci tensor...
It has less information...
Meaning to say...
It doesn't...
It itself can be zero...
Without the full Riemann tensor being zero...
So this is called the Ricci tensor...
And...
As always...
If you have a tensor...
You can raise and lower its indices...
That means there's also a thing called...
R mu tau...
There's also a thing called...
And also R mu tau...
With both of them raised...
You can raise and lower...
Indices using the metric tensor...
And so...
You ask...
For each such tensor...
There's another one with upper indices...
Another fact...
About the Ricci tensor...
Is that it happens to be symmetric...
In particular...
R mu tau...
Equals R tau mu...
Now that you just check...
By using its definition...
I don't know...
A simple...
Quick argument about it...
All of these things are fairly complicated...
This Ricci tensor...
Is symmetric...
Just a property that it has...
Defined the way it is...
And so...
A possible...
Left hand side...
Would be the Ricci tensor...
Question mark...
8 pi g...
T mu nu...
Now...
There's another one that you can make...
There's another one you can make...
Another tensor that you can make...
This was not the...
Unique...
Only one other...
Only one other possibility...
And that's to begin...
By contracting mu and tau...
Lowering...
You can...
Contract mu and tau...
By multiplying...
This object is called R...
It's a scalar...
It's R...
Mu mu...
Which is also equal...
To g mu tau...
Times R...
Oops...
G mu tau...
R mu tau...
The action of this g...
Lowers the index tau...
And makes it into mu...
And then it becomes just exactly this thing here...
These are the same object...
This is called the curvature scalar...
It's a scalar...
It has no indices left at all...
In the only one that's on the left hand side...
But we can multiply it...
By g mu nu...
Multiplying it by g mu
nu does give us a tensor...
That's another possibility...
I'm not recommending either of these at the moment...
I'm just saying...
From what we've said up till now...
Either of these could be possible...
possible laws of gravitation.
They both involve second derivatives
of the metric tensor equaling something
on the right-hand side,
which looks like a density of energy
and momentum.
OK,
which one shall we pick?
Well,
we know one more thing.
We know one more thing,
and that's
the conservation of energy and momentum,
or better yet,
the continuity equation for energy momentum.
If we believe that energy
and momentum has the property that
only disappears if it flows through walls of systems,
in other words,
if there's a flow,
then we are forced to the conclusion
that d mu,
covariant derivative of t mu nu,
is equal to 0.
That's the continuity equation.
d mu,
t mu nu is the continuity equation from which
it follows that d mu g
mu nu is equal to 0.
So the first thing we could
do is we could check whether either
of these two tensors satisfies this relationship.
If not,
then the left-hand side simply
can't be the right-hand side unless we give up
conservation,
continuity of the energy.
So when we've tried this multiple time
or the same thing over and over over and over,
we did until we were exactly at kind potential
order t mu nu .
OK,
so on toAngiology and tegenology.
equal to d mu g mu nu times
R plus g mu nu d mu R.
That's just a product rule for
derivatives,
covariant derivatives are no exception,
this is true.
Now what about
the covariant derivative of the metric tensor?
Remember what the covariant
derivative of the metric tensor is?
Zero.
Zero covariant,
that's where we started,
that's how we calculated the the
Christoffel symbols by starting with the
assumption that the covariant derivative of G
is equal to zero and the reason for
that is because covariant derivatives are
by definition tensors which in the
special good frame of reference
are equal to ordinary derivatives but the
ordinary derivative of G in the good
frame of reference,
the good frame of reference being the frame of reference
in which the derivatives of G are zero,
so the covariant derivative of G is
equal to zero,
this term is not there,
and now R is a scalar,
the covariant
derivative of a scalar is just the ordinary derivative.
Scalars don't have
any indices.
Covariant derivatives of scalars
are just ordinary derivatives.
What did I write here?
R plus,
that went away,
yeah,
that went away.
Okay what about this?
This is just equal to G
mu nu times the derivative of R.
Well certainly in general the derivative
of the curvature is not zero.
In general
the derivative of curvature,
the curvature of the curvature is zero.
So the derivative of the curvature is zero.
And there's multiple things,
inflammation is nowhere near even the provisional
derivative of R is.
dauphine is 0.
So the derivative of R came convenience
of r is equal to zero.
So
here's what we find.
First of all,
the
covariant derivative
the covariant derivative of
this guy over here
is not equal to
zero,
but it is equal
to just g mu nu
d mu
r.
So it doesn't work.
No good.
Bad.
What about this one?
Well,
we do the same thing.
We calculate d mu
of r mu nu
and it's a little harder,
but not much.
A little bit harder
I'll tell you what the answer is.
It's equal to
one half
g mu nu
d mu r.
Again,
it can't be zero
for the same reason that this one
can't be,
and happens
to be exactly
one half
the covariant derivative,
the
corresponding covariant derivative
happens to be one half.
But now
we know the answer.
If we
take g mu nu r
and subtract off one half
r mu nu,
or better yet,
take r mu nu and subtract
off
two or one half
Okay,
so what do I know?
I know that r
derivative of r
mu nu
is equal to one half
I know everybody got it,
I think I got it right Alright,
But I now have I now
have a obvious thing
to do.
We combine this with this,
R mu nu with some coefficient times g mu nu,
and then we will get a thing
whose appropriate derivative is equal to zero.
So what is g mu nu?
g mu nu is R mu nu
minus one half g mu nu R.
That's a theorem that there is nothing else made up out of two
derivatives acting on the metric that has the property that it's covariantly conserved.
This would be called covariantly conserved.
There just is nothing else.
That's it.
So either,
oh,
I take it back,
of course.
You could have twice it or
half of it or 17 times it.
But now it just becomes a question of matching this equation
to Newton's equations in the appropriate approximations where everything is moving non-relativistically.
And one of two possibilities,
either there is some correct numerical multiple of this,
which matches this or there isn't.
If there isn't,
then we're in trouble.
Then we're in trouble.
When I say that it matches it,
we look at the time-time component.
The time-time component of this equation
has rho on the right hand side.
It has t naught naught on the right hand side.
t naught naught is rho.
So we take this equation in the non-relativistic limit.
Everybody move it the other way around.
slowly,
not too strong a gravitational field,
we plug it in and we hope that
with some appropriate numerical coefficient here,
this equation and this
equation are the same in an appropriate limit.
Okay the answer is yes they are
the same and they're the same with coefficient one,
numerical coefficient one.
Just a piece of luck that
it turned out with the coefficient one,
nothing
deep about that.
And this is what Einstein,
this was Einstein's
calculation.
He knew what was going on
pretty much but he didn't quite know
what the right equation of motion was.
I believe in the beginning he actually did
try R mu nu equal to zero.
T mu nu.
And eventually found,
realized that it didn't work.
I don't know how
many weeks of work it took him to do
all of this but in the end he discovered
capital G mu nu equals R mu
nu minus one half G mu nu R.
This is called the
Einstein tensor.
This is the Ricci tensor
and this is the curvature scalar.
So this is now known as Einstein's
field equations and they do reproduce Newton in
the appropriate limit.
But now we see something interesting.
We see that in general the source of the
gravitational field is not just energy density,
but it can involve
energy flow.
It can involve momentum density,
it can involve mass density,
it can involve momentum density.
density and it can even involve momentum flow.
Now as a rule,
the momentum flow or even the energy flow,
certainly the momentum flow,
but even the momentum density
are much smaller than the energy density.
Why do I say that?
It has to do with the
speeds of light in the formulas.
If you put the speeds of light into the formulas,
just like energy is always huge
because it gets multiplied by c squared,
but on the other hand momentum is typically not huge
because it's just mass times velocity.
So if velocity is slow,
if you're in a non-relativistic situation,
when velocity is slow,
energy is big,
energy density is by far the biggest thing.
The other components of the energy momentum tense
are also big.
So the speed of light is much smaller,
typically decreased by powers of the speed of light.
So in the various non-relativistic situations,
the only thing that's important on the right-hand side,
in a frame of reference
where the sources are moving slowly,
the only important thing on the right-hand side is rho.
It's also true that in the same limit,
the only important thing on the left-hand side
is the second derivative of g.
So in the non-relativistic limit,
these things match,
but if you're outside of the non-relativistic limit,
places where sources are moving rapidly,
or even places where the sources are made
up out of particles which are moving rapidly,
even though the whole thing
may be not moving so much,
other components of the energy
momentum tensor do generate gravitation.
They do generate curvature,
and it's not just energy waves.
It's also gravity,
or mass,
as we sometimes call it.
ちょっと、
腰に。
In the Newtonian mechanics,
so you
can derive the continuity equation
by analyzing a little differential element of,
say,
a fluid or a gas or whatever.
Is there anything analogous?
Is there an analogous way to come up with this?
I mean,
this sort of seems like,
gee,
let's try this,
let's try that.
I'm sorry.
Huh?
Say it.
Is there some sort of basic physical way
to come up with this as opposed to?
This equation?
Yeah.
Without using the continuity equation?
No,
to obtain the continuity equation.
Well,
the logic here is a little bit different.
The logic is that the continuity equation basically
comes from the idea of conservation
and local conservation.
None of this crap where
you have something disappear and reappear
on an alpha centauri.
That logic is just as good in relativity
as it is in non-relativistic physics,
stuff
having to pass out through the boundaries in order
to disappear.
So in some sense,
the continuity
equation is more fundamental from this point of view.
But there is another point of view,
which we'll talk about maybe next time,
which
is the action formulation,
which is much more beautiful
and much more condensed,
where we introduce
a principle of least action for the gravitational field.
And all of this just pops out.
Hard calculations.
They're not easy,
but it pops out.
Therefore,
I think it should be a swept map
framework,
which is interesting,
because sometimes
I'm swamped on that.
How about you?
Well,
before something is Lambda- posture,
how do we get such behavior at a model,
then we can just to
pull out go to X alphabets
and get ourselves to draw a epoch of votre mental
Yes,
so what does that mean?
We'd want 0.7.
So by 0.7,
we cross gender overlap model for five sessions,
tensor,
two tensor I guess,
and that satisfies the continuity equation,
and that it's a strictly
a geometrical stuff.
Right.
So could there be something else?
There is no,
it's known that there isn't.
It's known that there isn't.
Yeah.
Is that a physical thing or a mathematical fact?
Well,
it's a mathematical fact,
but is it a physical thing?
Well,
I can't think of any simple physical argument for it,
but it is a fact.
And was that fact known by Einstein,
or was that determined later?
I,
oh,
no,
it's an easy fact.
The only tensor,
this was known from Riemann,
the only tensor that you can build that involves
only two derivatives of the metric was
the Riemann curvature tensor and things that descend
from it.
And that's determined by contraction.
So yes,
Einstein knew that it had to be
built up out of the curvature tensor,
and it's not
hard to go through,
to exhaust all possible things that
you can do with a curvature tensor.
I essentially did it.
All possible things that you can do with
the curvature tensor to make a thing with only
two indices,
there's only two things you can do.
One of them is R mu nu and the other,
and this,
you know,
this is not hard to prove.
It's very straightforward.
So Einstein presumably knew that,
that this particular combination satisfied a continuity
equation that was Einstein.
So he must have had to do a little
bit of work to calculate this thing over here.
D mu R mu nu,
this one.
He had to do a little bit
of work to calculate this thing over here.
So he must have had to do
a little bit of work to calculate that.
I assume that what he did was just plug in.
And it would take you about
15 or 20 minutes to do it.
As usual,
the principles are simple,
but by the time you've manipulated all the indices
and written down the Christoffel symbols and
worried about getting the signs right and
so forth,
it'll take you a good
15 minutes to get this done.
So I can envision him having done this thing.
Just a little calculation.
Noticed that agreed with this calculation and
that if he combined them in the right
proportions,
that he would have what he needs.
As I said,
there is another argument.
The other argument is much more elegant,
but this was the first round of things that he
did.
Yeah.
Two questions,
if I could.
One is when you did that contraction from the...
I don't know.
Tens of the four indices to the one...
Two indices.
Mm-hmm.
The stuff that we got thrown away,
is there any physical content to that?
Oh,
yes.
And oh,
Yeah,
yeah,
yeah.
Another way...
Yeah.
Right.
Okay.
So yeah,
there's quite a bit of content to it.
But let me point out one thing.
That just as in Maxwell's equations...
Yeah.
...there are solutions which don't involve sources.
All right?
You can find solutions of Maxwell's
equations that don't have any sources.
Or you can find solutions in regions
of space in which there are no sources.
Let's consider the case with either no sources or
when we're in a region of space where there
are no sources,
outside of all the sources.
Yeah.
Then on the right-hand side,
we have zero.
So let me just show you
that there's a simplification in that case.
It's just a little simplification,
but the equation does become simpler in that case.
Let's suppose that T mu nu is equal to zero.
In other words,
R mu nu...
...minus 1 half g mu nu.
R is equal to zero,
or better yet,
R mu nu is equal to
1 half g mu nu R.
Now let's calculate R by,
on the left-hand side,
contracting nu and mu.
It's equivalent to lowering an index here.
We have to do the lowering on this side also.
And then setting nu equal to mu.
Do you remember what g is
with one upper and one lower index?
It's the Kronecker delta.
Go back to your notes if you don't remember.
The g with one upper and one lower index...
...which means Kronecker delta.
Yeah.
Ordinary Kronecker delta.
In general relativity,
the Kronecker delta is always considered to be
a thing with one upper and one lower index.
But it means the same thing.
Zero when mu is not equal to nu,
one when it is equal to nu.
It's the unit matrix.
The reason...
Okay,
let's just remind ourselves of this.
All right,
so let's now contract mu with nu.
That means set mu equal to nu and sum.
What do I get on the left-hand side?
On the left-hand side,
I get r.
On the right-hand side,
I get one half r
times this object g mu mu,
or better yet,
delta mu mu.
What is delta mu mu?
Four.
There are four pieces.
Each...
Each delta...
Delta 0 is 1.
Delta 1 1 is 1.
Delta 2 2 is 1.
Delta 3 3 is 1.
This is just 4.
And we get the stupid equation
that r is equal to 2r.
The only solution of that is
that r is equal to 0.
Not the curvature tensor.
Not even the Ricci tensor.
But just the curvature scalar.
That does not imply that the Ricci tensor is 0.
It only implies what it implies,
which is the Ricci scalar is equal to 0.
In which case,
in this special case,
when this is equal to 0,
you can drop this term.
One half g mu nu r is just 0.
Einstein's field equations become a little simpler
in what is usually called the vacuum case.
The vacuum case means in regions
of space where there are no sources.
In regions of space where there are no sources,
the whole Einstein...
set of Einstein equations is just the equations
that r mu nu is equal to 0.
The solutions are not trivial.
They contain gravitational waves with no sources,
just like there are electromagnetic waves.
But another example is the Schwarzschild metric.
Now...
The Schwarzschild metric itself is analogous,
roughly speaking,
analogous to a point mass.
Outside the point mass,
there is no matter.
Nothing.
So just like Newton's equations,
where everywhere is outside the mass,
the equation is the same as
it would be for just empty space,
the Schwarzschild metric is also one
for which everywhere is outside the mass,
the equation is the same as
it would be for just empty space,
the Schwarzschild metric is also one
for which everywhere is outside the singularity.
The equation that's satisfied
is the vacuum Einstein equation.
So a simple thing...
It's not simple to do.
It's a real nuisance to do.
But a conceptually simple thing to do is to take the Schwarzschild
metric and calculate r mu nu and check that it's equal to 0.
You will find that it is.
If you take the Schwarzschild metric,
it's a bunch of g mu nu's,
sit down and spend the rest
of the day calculating Christoffel symbols,
and then curvature tensors and contracting them,
or put it on Mathematica,
and you'll find out that it's exactly equal to 0.
Now,
of course,
it's ambiguous at the singularity.
Singularity,
everything is so crazy it doesn't make any sense.
But the components which
you're contracting become infinite there.
It's sort of like the point mass,
too singular,
too undefined at the origin to have a value.
But everywhere is away from the singularity.
Yes,
the Schwarzschild metric is what is called Ricci flat.
Saying that this is equal to
0 is sometimes called Ricci flat.
It is not the same as flat.
So gravitational waves satisfy this.
Schwarzschild metric satisfies it,
except at the singularity.
And that's the basic facts
about the Einstein field equations.
I think we'll quit there.
Yeah.
Analysis,
but you leave T in.
Say it again?
You do the same analysis that you did there,
contracting,
but you leave T in.
You don't set it to 0.
You leave T in.
Oh,
okay,
good,
good.
Yeah,
yeah,
you can,
right.
Okay,
so you can do that.
Let's do that.
Yeah.
Okay,
let's see what we get.
We have R mu nu,
doesn't matter whether it's upstairs or downstairs,
R mu nu minus 1 half g mu nu,
R is equal to 8 pi g T mu nu.
Okay.
Now,
what are we going to do?
We're going to contract,
we're going to contract these two indices.
This is going to give us R minus 2R.
R is equal to 8 pi g T mu mu.
I contract the index or the same,
what's the same thing,
T mu nu g mu nu.
Okay,
so that now tells us,
let's see,
this is minus R,
minus R equals 8 pi g,
and let's just call it T.
T is by definition the scalar that you
get when you contract the two indices here.
So what do we have?
We have R is equal
to minus 8 pi g T,
and now we can put
that back into the Einstein equations.
Put this back,
we get R mu nu minus
1 half g mu nu times R,
which is plus 8 pi g mu mu.
8 pi g T equals
8 pi g T mu nu.
And now let's take this thing
here and shift it to the right.
This was a plus sign here,
huh?
So we get 8 pi g T mu nu,
8 pi g multiplies T mu nu
minus 1 half g mu nu T.
Okay.
Where T is gotten by contracting.
Right,
so here's what we get.
In other words,
Einstein field equations can be written with
R mu nu on the left-hand side,
but on the right-hand side,
you have to compensate by subtracting
1 half g mu nu times T.
Is there any physical significance to the scalar T?
Yeah,
it's called the trace of the energy momentum tensor.
And yeah,
the trace of the energy momenta—okay,
I'll tell you when it's zero.
It's zero for radiation,
electromagnetic radiation.
It's zero when the mass of the—
when the—it's zero for massless
particles like photons or gravitons.
It's—for electromagnetic radiation,
it would be zero.
T would be zero.
For particles with mass,
the energy momentum tensor,
this thing is not zero.
So—
Yeah,
a similar question.
Can you describe—
Can someone describe the physical meaning of
the Ricci scalar and the Ricci tensor?
The Riemann tensor is obvious,
but—
Yeah,
Riemann tensor has to do with going
around the little curve and seeing how—
What kind of—
Yeah,
what kind of rotation you do.
I don't know a simple answer to that.
I don't know any particular physical significance.
I don't know any particular
geometric significance to—or geometric significance.
I'm sure there is,
but whatever it is,
it's not really very transparent.
There are much simpler objects than the full Riemann tensor.
On the other hand,
it's kind of difficult
to visualize their individual meaning.
So I'm going to say no,
that I don't know a good
simple way to think about these things.
Okay.
I think one thing that I—
That's one of the...
Oh,
that's one of the major issues.
Yeah.
One of the major situations I discussed to
ask questions is I think these are pretty
complex,
but they're incredible.
It's not clear what they are,
but it's not that difficult.
Well,
your asking is-
I mean,
how many examples have you got this year?
Yeah,
how few some people came to me at the 박
one when I wascosm Изnagol SWR清 sign,
World Ocean E creamsiță
to zero where the Riemann tensor is not
equal to zero and an example that we'll
explore a little bit is gravitational waves.
Gravitational waves,
just like
electromagnetic waves,
they don't require any sources.
Of course really we really
expect that in the real world
an electromagnetic wave is made by an
antenna or something,
but as solutions of Maxwell's equations you can just have
electromagnetic waves that just propagate
from infinity to infinity and
just no sources.
In the same way you can
have gravitational waves which also have
no sources.
Those gravitational waves satisfy R
mu equals zero but they are
most certainly not flat space.
There's all sorts of distortions of space going
on.
So you can't just have a gravitational
wave and a gravitational wave and a
no sources in the non-matrix geometry.
So I think maybe a possible,
somewhat
satisfying thing is to see what a
geometry that has r mu equal to zero
but for which the curvature tensor itself
is not equal to zero and we'll
explore a little bit what a gravitational wave looks like.
So that
will help.
Same thing of course is true of the Schwarzschild metric.
As long as
you stay away from the singularity,
you'll find the T right in the matrix,
There's something there,
there's real curvature there,
tidal forces,
all sorts of stuff,
but R mu nu is equal to zero,
so yes,
R mu nu has less information
in it than the curvature tensor.
It actually depends on the dimensionality.
In four dimensions,
there is less information in the
Ricci tensor than in the Riemann tensor.
Turns out in three dimensions,
the amount of information is the same.
You can write one in terms of the other,
either way,
and in two dimensions,
all of the information is in the scalar.
That's all there is,
is the scalar,
and you can make the other things out of it.
So that must mean there's some invariance
by connecting the Ricci tensor and Ricci scalar.
I don't know how to phrase this,
but there are combinations that you can subtract that information out
of the Riemann tensor and not have it affect the gravitational field.
Would that be gravity waves,
or what would that be?
I'm not sure.
There's missing information,
and that missing information has no effect.
On the momentum-energy tensor,
correct?
Because the left-hand side is not the Riemann tensor.
Right.
So how is that lack of information manifest?
It means that for a given source,
there can be many,
many solutions,
many of which,
you know,
they all have the same left-hand side,
namely R mu nu,
but they simply have different physical properties.
So,
for example,
the simplest situation is to say,
what if this is zero?
If it's zero,
does it mean that there's no gravitational,
no interesting geometry at all?
No.
It allows gravitational waves.
Roughly speaking,
any energy-momentum tensor you
put there construct a solution,
and then add gravitational waves.
And then add gravitational waves on top of it.
Roughly speaking,
that's not exactly true,
but it's roughly speaking true,
that any solution,
you can always add gravitational waves.
All right?
So the gravitational waves must
be something that contains more information
than just the Ricci tensor,
and they do.
What about Fudge factor?
No.
No Fudge factor.
Yeah?
No cosmological constant?
No cosmological,
well,
no.
Well,
the cosmolo,
no.
The cosmological constant can be thought
of as part of T mu nu.
Yeah.
No,
we haven't,
we haven't said anything about cosmological constant,
whether or not it's there.
Yeah,
okay.
From this point of view,
the cosmological constant can either be
thought of as an energy-momentum tensor,
or a component to the energy-momentum tensor.
Let's call it T mu nu cosmological.
So the cosmological constant would be
some lambda times g mu nu.
So then,
if there was a cosmological constant,
you might write 8 pi g
times lambda times g mu nu.
Or this number here is just a constant.
Let's just get rid of it and call it some,
I guess it is really
the cosmological constant that appears there.
You could,
it only depends on geometry,
a number times geometry.
You can shift it to the other side of the
equation and think of it as part of the geometry,
part of the geometric side of the equation.
Or you can leave it on the right side
and think of it as part of the energy-momentum.
So the cosmological constant can
be thought of in either way.
Did Einstein use the equation you derived
tonight to calculate the orbit of Mercury,
which was then observed by astronomers?
So that equation was used.
Do you know of a source that
would show how that calculation was done?
Good question.
Let me see if I can find one.
It is probably in one of Einstein's papers,
all of which I have at home,
and I will see if I can find it.
Well,
I know how it was done.
You want to see it actually done,
though.
It was done by,
he didn't have the Schwarzschild solution,
but he did have the
approximation to the Schwarzschild solution,
at a fairly large distance.
Now,
the surface of the Sun is way,
way out at a distance much larger
than the Schwarzschild radius of the Sun.
Of course,
the Sun is not a black hole.
But outside the solar radius,
the geometry is exactly the
same as the Schwarzschild geometry.
He didn't have the Schwarzschild geometry,
but he had a pretty good approximation to it
that,
you know,
a hundred times larger
distance than the Schwarzschild radius.
It's more than a hundred times larger.
It's a million times larger than the Schwarzschild radius.
So he knew how to make a good approximation that
was true far from the center of a gravitating object.
And then he just solved orbits in that geometry.
And again,
in an approximation.
The thing that allows you to do that is the fact
that the Sun is so much bigger than the Schwarzschild radius.
And that means the current is
much bigger than the Schwarzschild radius.
So the corrections from Newton are small.
You can think of it as just small corrections from
Newton and work it out in a kind of perturbation theory.
Perturbation theory means just small
corrections to something you already know.
Most likely what he did was just
take the Keplerian orbits for a light ray.
You know,
just a straight line.
And do a light ray.
And do a little bit of
perturbation theory and work it out.
You asked me about Mercury or the bending of light?
I forget what you asked me.
Mercury,
yeah.
So he undoubtedly just took the ordinary Keplerian orbit.
Took the Newtonian solution plus a small correction.
And fit the small correction on the left hand
side to the small correction on the right hand side.
But then Schwarzschild immediately,
I think within a year or maybe less,
calculated his exact solution of the equations.
And from there you could do much,
much better than...
Okay.
You know that pretty much the
ordinary 1 over r squared potential,
or force law,
is the only power law,
force law,
which allows the orbits to be
closed without a precession of the orbit.
It's a curious fact and it's somewhat accidental.
For more,
please visit us at stanford.edu.