Stanford University.
Okay,
back to thermodynamics.
Now,
when I was going through my lecture notes for tonight,
I realized just how subtle some things can be.
And really why it is that students
eyes go like this when they're studying thermodynamics.
It is full of all these fancy calculus tricks,
with sometimes very little intuition
about what's really going on.
But it's really all in the calculus tricks.
You can do,
you can,
we're going to study tonight a particular,
and only one problem.
We're going to study the problem of pressure,
of an ideal gas tonight.
Now,
intuitively we know where the pressure comes from.
It comes from the molecules bouncing
against the walls of the system.
We could calculate it just by estimating the,
we've already calculated the average energy
of every molecule,
or as a three-halves kT,
three-halves the temperature.
We can estimate how many of
them are moving in each direction,
because they're pretty isotropic.
You might wonder,
incidentally,
if the molecules near the wall are isotropic.
After all,
the presence of the wall
influences what's going on near it.
And you might think,
well,
maybe there are more going horizontal to the wall
than going,
you know,
parallel to the wall and going the other way.
It turns out not to be true.
That even very close to the wall,
the distribution of velocities is still pretty isotropic.
But you might wonder whether that's
a principle or just an accident.
You might also wonder whether the velocities
near the wall happen to be different
than the velocities in the interior far from the wall.
In which case you'd be
making a mistake by just taking
the good old three-halves kT and using it
for every molecule no matter where you are.
Turns out you're not making a mistake.
But how do you know you're not making a mistake?
You know from statistical mechanics.
You know from an honest evaluation,
an honest set of principles,
which don't use intuitive pictures of
molecules hitting the wall and so forth,
but which really,
which really use the
basic foundations of statistical mechanics.
But the foundations of
statistical mechanics are mathematical.
They're very mathematical.
They're not comp- they're not hard,
but they're mathematical.
And as I sort of
emphasized to you over and over,
in situations where the rules are mathematical
and when you purposefully give up intuition,
you purposefully give up intuition because you're not
sure that your intuitions are correct.
Such as,
for example,
that the velocity distribution near the wall is
the same as in the interior of the wall.
So you purposefully give up
intuition and you ride the mathematics.
When you're riding the mathematics,
the rules are sort of these autopilot rules
where you first figure out what you want
and then you just start going with it,
using whatever tricks you have until you get there.
And then you just start going with it,
using whatever tricks you have until you suddenly
find yourself with a formula that you recognize.
And that's just the way it is.
You get good at it after a while,
and the great physicists that I
know all were very good at it.
And I don't mean people
who just studied statistical mechanics.
I mean all of the very,
very good physicists I know.
Somehow love thermodynamics.
Why?
It's fun.
But it's the fun of surprises.
It's the fun of surprising relationships which
suddenly fit together and tell you some physics.
That's what the attraction is for many of us.
Einstein was the grand master of thermodynamics.
Feynman was a grand master of it.
I'm a grand master of it.
Well,
maybe.
Maybe.
It's good stuff.
Anyway...
In the end,
when you finish your mathematics,
when you've written the mathematics,
can you check it with your intuition?
Because it's kind of tempting.
To see,
does that make sense?
Yes.
It does.
And what you're really doing is checking the intuition,
not the mathematics.
I mean,
it could easily be wrong that the distribution of velocities
near the wall is the same as in the interior.
You don't want to rely on that.
You don't want to go through
all of the mathematics and then say,
well,
I think I've proved that the rules
of calculus work in the right order.
I think it's going to work out okay because they agree
with my naive intuitions about the way molecules behave near the wall.
It's the other way.
You're checking your intuitions from the mathematics.
Okay,
so we could do a little calculation
of calculating the pressure on the walls,
given that the average velocities
of every molecule is three-halves kT.
We would probably do the calculation by saying,
let's not even talk about averages.
Let's say this room is filled
with molecules which are moving with velocity.
Now,
one-half mv squared equals three-halves kT,
right?
Let's just say three-halves temperature.
Use our,
you know,
the equation.
And,
you add three units equals
three-halves is single- einheit times m,
we got two-halves c.
And,
there we are.
Whoo.
A sin segT equals one-half mv squared.
Okay,
we got that right.
So we can solve this.
This is kind of fascinating.
I also,
this is a fact of science.
If you mean,
anyway,hur sixties or eighties is,
but nearly 모두 in Europe was made in the
lotus era and it seems to be timearius of haya.
that their direction of their velocities is isotropic.
We can calculate the number of
collisions on the wall per unit time.
We can calculate the momentum delivered
by each particle to the wall.
Particles bounce off the wall,
and the perpendicular component of momentum,
which is originally going this way,
is then going this way.
We can calculate the momentum delivered to the wall,
and,
of course,
force is rate of change of momentum,
and so we can calculate the force on the wall.
Pressure is the force per unit area,
and so we can calculate that.
It's fun.
You can try to do it yourself,
and you'll get the right answer.
You'll get the right answer.
In the case where the molecules
are completely free and so forth,
but that's not really good enough.
We really want a set
of rules which are good enough
that they could take into
account collisions between the molecules.
My God,
collisions between the molecules,
they could upset the whole thing a lot,
and they do.
And they do.
We want the set of rules which is robust,
and which doesn't depend on the detailed,
oversimplified,
supersimplified model of a free gas.
A free gas means a gas of particles
where the particles are not interacting with each other,
the ideal gas.
So the ideal gas is a place that's easy.
It's easy to do things with,
but it's not very general.
The rules of statistical mechanics are very,
very general,
and would be sufficient,
to calculate,
if you can do the calculations,
if you can do,
then you can calculate the relationship
between the pressure and other variables very generally.
What is it that we want?
We want something called the equation of state.
We would like to calculate
or know what the pressure is
as a function of temperature,
volume,
but the,
what is it that determines,
determines the gas in this room,
basically the temperature.
That's about it.
There's also the number of gas molecules,
oh,
there's also the,
sorry,
there's the number of gas molecules in the room,
number of molecules,
temperature,
and possibly the volume,
but it won't depend on the volume.
No,
sorry,
it will depend on the volume,
depend on the volume.
We would like to calculate the
pressure in terms of those things.
So we need a theory.
We need a set of principles.
Um,
um,
we're going to describe those principles tonight
and work out,
I hope,
the pressure of an ideal gas.
Um,
with no intuition whatever,
no picture in our minds of what we're doing.
I'm not saying that pictures
in your minds aren't good things
for understanding physics,
but there are times when
you want to suppress the pictures
and simply go with the mathematics and,
uh,
the statistical mechanics as one of them
because you want your rules to be general.
Okay.
Let me just remind you over here on this blackboard
of a couple of,
of a fact,
mathematical fact that we worked out before.
And then I want to prove a little theorem.
This is one of the damn trickiest theorems.
It,
uh,
drives people crazy.
It drove me crazy.
And I proved it once.
Once when I was a young,
young man.
And then I come back to
it every time I teach this subject.
And every time I teach this subject,
I cannot remember how you prove it.
And I have to sit with a
piece of paper for a half an hour
until I find,
and it's a very,
very simple,
uh,
theorem.
And then we'll use those theorems,
uh,
to calculate the pressure.
But I want to get to
some mathematics on the blackboard first.
Just so you know,
I'm not going to be doing this all day long.
Just so we have them.
And I'll try to remember not to erase them
so that we'll have them when we need them.
Please don't let me erase.
Alright,
the first thing had to do
with entropy.
And entropy is the summation,
you know what it is,
summation minus the summation of P log P.
P sub i log P sub i.
And if the distribution is the Boltzmann distribution,
it's minus the summation.
Now P sub i is one over the partition function.
E to the minus beta times
the energy of the ith level.
That's P sub i.
And then logarithm of P sub i.
So what's the logarithm of this object here?
It's minus beta E sub i,
the logarithm of this one,
minus log z.
Alright,
so,
um,
everybody recognizes this.
This is a product.
The logarithm is the sum of the logarithms
of the two factors in the product.
So that's minus log z,
minus beta E sub i.
Minus signs cancel.
Might as well get rid of them now
so that we don't make mistakes later.
And then if you remember,
the first term here,
is just beta times the average energy.
Probability for i
times E sub i,
when summed is just the average energy.
So the first term just gives us beta
times the thing we've been calling E,
the average energy.
Okay,
so let's get rid of it.
We've,
we got it.
Now let's get the second term here.
Well,
it's times log z.
Alright,
we have this sum to do here.
z and log z don't depend on i.
What depends on i is only this
minus E to the minus beta i.
What is the sum of E
to the minus beta i over i?
It's z.
That's the definition of z.
So,
the z that you get from the summation
cancels the z over here,
and all you get is plus log z.
That's the entropy.
I would have said like n log z.
n log z?
What is n?
Well,
you have a summation
summing a bunch of terms that are one.
What's one?
The summation of E to the minus beta i,
Okay.
is z.
Cancels the z in the denominator.
Okay.
It's easier to see if you
keep the first part of that summation
just as p and i,
rather than backing it up.
Mm-hmm.
Yeah,
that's true.
Right.
Okay,
let's just rearrange it a little bit
into a sort of standard form.
This is,
this is the formula.
This is the formula.
Let's remember that beta is one over the temperature.
And let's,
okay,
so we have S.
You have to one over it.
One over it.
Sorry,
one over.
What did I do?
Beta.
This was beta E one over temperature.
Okay,
right.
So let's multiply it by temperature
and write the formula in the following fashion,
only because this is sort of standard.
Energy minus T times S.
Energy,
is it energy minus?
Yes,
I think it's energy minus T times S
is equal to minus T log z.
I've multiplied by T,
so that means we have T times S.
We get rid of the T in the energy term,
energy minus T times S,
and that's equal to T times log z
with a minus sign.
I think with a minus sign.
Yeah.
Yes,
with a minus sign.
This thing has a name.
It's not important what its name is.
Well,
it's important only because you may want
to be using it over and over.
If it occurs over and over in physics,
we'll want to have it given a name.
For our purposes,
we really just want this formula here.
This is the important formula here
that we're going to use.
Okay.
But we might as well give this a name.
First of all,
its name is A,
and it's called the Helmholtz free energy.
Things are given names when
they occur over and over again.
We're going to find out
that it plays a leading role
in calculating things like pressure
and all kinds of other things.
Okay,
so this is called A.
And it's another thermodynamic variable.
We have energy.
What do we have?
We have temperature.
We have entropy.
And we now have a new
thing called the Helmholtz free energy.
Helmholtz.
H-E-L-M.
H-O-L-Z.
And at the moment,
it's simply an object which has occurred once
and therefore not very interesting.
We're going to see it occurring once more tonight.
But I tell you that
it occurs all over the place.
Okay,
that's one piece of information
that we'll need in this form.
We don't need the fact that it's called A
or that it's called Helmholtz free energy.
We need this equation.
The next equation,
this is not the hard,
this is not the theorem which drives me crazy.
The theorem which drives me crazy,
I will...
What we're going to be doing is
introducing yet another variable into the problem.
I call variables of this kind control parameters.
And in notes,
you will see something about control parameters.
Control parameters are parameters that you
as an experimenter easily can change.
They're parameters which are macroscopic.
They're not trying to change details
of one molecule at a time.
And an example would be the
volume of the container of your gas.
You could have a piston.
You could have a block,
a cylinder of gas with a piston in it
and,
you know,
move the piston back and forth.
And in the process,
change the volume of gas.
So volume is a control parameter.
Other control parameters,
magnetic field on a system,
the electric field on a system,
or applied electric field,
applied magnetic field.
I don't know,
can you think of any others easily?
No,
no.
Pressure,
we're going to see the relationship.
Yeah,
you can,
but...
Variables come in pairs.
One is usually called the control parameter
and one is called the conjugate thermodynamical variable.
Pressure and volume are closely connected
and they're conjugate pairs.
Yes,
you can change the pressure.
You can have a pressure gauge in here
and by moving the piston,
change the pressure.
But,
of course,
what you're doing is changing the volume
and the response is a change in pressure.
Are you assuming that all the molecules are the same?
Absolutely not.
So there could be different gases.
We're not even assuming it's made of atoms.
Whatever it's made out of.
But,
yeah,
we're not assuming that it's a gas.
Could be a liquid.
Could even be a solid.
Could be a solid in here,
and we'd be squeezing on the solid.
That's why it's important to have general methods.
You cannot use the ideal gas
law for a solid in there.
What I was thinking was that you were changing
the amount of material inside.
Yeah,
you could change the number of molecules.
that's a control parameter.
Right.
Okay.
Could you have steam and condensed water?
You have two states.
If they happen to be in equilibrium,
there is a temperature.
If you're at the boiling temperature exactly,
then you can have steam and water in there simultaneously.
Yes.
Yeah.
So it's neither a gas
nor a liquid in that situation.
Right.
And if it was in a gravitational field,
the liquid might sit on the bottom
and the gas might sit on the top,
but it would still be thermal equilibrium.
And you could still study it by the methods
we're going to be using.
Okay,
so let's,
I'm going to write down,
I want this theorem just
because we're going to use it.
So let's put it on the theorem blackboard over here.
Or our,
I don't know whether it's a theorem.
It's too simple to be a full-blown theorem.
But here is what it says.
Supposing you have two functions of two variables.
That sounds complicated.
One of the functions we're going to call E.
It will be the energy later.
And the other function we're going to call the entropy.
S,
we're going to call S.
And these two functions are
functions of two other variables.
Namely,
remember,
energy,
entropy over here.
Two other variables,
the independent variables in the problem.
And those we're going to call,
T and V.
I'm not,
there's no significance to the way I'm lining them up.
Just think of these as the independent variables
that we can control from outside.
The temperature,
if we like,
and the volume.
So those are independent variables.
And given the nature of the system,
given the nature of the gas,
whatever it happens to be,
given the temperature and the volume,
the dependent variables,
the ones that if you knew enough,
you could calculate,
would be the energy and the entropy.
Those are the two variables.
Now,
some was in there that might,
yeah,
those are the things that we're interested in.
Alright,
the following theorem.
You're going to hate this theorem
because it's going to be totally unintuitive
and you're going to ask,
what's it good for?
Looks like a silly theorem.
But here's the theorem.
And it has nothing specific
to do with the particular nature
of these functions,
of what they are.
Two dependent variables,
two independent variables.
Okay?
It says,
the theorem says that the derivative of the energy,
or E,
the derivative of E,
with respect to the independent variable V,
at fixed S,
now that's a funny thing to do.
If these are the independent variables,
you usually differentiate the dependent variables
keeping some independent variable fixed.
But we're going to do something different.
We're going to differentiate E with respect to volume,
keeping the entropy fixed.
We'll see what that means in a moment.
Okay?
That's what we're interested in.
And that's,
the sum of two terms,
or actually the difference of two terms,
one of them is the derivative of the energy,
of E,
with respect to the,
with respect to the volume,
keeping the temperature fixed.
Well,
that looks a little more normal.
We're differentiating a dependent variable
with respect to an independent variable
keeping the other independent variable fixed.
That's what we normally do in calculus.
But,
there's an extra term here,
and the extra term is minus the derivative of E
with respect to the entropy
at fixed volume,
which is another little weirdo,
calculating the derivative of E
keeping S fixed,
no,
sorry,
calculating the derivative of E
with respect to S
keeping the volume fixed.
That's another weird thing.
And then the derivative of S
with respect to the volume
keeping the temperature fixed.
That's a minus.
Hmm?
Plus or minus?
Minus.
Minus,
yeah.
Multiply.
Sorry,
where?
Last term.
The second term is the multiplication of the...
Oh,
this is multiplying.
Multiply,
yeah.
Yeah.
This is a really weird,
totally unintuitive,
and I think if you sat
down to try to prove it,
you'd probably wander around in the,
in the dark for quite a while.
So it takes me,
I would say it takes me
a half an hour on a good day
to remind myself what this means,
how you prove it,
and then I'll be back in a minute.
Do you want to see the proof?
It's a lovely little proof.
Yeah.
I like it so much
because I figured it out myself.
You sort of fall in love with those little things
that you figure out yourself when you're young.
But I think I could still do it now.
In fact,
I did do it now.
I did it this afternoon.
All right.
Let's draw our independent variables.
Let's hope I can do it now.
Temperature and volume.
Or T and V.
Okay.
Now,
there are two dependent variables.
One of them is called S.
Let's draw the contour lines of S.
But I'm only going to draw one contour line.
I'm going to draw some specific line
along which S is constant.
I don't know if it looks like that or not.
I'm just drawing a line.
There's S.
S is equal to some constant.
Of course,
there are other contour lines,
but I'm not going to bother drawing them.
There's one contour line.
That's S equals constant along there.
That's fixed S.
That's the important thing.
And we want to calculate
the rate of change of E.
That's another variable.
With respect to volume.
In other words,
how fast E is changing
as you change the volume by the volume.
But along a line of constant S.
That's what this says.
Keeping S constant.
So here we are.
We're at a point over here.
We're going to change the volume
to go to a point over here.
And we're going to stay
on a line of constant S.
So along that line of constant S,
we're calculating,
if you like,
delta E by delta V.
Along that line of constant S.
I use the notation delta E and delta V
because I like to remind myself
that these things are actually ratios of differences.
Alright.
Now,
let's write down the following formula.
When I'm using delta E,
I'm not distinguishing it from DE.
It's infinitely small.
It's a differential.
It just helps remember what you're doing
to remember that they're ratios of small differences.
So delta E is partial of E
with respect to volume
at fixed temperature times the change in volume.
And moving from any point to any other point,
the rate of change of E with respect to V
at fixed temperature times dV
plus DE by DT
at fixed V times delta T.
Alright.
What these are,
if you like,
these two things are
the first one is the rate of change of E
with respect to V
keeping the temperature fixed.
In other words,
it has to do with moving from here to here.
And the other one is
the rate of change of E
as you change temperature
keeping volume fixed,
keeping V fixed times delta T.
Is that the usual definition of partial derivative?
Yeah,
yeah,
yeah.
This is perfectly normal.
Nothing special yet.
Okay.
Now,
the first term here
is the first term over here.
It's this second one
that we want to manipulate and fool around with
and see if we can
understand why it's equal to this.
Alright.
So,
there's two steps.
The first is to write
that the rate of change of E
with respect to T
let's move it down on the blackboard
give it some more room
plus
what did I have?
DE by dV
at constant
sorry,
the E by DT
at constant V
times delta T.
Alright.
The first thing we're going to do
is write
now all of this is justified
you know,
you can
at any given point
you can start playing in any number of different directions
manipulating various things
and so the process is a sort of branching tree
of possible formulas that you can write.
But fortunately it's not that big.
And if you're lucky
you'll hit one along the way.
And you'll have a tree somewhere
that says
I noticed something good.
And I'm really afraid that sort
of is the way it is.
Eventually you get good at it
and you get an instinct
you get an instinct for what to do next.
Alright.
So,
DE by dV
let's just look at this.
We have on here DE by dS
at constant volume.
But this is DE by DT
So think of the volume as fixed
and
DE by DT
at constant volume
is the same as
DE by dS
at constant volume
times the S
by
I forgot what I had here.
What the...
I had the E by DT,
right?
Yeah,
I had the E by DT.
So the S by DT
also at constant volume.
Okay,
so here I have my DE by dS
at constant volume.
Oh,
let's do one more thing now.
Sorry.
We're interested in the rate of
change of E with respect to V.
That means we should divide by delta V
on both sides.
We should get rid of the delta V
divide it by delta V
divide it by delta V.
Okay,
so now we're cooking.
We're cooking.
But where so far have I put in
that I've moved along the line of constant S?
I haven't.
Nothing in here has told me
that I'm moving along the line
from one point to another
along a line of constant entropy.
Now why we're interested in constant entropy
will come out.
Not from this formula,
but it will come out soon enough.
So,
good.
Okay,
so
we're moving along this line.
How can we characterize this line?
This curve at this point
is characterized by a slope.
That slope is just delta T by delta V.
Let's see what we can figure out about it.
Let's use a little bit of calculus
to see if we can work out something about
delta T by delta V.
So,
let's write down the condition
that we're moving on a line of constant S.
That means along this line
dS is equal to zero.
Along this line,
And now,
what we have to do is write
that dS
is partial of S
with respect to volume
at fixed T
times d volume.
Delta,
sorry,
delta volume.
Plus partial of S
with respect to T
at fixed volume times delta T.
But along this line,
dS is equal to zero.
Right?
dS is equal to zero along this line.
It's the definition of the line.
So,
let's make this equal to zero.
And now we're going to be able to get a
formula for delta T by delta V
in terms of these partial derivatives.
You see where I'm going?
Alright,
so let's divide by delta V
because what we want is delta T by delta V.
So,
let's divide by delta V.
Here we have our target over here,
delta T by delta V.
And we can now immediately read off
that delta T
by delta V
is equal to minus
dS by dV at constant S.
So,
we're going to get a formula
at constant T
divided by dS by dT
at constant V.
This would be true for any function S whatever
on this map here,
that the slope of the contour lines,
this is the slope of the contour lines,
is related to certain partial derivatives.
I don't know if I...
It takes me a minute or
two to see why this is.
I have to go through
this little step here to see.
But now we know what
delta T by delta V is.
So,
let's put it in.
It first of all gives us a minus sign.
Okay.
And then,
delta T by delta V
is partial of S,
let's write it out,
partial of S with respect to
V at constant T.
Divided by partial of S
with respect to T
at constant V.
So,
we have four factors in there.
Four factors,
three in the numerator,
one in the denominator.
This is in the denominator here,
dS by dT.
But fortunately,
by a great stroke of luck,
the thing in the denominator
happens to be the same thing
as one of the terms in the numerator.
Alright?
So,
again,
as I said,
we could have gone off
in all sorts of random directions,
but this direction seems like a good one
because this thing is getting simpler now.
So,
let's get rid of the numerator,
sorry,
the denominator,
and the numerator.
And we're done.
Well,
we're done.
What have we done?
We've proved this little lemma here.
Okay.
I cannot prove this lemma without drawing this picture.
It's something you ought to be able to prove
just by mechanical steps,
but I cannot prove it without drawing the picture
and then figuring out what I'm doing.
Can I ask a question,
please?
In order to reduce,
we have to be sure that the derivative of
entropy to temp
with respect to temperature constant V
is not zero.
Yeah.
Do we know that?
For most systems in most circumstances,
yes.
There are some special cases
where it's not true,
and then you'll have to be more careful.
But generally speaking,
yes.
Entropy is a monotonic function of temperature.
And the reason is,
the reason is simple.
The Boltzmann distribution,
as you change the temperature,
if you increase the temperature,
it gets narrower.
As you decrease the temperature,
it gets broader.
And entropy is just a measure of that width.
So,
typically,
yes,
there's some very special cases,
but,
uh,
yeah,
things are
nicely behaved as a rule.
Okay,
so here we have our
two facts.
The third fact
has to do with the definition of pressure,
and I want to make very clear that pressure is
just one special case,
of a response to a control parameter.
I'll show you what I mean
by a response to a control parameter.
So,
I was going to say one,
one,
one thing we have to do,
but actually two,
but they're easy.
The first thing is to understand what pressure really is.
Here's our cylinder.
Here's our piston.
The molecules in here are
hitting the piston and so forth,
exerting pressure on it.
Supposing we move the piston a little bit.
The pressure in the interior
does work on the piston.
Okay?
If we move the piston out,
the pressure pushes out
and does work on the,
uh,
that work,
where does that work come from?
That work is energy.
The work done on the piston
is equal to the change,
an opposite sign,
if the,
if the gas does work on the piston,
then there's a change in the energy in here
of negative sign.
Okay?
Uh,
I'll tell you what,
maybe,
maybe it's smarter to put this upright
in the following way,
and you can think about it.
Yeah.
The,
imagine the piston rises a little bit.
Well,
that means there's been an increase
in the energy in the,
in the gravitational potential energy
of the piston in this case.
Alright?
That's called the work done on the piston.
Okay?
By the,
uh,
by the pressure.
And by energy conservation,
any work that's done on the piston
must be taken away from the,
uh,
from the gas.
So energy conservation tells us
that the change in energy of the gas
is minus the work done on the piston.
Now let's suppose that the
area of the piston is A,
and let's suppose that the piston is moved
by an amount dx,
vertically.
Well,
dx vertically,
then,
and let's,
we also have to imagine something else.
We have to imagine,
first of all,
that we do this slowly.
Um,
some odd things can happen if you do it fast.
For example,
you could pull a piston out so fast
that no molecule has a chance
to hit the piston as it's moving.
Then during that period,
there'd be no pressure on it.
Okay?
That's a rather extreme situation.
But it does illustrate for you
that you want to define pressure
by being able to average over many clouds
and not by being able
to measure the amount of energy
So you want to do this slowly.
You want to do this in a very slow motion.
And there's something else you want to do.
You want to make sure that no energy
comes into the system from outside.
In other words,
you want to insulate the walls of the system.
Okay?
I remember when I was a undergraduate,
I learned the word adiabatic.
I had no idea what it meant,
but my professor of engineering told me
that it means that a system is insulated
from heat coming into it or out of it.
And then later on,
when I was in graduate school,
another professor told me adiabatic means slowly.
Well,
what adiabatic means is slowly and
no heat comes into the system.
Okay?
If you move the piston adiabatically
with no heat coming into the system,
and the change of the energy of the gas
is minus the work done on the piston
and minus the work done on the piston is
minus is the force on the piston.
That's the pressure times the area.
Pressure times area.
That's force.
Pressure times area is force.
That's definition of pressure.
Force per unit area.
That's force times dx.
And area times dx is the
change in the volume of the gas.
Right?
Area times dx is the change in the volume,
so we can write adx as dv.
This is what's true,
and this defines pressure.
You can...
It defines pressure.
In fact,
here's the way we can write it.
We can write it that
it is the change in energy
with respect to volume...
The only question is what do we keep fixed
in doing this derivative?
What do we keep fixed?
At some rate of change
of energy with respect to volume,
under the circumstance that
we do the operation adiabatically.
Okay.
Now,
there's another aspect of the notion of adiabatic.
Anybody know another meaning to adiabatic?
No change in entropy?
The second law of thermodynamics,
which we will come to,
says that entropy...
always increases except when it doesn't.
When it doesn't increase,
it stays the same.
It never decreases.
Okay.
Never say never,
but never mind.
Um...
Okay.
What are the processes where the entropy doesn't increase,
where it stays the same?
Those are the adiabatic ones.
So let's...
Let me explain to you...
I'm going to explain it to you
from a quantum mechanical point of view.
And the only aspect we're
going to use with quantum mechanics
is that energy levels are discrete.
Nothing else.
In other words,
the E...
There they are.
E sub i up there.
Definite energy levels.
So we have our box of gas.
And there's a...
And here I'm going to plot
the energy levels.
And it has a collection of energy levels.
A collection of possible energies
that the gas in the box can have.
Not the single particle energy levels.
The possible energies of everything inside the box.
There's some discrete collection of numbers.
In quantum mechanics,
in any case.
Now we're going to change the volume.
We're going to change the volume.
And what happens to the energy levels?
Do they stay the same?
No.
Why should they?
If you want to calculate the energy levels,
you have to solve some problems,
some Schrodinger equation,
whatever.
And the Schrodinger equation depends
on the size of the box.
And the energy levels change.
Actually,
I've got it right upside down.
If you increase the volume of the box,
the individual energy levels surely go down,
but it doesn't matter because we're just being general.
We could imagine a situation
where the energy levels go up.
It doesn't matter.
All right.
Now what is true?
Now this is something that I'm
not going to prove for you.
It's a quantum mechanical theorem.
It is called the adiabatic theorem.
And what it says is that
if a system has a definite energy
and you slowly change the parameter,
in this case the volume,
whatever control parameter it happens to be,
if you slowly change it,
the system will stop.
It will stay and simply ride along the energy level,
keeping not the same energy,
but it won't jump from one energy level to another.
It will simply stay.
If this is the 500,000th and 37th energy level,
the system will stay in the 537,
whatever I said,
whatever the number is.
In other words,
the energy levels will be remembered,
and
if it started here,
it will be here.
If you change a system rapidly,
this is not what happens.
you can have jumps from one energy level to another.
That's what's special about adiabatic.
If you go slowly,
the energy levels,
the value of the energy changes slowly,
but you don't jump from one to another.
That means if you started out
with a collection of problems,
you realized that you weren't necessarily
on the same plane.
You think you're on the same plane,
but you show it to
a set of people and then
you change themittal graph,
you get what's called gibbons chess,
to improve the depends of each subtype data.
Well,
you'll still have zero everywheres except
for the energy level over here.
If you have
probability a half here and a half here,
it will remain a half and a half.
So while the
energies change,
the p sub i's don't.
And the entropy is just
built from the p sub i's.
It doesn't care what the energies are.
If you have a probability distribution,
then
s is equal to minus summation i
p sub i log p sub i.
And if all the probabilities stay
the same,
then you can be sure
that the entropy stays the same.
That is why an adiabatic process
is also sometimes called an isentropic process,
meaning to say that the entropy doesn't change.
That's the general definition of adiabatic.
Okay.
No change in entropy.
Now,
of course,
slow would not be good enough if you could put
heat into the system.
If you put heat into the system,
well,
that's corrupting it and
changing the system,
changing the energy.
That's not what you want to do.
Adiabatic
means slow with no added or subtracted heat.
And under those circumstances,
adiabatic
also means constant entropy.
So now we know what
to hold fixed in this formula.
The change
in the energy with respect
to volume holding the entropy fixed.
Well,
that,
of course,
is the reason that I went and...
That's the reason we...
Okay.
...spent a little bit of
time on a formula up there.
This formula is good enough,
but
it's kind of hard to calculate things at fixed entropy.
You have to figure out...
What you're
usually provided with,
the easy thing to calculate,
is things at fixed temperature.
You stick
in the temperature into the
Boltzmann distribution and you calculate.
And what you get out is
an answer which depends on the temperature.
The easy thing usually
to calculate is how things vary with temperature,
just because you...
The temperature is a thing
which directly appears in the Boltzmann distribution here.
So it's always easier to work as a function
of temperature than as a function of anything else.
Okay.
So what I'd like to do is to
convert this to something that involves derivatives with
respect to temperature instead of entropy,
and then we can go
back and see what we can
learn from the Boltzmann distribution.
Okay.
So here we have that this is equal,
then,
to the derivative of the energy with respect
to the volume at fixed temperature.
Okay.
In other words,
holding fixed the temperature
in the Boltzmann distribution minus...
I'm
going to rewrite this...
Minus the derivative of the
entropy with respect to the volume
at fixed temperature times the derivative of
the energy with respect to entropy at fixed
volume.
Now this looks terrible.
Looks too complicated.
But fortunately,
this is something
we've seen before.
Anybody remember what dE by dS is?
Temperature.
The temperature.
Holding the volume fixed.
Holding the volume fixed means you're holding
the system fixed.
You're not changing the control parameters.
It's just the original
system with fixed energy levels,
and you're holding that fixed.
Under those circumstances,
dE by dS is just the temperature.
Remember,
that's dE equals T dS.
dE equals T dS.
So
dE by dS is the temperature.
So this is not quite so bad.
We can replace this factor
over here just by the temperature.
It's getting simpler.
Do we have a negative sign?
A negative sign for pressure?
Yeah,
from here.
Thank you.
Now the only derivatives are derivatives
with respect to volume at fixed temperature.
That
sounds promising.
Volume and temperature can be
thought of as independent variables,
and
the only derivatives that appear
are sort of familiar things,
how the energy changes
with respect to volume at fixed temperature,
and how S changes with respect to volume at
fixed temperature.
T,
that's just the temperature.
step this also happens to equal
minus the derivative with respect to the
volume at fixed temperature of the energy
minus T times S okay the first
term you can see the e by dv
that's the e by dv at fixed temperature the
second term if I differentiated with
respect to volume at fixed temperature I
would get two terms from the product here
one of them would be T times the
derivative of S with respect to the
volume that's this one what's the other
one the other one is derivative with
respect to the volume of the temperature
at fixed temperature how does the
temperature change as you vary the
volume if you keep the
temperature fixed it doesn't change right
okay
so the second term isn't there and
now we have our fundamental theorem that the
pressure is equal to the derivative with
respect to the volume of the Helmholtz
free energy at fixed temperature now
that is much simpler than anything else
you can imagine for the pressure and in
fact we know a little more we know that
the
temperature is equal to the volume
of the Helmholtz free energy at fixed
temperature and the volume of the Helmholtz free
energy is just minus T log Z so if
we can calculate the damn partition
function we're sort of finished so let's
write that again I think it's plus
now this would be plus plus the derivative
with respect to the volume this is
at fixed temperature so we can take the
temperature on the outside let's we don't
need the plus sign there the temperature
se square of square so these
things have the bottom side president just
to square down so we
can take the top of the
right above the bottom side and
then we can take the bottom of
the finns part checks and then we got
to find p is equal to degree p critical
number
for the
temperater
we
Everything I've done up till now is completely general.
It wouldn't matter if it were a liquid,
a gas,
a plasma,
or a solid,
a solid inside the cylinder.
Doesn't matter what the chemical composition is.
This is what statistical mechanics,
not kinetic theory.
Kinetic theory is this intuitive
picture of molecules bouncing around.
This is what statistical mechanics says.
Pressure is equal to temperature times
the derivative of the partition function.
Now you can calculate,
you can,
sorry,
you can carry this out for basically any control parameter.
I just used volume as
a control parameter because it's familiar.
For any control parameter,
there is always a derivative of energy,
with respect to the control parameter,
at fixed entropy.
That is called the conjugate thermodynamical variable.
Volume and pressure
are conjugate variables thermodynamically.
There are many others.
I'm not going to go into them now,
but anytime you have a control parameter,
then you can ask how the energy of the
system depends on the control parameter at fixed entropy,
Moon finds another variable力 to Gefühl
which plays the role of pressure alright,
but let's now that we've
cities,
This is going faster than I thought.
I thought this was going to take a long time.
Well,
okay.
Yeah.
In the world,
there's one point.
You see the power of defining,
it's not that I was saying,
you see the power
that this quantity potentially can have.
It just appears all over.
Do you remember another thing that log z depended on?
No,
not that it depended on log z.
The derivative of log z with
respect to beta was the average energy.
Log z has a lot of stuff in it.
Okay,
when you know log z,
you know a lot of stuff.
All right,
again,
you wanted to ask a question.
Yeah,
it has to do with sort of the adiabatic thing.
It seems that this principle
is a constraint that's throughout thermodynamics.
What happens if you don't use,
if you're even testing quickly
and it's not an adiabatic movement,
you have a potential energy component to it.
That's the only difference,
isn't it?
No.
Then it becomes a complicated non-equilibrium process.
I just gave you an example.
If you move it fast enough.
No molecule will hit the wall.
There won't be any pressure.
But,
of course,
what will happen is you've made a very sudden change.
And how will the system respond?
The system will respond by a
shock wave going through the fluid.
You know,
imagine that you had a fluid and you suddenly,
it's easier to think about
if you suddenly squeeze the fluid.
You can change the volume in either direction.
You suddenly squeeze the fluid.
You make a shock wave going through the system.
You'll also make a shock
wave if you pull it away.
And very complicated things happen.
And it's not controlled by simple statistical mechanics.
It's controlled by the whole dynamics,
the whole non-equilibrium dynamics.
The only thing you can be
sure of is that the entropy increases.
Now,
you can actually work out,
for the special case that I said a moment ago,
that you move the piston so fast
that no single molecule hits the wall.
Then you know that there's
no work done on the piston.
And the change in the energy is absolutely zero.
If the change in energy is zero,
but the volume has changed.
So you can learn some things about that situation.
You can work out some things about it.
You can figure out what the final temperature is.
It's solvable.
But if you were to have squeezed the gas suddenly,
then all kinds of very complicated things happen.
But going out,
if you do it going out suddenly,
the system is not in equilibrium,
but the system will return to equilibrium,
which it acts as a kind of potential energy
that gets turned into kinetic energy
as the molecules fill up that space.
Yeah.
But the question is,
what temperature does it return to equilibrium?
And that can be a very,
very complicated problem.
Not easy.
Sometimes,
once in a while,
it's easy.
Question?
Yeah.
I'm confused about something in your derivation.
Of what?
T and V are the independent variables.
E and S are the independent functions,
if you will.
Yeah.
Those independent variables.
So if you get two independent variables,
T and V,
I don't even kind of know
what is delta T over delta V?
Then you need to...
This one?
Yeah,
what does that mean for two independent variables
to talk about delta T over delta V?
This was delta V and delta T,
given that you were moving
along a line of constant entropy.
Okay?
That's what we used here.
We calculated delta T by delta V along a
line of constant entropy by saying dS equals zero.
Yeah.
Well,
you can think of that as just as a constraint.
As a what?
Yeah.
A constraint.
Right.
Can I ask a question,
please?
When we say slowly,
is there a physical parameter that has to be
less than or more than or something that defines slowly?
Of course.
That itself may depend on the details.
But,
you know,
roughly speaking,
it means many,
many molecules have collided with each other.
So,
I'm going to give you a
general idea of what that means.
So,
a small rule of thumb is that there are multiple collisions with the wall
so that you can average over the details of the molecular collisions with the wall.
So,
you know,
I...
You could...
We could...
We could examine specific cases
and some questions have very,
very general answers.
Some questions depend on the details.
the question of exactly what time scales constitute
slow can be one that depends on the details.
The question of what happens if you move
sufficiently slowly does not depend on the details.
So these are good questions,
but let's do what we can.
Alright,
so there we are.
T,
derivative of log Z with respect
to the volume at constant temperature.
Now,
when we work with the partition function up there,
of course we fix the temperature.
We say what beta is.
So typically when you calculate a partition function,
it is the partition function as a
function of other variables at fixed temperature.
You worked it out at fixed temperature.
Let's go back to the
partition function for the ideal gas.
This is going to be
very easy from this point on.
Here's the ideal gas.
And the partition function was an integral.
I'll just remind you what it was.
It was an integral over all the x's and all
the p's of e to the minus beta times the energy,
which was p squared over 2m.
I'm not going to write it in great detail.
This was an integral over how many x's are there?
3n.
And how many p's?
Now,
if you remember this factored,
the p integration doesn't depend on x at all.
And the x integration just gives you what?
If there was only one particle,
it would give you the volume.
And if there are n particles,
it gives you the volume to the nth power.
So there's volume to the nth power
times
an integral which depends on the
temperature but not on the volume.
The p integration does not depend on the volume.
So there's whatever was here.
Some function of beta.
The reason it doesn't,
and we either may or may not stick
in the factor of n factorial in the denominator,
that doesn't make any difference.
Why?
Because we're going to wind up
and this factor doesn't make any difference.
The reason is because we
have to calculate logarithm of z.
And logarithm of z is going
to be a sum of two terms.
So let's work out the logarithm of z.
This is z.
Log of z
equals n log v
from v to the n.
And then there's a term that's constant.
It depends on the number of particles,
but it doesn't depend on the volume.
We can put it down here.
Minus log n factorial.
And then there's something here which
is plus log of function of beta.
Beta being the inverse temperature.
Only one term here depends on the volume,
and it's this one.
The one that just came from the fact that we had
to integrate the position of the particle over the whole volume.
Nothing else depends on the volume.
So when we differentiate with respect to the volume,
we can forget everything else.
Plus uninteresting stuff.
Okay,
what is the derivative of the log
of z with respect to the volume?
Is equal to n.
Derivative of log v with respect to v?
1 over v,
right?
1 over v.
Now,
we're supposed to multiply that by the temperature.
And what do we get?
We get the pressure.
You recognize that?
PV equals nt.
In this case,
isn't n the number of...
Number of particles.
Well,
when we started off defining this,
we said that we were going to duplicate our container,
our system.
We've done that.
We're finished with that.
That was just a trick
to calculate the Boltzmann distribution.
Okay,
so now n has changed the definition.
Yeah.
The ideal,
right,
it's just the number of particles.
Okay,
right.
Notice that n over v is the density.
n over v is not some crazy thing.
So what does it say?
It says,
we can write it in various ways.
You can write it pressure times volume equals n,
the number of particles in the sample,
times t.
Now,
you may be used to
seeing this as PV equals nkt,
where k is the Boltzmann distribution.
And of course,
there is a Boltzmann constant here
if you work in laboratory units.
Or you can divide by n and
write that p times the density of particles,
the number of particles per unit volume,
is equal to the temperature.
One over rho.
Yeah,
you can do that.
yeah,
yeah.
I'm sorry.
They want to divide by the volume,
not by n.
P equals n divided by v,
which is rho times temperature.
Density times temperature equals volume.
In fact,
our Boltzmann constant,
but we're grownups,
so we're used to getting,
throwing away Boltzmann constant.
This is the equation of state of an ideal gas.
So it is exactly what you see.
And it's not what you would have computed if you would
have just used the intuitive picture of molecules bouncing off the wall.
But here it's justified.
And more than that,
there's power in this method.
Any time you can do the
integrals necessary to calculate the partition function,
you have a precise way of calculating.
So this was just the simplest of many,
many examples where people can calculate.
Here we did it in order to
see how the basic concepts fit together.
This is how the basic concepts fit together.
And that's it.
That's the ideal gas.
We're finished early today.
So we can go back
over it if there are questions.
I think I was fairly clear tonight,
but if not...
You had mentioned you were going to cover fluctuations.
Cover what?
Fluctuations.
Oh,
okay.
Well,
let's do that.
Okay.
Yeah,
all right,
we have some time.
Let's do fluctuations.
I didn't bring any notes for it,
so we have to wing it.
Okay.
What is a fluctuation?
If you look in the box of gas like this,
and it's in equilibrium with another system,
so that it's exchanging energy with it,
the energy won't be a definite value.
The thing we've been calling energy is the average energy.
The energy will fluctuate.
Okay.
The fact that the energy fluctuates in certain ways is evidence
that the system is really made up of molecules and so forth.
But we have to come to a definition.
We need a definition of the fluctuation of
a quantity when you have a probability distribution.
Okay,
so the standard definition...
Let's begin with a quantity whose average is zero.
Okay.
Begin with a quantity whose average is zero.
That means the probability distribution for it...
Well,
it doesn't literally mean...
It doesn't necessarily mean that it's synthetic.
It doesn't say that it's filtered
in any sense at the origin.
But the average is zero.
That doesn't look like a zero average,
does it?
Okay.
All right.
The definition of the fluctuation...
And it's not a complete
description of the probability distribution.
It's just a description of one aspect of it,
which is kind of an approximation to its width.
The average...
Let's just call this quantity x.
The average of x is zero.
That's not telling us anything.
We knew the average was zero
because we set it up that way.
But the average of x squared is not zero.
Why not?
Because x squared is never zero.
It's positive on this side.
And the average of x squared is
a measure of the width of the distribution.
So the fluctuation...
Usually called delta x.
The uncertainty in x,
or whatever we like to call it,
is the square root of the average...
Did we use this symbol for average?
X squared.
Or,
let's get rid of the square root.
The squared...
Mean squared fluctuation is the average of x squared.
Okay.
Now let's suppose that it's not square.
It's centered at zero.
So that the average is not zero.
All we have to do is shift the variable so
that the average does become zero and do the same thing.
In other words,
we define a new variable called
x minus the average of x.
What's the average of x minus the average of x?
Zero.
Prove that.
There's something to prove.
Prove that the average of this quantity here is zero.
Okay.
It's something you should prove.
All right.
So now we have something,
a new quantity,
which has just been shifted so that it's average
is zero,
and now we have to prove that
the average of this quantity is zero.
And what's the fluctuation in it the fluctuation in it is the
square is that is the average of the square of this thing?
So we want to take this
thing we want to square it
And we want to average the whole thing
It's an it's good.
It's a good quantity
Let's calculate let's see what we can do with it.
Let's see if we can
Make some sense out of
it first of all we square
Before we average
So we're averaging x squared
Minus twice x times the average of x
Plus
Average of x squared
And we want to average the whole thing
Now the average of x squared.
That's just a number
That's a number.
It depends on the probability distribution,
but it's just a number
What is the average?
The average of the average of x squared
It's just equal to itself.
It's just the average of x squared
the average of the average of a
of an
yeah
The average of an average is just the average
Okay,
so this is just the average of x squared.
What about this one here?
not quite
Minus two times the same thing okay,
so the average if I average this quantity here.
It will be minus two times the average
If I do the average of x squared
So I'm going to take the average of x squared
And what about this one?
It is what it is
It is what it is,
but it is not this thing
Why not?
It's not the square of the average.
This is the square of the average.
It's the average of the square
So this is average of x squared
minus twice this plus 1 times that
is minus average of x squared.
That's called the fluctuation or,
I don't know,
does it have
another name?
The,
is there another name for this thing?
Variance,
yeah,
the variance.
Right,
this is called the variance,
but what it means is it's the fluctuation away
from the norm,
away from the average.
Alright,
so let's keep that in our bag of
tricks,
that the uncertainty in x or the fluctuation in x,
the square of it,
is by
definition the average of the square
minus the square of the average.
Now let's see if we can
calculate the fluctuation in the energy.
We'll calculate the fluctuation
in the energy in terms of the partition function.
What do we have?
We're armed with one quantity,
always one goes back to the partition function.
It really does contain,
what you really,
yeah?
I can't see that.
That's delta x and what's the superscript?
It's true.
Superstore squared.
Squared.
It's just a definition.
The left-hand side is a
definition of the square of the
fluctuation.
You know,
one might write that delta x
is the square root of this thing,
and talk about root mean squares and stuff like that,
but this is,
this is definition.
But what it does is it does measure the average,
what it measures is the width of the distribution,
how broad the distribution is.
That is a name too.
Which?
The square root.
Probably called the root mean square or something.
Oh,
the standard deviation?
Standard deviation,
yeah.
And it's used in all physics papers,
you read about sigma.
Yeah,
yeah,
all that stuff is there.
Right.
But now we actually want to,
we actually want to calculate.
What it tells us is how much honest,
real experimental fluctuation we expect
in the measure of the energy.
So,
how much is the measured quantity?
How much will it vary when
you measure it over and over again?
Why does it vary?
It varies because there's energy coming
into and out of the system.
It is really fluctuating.
It's not just a mathematical definition.
The energy in a box does
fluctuate if it's in equilibrium with a,
with a bath,
with a heat bath.
Okay,
so let's see if we can calculate it.
We've already calculated,
this is now we want to do the energy.
We want to do energy.
So let's apply this to energy.
The uncertainty in the energy,
the square of it,
is the average of the energy squared
minus the average of the energy squared.
You see that these are not the same.
What was the average of the energy?
Remember,
in terms of the partition function?
Minus the log Z by the beta.
Alright?
Remember that?
The average energy...
So we have the average energy already.
We don't have to do any more work on that.
But what about the...
What?
average of the square of the energy,
let's go back to,
first of all,
what was the trick
that we used to calculate the average energy,
remember?
We said that the average energy
is summation 1 over z,
e to the minus beta e sub i,
e sub i.
And then we recognized that
multiplying by e sub i here is the
same as taking minus the derivative with respect to
beta.
So this is equal to 1 over z,
d by d beta with a minus sign of z.
z is the sum
without the e,
and d by d beta
is the sum with the e.
So this term we have under control,
but suppose we want to get
the average of the energy squared.
What do we do?
Average of the energy squared
means the energy is squared here.
We differentiate
twice.
We take a second derivative.
Taking a second derivative,
now we don't need a minus
sign,
but we're going to take a second derivative,
and we're going to take a second derivative.
Now,
this is the same as the first derivative.
We take a second derivative,
and we're going
to take a second derivative.
So this is the average of the squared energy,
and we're going
to take a second derivative of z.
And this is equal to 1 over z,
e to the minus beta
squared.
Do I have that right?
Help,
help,
do I have it right?
Looks good,
huh?
And
then minus,
no,
minus,
because it's squared,
d log z,
or let's just write it this way.
1 over z squared,
dz by d beta squared.
So this is the fluctuation in the energy.
Let's see if we can do anything with it.
First of all,
it tells us we can calculate
the fluctuation if we know z.
Again,
it shows us the power of the partition function.
All
of statistical mechanics is about the power
of the partition function and the power of
differentiation.
Okay,
let's take a look at this.
This sort of looks,
let's see,
let's take a look at
the following quantity,
the second derivative with respect
to beta squared of log z.
Is
that what I want?
Yeah,
let's take a look at that.
Let's see what it is.
All right,
so it is,
is that
what I want?
I'm not sure if that's what I want.
Yeah,
it is.
d by d beta,
let's see,
d by d beta of 1
over z dz by d beta.
I think that's the same as
this.
Is it not?
Yeah,
yeah.
This is the second derivative of log z.
Here is the first derivative of
log z.
differentiated it again.
Let's focus on this thing over here.
It has two terms.
The first term is 1 over z.
The first term is gotten by differentiating dz by
d beta.
That gives us 1 over z times
the second derivative of z with respect to
beta squared.
And then what about the second term?
The second term is obtained
by differentiating the 1 over
z times dz by d beta.
What's the derivative of 1
over z with respect to beta?
Minus 1 over z squared times dz by d beta.
Exactly this.
So we have an even simpler formula for the fluctuation.
This is the
fluctuation delta E squared.
But yikes,
this is even simpler.
What is 1 over z dz by d beta?
It is d log there,
but it's the average energy isn't it?
Or minus the average
energy.
This is minus the average energy.
So here we have another formula that it's
d by d beta of minus the average
energy.
Anybody know what this thing is?
Hmm?
It tells you how the energy changes with temperature.
Beta is essentially,
let's rewrite it.
Let's write this as d by d
temperature times d temperature by d beta.
Let's rewrite it.
Let's write this as d by d
temperature times d temperature by d beta.
What's the temperature?
Temperature is,
what's the,
the temperature is 1 over,
beta is 1 over temperature squared.
Other way around.
Beta,
temperature is 1 over beta.
So what's d t by d beta?
Beta temperature is 1 over beta.
The derivative is equal to minus 1 over beta squared.
Is that right?
Yeah.
So what's d t by d beta?
Just minus 1 over beta squared?
What's d t by d beta?
Which is temperature squared?
Do I have that right?
Yes.
Yeah.
So I think this is just temperature squared here.
If I,
if I,
I don't have these things memorized,
so I might be,
I think that's right.
Temperature squared,
there was a minus sign,
so the minus sign I think goes away.
It's temperature squared times the derivative of
temperature of energy with respect to temperature.
Anybody know what the word is for
the derivative of energy with respect to temperature?
Specific heat.
Specific heat is the question,
how,
how much do you have to change the energy?
To make a certain change in temperature?
How much do you have to heat a bucket
of water to change the temperature by 1 degree?
This quantity,
e,
derivative of e with respect
to t is the specific heat.
Do you know the symbol for specific heat?
C.
It's called C.
It's not the speed of light.
Do you have to specify if
you kept volume or pressure constant?
Here you're keeping fixed,
yeah,
here,
yes you do.
This is keeping the volume fixed.
Yeah,
we're keeping the system fixed,
we're not varying the control parameter here in this,
in this derivation.
So right,
so this is the deriv,
this is the,
the,
this is the specific heat at constant volume.
In general,
constant control parameters.
So it's C sub V.
Well,
the specific heat might be defined as the,
by dividing by the total number
of particles in the system or something.
But what this is,
is the rate of change of
the energy with respect to temperature.
This is a famous formula.
I think,
I,
it may be due to Einstein,
I'm not sure.
Uh,
Einstein and Gibbs and,
I don't know who,
uh,
it's probably Einstein.
Oh,
and Gibbs.
So,
the fluctuation in energy,
if you know the specific heat,
you multiply it by the temperature squared
and that will tell you how much,
um,
fluctuation there is.
Now,
I left out something.
I did leave out something.
What I left out was the Boltzmann constant.
I believe there's a K Boltz,
um,
I think the whole thing has one
factor of K Boltzmann in front of it.
With my definition,
let's see,
what was C V?
C V was the derivative
of energy with respect to temperature.
But,
yeah,
but I think there,
I think there's,
uh,
from the change of variables here,
I think there's a K downstairs
and two powers of K upstairs.
Yeah.
So I think if you were working in laboratory units,
I think this would have a
K Boltzmann in front of it.
That means it's small.
Fluctuations are small.
We,
we expect fluctuations.
Uh,
we have a lot of particles.
You expect the fluctuations to be fairly small.
And that's where the smallness comes from.
So this is the fluctuation in the energy of a,
uh,
of a,
of any system.
This is not specific to any particular,
this is specific heat,
but it's not specific to any particular,
um,
system.
And so if you measure the specific heat
as a function of,
well,
if you measure the specific heat,
period,
and you multiply by the temperature squared,
and then you sit around
measuring the energy in the sample,
you should expect to see
an energy fluctuation equal to this.
Does it change in pressure?
Why do we expect the
specific heat to be a constant?
Constant with respect to what?
dE dt.
Sorry.
If you change,
why would it be dE?
dE dt.
Be constant?
It's not constant.
This is at this temperature.
So Cv is a function of temperature.
Yeah,
Cv is a function of temperature,
and the fluctuations are a function of temperature.
Yeah.
No,
it's not a function,
right?
So this is,
again,
part of the beautiful structure of statistical mechanics.
This goes beyond thermodynamics.
Whenever you actually see at the
end of a formula like this,
a,
uh,
a k-Boltz model,
it's beyond statistical mechanics.
It really does depend on
the fact that the systems have,
are made up out of molecules and so forth.
It depends on Avogadro's number,
essentially.
k-Boltz is closely related to Avogadro's number.
So...
I have a question,
please.
Yeah.
If you kept pressure constant instead of volume constant,
and therefore you could do it
perform work because it was moving...
Does this become different?
Well,
this was the derivation of the fluctuation of,
um...
No doubt,
offhand,
I don't remember the connections
between all the specific heats,
but,
um...
Uh...
Yeah.
You get the wrong answer if you use Cp here.
Isn't the specific heat a constant for a given material?
Good.
Yeah.
The thing that I'm calling the specific heat,
I think is maybe not what
we would ordinarily be calling this.
Normally the specific heat,
uh,
would be a constant in,
um,
it's per unit,
mass of the material or something.
All right.
So actually this would be the specific heat times...
What's the definition of specific heat?
It's the rate of change of
energy per unit temperature per unit mass.
For example.
Okay?
So that means this,
this specific heat over here is really the
specific heat times the mass of the sample.
It's called heat capacity.
Ah,
good.
It's called the heat capacity.
Yes.
That's,
that's the term I should have used.
It's the heat capacity,
but the heat capacity depends on the mass,
the mass of material that you have.
All right.
So in other words,
roughly speaking...
This is proportional to the
number of molecules in the sample.
Okay?
This is proportional to the number of molecules,
how many,
um,
uh...
But,
uh,
it's,
it's the measured specific heat
times the mass of the sample,
or what is called the heat capacity.
Right.
Yeah.
Yeah,
that's the,
that's the word I should have used.
So...
Any other questions?
Go home and look up,
uh,
heat capacities and so forth and
see how big the fluctuations of a,
uh,
of a liter of,
um...
Water would be.
The important thing here,
as I said,
is that these four...
Formulas here don't depend on the details
of what things are made out of.
Once you measure the specific heat,
you know the fluctuations without having to worry about
what kind of material it is or anything else.
For more,
please visit us at stanford.edu.