Stanford University.
All right,
let's come back to the second law for a minute,
a little bit.
And talk about Poincare recurrences.
Poincare recurrences are,
I am not sure whether Poincare was
really the first one to think about it.
I have a feeling that
Boltzmann again probably understood this.
Was Boltzmann,
Boltzmann was before Poincare?
I think so.
So here's a question,
here's a question you might ask.
Let's suppose you start out with the air in
this room all on one side of the room.
This is not an impossible thing to do.
You put a wall in.
You have
to evacuate the air out
of one side of the room,
stick it into the other side of the room,
and start with an initial condition with all
the air on the left side of the room.
And now you let it go.
Okay,
what happens?
Comes to thermal equilibrium,
fills the room pretty much uniformly.
Entropy increases.
But what if you sit there and you wait
and you wait and you wait and you wait?
Sooner or later,
sooner or later,
the unlikely will happen.
The unlikely event will happen where by accident
or by just waiting long enough in time,
all of the air will reappear
in the left side of the room.
Or in the top half of the room or whatever.
But let's say the left half of the room.
That's called a Poincare recurrence.
And it's,
it's really no different than saying
that if I flip a coin,
a null,
times I will get a million heads in a row.
Very unlikely,
but if I do it enough
some fluctuation will happen.
Okay,
so the question is,
roughly speaking,
how long do
you have to wait for the air to
all appear in one side of the room?
Is it a
year?
Is it ten years?
Is it a hundred years?
Is it the age of the universe?
So
let's see if we can get a handle on that.
You start out with the idea of phase
space and phase space is the space
of the coordinates of the molecules and the
momentum of the molecules and of
course it's very high dimensional six n
dimensional.
Six n because each particle has three coordinates,
each
particle has three momentum components,
and if there are n particles there are six n
coordinates of this a very high dimensional space.
Okay now as
As far as the momentum space goes,
that's kind of bounded.
It's bounded because if any
particle has an enormous momentum,
it will have a very large energy.
And there's a certain amount of
energy that you put in the box,
no more than that.
So pretty much we can say the
momentum dimension in this box is bounded.
And let's just bound it by saying
the momentum is definitely within some range here.
And it doesn't matter how many particles we have.
It doesn't matter how big the system is.
It doesn't matter what the temperature is.
The higher the temperature,
the more uncertain the momentum is.
But if the temperature is reasonably low,
then the momentum direction here
is pretty much bounded.
And the answer is,
well,
x-axis,
that runs from the left part of the
room to the right part of the room,
sort of.
And to say that we started
out in one half of the room
meant that the phase point was in here.
In other words,
the system started in phase space somewhere in there.
Let's not be detailed about where it is in there.
It's somewhere in there.
So the probability distribution is spread out
over here.
And now we wait for a while.
And what happens?
The phase point starts to move.
Now,
it moves chaotically.
Chaotically,
for our purposes,
just means pretty unpredictably.
And not unpredictably because the laws of physics
are unpredictable in principle,
but because trajectories,
like the example of the billiard balls,
errors,
or a slide,
like differences
tend to magnify themselves after a while.
And so even if we started out two very,
very
similar trajectories,
they would very quickly depart.
And you can pretty much imagine that this
means that this phase point moves
around in here in very,
very complicated ways
and pretty much fills up the phase space,
fills up the phase space,
in this case.
sense that if you coarse-grain it and
fuzz your eyes a little bit and wear
somebody else's glasses,
it will look like it's pretty much filled up the
phase space.
Okay,
so what percentage of the
time would you expect that the
phase point resides such that the particles
are all in one half the room,
if this were the picture?
Looks like half the time.
That's crazy!
We don't expect
half the time the air molecules to be
in the left half of the room or the
right half of the room.
And the mistake we're making is we're drawing a picture
in just two dimensions.
Alright.
In two dimensions,
if we divide the X space in
half,
and say we're to the right,
we're talking about half the volume of the
phase space.
What happens though,
if we have n coordinates,
and we're not talking about the part of the phase
space where one particle is on the right-hand side,
but where all of them are
on the right-hand side.
So let's just say there are two particles.
Let's forget the
momentum for a minute and just draw the two coordinates,
X1 and X2,
or X and Y.
X and Y are the
first X and the second X.
And to say that both of
them are on one half of the room is to
say that the phase point is somewhere in the quarter
of the square.
So suppose there were only
two particles moving in one dimension,
and
we start somewhere and they move
around and the system moves around randomly.
Two particles
scatter off each other,
they do very random things.
What percentage of the time are both
particles moving?
One quarter.
In the left-hand side of the room?
A quarter,
right?
What if there are three particles?
One over two to the third.
And what if there are n particles?
One over two to the n.
One over two to the n is right.
One over three n?
That depends on how we're constraining it.
If we said all the particles are to the left
but not the...
we just said to the
left and left it at that,
didn't care where they were
up or down,
then I think it would be
one over two to the n.
All right,
there's another way
to think about it,
and that's to say,
let's take the phase space and identify a subregion
of it as the subregion which we're interested in.
Interested means an interesting configuration
that is very unlikely.
All right,
so here's a little region of the phase space.
The phase
space is much bigger,
and the volume,
let's say the whole volume of the phase space,
is
very small.
Let's forget momentum.
Momentum is not important in this.
What is the volume
of the phase space if there are n particles?
It's the volume of the box raised to the nth
or the three nth power,
depending on...
right.
So the volume of the whole phase space,
because
it's an n-dimensional phase space,
or a three n or whatever,
let's forget the three.
The
volume...
of the whole phase space
contains a volume to the nth.
That's the same volume to the
nth that we discovered when we calculated
the partition function and we integrated over
position.
Volume to the nth.
Let's suppose this region of
phase space over here has a
much smaller size.
All the particles have to be in there.
Then,
the volume of this region of phase space,
with all the particles in here,
will
be some little v to the nth.
This is the volume of the box,
incidentally.
This is not the
volume of the phase space.
The volume of the phase
space is v to the n,
the volume of the
box.
And if we're asking about all
the particles being in some small volume,
could be half.
I mean,
this could be half of the big volume.
Okay.
This is some smaller region,
and that's
and the volume of this region of
phase space is little v to the n,
what percentage of the time would you
expect the phase point to be in here?
Little v to the n over little v
to the n over big V to the n.
Now,
little v to the n could be some small number,
whatever it is,
but what about big V to the n?
Big V to the n is proportional
to the entropy of the whole system.
The entropy of a region of phase space
is the logarithm of the volume of that region.
If all you knew,
is that the system was
in some region of phase space,
the volume of that region
of phase space is the logarithm,
is the entropy.
Yeah.
Is that the volume of configuration space?
Yeah,
we're not worrying about the momentum now.
Yeah.
Why?
The momentum is the momentum,
roughly speaking,
of whatever the temperature is.
So let's not worry about that.
Okay.
So roughly speaking then,
this here,
little v to the n,
is the entropy that a gas would
have if it was in this little region,
if all the particles were in that little region.
Let's take the little region to be pretty small.
So that's just some number.
But what's about big V to the n?
That's the entropy of the whole gas and thermal equilibrium,
or sorry,
it's the exponential of the entropy.
Logarithm of V to the n is
the entropy of the gas in this region,
and V to the n
is the exponential of the entropy.
So what this is telling us is
that the likelihood of finding a system
in a tiny volume of phase space here
is always proportional to e to the minus,
because it's in the denominator,
e to the minus the entropy of,
of the thermal equilibrium state.
The meaning of that is that it's very improbable.
e to the,
e to the entropy,
e to the minus the entropy is a very,
very small number.
What's the entropy of the,
of the molecules in this room?
Roughly speaking,
proportional to the number of molecules.
It's pretty close to just being the number of molecules.
10 to the,
no,
it's more than 10,
10 to the 30th,
I'm not sure exactly what,
something like that.
So V to the n,
or the entropy,
is,
is 10 to the 30th.
The probability of finding yourself in
a tiny little volume of phase space
like this is not e to the entropy,
it's,
sorry,
it is e to the minus the entropy.
e to the minus the entropy is the
probability of finding yourself in a small region.
It's the same as this 1
over 2 to the n here.
It's the same as this
1 over 2 to the n.
In the case that we studied over here,
little v over big V was a half.
But,
and a half is not a terribly small number,
but when it's raised to
the power 10 to the 30th,
that is a very small number.
Okay,
so the likelihood
at a random draw of a point
from the phase space that you find yourself
in this tiny volume of phase space here
is,
in this case here,
1 over 2
raised to the 10,
not to the 30th power,
to the 10 to the 30th power.
That's a pretty small number.
How long do you have to wait on the average
to find yourself in that region?
Well,
about a time of order
2 to the 10 to the 30th.
If the fraction of time that
you spend in that odd region
is 1 over 2 to the 10 to the 30th,
then how long do you have to
wait till you find yourself in that region?
2 to the 10 to the 30th.
In what units?
Years?
Seconds?
It doesn't matter.
What is the objective of doing this?
Oh,
it's...
Why is this interesting?
Why we do this exercise?
We do this exercise just to understand it.
Just to understand it.
To understand in what sense
systems are reversible.
The answer is,
if you wait long enough,
they will reverse themselves.
And if you really have a sealed room here,
and you let it evolve,
let's say starting from the odd state,
it would come to thermal equilibrium,
or what looks like thermal equilibrium.
It would spend a long,
long time there.
But every so often,
every 1 to the 2 to the
10 to the 30th years or whatever,
you would find the molecules in half the room.
You wait long enough,
and then you go down again,
it equilibrates again,
it looks conventional,
and then all of a sudden you find
the molecules in the other half of the room,
or that corner of the room.
And if you integrate it or study it
over sufficiently long times,
you will discover that the entropy goes down,
or that the...
oddness goes up and down,
and up and down,
in a completely time-symmetric way.
Okay?
In a completely time-symmetric way.
What's not time-symmetric
is if you knowingly start
in a very odd configuration.
In other words,
you knowingly start
in a tiny volume of phase space.
Most likely,
the next thing is to find yourself
out of that volume.
So if you start in an odd situation
with all the molecules in the corner of the room,
you expect the next thing to find
is the molecules spread out.
In fact,
you'll find the next thing
and the next thing and the next thing
is pretty much to spread out uniformly,
and that sounds like it violates
the reversibility of the physical laws.
But in fact,
if you were to have waited long enough,
you'll find it reversing itself
and doing everything imaginable
for a closed system.
I have a question,
please.
You said that time didn't matter,
seconds,
who cares.
But let's say it's 10 to minus 30
or 10 to minus 40 times.
What happens then?
It seems to matter somehow.
No,
no,
it doesn't.
Well,
some,
yes,
of course,
but let's just see.
Okay,
so we have a number
2 to the 10 to the 30th,
okay?
Now,
I'm going to change units.
This unit is the units
of seconds.
Supposing I change the units of hours,
what does this number become?
Times 2 to the 10 to the 30th.
2 to the 10 to the 30th.
Subtract 3.
Divided by?
Divided by what's,
3,000 or something.
Let's say 10 to the 3,
right?
Okay,
that's the same as 2
to the 10 to the 30th minus 3.
It doesn't matter whether,
right.
10 to the 30th minus
3 is 10 to the 30th.
Does it mean that if we were to invent
a short time equivalent to 10 to minus 3,
you know,
the opposite,
will it,
for that infinitesimal time,
actually come back to that volume?
Yeah.
Infinitesimal fraction of the time.
How long it actually spends in the corner,
that depends on how fast the molecules are moving
and so forth.
The quantum limitations,
I assume.
There is a quantum version of the,
of the Poincare recurrence theorem.
But we want to get into it now.
All right,
so that's just,
it's more than an interesting point.
It's a deep conceptual point that resolved
and helped Boltzmann resolve the puzzle of
the one-wayness,
the apparent one-wayness of time
and the two-wayness of the laws of motion.
Of course,
what it required to make sense out of it
is that we eventually,
we would eventually have to understand
why the universe started
in a little corner of phase space.
That's a separate issue.
Boltzmann knew that.
He knew that and he,
and he said so.
He said.
I was thinking,
could this have application in cosmology?
Absolutely.
And it's still a open and,
and question that's constantly being addressed.
Why did the universe start in a,
in a small corner of phase space?
I was thinking after the universe spreads out,
have you waited long enough?
Yeah.
This is a,
this is a,
it's a good question.
And it is one which we're working on.
I'll just say.
Question.
I think the answer is the
universe must not be a closed system.
If it's a closed system,
it will just recur and recur and recur.
And,
and that does not,
that doesn't make for a
good statistical explanation of the world.
Yeah.
I didn't understand when you said,
I think you said that time was symmetric.
If you watch,
if you watch the closed system long enough,
you would find that,
let's call it some measure of the localization of the particles would decrease if you started off in a corner and sit
there pretty delocalized for a long time and then pop up and then go back down and pop up and go back down.
But the time scale to discover the,
this reversibility that what goes up must come down,
so to speak,
is this two to the 10th to the 30th.
You're not saying that,
you're not saying that it takes as long for it to
move out as it does to come back to one corner.
Well,
it does.
Yeah,
everything is,
everything would be symmetric.
Every now and then you would find the molecules
in exactly the right configuration to swoosh into the corner.
Pretty much the same way
they swooshed out of the corner.
Oh,
I see.
You're comparing two exact same states.
Yeah.
Okay.
So you'll see everything happen.
You'll see everything happen in both directions.
Excuse me.
Yeah.
So this doesn't really have anything to do with
the fact that they started in a small area.
You could start with a room just like this,
right?
And then eventually all the air
will be in a small area.
Yes,
yes,
yes.
But if we're trying to understand why
the world looks the way it is,
you see,
the problem,
and I think Boltzmann knew this,
it's a more recurrent problem in recent years,
is if the universe really were a
closed box and you were to ask,
what's the most likely configuration to
find a planet with people on it?
What's the most likely possibility?
You would discover that the most likely possibility is,
is to have uniform gas everywheres,
except the smallest possible amount of
gas necessary to make up a planet,
having condensed into the planet.
The chances that you would see two planets,
the chances that you see one planet are very,
very,
very small.
The chances that you see two
planets are vastly more negligible than that.
So if you were asking the question,
what should astronomers expect?
What should astronomers expect to see in a world,
given that there are astronomers,
a conditional probability,
the conditional probability that there is a planet,
and on that planet there are astronomers,
and they do astronomical observations,
what's the most likely thing they will see?
The most likely thing they will see
is they will look out and see nothing.
Or they may see some gas out there,
but they will not see it condensed into another planet.
By far,
the most likely thing to see is one planet,
if you know that you have one,
and not two.
What's the probability that you'll
see the universe filled with stars?
Absolutely negligible,
unless you know that in the fairly recent past,
in the fairly recent past,
that you started with some
very exceptional and unusual starting point.
And then the flow out from that starting point,
is likely to have certain kinds of structure
that a random fluctuation would not have.
Anyway,
that's called the problem of Boltzmann brains.
It's called the problem of Boltzmann brains
because people went a little bit excessive on it
and said the most probable astronomer would be
a single astronomer's head disconnected from anything else
but it is a problem,
it's a problem of using statistics to
understand the world the way it is.
And it's always a conditional question.
The conditional question is always given that we're here,
that etc.,
all the various things,
what's the probability that we see X?
And the probability in a
closed universe that we see X
would be much higher
to see only X and not Y,
Y meaning some other planets and things like that.
So it's not a good theory to think
we are just a result of a random fluctuation.
If we were the result of a random fluctuation
where things just assemble themselves sort of accidentally
or what is apparently accidentally into
a planet with people on it,
we would have no explanation of the world
and we would have no
explanation of the coherence of history,
why history looks like it had a coherent past
and why there's a consistency to historical evidence
if the universe just materialized by random fluctuation,
not the universe but the planet,
just materialized by random fluctuation
with us sitting here today.
It seems like if you're starting up with a place
and you're trying to explain,
so to speak,
then you can talk about the
probability of finding one planet like this,
and it's very small.
The probability of finding one planet
is much bigger than finding two.
Right,
but you can talk about the conditional probability
that given that there is one planet,
what's the probability of finding another one?
That seems like it would be the same.
No,
the same as just finding one?
No.
Given that you know one exists,
so we can talk about conditional probability,
what's the probability of a second one?
Extremely small.
But I mean,
it seems like the same
as when you don't know any exist,
it's the same as the probability...
No,
if what we're relying on is random fluctuations,
and here we have a
situation where randomly in this room
a collection of molecules randomly materialized
and formed Boltzmann's head.
Okay?
Formed Boltzmann's head.
That is a very small probability.
I'm talking about like that's the longest...
Wait,
wait,
wait.
I'm not sure you understand.
Maybe I didn't,
but let's just explain it anyway.
The probability that we discover a Boltzmann's head
is going to be a very,
very small number.
Given Boltzmann's head has formed,
Boltzmann looks around and he says,
I wonder what the probability is
that my wife is here also.
Very,
very,
very tiny.
Much,
much tinier than this.
Boltzmann.
Okay,
now that's not what you were asking,
you said.
Okay,
well this is the way I'm thinking of it.
Imagine,
talk about playing the lottery.
And you've got two people who've played the lottery
the same number of times,
and one of them has won once,
and the other has won zero.
Now what's the probability the next time those two play,
what are the two probabilities of them winning again?
And they're equal.
You see what I'm saying?
It doesn't matter if the other
guy won once in that sense,
because they're in the game.
That's right.
So the probability that there's
a discovery of a Boltzmann's wife
in the room is very,
very tiny.
It's equally tiny if Boltzmann happens
to have been discovered in the room.
It's equal.
Right.
Equally improbable whether,
that's right,
but very improbable.
So in other words,
Boltzmann ought to be very,
very surprised
that his wife is there.
He,
first of all,
is surprised that he's there.
Well,
maybe he doesn't know the theory very well.
He doesn't know too much about the,
he knows a little about the theory.
And he discovers he's there.
He says,
oh,
what a wonderful accident.
How happy I am.
I wonder if my wife is here.
Nah,
that would be too much of a good thing.
He looks around.
He finds her.
He says,
what is his conclusion?
His conclusion is,
you know,
I think my world is probably
not a world of random statistics.
It's probably not a world
of a closed volume of molecules
which just randomly assembled me.
He couldn't say that before.
What he would say before is,
look,
I'm here.
I know that if we wait long enough,
I will be here.
When will I be here?
Is it a fantastic piece of luck
that I happen to be here right now?
No.
At some point in time,
I'm going to be here.
This happens to be the time I'm here.
He says,
if that's the right theory,
that I'm here just because the gas
in the room eventually assembled into me,
and when else could I
be here except when I'm here?
It's when I'm here.
But I think the best prediction I
can make is that if I look around,
I will find the rest of
the room pretty much in thermal equilibrium
with no fancy structure in it.
In particular,
my wife won't be here.
If he discovers his wife,
he will say,
that's extraordinarily unlikely,
even much more unlikely,
so my theory is probably wrong
that I'm the result of a random fluctuation.
That's,
yeah,
okay.
All right,
this is good.
What is historical coherence?
You mentioned the word historic.
Can you define it?
We couldn't explain it historically.
One textbook says George Washington.
George Washington chopped down a cherry tree,
and then you go and look at another textbook,
it says the same thing.
But if the world was just a fluctuation,
it was just made by fluctuation,
and one textbook happened to say
George Washington chopped down a cherry tree,
there'd be no reason to expect the
other textbook to say the same thing.
He chopped the tree.
Why would they not vote for him?
No,
no,
he didn't chop the tree.
The world just materialized accidentally in a configuration
in which the textbook said he chopped the tree.
Don't worry about it.
This is not the right theory of nature.
Yeah,
doesn't this just say that
we could live in a world
that's closed system that's extremely long,
time constant to reach equilibrium?
Yes,
but it would still be true.
Yeah,
you could say that,
but then you would nevertheless say
if you wait long enough,
there will be many,
many,
many replicas of you
in the future,
and almost all of them
will not see a coherent history.
So if you make your best guess,
you find yourself here today,
and you ask,
how did I get here?
The overwhelming majority of people
who wake up in the morning
and ask that question will be ones who
came out of one of these random fluctuations.
Now,
is this a serious concern?
Should we worry about that?
I can tell you,
cosmologists do worry about that.
Serious theoretical cosmologists.
But I'm not going to try to sell you anything.
It is something that is of concern,
that if we want to use statistics
and ask what's the most probable thing we should see,
given that we're here,
we have to take into account all
the ways we could have gotten here.
Most of the ways we could have gotten here
would be by random fluctuation,
and history would be,
and history would not be coherent for them.
Okay,
that's the problem with Boltzmann brains.
Question?
Is there anything that can be said about
the fact that life seems to decrease entropy?
No,
of course it doesn't.
no,
Life does not...
Yes,
but it's always at the cost
of something else increasing its entropy.
The second law does not say
that some subsystem of the world can't decrease its entropy,
but it will always be at
the cost of some other subsystem
increasing its entropy even more.
So...
But it seems like it sticks and
it goes for a very long time.
It's not just something that comes together and goes away.
It seems to keep maintaining itself.
It seems kind of a little strange.
It's the flow of energy from the sun.
The Earth is not in equilibrium.
It's in a stationary configuration.
Stationary means it stays the same,
but there's a flow.
If you have a system which
has a flow moving through it,
it can create interesting structures.
For example,
a flow of water through a pipe can create vortices
that spin off and spin off.
Those vortices have a structure.
You know,
little eddy currents and so forth.
Eddy currents have a structure.
The water flows through a pipe.
The water flowing through the pipe creates them.
And you can imagine that little
eddy currents could have enough structure
to have some interesting properties.
But if you stop the flow by
sealing off the ends of the pipe,
then what happens?
The eddy currents disappear,
and it just returns to a quiescent,
dull,
boring equilibrium.
So what is the flow in the case of life
that allows this kind of apparent...
violation of the principle?
Incidentally,
of course,
even in that flow situation,
the total entropy of everything is increasing,
even though you're making it
a pump and a sink of...
The water's coming in one end,
going out the other end.
It comes out warmer out the other
end than it came in this end.
So altogether,
the second law is not being violated.
The same thing is true on Earth.
The flow is the flow of energy from the sun.
If we sealed up the Earth,
didn't let sunlight in,
didn't let sunlight out,
everything would eventually come to thermal equilibrium.
It would be dull.
There would be no life.
And we would just have featureless...
thermal equilibrium.
Life is a kind of eddy flow.
It's a kind of eddy currents or little vortices
that appear in a moving fluid,
the fluid being energy from the sun.
Okay.
Well,
we spent an hour talking about interesting things.
Now we can get back to some dull things.
Magnets.
Magnets are...
When we talk about magnets,
incidentally,
in statistical mechanics,
we're usually not talking about pieces of iron.
We're usually talking about mathematical models
of a certain kind of system
that has certain features that resemble magnetism.
So first of all,
what is a magnet?
Whatever a magnet is,
an ordinary magnet,
it's made up of lots of little magnets.
Little magnets could even be
as small as a single atom.
Or they could be little crystal grains.
But whatever a magnet is,
it's made up of little magnets.
And typically,
at room temperature,
at some ordinary temperature,
room temperature being rather high in this context,
could be rather high,
but certainly at very high temperatures,
at a temperature of 1,000 degrees or whatever,
those little magnets are randomly oriented
in such a way that the net sample
doesn't have a net orientation.
The orientation is random.
And not just is the
orientation of the whole thing random,
but the relative orientation of
the parts of it are random,
and so there's no net magnetization.
You don't see a magnetic...
a macroscopic magnetic field.
There's no magnetic field from it.
If you cool it down,
and if the energies stored
in pairs of these little magnets
is such that the magnets like
to line up in the same direction,
as you start to cool it down,
you find out that lumps,
groups of magnets,
groups of little magnets tend to be in alignment,
but other little groups of magnets
tend to be in alignment,
but in other directions.
And you'll find sort of domains,
domains which are magnetized,
which means they tend to point in the same direction,
but these domains are still fairly small.
If you cool it down...
Now,
these are experimental facts,
and not completely hard to understand,
but as you cool it down more and more,
energy,
the energy consideration,
that things like to be in the same direction,
like means that the energy is lower
if the magnets are parallel.
If the energy is lower if the magnets are parallel,
then as you suck energy out of the system,
more and more of them
will want to come into alignment,
and these domains will start to grow.
And eventually,
you may or may not hit a point
at finite temperature,
not at zero temperature,
you may or may not hit a point
at which all of a sudden
these domains become infinitely big
so that the magnets tend to be somewhat lined up
everywheres in the same direction.
That's called a ferromagnetic transition,
and it's a phase transition,
and it's basically the simplest kind of phase transition.
Certainly at zero temperature,
you'll expect them to be all lined up.
Why is that?
Because at zero temperature,
the only state of importance in Boltzmann distribution
is the lowest energy state.
When the temperature is zero,
only the lowest energy state,
and the lowest energy state,
all the microscopic atoms
or the microscopic magnets line up.
Yeah?
Question.
If you have two,
I'm thinking about microscopic magnets,
wouldn't they prefer to anti-align?
It depends on the details.
In a piece of iron,
they like to align.
I know what you're thinking.
Yeah,
you're thinking North Pole wants to grab the South Pole.
It's just a little more complicated.
And that's partly why there
aren't that many magnetic materials.
Right.
There's a tendency for them to want to anti-align,
but there's also competing things going on.
Do they have to have an external
magnetic field in the cool to line up?
No.
But which direction they line up in may be random.
Right.
And that in itself is called spontaneous symmetry breaking.
We're going to be talking about simple magnetic systems,
the tendency toward order as you cool them.
Order means parallelness in this case.
And the,
okay,
so let me make a
remark about what you just asked.
I think you just asked it.
They could all line up this way,
or they could all line up this way,
or they could all line up that way.
And which way do they line up?
Which way do they wind up lining up?
And that itself might be defined or
determined by the tiniest little stray magnetic field.
Just one molecule,
just one little elementary atom being in a magnetic field,
which tends to line it up a little bit,
may govern the whole thing about
the way the whole system lines up.
There's a symmetry.
The symmetry is which way things point.
If they wind up pointing in a direction,
that symmetry is broken.
That's called breaking the symmetry.
There is no more symmetry,
or at least it looks like there's no more symmetry.
But it's spontaneous.
There's no magnetic field
pushing everything in that direction.
It just had to pick a direction.
It picked a direction.
It may be because of a tiny,
tiny,
tiny little stray magnetic field.
But we're going to talk about it.
These are the things we're going to talk about.
And the point at which the symmetry is broken,
the point at which the magnets tend
to line themselves up in some direction,
that's a phase transition.
And that phase transition is
called the magnetic phase transition.
All right.
So first of all,
don't think about literal magnets,
because the model systems that
are studied often are quite unrealistic
as theories of physics.
They're not really magnetic.
They're just a bunch of ferromagnetic chunks of iron.
What makes them interesting is,
of course,
that they resemble a lot of other things in nature
and that they're mathematically simple enough to study
and interesting enough to
exhibit features like phase transitions.
That's what makes them interesting.
OK.
So let's start with the very,
very simplest magnet.
As I say,
don't think of it as a real magnet.
This kind of magnet either
points up or it points down.
It doesn't get to point in random directions.
You can think of it as
heads and tails if you like.
But this very simple mathematical magnet
either points up or it points down.
So and we'll...
It doesn't matter how they're laid out on the blackboard,
but let's lay them out and align.
Some of them are up.
Some of them are down.
And we want to make a statistical mechanics of this
and ask such questions of what's
the relative percentage of ups and downs,
what's the energy of the magnet,
and so forth.
All right.
So before we begin,
if we're going to be talking about statistical mechanics
in the Boltzmann distribution,
we have to have an energy function.
Remember,
e to the minus beta times the energy.
We have to know what the energy is.
So,
yeah.
When you say them,
do I think of these as particles or...
You can think of them as atoms in a crystal,
for example.
Yeah.
You can think of them as atoms in a crystal.
The atoms have electrical currents or maybe they have spins.
Electrical currents make little electromagnets.
And so each atom is a magnet
with a north pole and a south pole.
But for the simplest model,
if you've ever studied,
which we're going to begin with,
the atoms point up or point down,
and they can't point any other way.
And again,
the purpose of this is to be simple.
Okay.
So there's a lot of them.
How many of them?
Capital N.
And what is the energy?
We're going to start with a very,
very simple version.
In the very simple version,
there's no interaction between the atom,
between the magnets at all,
but there is a magnetic field.
There's a magnetic field either
pointing up or pointing down.
I'm not sure which way my notes actually correspond to.
There's a magnetic field.
Each atom has a magnetic moment.
That's just a little number attached to it,
which tells you how strongly
it interacts with the magnetic field.
It has a magnetic moment called mu.
It has to do with...
with the strength of the magnet,
basically.
There's a magnetic field.
The magnetic field is either pointing up or down,
and I can't remember which way I chose it.
Well,
let's not worry about it.
But the energy of one of these magnets
is different if it's up or if it's down.
In particular,
if the magnet is up,
I think we give it a plus energy,
and if the magnet is down,
we give it a minus energy.
So let's invent a variable for each magnet.
Let's give it a name.
Let's call it sigma.
This is the sigma for the first atom.
And this is sigma for the second atom.
Blah,
blah,
blah.
And sigma is either plus or minus one.
It's just a label or a variable
which is plus or minus one.
So if the first spin is up,
that means sigma one is up.
It's plus.
If the second spin is down,
it means sigma two is minus.
And so forth.
Okay,
what is the energy of this system?
If the spin is up,
then the energy is positive,
and it's just equal to mu times h.
What if the spin is down?
What's the energy then?
Okay,
supposing there are n,
little n,
little n spins up,
and little m spins down.
What's the energy?
The energy is equal
to little n minus little m
times mu times h.
Mu times h is the energy
of one spin if it's up,
and minus mu times h
is the spin if it's down.
n,
little n,
equals the number of ups,
and little m is the number of downs.
What's little n plus little m?
Big N.
So little n plus little
m is equal to capital N.
Okay,
we're good to go now.
We can write down the Boltzmann distribution,
and we can calculate anything we want
using statistical mechanics.
So let's do that.
What are the dimensions,
please,
excuse me,
of h and e?
What are the dimensions?
I mean,
is h a number or a magnetic field?
For us,
it's a number.
It's the strength of the magnetic field.
It's an external magnetic field
imposed on the magnet from outside.
So for our purposes,
it's a number.
And mu is also a number.
And we might as well put mu and h together
and just call the whole thing a number.
That's often done.
Sometimes it's called little h,
but I thought I would just
expose the various pieces of it.
Would you prefer it called
big H times mu little h
and never see mu and the big H again?
We could do that.
It doesn't matter.
OK.
All right.
Now...
Excuse me,
what is e?
Oh,
sorry,
e equals...
This is the energy,
and it equals...
Good,
thank you.
Energy equals that.
OK.
Now,
how many configurations are there...
How many configurations are there
with little n ups
and little m downs?
Without asking which ones are which,
how many configurations are there?
We have capital N things,
and we want to group them into two groups.
One group of little n
and one group of little m.
How many such configurations are there?
How many such arrangements are there?
That's a combinatoric problem.
All right.
Yeah.
Yeah,
but let's write it down.
The number of configurations with this value of energy...
The number of configurations with this value of energy
is capital N factorial...
This is number...
Not mumber,
number.
Number of states...
for a given n minus m
is n factorial
over little n factorial,
little m factorial,
remembering that little n and little
m add up to big N.
That's the number of such configurations.
All right.
Let's take one of those configurations
and ask what the Boltzmann weight is for that.
The Boltzmann weight means e to
the minus beta times the energy.
All right.
In fact,
what we're going to be doing
is working out the partition function.
The partition function is the sum over all configurations.
That means it's the sum over n and m
such that little n plus little
m is equal to big N.
I won't bother writing that,
but keep that in mind.
Times e to the minus beta times the energy,
which is mu h times n minus m.
So we just take this thing
and we add them all up.
Now,
for each n minus m,
there's going to be a certain number of configurations,
and that number of configurations
is this combinatoric coefficient here.
So we can write this...
Yeah.
n,
nm is not too variable.
Yeah,
they are.
The number of ups and the number of downs.
Well,
I'm just saying it's not two
variables that are independent of one another.
They have to add up to capital N.
That's all.
So,
but I'm just saying if you have...
You can't use both of them as indices.
No,
no,
they're not.
That's what I'm saying.
You sum over n and m,
making sure that n plus m...
Yeah,
okay.
Quick question.
You can write it another way.
Well,
m is equal to n minus n,
so it's just...
Yeah.
Yeah,
so let's just leave it this
way to keep the notation simple,
but...
You don't need a combinatorial function inside
the sum there before that makes sense?
No,
each individual configuration gives this,
and the number of configurations
with a given energy is this.
All right,
so let me...
You'll understand when I write the formula.
All right.
It's the sum over just n,
little n,
of n factorial over little n factorial
times big N minus little n factorial.
This is capital N factorial,
little n factorial,
little m factorial,
all right,
times e to the minus beta.
And...
So let's leave it this way for a minute.
In fact,
let's not leave it this way.
Let's write the following.
e to the minus beta mu h n,
and let's call that x.
And let's call e to the plus beta mu h.
I could call it 1 over x,
but I'm going to call it y for a minute.
Let's take these two numbers here.
Call e to the minus beta h x,
and the other one y.
Okay,
so what's e to the minus beta h times n?
That's x to the power n.
Do you see that?
Can you see that?
That's x to the power n.
And what about the other factor here?
That's y to the power m.
Let's call there as mu h times m.
All right,
so let's check this out.
I just...
Remember here,
my first example asнalified e to the power n.
This actually is a somewhat semantic symbol,
It's a...
If you closed it in a few lines like this,
it would call ho of e
to the minus beta into 0.
that means thecych is off.
And cox would be 0.
笑
x plus y.
This is the binomial expansion.
This is the binomial expansion and
this whole thing is just equal to
x plus y to the capital N.
All right,
that's the binomial expansion.
And so we've solved it.
We've figured out what z is.
Let's write it down.
Z is just x,
this is z is equal to x,
which is e to the
minus beta mu h plus y,
which is e to the plus beta mu h,
all raised to the capital N power.
That's it,
that's z.
That was easy.
This function,
does that function have a name?
Well,
let's multiply it and divide it by two.
How about this function?
Does it have a name?
It's the hyperbolic cosine,
right?
So let's call it that.
We might as well.
So the answer then is two to the N.
Now two to the N
is not going to be interesting.
It's a number.
A multiplicative factor in the
partition function usually doesn't do anything,
but
we'll leave it there.
And then hyperbolic cosine of
mu h to the power N.
That's the partition function.
Sorry,
beta mu h.
My mistake.
Beta is awfully important.
It's the inverse temperature.
Without it,
we can't differentiate with respect to it.
All right.
So that's our partition function.
Now,
supposing we're interested in the question,
what is the relative percentage
of up spins and down spins?
What's the relative percentage?
That quantity has a name.
It's called the magnetization.
The magnetization is zero if there are
as many up spins as down spins.
The magnetization is plus if there
are more up spins than down spins.
And magnetization is minus in the opposite situation.
So let's define,
first of all,
let's define the magnetization.
N minus M is the difference
between up spins and down spins.
It's sort of the magnetization,
but it's usual to divide it by capital N,
and then,
so that it becomes the magnetization per magnet,
if you know what I mean.
So the,
let's call the magnetization M is equal to N
minus M times mu h divided by capital N.
That's a definition.
The magnetization,
and what is it?
It's the bias for each particle,
whether it's up or down.
If the magnetization is pi
n minus n minus mu h,
then the magnetization is equal to
mu h divided by capital N.
So if the magnetization is positive,
it's sort of the average upness or downness of each,
oh,
I take that back.
The magnetization is just this.
Doesn't have the mu h there.
And that's definition.
That's definition,
all right?
The magnetization is clearly related to the energy.
Let's just write a few equations here,
and then we'll be able to use the partition function.
The energy is equal,
the energy is equal to N
times the magnetization times mu h.
All I've done here is say that
N minus M is the magnetization times N,
that's this,
times mu h.
All right,
so we'll use this.
We'll come back to it.
Too many definitions,
but magnetization is an important one.
It is,
roughly speaking,
the most important one.
The probability of being up minus the
probability of being down for a given spin.
Okay,
how can we calculate the magnetization?
Well,
one easy way is to
calculate the energy of the system.
If we know the energy of the system,
and we know the number of particles,
and we know mu,
and we know mu h,
we can calculate the magnetization.
So the first thing we
will calculate using the partition function,
the partition function is the average energy.
From that we can read off the magnetization.
But the magnetization is for a particular configuration.
Are you talking about some average magnetization?
No,
we're talking about the average magnetization.
We're talking about the average.
Absolutely right.
This is a particular configuration,
and we should say that the
magnetization is equal to mu h.
This is the average of that.
You're absolutely right.
It's the average of it.
It's the average over the
statistical distribution of the Boltzmann distribution.
And of course,
this is also the average energy.
Yeah.
Right.
Okay.
Hell,
what did I do?
There it is.
All right,
so what do we do to calculate the average energy?
We calculate...
Is that obvious?
That it's true?
Which is true?
That the average energy equals the average magnetization?
No,
this is the energy.
Right,
but that's a particular case of it,
right?
No,
that's the energy.
Given n and given m,
that's the average of it.
Right.
That's...
This is the energy...
Sorry.
This is the energy for a given configuration.
Right.
The average energy is the
average value of n minus m.
So...
Well,
Goley's taken into account.
Hm?
With the probabilities taken into account.
Yeah,
with the probability...
yeah.
And all I'm asking is,
is it obvious that that average
energy is equal to that equation
involving the average magnetization?
It's not...
I mean,
it's probably true,
but it's not obvious to me.
Okay.
I mean,
call that E...
Say E sub a.
Here's an equation that configuration by configuration...
All right,
let's...
Look.
It is obvious.
You think about it.
For every configuration,
the energy is proportional to n minus m.
If you average both sides,
the average energy will be proportional
to the average of n minus m.
So the average energy...
We can put averages around all of these.
If something is equal to something else in the equation,
plus configuration by configuration,
then it will also be equal in the average.
So the average magnetization
also involves the probabilities.
Yeah,
absolutely.
Yes,
yes,
yes.
All of these...
Yeah,
everything in statistical mechanics is average.
If you write that last equation
with all the brackets you need,
only the brackets on the right-hand side around n.
No,
actually...
No.
Around capital N?
No,
no,
no.
Around E.
No,
no,
no.
Bottom equation.
Yes,
yes,
of course.
Around this n here,
big N?
Around E and then around big M.
Big M,
big M,
not big N.
Right.
Big N is a number,
big M...
Yes,
all right.
That's right.
All right,
so let's write it the way you want it.
The average energy is equal to n mu H,
all of which are fixed numbers,
times the average magnetization,
let's call it.
Now,
strictly speaking,
with the usual definition,
you don't have to put an average
here because the definition of magnetization is average.
It's also true that in statistical mechanics...
Not an average?
No,
average over the probability distribution.
Okay.
Average over the same exact thing
we did with the ideal gas.
We have a probability
distribution and we calculate averages.
We calculate averages from that probability distribution.
How do you get them all to
line north-south without biasing up or down?
They are biased,
sorry,
what?
You get them not to be east-west,
but...
No,
no,
this is a model in which by definition
these things can only point up or down.
This is a mathematical model...
They're not biased up or down,
for the moment?
They may be biased up versus down,
but they're not biased...
But there's no such thing as east and west.
Well,
that partition function is totally unbiased.
Oh,
it's very biased.
The energy prefers the molecules to be down.
Remember,
the energy is plus if they're up,
minus if they're down.
Systems like to be...
have to have lower energy,
meaning to say that the
Boltzmann distribution favors lower energy.
This is most definitely biased by
the presence of the magnetic field.
So there's no symmetry here.
This is a problem that has no symmetry.
It's biased for the atoms to point down,
and it costs energy to tip them up.
Which way are they likely to be?
Okay,
let's see if we can make some guesses.
Which way will they be at zero temperature?
Right?
No,
definitely not right.
Down.
Right,
so at zero temperature,
what do we expect the magnetization to be?
We expect everybody to be down,
and that means the magnetization will be minus one.
What do we expect at infinite temperature?
Yeah.
Well,
a lot of them are down.
We expect...
at average...
at infinite temperature,
everything is just maximally random.
All states are equally probable.
And so at infinite temperature,
we expect the magnetization to be zero.
So it goes from one at
zero temperature to zero at infinite temperature.
This is what we expect.
This is right.
This is correct.
Sorry,
it goes minus one to zero.
At no point will it be positive,
because the average magnetization will not
be positive because of the bias down.
It's that the infinite...
Infinite temperature will defeat the bias.
Infinite temperature is just so random that
the little bit of magnetic energy is unimportant,
and so it will be random.
But at no point will the average magnetization be up.
It won't be positive.
Okay,
let's...
I hope I'm right.
What would you have to do to make it up?
Switch the magnetic field the other way.
Make the magnetic field negative.
Right.
Switch the magnetic field.
Okay,
so where are we?
Instead of calculating the magnetization,
I'm going to calculate the average energy.
We know how to calculate the
average energy from a partition function.
Remember,
the average energy...
and I'm just going to write E,
no averages...
is equal to minus the derivative of
the logarithm of Z with respect to beta.
So there's a little bit of algebra to do here.
We might as well do it.
I know it tends to put
people asleep to watch me do algebra.
The logarithm of Z...
has a constant from here.
That's going to go away when we differentiate,
so let's not even bother writing it.
It's equal to n log of the hyperbolic cosine...
This is a terrible function...
of beta times mu h.
n times the logarithm...
Notice,
first of all,
that it's proportional to n.
That's a good thing because typically energies,
when we differentiate,
will be proportional to n,
and that's natural.
Let's differentiate this with respect to Z...
Sorry,
with respect to beta.
The derivative of log Z with respect to beta...
First of all,
we'll have an n.
Now,
the derivative of logarithm of an argument
of a thing is one over that thing.
So that will give us,
in the denominator,
hyperbolic cosine of beta mu h.
And then in the numerator,
we have to differentiate...
cosh beta mu h...
with respect to beta.
So what happens when you differentiate cosh?
What is the derivative of cosh?
Cinch.
So that's cinch...
beta h...
Sorry,
beta mu h.
And then you have to differentiate the cosh...
Sorry,
you have to differentiate this thing with respect to beta.
So that gives you another mu h.
mu h outside.
Now,
is that the energy?
Not quite.
Minus sign.
This is the energy.
Minus.
Okay,
so we have the energy.
And we want the magnetization.
So what we want to do with it is
divide it by mu h and divide it by n.
So the magnetization...
is equal to...
minus...
And as I said in the first place,
it comes out minus.
We're dividing by n and we're dividing by mu h.
And so it's just exactly...
cinch...
beta mu h over cosh.
That function also has a name.
It's equal to the tanch...
of beta mu h.
With a minus sign.
With a minus sign,
yes.
With a minus sign.
Okay,
so now all we have to do to understand
this system is understand what the tanch function looks like.
Incidentally,
beta is one over the temperature.
Okay.
So we just want to plot this
function as a function of the temperature.
Mu times h,
that's just a number.
It's not so interesting.
We could absorb it into beta here.
We could plot the thing as
a function of beta mu h.
They come in together.
Okay,
so the question is what
does a tanch function look like?
You can work out what the
tanch function looks like by yourself.
I will show you what it looks like.
Well,
first of all,
cinch and cosh,
for very large values of the argument,
become equal to each other.
They're basically both exponentials of beta mu h.
Let's write them down.
Cosh of x is equal to e to the
x plus e to the minus x over 2.
Cinch of x equals e to the x
minus e to the minus x over 2.
When x gets large,
let's go to large x,
when x gets large,
what happens to e to the minus x?
It just goes away.
So for large x,
they both are equal to e to the x,
and their ratio is 1.
So very far away,
cinch over cosh,
I'm not including the minus sign now,
just the cinch over cosh,
the tanch function,
goes to 1.
Incidentally,
for negative x,
it goes to minus 1.
But let's not worry about that.
x is going to be positive in this problem.
Now what does it do near the origin?
Near the origin,
cosh is equal to 1.
x equals 0,
near the origin.
e to the x is 1.
This is 1 plus 1 is 2.
What about this one?
That's 0.
But what about the linear,
what about the correction to it
if we expand e to
the x as 1 plus x?
So the e to the
x will be 1 plus x
minus e to the minus
x is minus 1 plus x
divided by 2,
and the answer is just x.
The first derivative here is 1.
In other words,
it starts out just looking like x,
and it very quickly just bends over.
It's a very boring function.
It starts out linear,
and then it gets tired quickly,
and it just flattens out.
That's the tanch function.
All right.
And this horizontal axis is beta times mu h.
Now keeping in mind that
beta is 1 over the temperature,
what is the magnetization when the temperature is small?
That's when beta is large.
When beta is large,
we're way out here,
and the tanch function is 1.
So the magnetization is minus 1.
Zero temperature,
all the spins align themselves down.
Okay.
What about infinite temperature?
Infinite temperature is beta equals 0.
Beta equals 0.
Well,
first of all,
the magnetization is 0.
Beta equals 0.
The magnetization is 0,
as expected.
And this just fills in the details for us.
This just fills in the exact details for this problem
of how the magnetization
goes from 1 at low temperatures
and goes to 0 at high temperatures.
Okay.
So,
you asked me how can you get the magnetization
to go in the opposite direction.
Well,
the answer is to allow h to go negative.
If h goes negative,
then it looks like that.
So if the magnetic field flips sign,
everything just reverses.
I have a question,
please.
This looks like a continuous,
but you said there is a temperature with...
No,
no,
not in this system.
Not in this system.
This system does not have a phase transition.
No.
This is too simple.
The first interesting system
that has a phase transition
is the two-dimensional Ising model.
But first we're going to do
the one-dimensional Ising model.
Ising
was
not a very good student.
He was a student of Lenz,
L-E-N-Z,
who was famous for the...
for a number of things.
For one of the things he was famous for,
or he was not famous for,
was inventing the Ising model.
He gave his student one problem
to determine whether there was a phase transition
in the Ising model,
in the one-dimensional Ising model.
And his student got the wrong answer.
He said there was a phase transition,
there was not.
That's all,
as far as I know,
that Ising ever did.
So why it's called the Ising model is just...
And Ising is the most famous model,
the most famous name in all of statistical mechanics.
ありがとうございました
way it goes.
Win some,
you lose some.
You win some,
sorry,
you lose some,
you win,
I don't know.
Okay,
what is the Ising model?
Now the interesting thing about the Ising model
is it is symmetric between up and down.
So therefore,
if there is any magnetization,
it's because somehow the system
has spontaneously broken the symmetry.
In the one-dimensional Ising model,
that does not happen.
In the two-dimensional Ising model,
it does happen.
So I will define all of
these Ising models for you right now.
They work the following way.
The energy is not stored particle by particle.
There's no energy.
We have no external field.
So if the particles didn't interact with each other,
if the little magnets didn't interact with each other,
there would be no energy.
And if there's no energy,
all configurations are equally likely.
In this case,
the magnetic field that each spin sees
is due to its neighbors.
If its neighbors are up,
it feels a magnetic field up.
If both neighbors are down,
it feels a magnetic field down.
And if one is up and one down,
it feels no magnetic field.
So what we're saying is that
the energy is associated with pairs,
with pairs of neighboring spins.
And if the pairs are in the same direction,
let's take that to be lower energy.
We have to make a choice now.
Do we want the interactions
to favor alignment or anti-alignment?
If it's anti-alignment,
this is alignment.
This is alignment,
and this is also alignment.
The energy is going to be equal for this configuration
as it is for that configuration,
and unequal to this configuration or that configuration.
You get it?
All right,
good.
So we come back to these variables sigma.
And we say if sigma is aligned,
if the two neighboring sigmas are aligned,
just focus on two spins,
if they're aligned,
then the energy is lower.
If they're unaligned,
the energy is larger.
So let's take the energy to be
some number which is usually called J.
I don't know what J stands for.
It's usually just called J.
It's just a number.
It has an energy scale.
It's an energy scale for the problem.
J times sigma of particle
one times sigma of particle two.
Only two particles for a moment.
These are two neighboring particles on a lattice.
Now later on,
we'll allow the lattice.
Now the lattice is just a line.
Later on,
we can have the lattice be a two-dimensional lattice
or a three-dimensional lattice.
One and two are neighboring sites on the lattice.
And this is the energy of the one-two pair.
Now,
this energy is going to be lower if they're anti-aligned.
Because if they're anti-aligned,
sigma one times sigma two is negative.
I want the energy to be lower if they're aligned.
So I'm going to put a minus sign here.
With this energy,
the energy is low if the spins are aligned.
And it's higher if they're anti-aligned.
Now,
supposing we have a line of them.
And each one is interacting with its neighbor.
Then we can write that the energy is equal to a sum
minus J of sigma of N times sigma of N plus one.
Does everybody understand what that means?
The product of the spin...
Spin,
I call it spin.
The product of the magnetic moment
at each site times its neighboring site.
Each one,
each pair,
each neighboring pair counted once.
Okay,
so this is our expression for the energy.
Now,
let's think about it for a moment.
What do you expect to happen at infinite temperature?
The general rule is that
infinite temperature is just random chaos.
Everything is equally likely.
Zero magnetization.
And we'll worry about the energy,
but yeah.
Right,
everything is just random.
And so in particular,
zero magnetization.
Everything.
Every product will be zero,
too,
because one is one and one is zero.
Every product will be on the average zero.
That's right.
Why does that bother you?
It means the energy is there.
Well,
don't forget,
the energy,
if they're all parallel,
is negative.
So you're starting with a negative bias.
You're starting with the
ground state having negative energy.
So the zero of energy,
so to speak,
is a big negative number.
So having zero energy is effectively having a
lot of energy relative to the ground state.
All right.
すっきりと見る
Why are the products up in zero?
I thought sigma was either plus one or minus one.
It is,
but on the average,
if the neighbors are randomly
distributed,
yeah,
the average.
If you have random chaos,
that means
there is likely to be found parallel is anti-parallel.
So the average energy will be zero,
which is a lot of energy.
But what about zero temperature?
What would you guess for zero temperature?
They'll be aligned,
right?
They'll want to be aligned.
But which way?
Are they going to be this way?
All of them.
Everybody aligned this way or everybody aligned this way?
You can't tell offhand.
There are two ground states.
Ground states mean states of minimum energy.
And they will both come in with equal probability.
And they're going to be aligned.
They'll both come in with equal probability.
But now let me add one more thing.
Let me suppose that there's a magnetic field,
external magnetic field,
but it's only acting on one particle.
One out of 10 to the
23rd has a little stray magnetic field.
And let's say that magnetic field is along one axis.
Then what is the ground state?
The ground state has a definite orientation.
Even if that magnetic field is very small,
the ground state still has a definite orientation.
And at zero temperature,
at strictly zero temperature,
the Boltzmann distribution always favors
infinitely strongly the lowest energy state.
So that means that even the tiniest little magnetic field,
stray magnetic field,
is going to be aligned with the ground state.
Well,
the Boltzmann distribution will favor all
of the spins pointing along one axis.
If you were to apply that tiny magnetic field,
let the system come to equilibrium at zero temperature,
and then remove the magnetic field,
the system will remember it.
Everybody's holding everybody else in place.
And the possibility of them all
simultaneously jumping to the opposite state
is remote if there's enough of them.
So that's called spontaneous symmetry breaking.
That is what spontaneous symmetry breaking is.
In this case,
it's very simple.
And this example has a symmetry.
We can actually say quantitatively
or mathematically what that symmetry is.
A symmetry is usually represented by a
mathematical operation on the degrees of freedom.
What mathematical operation would you do on sigma
if you were to change from up to down?
Multiply it by minus one.
Right.
Okay.
Let's go back to the earlier case over here,
where the energy,
in this case we could say,
the energy was proportional to just sigma itself,
not sigma times a neighboring sigma,
but just sigma by itself.
Does that have a symmetry?
No.
The energy itself changes sign when you change sigma.
And that's not a symmetry.
Symmetry is actions that you can
do that don't change the energy.
Okay.
What about this system?
Supposing you change the sign of one spin,
one of them,
sigma one and not sigma two.
Is that a symmetry?
No.
The energy changes.
But what if you change them both?
If you change them both,
then the energy doesn't change sign.
So if you go from two up to two down,
that's a symmetry.
Now we have this whole vast array of them,
and what if we change all of the sigmas simultaneously?
We write formally the equation sigma of i
for all i goes to minus sigma of i.
We replace every sigma by minus its value.
Then the energy doesn't change.
And that's what it means to have a symmetry,
an operation that you can do
on the coordinates of a system
that don't change the energy,
no matter what state,
for every state.
Whatever the state is,
there is another corresponding state
which has the same energy but
in which the spins are all reoriented
opposite to what you started with.
And that ensures that in some sense,
there's no bias to up or down.
If the system is going to flop
itself all simultaneously into up at zero temperature,
that means it could have also flopped itself into down.
There's no way to predict in advance,
unless you know that tiny little stray magnetic field,
there's no way to predict in
advance which way it's going to go,
but it's going to go one way or the other,
because the Boltzmann distribution says you've
got to be in the ground state.
So you've got to be in
the ground state for zero temperature.
And as I said,
the little tiny stray magnetic field,
which will determine which one it is,
but it will be one of them.
All right,
so clearly the next thing we want to do
is to solve the one-dimensional Ising model.
We want to find,
what do we want to do?
We want to calculate exactly the same,
not the same part,
we want to calculate the partition function
for this.
So we're going to do that in the next time,
we're going to do that in the next time,
we'll work it out,
and we will see that there is not,
it does not have a
phase transition at a finite temperature.
Nothing funny happens at finite temperature.
Contrary to what Ising thought.
It took a few more
years for a couple of physicists
named Cromers and Wannier to
prove that if it's a two-dimensional,
two-dimensional lattice,
there is a phase transition.
And that's a beautiful story,
and we'll try to do it.
For more,
please visit us at stanford.edu.