Stanford University.
Let me go back and remind you,
what we're going to do today is
we're going to study the Ising model.
I was terribly unfair to Ising last time.
I was.
I looked it up and I was somewhat off base.
I said
that Ising failed to solve the model correctly or whatever.
No,
I think he solved it correctly and
then thought there was a phase
transition in the one-dimensional Ising model.
That would be totally
inexcusable.
It's not exactly what happened.
It wasn't that bad.
He solved the one-dimensional
Ising model correctly.
It had been given to him
by his thesis advisor as a problem,
Lenz,
the famous
physicist Lenz.
And he solved it correctly.
He realized it didn't have a phase transition,
but
on the basis of that,
it was a problem.
And he said,
well,
I'm going to solve it.
And he said,
well,
I'm going to solve it.
And he said,
well,
I'm going to solve it.
And on the basis of that,
he believed
and wrote in his thesis that the Ising model
in any dimension does not have a phase transition.
And that was wrong.
That was incorrect.
And we're going to talk about that today.
We're not going
to solve the higher dimensional Ising models.
They're too hard for us.
They are very hard.
But we will use an
approximation method that's physically very intuitive.
And we'll see that in
Higher dimensions,
sufficiently high dimensions,
there is a phase transition.
And we'll talk about what that phase transition means.
Phase transition means a sudden change in
the properties of the system as you vary,
for example,
the temperature.
But let's go slow.
Let's take it in steps.
Let me go back to the
simple example that we studied last time.
We studied the
problem of a collection of little magnets.
Each magnet could be up or down.
And there was an energy function.
And the energy function differed between up and down.
Let me write it again.
The energy of a magnet when it's up is
different than the energy of a magnet when it's down.
We introduced a little variable called sigma.
Sigma could be plus one or minus one.
Plus one up,
minus one down.
And we wrote an energy function.
I wrote it last time as a magnetic moment mu times a magnetic field
b times the thing which tells you whether the spin is up or down.
I'm going to change the notation.
This is too complicated.
Mu times b,
they just come together and they'll always come together.
So we might as well just call them.
I'm going to call the product one thing.
And I'm going to call the product j.
Turns out that is a standard
notation for what we'll be doing later.
So we'll just call it j.
What j stands for I do not know.
And I'm also going to make it minus.
It doesn't make any difference to the physics because it really
is just a redefinition of what you mean as up and down.
If the original energy favors the negative,
then it's minus.
If it favors the down,
then if I change the sign it favors up.
But other than that,
the interchange of up and down,
there really is no difference.
So let's see,
the way I have it now,
it will favor up.
It will favor sigma being
positive because if sigma is positive,
the energy is negative.
And of course,
lowering the energy is favorable.
Lower energy is favorable,
especially at low temperatures.
All right.
So then what we did is we said,
We studied a whole group of them,
and we did some combinatorics to try to calculate how many states
there are with a little n up and a little m down
But we could have done something much simpler.
I did it that way just
to do it in some careful detail
But we can actually do something else
We've already learned that you can always think of a subsystem
as a system being a small subsystem plus a heat bath
And in that case,
the rest of the heat bath is just what,
it just provides the heat bath,
it's what brings one of these systems to equilibrium
And we could just focus on one of them
We could just focus on one spin,
that's a spin,
I call it spin 1
One of these little magnets
And just assume that it is
in thermal equilibrium with its environment,
its environment being the rest of the magnet
Alright,
in that case,
then we would just focus
on one of these little guys,
and we would write the partition function for
one of them as being summation over the configurations
How many configurations are there?
Two!
It's going to be easy
Two configurations
E to the minus beta times j,
sorry it's going to be plus beta j times sigma
Why plus?
Because we're supposed to write e
to the minus beta times the energy
And that's what we want to calculate
What is the sigma doing there?
The sigma is just telling
us whether it's up or down
So there's really just two terms
One term,
sigma is up
That gives us e to the beta j
And the other term,
it's down
So it's e to the minus beta j
That's the partition function for just one spin
One of them is minus
One of them is minus,
e to the beta j,
e to the minus beta j
Okay
When we calculated it,
thinking of the whole system as one system
Remember the answer we got?
It was eightег
little spin we have a factor like that.
Let's concentrate on that spin.
That's z.
And that happens to be twice
the hyperbolic cosine of beta j.
When we did
it last time we got twice the hyperbolic
cosine of beta j raised to the number
of powers of each spin.
When we took the logarithm of that,
which is the
interesting thing,
it simply becomes the sum.
For example,
the energy,
which is
just the derivative of the logarithm,
is nothing but the sum of the energies of
the individual ones.
Here we're concentrating on one spin at a time and
one magnet at a time and we'll
calculate exactly the same energy for it.
So let's
calculate the energy.
The energy can be calculated
as 1 over z with a
minus 1.
The derivative of z with respect to beta,
this is the same as the derivative of
the logarithm.
The derivative of the logarithm of z
is just 1 over z times the
derivative of z.
Okay,
so this is not so hard.
The derivative of z with respect to
beta has a 2.
And then what's the derivative of hyperbolic cosine?
It's
hyperbolic sine.
So we will get a
hyperbolic sine of beta times j.
But then we have to
differentiate the argument of the cosine,
the cosh,
with respect to beta,
and
that gives us another j.
And that's it.
No,
not yet.
We still have to divide by z.
That's going to get rid of this 2 here.
I look at it here and I say,
that's just a
numerical multiplication.
I know numerical multiples don't matter,
but now we see exactly why.
When I divide by z,
the 2 will just cancel,
and I will get j sinh divided by cosh,
which is called j times
the hyperbolic tangent of beta j.
This is the,
did I?
There's a negative sign.
Yeah,
there is a negative.
There is,
on the far left,
look at it.
Yeah.
Yeah,
it's minus 1 over z at the left.
Yes,
I know.
I know,
Yeah,
that's true.
OK.
So that's the average energy of one of these spins,
and you can also ask,
what is
the probability that the spin is up versus down,
or what is the average?
Sigma is the
thing which can take on the
value plus 1 and minus 1,
but what is the average sigma?
Well the energy is minus j times sigma.
This is the average energy.
It's pretty clear that
the average sigma is just
the same thing without the j.
So let's write that.
Let's
first of all write that the energy,
and this is the average energy,
and it's now the average
energy of one particle.
It's not the average energy of the whole system.
That's the way
we're going to focus on it now.
And that's equal to minus j hyperbolic tangent of beta
j.
I'm just rewriting the same thing.
And we can also talk about the average spin,
and the average spin,
or the average,
I keep
calling it spin,
I should call it the magnetization,
the average value of the upness or downness
of the magnet,
that is just equal to tangent,
hyperbolic tangent of beta j.
OK.
This is,
we're going to need this.
We're going to need it,
but let me just draw a picture
of it.
Hyperbolic tangent is a function which looks like this.
Now,
this is a hyperbolic tangent
of x.
And x is beta j.
OK.
So this is a hyperbolic tangent of beta j.
J is a number.
We could
have set j equal to 1.
I don't even know why I bothered keeping the j.
I could have left
it equal to 1.
It's tanh of something
proportional to the inverse temperature.
OK.
The slope of the
hyperbolic tangent over here is 1.
It just has a unit slope over here.
And then it asymptotically
becomes flat and goes to a constant,
namely 1 over here,
and minus 1 over here.
OK.
So
let's think about what that says.
If beta is very,
very large,
that means low temperature,
and let's suppose j is positive.
then beta j is very large and positive.
That's way out here.
And what it's telling us is
that the spin will point up
with probability very,
very close to 1.
The value here is 1,
and the average of the
spin is very close to 1.
The only way it can be close to 1,
if the only values it can
take are minus 1 and 1,
the only way the average can be really close to 1
is if the probability is almost exclusively for it to be up.
And that's what's going on out here.
On the other hand,
we can also look at the negative axis.
Beta,
we don't want beta to be negative.
Beta is the inverse temperature,
but j can be negative.
That just corresponds to having put in the other sign,
and all it does is flip up and down.
So,
as you might expect,
what goes on,
way out here,
when beta j is very negative,
is the spin wants to point in the opposite direction.
The magnet wants to point in the opposite direction,
and that's all that's happening here.
Otherwise,
the two sides are completely symmetric.
Notice that at the origin,
now where is the origin here?
The origin means beta j equals 0.
That means very high temperature.
Very high temperature beta is the inverse.
The inverse temperature,
very high temperature,
the temperature is just so high
that it's constantly being kicked around,
and it overcomes,
the temperature just overcomes any bias
for it to be up or down,
and so on the average is just plain 0.
Okay,
so this was a very,
very simple system.
Now we want to come
to the next most complicated magnet,
and it's the one that we talked about.
But let's go back to it.
The Ising model,
which is,
and the one-dimensional Ising model,
which is at each point along a one-dimensional array,
there's a sigma.
Sigma is either up or down.
The new thing is that the energy
depends on the relationship between neighboring ones.
The energy is now the sum.
Now,
this is not the one part.
This is the particle energy.
This is the total energy.
You know,
we better keep in mind that this thing
over here is the energy of just one spin,
not the whole thing.
Okay,
now I'm actually studying the whole shebang.
The energy is the sum of all of them,
of the product of neighbors.
Let's call it sigma i times sigma i plus 1.
And then you go to each side,
and you multiply the spin by the
spin or the value of its neighbor.
We'll also put a j there.
The j is just a numerical constant,
which I'm sort of sorry I introduced,
but let's leave it there.
We've...
since I started.
And I'm also going to put a minus sign there.
Okay,
that's the energy.
The minus sign means that it favors them being parallel.
You want to lower the energy as much as possible,
and you lower the energy by having them all parallel.
If they're all parallel,
the product of the spins
is all equal to plus 1,
and with the minus sign that I included here,
the way to lower the energy
is to make them all parallel.
What would happen if I put plus j in here?
Oh,
first of all,
let's...
let's imagine now the ground state of the system.
What is the ground state of the system like?
The ground state will have...
the lowest energy will have them all lined up.
But in which direction?
Up or down?
There's two ground states,
and they're the same.
They have the same energy.
All ups or all downs.
Now,
what would happen if we change the sign of j?
In other words,
make it plus j.
Sigma i,
sigma i plus 1.
Is it really a different system?
No.
It's really the same system,
and all you have to do
to see it's the same system
is to redefine every other spin by changing its sign.
On every other spin,
what you called up,
you now call down.
You redefine the variable,
and then what you find out is the ground state
wants to have them all anti-parallel.
Up,
down,
up,
down.
But it's really mathematically an identical system.
And again,
there are two states.
This particle could be up,
in which case this one will be down,
in which case this will be up,
in which case this will be down,
or the opposite.
So it's mathematically identical.
Yeah?
Fix your mic real quick.
No,
you're missing the point of this.
This is in place of my coffee.
Okay.
Good.
And what we want to calculate is the usual thing
we want to calculate our friend,
the partition function,
our best friend,
the partition function.
And what is that?
That's e to the minus sum.
Now what are we summing over?
We're going to be summing over all possible configurations.
Any one of these could be up or down,
and that's a huge sum,
all right?
But we're going to do it.
E sum,
e to the minus j summation sigma i,
sigma i plus 1.
It looks terrible.
It looks very hard.
Oops,
I missed,
I left out something.
Beta.
The temperature,
the inverse temperature.
So there's a beta there.
Did you say that there's no external field?
No what?
Did you say there's no external magnetic field?
No external magnet for the moment,
yeah.
No external magnet.
We could do it with an external magnet too,
and we will discuss that at some point.
But for the moment,
no external magnet.
And this is the problem we want to do.
Okay,
let me first organize a question that we can ask.
I would like to know
the answer to the following question.
Supposing I know that the,
the magnet over here is up.
Then I could ask,
knowing that the magnet over here is up,
then what is the probability that
n links down the chain here,
it's also up?
That's called a correlation function.
It's the conditional probability that if we
know that a spin over here is up,
what's the probability at some
other place that it's also up?
Could ask it a different way.
You could ask what is the,
it's the same question really,
what is the average of the
product of spins at two different locations?
What is the average?
Now you might think,
in this case you'd be right,
you might think that if you
go far enough down the chain,
that a spin being up over here
would have very little effect farther down,
and you might expect then that the
average of the product would be zero,
because whatever this spin is up here,
this one has equal likelihood to be up or down.
You might,
you might guess.
But you might be wrong too.
There might be an effect of
just having one spin up over here
that would propagate all the way through the system
and tell you that there's a
net bias throughout the whole sample.
You could diagnose that by looking at the average property,
the average value of the spin over here,
let's call that at point I,
times the spin at I plus N,
where N is N units down the chain.
If there does exist this memory,
this kind of memory,
where if this spin is up it biases the system
all the way to infinity,
then this would not go to zero with large distances.
If on the other hand
that bias does go to zero,
then this one being up would not bias this one,
and on the average the product would be zero.
So this is an interesting diagnostic test
of the effectiveness of one spin being up
on its neighbors,
and how far that propagates down the chain.
Okay,
so let's see if we can guess
what the answer is for this case.
Think of this instead of as
a spin chain or a magnet,
think of it as a game of telephone.
You know the game of telephone
where you whisper to your neighbor.
So we have a long chain of people,
and a message is going
to start at one end somewhere,
it doesn't have to be at the end,
it could be over here,
and the message is going
to be a very simple message,
either zero or one.
We're not going to make fancy messages
like the kids who play this game,
you know,
my dog had a heart attack and therefore I'm
off dog food for the rest of my life,
I don't know what,
but
no,
just zero or one,
zero or one.
And people hear pretty well,
and people talk pretty well among this group of people,
but the fidelity is not absolute.
It's not absolutely perfect.
It's pretty good,
but it's not absolutely perfect.
The question is how far down the chain
does the signal propagate before it gets lost,
before it just becomes equally likely far down the chain
that the person agrees with the starting point or disagrees.
The answer is no matter how good the fidelity,
as long as it's not absolutely perfect,
you'll lose memory sufficiently far down.
If there's a probability for an
error of one percent in each time,
then the probability for no error is 99 percent.
But then to go two units down the chain,
it's 99 percent of 99 percent,
and that's .981,
right?
100 minus one squared.
Which is 100 squared minus twice 100 plus one.
Right.
.981.
I just said the binomial theorem.
Binomial theorem.
.981.
I'm not going to try to do the next one.
But,
you know,
each time it goes down by a factor of .99,
and if you go far enough down the chain,
that product will get arbitrarily small.
And so the probability,
100 units down the chain,
that the signal is remembered with good fidelity is zero.
Well,
not zero.
100 units down the chain is
about where it begins to fail.
Seriously.
10,000 units down the chain,
basically no memory.
The same is true.
It's the same thing here.
If this bin is up,
and there's no signal now,
but there is a bias,
and the bias is the energy bias here.
The system prefers a lower energy.
At zero temperature,
zero temperature is like the perfectly accurate signal.
Infinite fidelity.
That's like the situation where there's no loss whatever.
And then everybody just lines up.
If this gentleman says up,
then this lady down here will say up.
If this gentleman says down,
this lady will say down.
So there's perfect correlation.
But if there's any slight infidelity,
not the word I was looking for,
but this,
this,
yeah,
you know what?
It will fade.
And that's what will happen here.
That's what will happen here.
And Ising got that right.
He got that right.
Okay,
so let's see if we can calculate.
Let's,
what's the trick?
There is a trick.
The trick is a marvelous trick.
I imagine it was invented by Ising.
I don't know.
And the trick was to focus,
instead of on the spins,
on the links between the spins.
So here is what I imagine Ising said to himself.
He said,
look,
there are two possible configura,
there are two possible values that the first,
we're going to imagine for the moment
that the chain is finite.
Let's imagine the chain is finite.
And then we'll let it get very big.
But let the chain be finite.
And the first spin can either be up or down.
Let's start by assuming it's up.
And later on,
we'll put back the configurations where it's down.
So we're going to write the partition function
as a sum of two terms.
In the first term,
the first one is up.
And in the second term,
the first one is down.
But let's concentrate on the one
where this spin is up to begin with.
This one at the beginning of the chain is up.
All right.
Then I can either use as my information
about this next spin here,
I can either use the value of the spin
or I can talk about the
product of this spin times this one.
Okay.
For example,
let's take sigma one times sigma two.
Since sigma one is known to be up,
sigma one times sigma two will tell you
everything you want to know about sigma two.
So let's call that mu one.
And what is it?
It's a variable that has to do with the relationship
between the first spin and the second spin.
Okay.
It's a variable which has to do with the relation.
But if you know it,
then you know what the second spin is.
Okay.
What about the next one?
Let's introduce sigma two times sigma two.
Let's take sigma three and call that mu two.
That's telling you,
if you like,
the state of the link between.
Think of,
instead of thinking of the spins,
think of the links.
The links have two possibilities,
either parallel or anti-parallel.
That would tell you nothing about any individual spin
unless you knew the first one was up.
If you know the first one is up
and you know mu one,
then you know sigma two.
Supposing you also know mu one and mu two.
Then you know what sigma three is.
And in fact,
sigma three will just be mu one times mu two.
Why is that?
If mu one is up,
mu one times mu two,
sigma two squared is one.
Sigma two is either plus or minus one.
So multiplying it by itself gives you one.
And you find out that sigma
three is mu one times mu two.
So if you know mu
one and you know mu two,
you know the first three spins.
Obviously,
if you know the mus
for all of the links in between,
you know all the spins.
And there's no redundancy,
there's no double counting.
As long as you know
that that first spin is up,
then there's no double counting.
It is equally good to know the mus,
which live,
so to speak,
on the bonds between the spins,
as it is to know the spins themselves.
But that's very useful.
Why?
Because the energy is just made up
out of these bond variables.
Bond meaning the relationship between neighbors.
So here's what we can write.
We can write that this energy
is just the sum over the bonds.
Let's call them the bonds.
The neighboring bonds.
The sum over the bonds,
first bond,
second bond.
Notice there's one fewer bond
than there are particles.
But it's sum over the bonds
of mu i.
In other words,
it's also a sum over i.
Let's just call it sum over i.
Of mu i,
in other words,
the first bond variable,
the second bond variable,
and so forth,
times minus j.
We're not even multiplying anything anymore.
It's just the individual bonds.
And the individual bonds are all independent.
There are no relationships between them.
As long as you know
that that first spin is up,
there are no relationships between them,
among them.
And it is as good to know the mus
as it is to know the sigmas.
So you can substitute,
you can write,
you can substitute the sum over spins,
you can substitute for it
the sum over the values of the bonds.
What are the possible values of the bonds?
Plus one and minus one.
Now it's plus one if they're aligned,
and minus one if they're anti-aligned.
So we can write this as z,
instead of the sum over the spins,
this is sum over the spins,
it's sum over the bond variables,
e to the minus j.
j beta times the ith bond.
Now in fact,
I'm going to tell you
that it's twice this answer.
Why is it twice that answer?
You can start with the other one.
Because we could have started with the first bond down.
But a factor of two is no big deal
in a partition function.
So the other thing is to remember,
if the number of,
magnets is very large,
it doesn't matter much,
but we should remember that there's one fewer bond
than spins.
Other than that,
this has now reduced
to exactly this problem.
Except that I've,
except mu,
in this here is called sigma.
It's a sum over uncoupled individual bonds,
and it has exactly the same form
as the partition function for,
for the simpler magnet.
But remember now,
a mu does not stand
for the value of a magnet.
It stands for the relationship between two magnets,
between two neighbors.
But still,
we know the partition function.
There it is.
Same thing.
Twice,
cosh beta j.
Okay,
so let's write it in full.
It's twice this.
So it's gonna,
we're gonna have an extra factor of two
on the outside of it.
Then twice cosh beta j.
And now let me put in
the thing which I didn't put here,
which was if I have a lot of spins,
this gets raised to the nth power.
So this is now to the number of bonds
which is the same as
the number of magnets minus one.
That minus one is not gonna,
okay,
so are you with me?
Everybody with me?
I have a question,
please.
Yeah.
In the first expression of z,
where you had sigma i sigma i plus one,
there was a sum.
The sum is gone in the lower one.
Why is that?
Sorry,
where were you?
The last line and the one before.
Oh,
sorry.
No,
there's certainly a sum here.
Excuse me.
There is a sum here.
Is this what you're talking about?
Yeah.
Minus sum over i of that.
All right,
but the point is,
of course,
that some...
Is that the argument of the Cauchon also,
the sum?
No,
no.
That sum...
It's raised.
Remember that a sum and an exponent
just means a product.
Got it,
got it.
Right.
So this is just a sum over each individual bond.
This thing just factorizes into separate sums
for each one of the bonds.
All right.
So all it is,
each one of the bonds
is the energy as a sum.
That means the Boltzmann factor here is a product.
And it's just summing over each spin individually...
Not each spin,
each bond individually.
It just factorizes.
If you have trouble seeing exactly why it factorizes,
the thing to do is to
write it down for three spins
with two bonds.
Okay?
Just write it down with three spins,
two bonds.
Write down the full expression,
and you'll see very quickly why it factorizes.
So that's what ultimately yields the n and the exponent.
That's what yields the n and the exponent.
Yeah,
that's right.
That's right.
And we actually did it both ways.
We did it last time for the single spin,
but for the problem on the top,
we did it both ways.
We did it by thinking of the whole system
and counting all the configurations,
and then later we just did it for one spin
and then took it to the nth power.
And that's a legitimate thing to do.
All right,
so we've reduced it to
exactly the same problem as before.
The only difference is the physical meaning
of the degrees of freedom
here is a little bit different.
Okay.
Now,
what is the average...
Let's not ask about the average of the spin.
Let's ask of the average of mu.
The average of the function.
The average of the product of neighboring spins.
The average of the product of neighboring spins
anywhere along the chain
is going to be exactly the same calculation as this.
So let's write it down.
The average...
We could either write it as any given mu,
or we can write it as the average of
sigma i,
sigma i plus 1.
That's going to be tanh beta j.
You know,
I think with my current setup,
it's tanh beta j.
Tanh beta j,
that's correct.
So,
it's not zero.
There's the product of them...
The fact that it's not zero and positive...
We're taking j to be positive.
The fact that it's non-zero and positive
tells us that there's a net tendency
for i to line up in the same direction
the i plus first one.
That's the same thing as saying there's a bias
for mu to be positive.
There's a bias if the first spin is found up,
the next one has a better than even chance
of also being found up.
And what's the better than even chance?
Basically,
tanh beta j.
Okay.
So,
this tells us the correlation between neighbors.
And there is a correlation between neighbors.
But let's now go far down the line.
Let's now ask exactly the question
which I asked when we started.
What's the correlation
between the first spin,
the ith spin over here,
and one n units down the chain?
How are we going to get at that?
Well,
the answer is very simple.
You just write...
Let's see,
let's use this blackboard over here.
Here's what we want to calculate.
The average of sigma i...
Let's...
Times...
Sigma i plus n.
I'm leaving a gap in there
because I want to write some things.
Okay.
What I'm going to put in here
is sigma i plus 1,
sigma i plus 1.
What's sigma i plus 1 times sigma i plus 1?
I didn't do anything.
And then I'm going to
put in sigma i plus 2,
sigma i plus 2.
And so forth
until I get to the last one here.
But now I can write this
as the product
mu 1,
mu 2,
mu 3,
dot,
down to mu...
Now,
how many is it?
How many do I have going down there?
Is it n minus 1?
It's n minus 1,
right?
Where mu 1 means this thing over here,
the next mu 2 is this thing over here,
mu 3 is the next one here,
until we get down to the end of the chain.
All right.
So now all we want to know
is the average
of the product of these.
But all of the mus are independent of each other.
The energy is the sum of the energies.
The problem completely factorized.
The average of any one of the mus
is tanh beta j.
So what's the answer?
The answer is tanh beta j
to the power n minus 1.
In other words,
the number of steps
between the first spin and the last one.
This formula is expressing exactly the idea
of the game of telephone.
بات
If you lose,
tanh beta j is,
first of all,
always less than 1,
except when beta is infinite.
That's absolute zero temperature.
Zero temperature,
perfect fidelity,
this is 1,
and no matter how far down the line you go,
the answer will be 1,
which is the statement that at zero temperature,
if you know that this one is lined up,
every one of them is lined up.
There are only two possibilities,
everybody lined up this way
or everybody lined up that way.
In either case,
the product is 1.
But if there's any loss of fidelity at all,
which means in this case
the temperature is not absolutely zero,
then this tanh beta j is less than 1,
and each time you go another step,
you lose a factor of tanh beta j.
That's like losing this 99% of 99%.
And so,
whether you like it or not,
when you go sufficiently far down the chain,
this correlation function will become arbitrarily small.
There will be no or negligible exponentially small memory.
This is an exponential function of n,
a number less than 1,
raised to the nth power.
So the correlation falls exponentially with n,
with distance.
I thought the correlation function was just
sigma i times sigma i plus n.
The average of it.
Right,
right.
But I mean,
it doesn't have all these ones
in between that you have here,
right?
No,
no.
I did a trick.
I put ones in here.
I put ones in there.
Why?
Because I wanted to re-express it in
terms of the things which I knew,
which are the mu's.
It's a marvelous trick.
You concentrate on the bonds
instead of the spins themselves.
I don't know.
I don't know if this
was invented by Isaac or not.
If it is,
he deserves some applause.
All right.
Okay.
This incidentally is a pattern.
This incidentally is called a duality.
In modern physics,
this could be thought of as the first duality,
equivalence of different systems.
We found an equivalence.
Between a theory of spins
which are connected nearest neighbor
with another theory up there of just
spins which are uncoupled to each other.
With a change of variables.
A clever change of variables
which basically took sites to bonds,
which interchange sites and bonds.
Sites are the points of the lattice.
Bonds are the sites and links
of the things we would say.
That's the first example of a
duality between different statistical mechanical systems.
Yeah.
Edges and vertices.
It's not always edges and vertices,
but in this case it is.
At one point you said
there was a bias to anti-alignment,
because that's a lower energy.
That's always minus one.
No,
no.
It's,
the lower energy is when they're aligned.
I think.
That's the part I missed.
Yeah.
Okay.
If they're aligned,
the energy is negative.
That's why I put the minus sign here.
So the minus sign means this
is a lower energy state than this.
Yes.
Not what a magnet.
Hmm.
That's what a ferromagnet does.
Ferromagnets,
the magnets line up.
Right.
It's a matter of very intricate detail whether the little
elementary magnets in a material prefer to align or anti-align.
Most of the times they prefer to anti-align,
but in iron they prefer to align.
Hmm.
And as I said,
it's a matter of detail.
Not the,
and those are details we're not going to go into.
Hmm.
Okay.
Okay,
so we found out some
things about the one-dimensionalizing model.
And what we found out is that it's never magnetized.
Magnetize,
except at zero temperature.
Magnetized,
magnetized can translate into the statement
that there's this long range memory.
If one spin is up,
all the others will be biased up.
That's called magnetization.
And it's equivalent,
in fact,
to the statement that if you put a tiny,
tiny magnetic field on the system to bias it,
it will cause everything to line up.
We'll see that.
We're going to see that in
a little calculation in a little while.
Okay,
this is a boring system.
Has no phase transition.
It does exactly what you
might have expected it to do.
Correlations fade as you go down.
Down the line.
And the reason is simple.
It's the same reason as in the game of telephone.
There's a statistical probability that you'll make an error.
Once you make an error,
you start over again with a new message.
And you wait until you make another error.
And then you start over again.
And that's the way it goes.
Nevertheless,
there will be some clumping of
a tendency for clumps of a thing.
Just like in the game of telephone.
There will be long stretches of agreement.
Long stretches of agreement.
And then statistically,
on the average,
every so often,
a switch.
But then,
long chain of agreement again.
And then a switch.
Okay.
So,
yeah.
What about high temperatures?
High temperatures?
Then that's like the fidelity being very bad.
Infinite temperature is like the situation
where you just can't hear your neighbor.
You get no information from your neighbor.
So you wind up whatever your
neighbor says making a random guess.
In that case,
let's see.
That's the case.
Beta equals zero.
Tantrum of zero is zero.
So that's a statement that there's
not even correlation between the nearest neighbors.
Okay.
Excuse me.
Boring system.
How do you make it more interesting?
Well,
what's wrong is the dimension is too low.
And a one-dimensional chain,
once you make a mistake,
that next fellow doesn't have any
support telling what the right answer is.
Because he just gets his message from the previous person.
Okay.
What about higher dimensions?
So now instead of playing telephone,
let's play a different game.
Kevin over here starts a message.
And he sends the message correctly to the fellow above.
The fellow in the back of him,
the fellow to the left of him.
And then they each send
the message to all their neighbors.
In particular,
they will wind up sending a message to the
person that Kevin has already sent the message to.
He's going to use his judgment.
And in particular,
as this spreads throughout here,
people are getting messages from different sides.
They're going to be able to make their judgments.
In fact,
everybody will get basically four messages
from all the people around them.
If one of those messages happens to be wrong,
but three of them are right,
what will he do?
He'll do what computer scientists call error correction.
Error correction just means he will take the majority vote.
This works much,
much better.
And in fact,
if the fidelity is good,
the bias of the initial message
will spread throughout and off to infinity.
Same thing happens in the two-dimensionalizing model.
That the bias of any one
spin will bias the rest of the...
And in fact,
we could just say,
putting a little magnetic field on one spin
in two dimensions will bias the whole sample.
It's not completely obvious.
When I thought about it a little bit,
I realized I can't prove that.
I actually can prove it,
but I can't prove it in an easy way.
The way I prove it is by
going through the analysis of the two-dimensionalizing model,
which I know how to do.
But the fact that Ising got it wrong,
it wasn't...
There were worse things in the world.
He got that wrong.
And in fact,
he thought it was wrong in every dimension.
But if you think about it for a minute,
you realize that it's very dimension-dependent.
Why is it dimension-dependent?
Well,
in one dimension,
each person has two neighbors.
That's not very many.
It doesn't have much of a support system.
It gets the message really only from one direction.
How many neighbors does a two-dimensional system have?
Four,
if it's a square lattice.
So that means you're getting messages from four people.
You have a pretty good chance
of getting a message from four people.
You have a pretty good
chance of getting the right answer,
even if the fidelity is not so good,
if you use some weighting procedure,
such as taking the majority.
You do pretty well.
You do much,
much better than if you were
just getting the message from one person.
How about in three dimensions?
You have six neighbors.
How about 10,000 dimensions?
Whatever it is.
20,000 neighbors.
I used to have this friend,
Artie Harris.
Artie Harris was the first black Mr.
America.
Anything you ask him,
anything he'd tell me,
he would say,
a hundred men can't be wrong.
I don't know why he had mine.
But in high dimensions,
it's true.
A hundred neighbors won't be wrong very often.
Fluctuations among large numbers of
variables tend to be very small
in comparison with the net,
you know,
if you have a hundred pluses or minus ones.
Then the average,
the average fluctuation will be much smaller than the net
magnitude of the square root of n kind of statistics.
So you have a much better shot at being able
to propagate the information of one spin throughout the entire lattice,
the higher the dimensionality.
So that leads us to ask the question,
what would the Ising model
be like in very high dimensions?
Some limiting number of dimensions,
10,000 or whatever it is.
And what can we say about it?
Does this correspond to any sort of physical phenomenon?
Higher than three dimensions?
Ising model?
It turns out two is high enough.
It turns out that two behaves like 10,000.
Curious.
Two is high enough.
لا
باتت
To answer the question,
where does n or the number
of dimensions d become large enough
to be able to trust large dimensions is hard.
Three is very large in this game.
But that's as a matter of computation,
having solved it or solved it numerically or whatever,
we know that three is a very large dimension.
So the answer,
which is not obvious,
is that only the one-dimensionalizing
model does not have a transition,
does not have this tendency.
But that's not something that could have predicted easily.
What could have predicted easily,
not too hard,
and we're going to do it tonight,
is that in sufficiently high dimensions,
there's an awfully good argument
to say that there's a transition.
At high temperatures,
everything.
Everything's random.
And as you lower the temperatures,
everybody wants to line up.
And that line up propagates
throughout the system to infinity.
Okay.
Let's,
the trick that I'm going to use,
there are many tricks to do this with.
I'm going to use something called mean field approximation.
I'll tell you what it is.
Each site is surrounded by how many neighbors?
We're going to do d dimensions.
d dimensions.
d stands for dimension.
Each site has,
is surrounded by 2d neighbors.
We're going to imagine d is very large.
And because d is very large,
you can imagine that all
of the neighbors define a field,
let's call it a field,
whose fluctuation is much smaller than its average value.
If you have a large number of variables,
and they're biased,
so that they all add up to something of order,
the number of variables,
the fluctuations are random.
that will typically be much smaller than the bias.
Okay,
so that's what we're
going to do.
Let's focus on that spin.
And all the others we're going to make an
approximation about.
Let's focus on this spin and write its energy,
just the
energy of this one spin.
The energy of this one
spin is minus J times sigma
times the sum of the neighboring spins all around it.
Okay,
so this is the sum of
the neighboring spins,
sum of the neighbors in the IGHBOR.
Now let's
suppose that there is a bit of bias.
Okay,
so let's suppose that there is a bit of bias.
And that the average of the spins is not zero.
Of course,
we're going to check that.
That's what we're going to try to check.
Let's suppose that the average of the...
I'm going to write a formula.
The formula would allow the spin to be zero too,
but
let's suppose throughout this lattice that
the spin has an average called sigma.
Maybe I can make it simpler.
Let's call it sigma bar.
The average spin...
And we don't know what the average spin is.
It might be zero,
it might be plus,
it might be minus.
We don't know what it is.
But I'm going to replace the sum over
neighbors here by simply twice D times the average.
Now that's a pretty good approximation
if the number of neighbors is large.
And the larger the number of neighbors,
the better the approximation.
Large numbers,
as a typical rule,
we're allowed to average,
and the fluctuations are small.
So we can replace this by minus J,
2D because there are 2D neighbors,
minus 2DJ.
And not sigma times its neighbors,
but the particular spin at
this point times the average spin.
So that's the energy of one particular spin sitting in
the bath or in the field of all the others.
This is called mean field approximation.
Mean not being in the sense of nasty,
but mean in the sense of average.
And field now being the field experienced by
one spin in the field of all the others.
So this is the energy
of this particular spin over here.
And now what we can do with it
is do the partition function of that one spin.
Okay.
In fact,
we don't even need to do the partition function.
We know how to do the partition function.
It's exactly the same calculation we did over here,
except instead of writing J,
we will write 2D times J.
Exactly the same calculation as here.
Except every place we saw J in the upper calculation,
we will have 2D times J.
So I can immediately write
down what the average spin is.
I can immediately write down
that the average of this spin,
this one over here,
let's call it sigma double bar for a minute.
The double bar indicates that I'm talking about this one.
It's average spin is just going to be tanh.
Now it's not going to be beta J.
It's going to be beta
times 2D J times sigma bar.
What did I say?
Did I say every place that we saw J,
we should stick 2D J?
No.
Every place we see J,
we should stick this whole thing.
2D J.
2D J times sigma bar.
This spin over here is moving
in the background of all these others,
and the others all constitute a constant
field that we just called sigma bar.
So the answer is going to be the average of
this spin is hyperbolic tangent of 2D J sigma bar.
Beta.
Beta,
thank you.
2 beta D J sigma bar.
Let me write it over again.
Let's go to this blackboard over
here and write it nice and clear.
Sigma double bar,
the average of this particular spin,
is going to be hyperbolic
tangent of 2 beta D J.
Time sigma bar.
Sigma double bar.
Now,
this mean field approximation is
also sometimes called self-consistent field approximation.
Why self-consistent?
Well,
self-consistent because,
hopefully self-consistent,
because this spin over here is
no different than all the others.
It's just one of the many spins in the system.
And if all of these have
an average equal to sigma bar,
the physical intuition would require that you would say
that the one over here also has the same spin,
same average.
That's got to do with translation invariance.
It's got to do with that every one is really
the same as every other one for a big sample.
And so,
the self-consistent field theory,
is to say that sigma bar,
sigma double bar is the same as sigma bar.
We have an equation.
We now have an equation for what sigma bar is.
It's an equation.
It tells us what,
well,
it could tell us what sigma bar is.
It's just a simple proportionality.
I mean,
you're saying sigma bar is proportional to itself?
No,
you're saying sigma bar is proportional.
Inside the argument.
Yeah,
yeah,
yeah.
It's inside the argument.
I put the bracket.
I put it around here to
indicate that this was a constant.
Okay?
It's a constant with
proportional to the inverse temperature.
But yes,
but this is,
yes,
this is inside the bracket.
Sigma bar is inside the bracket.
So this is an implicit equation for sigma bar.
We want to solve it.
Does that mean high temperature?
This is for all,
this equation would apply to all temperatures.
When the variable is equal.
It's almost equal to the tangent.
Doesn't that mean very small variable?
One solution.
No.
Tangents can go anywhere from zero to one.
Tangents can go,
actually,
tangents can go anywhere from minus one to one.
Okay.
So the question is how do we solve this?
And how do we get an intuition?
Question?
Yeah.
So before,
I would have expected you to have written angle.
Okay.
So I would have expected you to
have written angle brackets sigma equal tang.
Yeah.
Is the single bar the same as?
I just didn't feel like writing angle brackets.
Okay.
You didn't hear me when I said it.
I'm sorry.
No.
Yeah.
I decided to use the bar
notation instead of the bracket notation.
Another question.
I'm a little confused about your D.
I can see how you could have three or four,
but if you talk about greater than four,
are you talking about nearest neighbor,
next nearest neighbor?
No,
nearest neighbor.
These are all nearest neighbors?
Yeah.
How many nearest neighbors does
the lattice in D dimensions have?
In one dimension,
two.
In two dimensions,
four.
In three dimensions,
six.
How many in four dimensions?
Eight.
If you included next nearest neighbors.
So you're just assuming D is
the bar in the dimension of space?
Yeah.
Would that be equivalent to getting a higher dimension?
Okay.
So you're just assuming D is
the bar in the dimension of space?
Yeah.
Yes.
Next nearest neighbors would go in the same
direction as going and making a higher dimension.
Absolutely.
But you'd have a little scale factor there,
wouldn't you?
Hmm?
Wouldn't you have a scale factor for
next nearest neighbor and next next nearest neighbor?
Don't you have some geology?
Yeah,
sure.
Sure.
So we picked a particular situation and
study it as a function of dimension.
We could study it as a function
of the nature of second nearest neighbor couplings,
third nearest neighbor couplings.
We could do all these things.
This is just one way of making
a spin have a lot of nearest neighbors.
The physics of high dimensions is
not something we realize in the laboratory.
We do this all the time.
We want to prove something about a system.
It's a little too hard.
We can't get our hands on it.
But we can go to some limit.
Where it becomes much easier.
We prove it in the limit.
We haven't proved it for the physical case of interest.
But at least we can prove that somewhere between,
in this case,
one dimension and a hundred thousand dimensions,
a certain new kind of behavior
happens that wasn't present in one dimension.
Once we see how that works,
we can then ask where does the change happen.
And in this case it happens between one and two.
Okay.
But this is a nice simple example where you can see
what happens physically without having to solve a difficult mathematical problem.
When D is very large.
Okay.
So let's try to solve this equation.
The first thing to do is to change variables.
I know you hate to change variables.
But there's a good reason.
Tanch of a complicated thing.
I don't want a complicated thing in tanch.
That's a nuisance.
So I'm going to say 2 beta dj.
This is a number.
2 beta dj.
They're all numbers for our purposes right now.
This is just a number.
I'm going to change variables so that 2
beta dj times sigma bar is itself a variable.
And I'm going to call it y.
Why?
Because.
Tanch.
On the left side.
What about the right side?
The right side is just
y divided by 2 beta dj.
Okay.
Now to solve this equation I'm just going
to graph both sides and see where they intersect.
Okay.
The crudest way to solve an equation is to draw
a graph of both sides and see where they intersect.
This is y.
This,
the vertical axis is just tanch.
Tanch of y.
Okay.
And here's the tanch function.
Now the vertical axis is just tanch.
So the left hand side is
just a linear function of y.
Everything else in here,
let's,
instead of calling this beta,
let's take 1 over it and
put the temperature in the numerator.
It's the temperature.
Okay.
So let's plot the right,
the left hand side here
for different values of the temperature.
Let's use another color and plot
it for different values of the temperature.
First of all.
Let's go to very high temperature.
At very high temperature this is a very steep function.
Of course d is a large number.
So how big large temperature is may depend on d.
But eventually you get to a large enough
temperature that the slope of this side is large.
So we go to some very
large temperature and the slope is high.
And there's no intersection except
the intersection at y equals 0.
The answer,
the only possible answer to the self-consistent
field theory is that y equals 0.
But what is y?
Y is proportional to the average of sigma.
So we learn first of all that at very
high temperature that the average of sigma must be 0.
As expected.
That's not too surprising.
Okay.
But now let's start lowering the temperature.
As you lower the temperature.
The slope of this curve decreases.
There is a point where the
slope is actually equal to 1.
And the red line here is tangent to the tanch.
Tangent to the tanch.
What a lovely idea.
It's tangent to the tanch here.
Where does that happen?
That happens when the slope.
That happens when the temperature.
Let's write it down.
When the temperature.
Over twice dj is equal to 1.
That's when the slope.
Or when the temperature is twice dj.
Something happens.
Temperature is equal to twice dj.
When you go beyond that.
There's now some new solutions.
Soon as you get past 1.
You.
Could be over here.
Just as this line rotates.
Soon as it gets past slope 1.
There's now solutions along here.
There's also a solution over here.
And down here.
But let's assume that j is positive.
Just to be clear.
Let's assume j is positive.
So we're only interested in the right hand side here.
Now there are new solutions.
And for the new solutions.
Y is not equal to 0.
And therefore.
The average of sigma is not equal to 0.
In other words.
The system has an overall global average of spin.
Pointing.
All in the same direction.
Ah.
So.
The average of sigma is 0.
And that's the phenomenon of magnetization.
What happens here is called a phase transition.
Beyond that point.
There's a net magnetization.
There's an average magnetization.
Average field.
That just permeates the whole system forever.
Now wait.
Wait a minute.
You say hold on.
What about this solution?
How do I know that the right
solution wasn't the one at the origin?
For any value of the constants.
The red curve.
Does intersect the black curve at the origin.
So how do I know which one is right?
How do I know which one is right?
Well we're going to do a little calculation.
I don't think we'll do it tonight.
Maybe next time.
We're going to add to this problem.
A teeny little magnetic field.
That biases the system.
And we're going to discover.
That the teeniest little magnetic field.
Will tell us.
That the smallest little magnetic field.
That we should be on this branch.
On this branch of the solution.
And not here.
But we can see it another way.
Let's go to zero temperature.
Zero temperature is way out here.
And we know what to expect at zero temperature.
At zero temperature we expect alignment.
We expect everybody to align.
And so we expect these things
to lock into a parallel configuration.
It's way out here.
Everybody aligned.
And as you lower the temperature.
You slide in along this line.
Until you get to the transition point here.
And beyond the transition.
Lower temperature than the transition point.
The only solution is at the origin.
So that's the nature of a phase transition.
Which we'll talk about a little more.
But I think I won't try to do it tonight.
Next time we will put.
Actually it's pretty easy.
It's pretty easy from this point.
To put a little magnetic field in.
Is everybody up to a little magnetic field?
Ask a quick question.
What happens if you put D equal one?
Why does it stop working?
It's just too low.
The only guarantee is that
it's sufficiently high dimension it works.
We know Icing doesn't work for one.
And I thought there is a mathematical beautiful.
Something happens when you make D equal one.
Something blows up.
It does.
I'll show you what it is.
I'm going to think.
Yeah.
Let's go to absolute zero temperature first.
Absolute zero temperature everybody wants to align.
Now let's imagine writing the partition function.
As a sum of all the configurations.
How can we enumerate the configurations.
Starting with this configuration.
We can enumerate it by the
number of spins that are flipped.
Relative to this configuration.
So we can start with the graph.
In writing the partition function.
We would start with this configuration.
E to the minus beta
times the energy of this configuration.
At low temperatures.
Starting at low temperatures.
This would be the dominant configuration.
Then we raise the temperature a little tiny bit.
And some new configurations start to become important.
For example.
One spin flipped.
Let's flip one spin.
In fact.
Let's do the same thing over here.
Do the same thing over here in two dimensions.
Here we have plus plus plus plus plus plus etc.
As our starting point.
Everybody is pointing in the same direction.
Now let's ask what the next state is.
Next in energy.
This is the lowest energy state.
The energy is stored in the bonds.
That's sigma dot sigma.
Which is the energy of a pair of neighbors.
What happens if you flip one spin.
Instead of being plus.
Let's make this one negative.
How much energy do we get?
How many bonds have we broken?
A broken bond means that instead of having parallel.
We have anti-parallel.
How many bonds have you broken?
Four.
Right.
And.
Um.
Right.
And.
How many places are there that you can do that?
Basically.
On each side.
Each side.
The number of places you can do that.
Is the total number of sites.
Okay.
So that means there's a number of configurations.
That you can add in.
With one.
With four extra units of energy.
Now supposing you want to.
Break.
Or we want to flip two spins.
The next configuration.
What's the next configuration?
We flip two spins.
When you flip two spins.
What's the energy of that configuration?
Can you tell?
How many broken bonds are there?
Three.
Okay.
Let's see which bonds are broken.
The minus minus bond is not broken.
They're parallel.
Okay.
This one's broken.
that one's broken,
this one's broken,
and this one's broken.
One,
two,
three,
four,
five,
six.
So I've increased the energy by six units of
each broken bond cost a certain amount of energy.
And I've now increased the energy by six broken bonds.
Okay?
What would have happened if I would
have put the minus sign way out here,
far away?
Then I get eight.
Okay?
So each time I increase the number of flipped spins,
it costs me something.
In the Boltzmann factor,
e to the minus beta times the energy,
the energy goes up.
Each time I flip another spin,
Okay,
now let's compare that with a one-dimensional case.
How much energy does it cost to flip?
One spin.
How many bonds get broken?
Two,
right?
How about to flip two spins?
Hmm?
If they're adjacent,
if they're adjacent,
it's still just two.
How about three spins?
Hmm?
You can flip any number of them.
And still only cost two units of energy.
So...
Hmm?
But you picked them adjacent.
Yes,
I picked them adjacent.
That means there's a lot of
configurations all with the same energy.
Much,
much more here.
Here,
in this case,
the number of configurations with four extra units of energy
would be just proportional to the number of sites.
How about here?
The number of configurations with two extra units of energy,
that's proportional to the square of the number of sites.
It's proportional to the square of the number of sites
because you can pick any two bonds
and flip all the spins in between them.
So there's just a lot of configurations
where a lot of spins are flipped.
That's why it's unstable with respect
to flipping lots and lots of spins.
And as soon as the temperature is turned on,
it costs very little energy to
flip whole big loads of them.
Whereas here,
the flip one costs you some energy.
Okay,
that's the same as air.
But the flip two costs you more energy than one.
That's the basic mathematical thing that's going on.
And...
If you just simply look at this equation
that you got from this mean field thing,
you don't see any difference between
d equals one and d equals two,
is it?
Except in the factor of d there.
Except for what?
Well,
you see the difference in the coefficient here.
But I mean,
you still have the space transition phenomenon.
Yeah.
But does that mean...
No,
no,
exactly.
You don't see the difference
between one and two in the...
That's right.
But isn't it incorrect that the mean field...
Why are you confused?
This only made sense if d was large.
Over here it does,
but I'm trying to relate it back to this.
No,
the formula only makes sense if d is large.
Formula only makes sense...
The whole physics,
the whole argument only makes sense.
So how do you turn on a little magnetic field?
What's that?
How do you turn on a little magnetic field?
Alright,
so...
Now let's turn on a tiny magnetic field.
To do that,
where's our energy function?
Here's our energy function over here.
I'm still concentrating on one spin.
But now,
in addition,
we imagine the whole system
has an external magnetic field.
That means that each spin has an extra energy,
not related to its neighbors,
but just whether it's up or down.
Let's call the magnetic field B...
times sigma.
With B times sigma,
it's favoring down.
If B is positive,
But we're going to imagine
eventually that B is very small.
This is the extra energy,
not related to its neighbors,
and each one of them,
each one of them,
each of the spins has this extra term here.
Okay.
And that's the whole difference.
The whole difference is,
instead of tanh being tanh of 2dj sigma bar,
it's going to be tanh
of 2dj sigma bar plus B.
Notice,
sigma...
Sigma factors out.
Sigma...
Put some brackets around here.
It's exactly the same problem,
except we've replaced 2dj...
sigma bar,
sigma bar being a number.
We've replaced it by adding a B.
Okay.
What that does...
is it adds to the variable Y...
it adds...
plus B...
times beta,
I believe.
We want E times...
Which is the sign?
Which sign do I want?
I think I want a favor...
I guess I want a favor upspin,
so let's put a minus there.
Let's put a minus that favors upspin...
Yeah,
okay.
This favors upspin.
Then I guess...
I guess it looks like this.
Yeah.
So this is a new equation.
New equation.
Let's compare it with the old one.
Draw the picture.
We're just going to plot again the right hand...
Does everybody see what I did?
Yeah,
we just added a constant to the argument here.
That's all.
It's very simple.
Okay,
what does that do to the tanh function?
Don't you have to add the...
B on the...
left hand side too?
A what?
Okay,
that...
Doesn't that shoot the left hand side?
No.
Why?
No,
the left hand side...
No.
The left hand side was
the calculation of the average spin
in the background field.
Here's the background field now.
We calculate the average spin in that background field.
We call it...
Well,
it should be tanh 2 beta dj
sigma bar plus...
Exactly right.
What we did was we took this new energy function,
calculated the average of sigma,
but we do it exactly the way we did before.
The thing inside this blue
bracket is just a number again.
It is just a number.
So we calculate the average spin given
this expression for the energy,
and then we set that equal to the average.
We do the calculation and we get this number here.
Tanh y plus beta b.
That's gotten by saying the spin over here
feels its neighbors...
You're saying when you define y,
it has to be equal to...
Um...
The definition of y hasn't changed.
Sigma over 2b...
Oh,
yes,
yes.
Plus beta b.
Right there,
that's it.
y is still the same as it was before.
I have not changed the definition of y.
It's still 2b dj sigma bar.
So this is tanh of y plus beta b.
But that affects the left hand side too.
No!
It doesn't affect the left hand side.
The left hand side...
You're still finding y to be
the same thing you did before.
Yep.
y is exactly the same thing as it was before,
and it is the average spin.
We calculated the average spin
and set it equal to the average spin.
On the right hand side,
we did
a statistical mechanics calculation of the average spin,
assuming that the average spin had a certain value.
On the left hand side,
we said,
well,
okay,
then that must be the average spin.
So we're going to shift the curve.
That's why it's called self-consistent approximation.
You're going to shift the curve.
Hmm?
Yeah,
you're going to shift the curve.
All right,
so let's shift the curve.
Let's shift the...
That's exactly right.
We're going to shift the curve.
So let's see.
If beta b is positive,
that shifts the curve backward a little bit.
Okay,
that's the new curve.
And now let's draw the red curve.
The red curves are...
The left side is exactly
the same as it was before.
The right side,
the curve has just been shifted to the left.
By how much?
By beta b.
So this gap here is beta b.
Beta b here.
All right,
we start at the origin.
Same curves.
But now there's no ambiguity
about which solution we should take.
There is no solution at the origin.
No solution at the origin...
...anymore.
Only these points over here.
For positive j.
Let's say for positive j.
What happens at infinite temperature,
though?
At infinite temperature...
Okay,
so...
Let's see what happens at infinite temperature.
At infinite temperature,
this gets very close to vertical,
right?
This gets...
Very close to horizontal.
No,
no,
no.
Zero temperature is close to horizontal.
Yeah.
Infinite temperature is...
So here's our answer.
Here's where our intersection is,
right over here.
And at that point,
y is equal to zero.
But beta b will move to the right.
It will shrink.
Beta b goes to zero.
Beta b does go to...
No.
Yeah,
zero.
No,
no.
We're going to zero temperature?
Sorry,
we're going to large temperature or small temperature?
Beta goes to zero,
and the curve shifts back to where it used to.
Yeah.
Doesn't matter.
No,
no.
What do you want to do?
You want to go to large temperature or low temperature?
Very large.
Very large temperature.
Okay,
so beta then goes to zero.
Yes,
the curve shrinks back.
Because the area is the only function of the temperature.
Yeah.
Because if you vary the temperature,
you have to shift your tan function.
Yes,
yes,
yes.
Right.
So that means that even at very large temperature,
even among these...
You see what's going to happen?
You know,
you're right.
What's going to happen is this point
is going to shrink down to here.
It's going to move to here,
and
no more magnetic arrangement at infinite temperature
no you have certainly not at infinite temperature
at infinite temperature it's random
so the solution
the curve looks like this
and the solution is down near here
as you let beta get smaller and smaller
you find no magnetization
as you should for very very large temperature
alright
but now as you move
away from zero or infinite temperature
you see the only solutions lie on here
no matter how small
let's go to small temperature now
small temperature you move this way
back
okay so you're certainly on here
and even as you go to higher and higher temperatures
you stay on this curve
you stay on this branch of the curve
although the whole thing shrinks down to here
there's no question
of being stuck at this point for all temperatures
so randomly
temperature which is not infinite
there's only the solution up here
so no matter how small you make
the temperature as long as it's finite
sorry no matter
no matter how large you make the temperature
as long as
large or small
the only solution is up here
is it clear that as your temperature gets very small
so you're moving out along the curve
yeah
but the curve is moving
to the left very fast also
not very fast
it only can get to here
that's as far as it can get
no no no it's going to the left faster
oh is it letting the temperature go to zero yeah
yeah okay
so is it clear that your intersection is
going to be getting closer and closer to 0?
a height of 1?
Yeah.
Why?
Because this curve just moves.
I know.
But it just moves.
This horizontal line here just dominates everything.
Well,
that line is horizontal.
It's going to horizontal.
The question is...
I know.
But if you take a curve that goes
to horizontal here and you shift it a lot,
it's very close
to horizontal.
The extent of...
You got some kind of
limit thing you have to prove.
No.
No,
no.
It's the extent of...
I just understood this.
It's an add infinity.
The slope of the...
You're not add infinity.
You go towards infinity.
You just...
It's...
I'm just saying the slope of the line is...
The slope of the line,
the Y line,
is going down.
Okay?
It's going towards 0,
so it's going to intersect 1 at a long distance...
No.
It's not going to intersect.
The question is where does it intersect that curve,
not where does it intersect...
That curve is always just bounded by 1.
Also,
the slope at the place where it crosses 0,
the hyperbolic tangent,
it's getting
smaller and smaller,
so it's pushing out this way also.
Yeah.
Two things are happening.
The curve...
I just think that there's a little
bit more that has to be shown.
Yeah.
And you got a curve that's going up towards 1,
and if you move that curve...
If I bring this to
my car mechanic and I say,
Joe,
what is this going to do?
My car mechanic will tell me
every single time what it does.
Why?
Because he knows,
goddammit,
how cars work,
and this is enough for him.
Come on.
What are you,
kidding me?
Let me put it this way.
At some point,
at every point along that curve,
you're going to have a curve that's going
to be at some distance epsilon from y equals 1,
right?
Yeah.
And so if you keep
moving that thing over fast enough,
even though the curve is intersecting
further out...
Yeah,
but the curve is moving this way.
Right,
right,
right.
It's moving this way,
so all of it,
both things are going in the same direction.
Okay,
yeah.
Both things are going in the same direction,
right?
Yeah.
Okay.
All right.
Well,
thank you.
So we see just adding the tiniest little
bit of magnetic field will leave only the solution
up here,
the magnetized solution.
Yeah?
The external field is still present,
right?
Which?
External field.
Yes,
but the external field can be
made as small as you like.
Right,
but it's still present,
so the magnet will still be there.
Yes.
Yes,
but for arbitrarily...
Look,
think about it this way.
For arbitrarily small magnetic field,
which means bringing this intercept here to be arbitrarily
small,
tiny,
tiny magnetic field,
much smaller than the magnetic field of the Earth,
you
still have only the solution up here for fixed temperature.
Fixed temperature means for fixed slope here.
You let the magnetic field go to zero,
and you'll be on this curve.
Yeah,
but the magnet still have an orientation then.
Right.
This is an instability.
The tiniest,
tiniest magnetic field,
the tiniest,
doesn't matter how small it is,
it
will still bias it up to here.
That's called spontaneous symmetry,
right?
Magnetic field,
which is far too small to measure.
In fact,
if you look at the upper curve,
which is without the magnetic field...
Yeah.
And you assume the center red point,
the zero,
the origin,
making an infinitesimal
move to the left,
you see that the curve
will intersect infinitesimally up on the...
Here?
Yeah.
Right.
And that shows that there is a bias immediately.
No,
no.
That proves your point.
Even if it's just shifted infinitesimally to the left,
immediately it cuts the y-axis.
The point is that this solution is unstable.
Yeah.
But is it possible?
It's possible,
but it's unstable.
Okay.
You add the tiniest magnetic field...
Yeah,
now I understand.
...and we'll flip to...
Yeah.
I have a suggestion.
If we absorb the d-beta into
the y so that we're comparing tanning,
hyperbolic
tangent of y...
Yeah.
...to a left side that
has all the betas of expression...
Mm-hmm.
...then that left side becomes a
set of lines that intercept y,
have a y-intercept
of minus b.
So basically the graph...
These lines will intersect to the right,
then.
Yeah.
Well,
if we look at the graph on the top floor...
Mm-hmm.
Here?
Yeah.
Keep the hyperbolic tangent in the same place,
and then move all the red lines down by the...
Right.
Yeah,
that's what I said.
Yes.
That's what I said.
That's right.
Move a little to the left.
Then you'll only have the one intersecting...
Then we have only one dependence on beta.
You want to keep the hyperbolic tangent fixed,
right?
Yes.
Shift it a little to the left.
Right.
So which way does it shift?
Left.
All the red lines shift down.
Right.
No,
no.
It doesn't shift anywhere.
Mm-hmm.
The hyperbolic tangent stays...
And the red lines...
All the red lines shift down by b.
Yeah,
it shifts down,
which means it shifts to the right.
Yeah.
There you go.
So it's the same thing.
It doesn't matter which way you do it.
But it's clear that there's no way of
orienting that line so that it intersects the tangent
at two points.
Yeah.
Right.
So that's the argument.
The argument is that the solution where all
the spins are equally likely to be up and
down is unstable.
And what that solution is,
is it's sort of 50-50
probability of everybody being up and
everybody being down.
The whole world being filled with plus spins,
slightly plus the whole world being with minus
spins.
So it's a very good solution.
That has an average of zero.
But if you turn on the tiniest magnetic field,
the difference of energies will be enormous.
Why?
Because you have a billion light
years worth of spins all pointing up,
and you put in a
tiny little stray magnetic field,
the energy of up will be much lower than down,
just because
you have this great,
great big number of spins.
So the solution over here
is just exactly what I said.
It's all,
basically all spins pointing up,
or not all of them,
but on the average,
everything
pointing up.
Equal probability with average everything pointing down.
But that's an unstable situation.
Just a tiny perturbation in
the magnetic field will bias it.
And of course,
that's what really happens with a magnet,
right?
I mean,
you could imagine.
Right.
You could imagine that you
have a state of a ferromagnet,
a real magnet,
which has equal
probability of pointing everywheres.
And then you bring it
into the field of the Earth,
a tiny magnet that's not that small.
But you bring it into the field of the Earth,
and pretty quickly that magnet knows that
the Earth's magnetic field is there,
and it orients itself in that direction.
So this configuration was very,
very,
very strict.
The magnetic field is in a state where
it's equally likely to be in every direction.
That's unstable.
In just a small,
stray field will,
and the stronger the magnet,
the more it's unstable.
The stronger or the bigger the magnet,
either way,
the stronger or the bigger the magnet,
the more unstable it is.
So what causes the Earth to flip its magnetic field?
It's a question I don't know.
Does anybody know?
What's the question?
Why does the Earth's magnetic field flip?
I think somebody thinks.
I'm not sure.
I don't know.
I think the core of
the current flips direction over time.
Of course the current does,
but why?
Why is the iron core going in one direction,
generating current,
and it flips the other way around?
Why does it flip?
There's some instability.
I don't know why.
I don't know why,
other than to say there's a symmetry.
It could be going either way.
But why it flips,
I don't know.
It's very high temperature,
right?
The center of the Earth?
Yeah.
Pretty high.
That may have something to do with it.
ông日:「我走。」
I don't know why.
Somebody look it up.
I'm not sure anybody knows why.
Find any of you?
It may be because there's a time lag
because the Earth's field comes from,
I believe,
the motion of the core.
So there may be a time
lag between the field and the motion.
Why would that make a flip?
Well,
a time lag could generate instability.
I don't know how.
No,
it's some instability,
clearly.
Yeah.
It's some instability,
and I don't know why.
If somebody gets a chance to look it up,
or maybe I'll get a chance to look it up.
I don't know.
I know that it flips.
That's all I know.
Okay.
Yeah,
we'll talk a little bit more about magnets,
and then maybe metals.
Maybe metals.
I'm not sure.
Will you know next time what the fall will be?
Yeah.
For more,
please visit
us at stanford.edu.
Thank you.