Stanford University.
Okay, we have ten minutes for schmoozing.
Yes.
You made a comment last time.
Horizons are always hot.
Okay, yes, I hear you.
So in a scenario where you've just got a-
What?
In a horizon of what we call the,
you consider our universe horizon.
烤的烫
Do you mean how hot is
it or how is it hot?
How is it hot?
Like what the mechanism of it being hot?
Exactly the same as in the black hole.
Does that help you?
No.
All right, let's...
In the black hole, I kind of get
the energy of gravity and all this stuff, right?
You feel the weight.
Yeah.
All right.
You know, that's pretty much exactly what I
was going to start the lecture with tonight.
So make sure I start on that.
But I'm going to defer it until 7 because
that was about where I was going to begin.
On the black hole temperature, you said
you lowered the thermometer right near the horizon.
It's hotter.
If you did that experiment where you shot photons...
Yeah.
...at the black hole to build it up...
Yes.
...and you would still measure the same entropy?
Entropy...
Wait, let's be precise.
There's entropy, there's energy, there's temperature.
What are you asking exactly?
Entropy first.
We measure the same entropy because it would
still be the same probability of the photon
either being captured or missing.
After the photon falls into the horizon or onto
the horizon or whatever you want to call it,
the entropy or the hidden information...
Okay.
...is the same as the black hole.
And the information is hidden in the black hole.
The information is hidden in the black hole.
So what's hidden in the black hole?
Hidden information, if you like.
The information that's inaccessible to you
because it's either inside the black hole
or, from your perspective, very, very close to
the horizon and it would take forever for
a photon to get out.
The information that's hidden is one more bit.
So every time you drop a single
photon in, the entropy increases by one unit.
So it's the energy that you're...
Are you...
Like you're seeing a higher frequency photon drop in.
Yes.
...in the black hole?
So that's the energy that you're...
I'm not sure if you can see the energy.
I don't know if you can see the energy.
But every time you drop a single
photon in, the entropy increases by one unit.
So it's the energy that you're...
Are you...
Is it like you're seeing a higher
frequency photon because you're near the horizon?
Yes.
The question about the temperature of horizons...
Well, let me answer it now.
The horizon is always hot.
I'm going to come back to it in a minute.
It's always hot.
It's always hot in the sense that if
you lower the thermometer down, you would always
detect a very, very high temperature as
you get very close to the horizon.
So you can think of it as the horizon
being a place or a surface of extremely high temperature
which is constantly emitting and reabsorbing photons.
They're really quantum fluctuations.
And they're...
They're nothing more than the high
frequency quantum fluctuations that are taking place
in a small volume of space
in a small region of space.
The horizon makes them real in a way which
I'll come to, which we're going to talk about.
Makes them real thermal fluctuations
in a rather interesting way.
But every horizon always has the
property that the temperature, the actual temperature
of a real thermometer lowered down to the horizon...
The actual temperature of a real thermometer
lowered down to the horizon would record a
temperature which would be one divided by
two pi times the distance to the horizon.
The distance to the horizon in the denominator.
Every horizon, whether it's a black hole horizon
or any other kind, always has that property.
You asked me a question now.
I can't remember exactly what it was.
Well, I think when you're near the horizon...
Yeah.
The time...
The time sort of freezes.
Does that mean that the
photon that came in to build...
Yeah.
Let's forget the photon that
came in to build it up.
Let's talk about the photons which are being emitted.
Why when you stand far from
the horizon does the horizon not...
Or does the radiation that hits you...
Why isn't it this very high frequency radiation
that is emitted very close to the horizon?
In other words, you drop a thermometer down.
You discover that the region...
Near the horizon, the so-called near
horizon region is very, very hot.
Why isn't it hot far away?
I can assure you if we created a blank wall
over there or that wall and we heated it up
to some very, very high temperature and let's suppose
it was a very, very big wall and we
heated it up to some high temperature, I don't
think it would make much sense to say that
as we moved away from the wall that
the temperature went down like one hundred percent.
If we moved it down like
one over the distance, it wouldn't.
You would be blinded by high frequency photons
pretty much no matter how far you got from
that wall.
The high frequency photons that came out of
it, the gamma rays, the super gamma rays,
everything else that came out of it would
blind you pretty much no matter how far you
got from this very, very large wall.
Why that doesn't happen with
the horizon of a black hole?
Why when you stand back from it and get
a good deal of distance between you and the
horizon, why don't you get blinded
by these very high frequency photons?
And the answer?
What's the answer?
Redshift.
The redshift is another way of saying that
as the photons propagate away from the horizon,
they lose energy.
And they lose energy for exactly...
Exactly the same reason.
Kinetic energy.
They lose energy for exactly the same reason
that this piece of chalk does when you throw
it up in the air.
It is doing work, or you have to, in order
to raise it, you have to do work against the
gravitational field.
And if you don't do work to keep
it moving with the same velocity, then the velocity
will slow down.
Well, with photons, don't think about velocity.
Velocity is the wrong thing to think about.
Think about energy.
For a non-relativistic piece of chalk,
there's a close relationship between its velocity
and its energy.
But what's really happening is it's losing energy.
For a photon, the relation
between velocity and energy is different.
Namely, the velocity is always the speed
of light, and the energy is the energy.
But it's still true that as the photon
climbs out of the gravitational influence of the
black hole, it loses energy.
So in the transit between the horizon, very
near the horizon where it's very hot, and
far away, the photon loses an amount of
energy such that a distant observer doesn't see the
black hole as being very hot.
He sees it having the Hawking temperature.
And the Hawking temperature decreases with
the mass of the black hole.
Remember what it was?
The Hawking temperature of the black hole.
And you can think of it as the
temperature as seen by somebody looking at the photons
or being exposed to the photons
very far from the black hole.
The temperature, T-Hawking, is equal.
I'll write the precise formula for no particular reason,
but 1 over 8 pi times the mass of
the black hole.
There is an H-bar here, a Planck's constant, and
some numbers of factors of C, which I can
never remember.
C cubed, I can't remember
if it's upstairs or downstairs, but...
H-bar or just plain H, because
the pi is already in the...
I don't remember.
I think it's H-bar.
I think it's actually H-bar.
Right.
8 pi times the mass of the black hole.
So the bigger the black hole, the cooler it is.
Why does it look cooler for a big black hole?
Well, that photon that was created very near
the horizon has a more difficult time getting
away from the big black
hole than a smaller black hole.
In other words, it has to do more work,
it loses more energy in escaping from a big black
hole from the near horizon region than
it does for a small black hole.
So the effect is the temperature, the
effective temperature seen by an observer, for example,
far away decreases with the mass of the black hole.
But if you take this formula, you interpret
it in terms of the energy of typical photons.
In fact, the temperature of black body
radiation, the temperature of thermal radiation, is approximately
the same as the typical energy of any given photon.
So this just says the photons
typically have a temperature of about...
typically have energy 1 over
the mass of the black hole.
And if you then trace that inward toward the
horizon and say, how much energy did the photon
have to have when it started out in order
to escape and have this much energy when it
got out, you'll find the energy is always the same.
It's always about this 1 over 2
pi times the distance from the horizon.
How close can you get to
the horizon in a meaningful sense?
Well, the Planck distance.
The Planck distance sets the
scale for all quantum mechanical distances.
And so you might say then that
these photons originated in a thin layer.
This is the way it behaves.
This is the way the system behaves.
They have a thin layer, perhaps a Planck length
thick, near the horizon or right at the horizon,
and they're not moving.
This is the way they behave.
It's at the horizon and it is
continuously emitting photons and absorbing photons, emitting
and absorbing them.
The energy of the photons, as high
as you can imagine, the Planck energy.
Now, most of those photons don't get out.
Most of those photons don't get out.
What happens to them?
They fall back.
All right?
Here's the horizon of a large black hole.
And if the horizon is
hot, it's continuously emitting photons.
But though some of those photons go radially out, but very,
very few of them, most of them go off at some angle.
The ones that go off at an angle are pretty much
guaranteed to fall back into the horizon of the black hole.
It's only a tiny cone of angles
here that the photon can get out.
And that's the reason that the photons will escape.
So, in fact, the emission of
photons is a very slow process.
It's a slow process because most of them don't come
out at an angle which is appropriate for them to escape.
And most of them simply just fall back
to the horizon, fall back because of gravitation.
The ones that are coming out
can bang into the ones falling in.
And guess what happens?
They collide.
They're very energetic.
They make electron-positron pairs.
They make everything that you can think about.
And they make this thin
layer of very, very hot material.
It's like no material that
we ordinarily encounter in nature.
Much, much hotter.
And the surface of it is continuously emitting photons which
we see as having much, much lower energy than their emission.
That's the mathematical theory.
That's the consequence of
the mathematical theory of horizons.
There's another way to think about it.
Remember, we've drawn pictures of black holes.
The outside of the black hole was out here.
The inside of the black hole was in here.
Somebody a given distance from the black hole
is moving along a trajectory which looks like this.
Now, there are quantum fluctuations that take place.
Without trying to get into the depths of quantum field theory, let's just
use the rough metaphor of quantum fluctuations being closed loops of virtual particles.
So virtual particles are
constantly being created and annihilated.
And an observer far away just sees those particles created.
Doesn't see them, actually.
It all happens too fast.
Here are the lines of constant time.
Way out here is t equals infinity.
Somebody out here, a little fluctuation like
that lasts a tiny amount of time.
They can be detected.
They can be detected by
very high precision quantum electrodynamics.
And the properties of atoms and so forth.
But there are also fluctuations that take place over here.
Now, those fluctuations appear to
be emitted from the horizon.
The horizon is a place very
close to this light cone here.
They appear to be emitted
and fall back into the horizon.
That is exactly what these things are.
They are the quantum fluctuations which take place half
behind the horizon and half in front of the horizon.
And look to somebody on the outside
as something emitted from the horizon and reabsorbed.
Some tiny fraction of them
have enough energy to get out.
And we call that Hawking radiation.
If you were on the outside, would you see
it go from t minus infinity to t plus infinity?
Sorry, again?
It crosses those 45 degree lines.
And they are t equals the lower on the outside.
Yeah, well, okay.
So let's not, yeah.
There's a classical horizon which really looks like this.
But it's always convenient.
And we all do this all the time.
We draw a surface one
Planck length away from that horizon.
This is a surface one
Planck length away from the horizon.
All right.
It's one Planck length from here.
One Planck length here.
It's a surface, if you like, if we wanted to
draw this a different way, we would say here's the horizon.
And one Planck length away, a thin layer.
And the point here, of course, is that the horizon
is not really accurately defined to within a Planck length.
Quantum fluctuations not only of ordinary particles but of gravitation
and the structure of the horizon, they all take place.
So you really should think of the horizon.
The horizon is a sort of slightly thickened thing.
If you think of it thickened like that and a fluctuation
takes place, then this fluctuation doesn't occur at time minus infinity.
It occurs at some time in the remote
past or at some time in the past.
It's emitted out and it falls
back into the horizon over here.
So somebody outside would say, look, I see some photons
that look as though they're not actually in the horizon.
They're in the horizon.
I see some photons that look as though they were emitted from
somewhere that's very close to the horizon with very, very high energy.
They pop out and they fall back in.
That's what the mathematics gives.
And it is the same no matter what the horizon
is, whether the horizon is a cosmic horizon, whether it's a...
Now, for cos...
Oh, I guess...
Are you ready to begin?
Yeah.
We'll have a beer.
Ten after.
Oh, we spent more time on
that than I thought we would.
All right, well then, good.
Let's talk about cosmic horizons in the same vein.
There are many ways to draw the Sitter space.
The Sitter space is the
space which is exponentially expanding.
One way to draw it
is just to draw a triangle.
The time axis, which goes up to infinity.
Draw the blackboard and keep track of the fact in our heads that the
distance between any pair of neighboring coordinate lines here is exponentially increasing with time.
That's one way to draw it.
Another way to draw it is
to squash all of future time.
All of future time...
Down by coordinate transformation.
We did the coordinate transformation last time.
So that future infinity is a horizontal line like that.
Corresponds to t equals infinity.
I think I wrote down the metric for
you in a form which maps t equals infinity...
to a finite place.
I'll just rewrite it for you.
The original metric was the s
squared is equal to minus dt squared.
That's the usual thing.
Plus...
一
to the 2HT dx squared, where again, dx squared
stands for dx squared plus dy squared plus dz squared.
And this e to the 2HT,
that's the exponential expansion of the space.
Why does it come in with a 2?
Because it's really distance squared, right.
Distance between points is increasing like e to the HT.
And so a given dx corresponds to a growing distance which grows as e to
the 2, as e to the HT, and in the metric it's e to the 2HT.
Then we made a transformation.
Just in order, it's a, we
made a transformation of the time variable.
We wrote the time variable t,
I think, oh, what is h?
Right, h is the Hubble constant in this space.
All right.
It's a time variable.
It's also the expansion rate.
We wrote t is equal, I believe, to 1 over h
e minus e to the minus, minus or plus, minus, minus HT.
Sorry, T, capital T. Capital T
goes from minus infinity, is this right?
Minus HT?
Should be right.
Yeah.
Capital T goes from minus infinity deep in the past.
What happens to this thing
when T goes to minus infinity?
It gets big.
e to the minus HT gets big when T
goes to minus infinity, but it gets big in negative.
Okay, so the remote past T equals minus
infinity is also capital T equals minus infinity.
Yeah.
So, in the remote future, when this
T gets very big, that happens when what?
Do I have this right?
I don't have this right.
Excuse me.
Still true.
When this T is large and negative,
this T is also large and negative.
All right.
But now what happens when
this T is large and positive?
When this T is large and positive, then
this gets small and capital T goes to zero.
So T equals infinity is also capital T equals zero.
And this is just a trick.
It's a trick for getting the whole geometry,
or not the whole geometry, but the part we're
interested in, the remote future
in this case, onto the blackboard.
Now, what happens if we rewrite this metric?
It becomes minus infinity plus
x squared, in terms of T.
Let me just remind you, it becomes minus,
sorry, plus minus dt squared plus dx squared,
all times 1 over t squared.
1 over t squared h squared to be exact.
Notice that when T gets very small, the distance
between the two has to be equal to infinity.
Okay?
Yeah.
Okay.
All right.
the distance between points gets very big,
just as it did on this side over here.
This is just a rewriting of this,
and t goes to zero is the remote future.
The nice thing about writing the metric this way
is that in these coordinates,
light rays move on 45-degree angles.
That's very helpful in thinking about this geometry
and asking who can communicate with whom.
Let's get rid of this here.
Why is it that light rays move on 45 degrees
in this metric here?
Well, the rule for light rays
is that the metric should be zero,
that the interval should be zero.
So dt squared minus dt
squared plus dx squared equals zero.
It's the same as dt equals dx, right?
And dt equals dx is just a 45-degree line.
If the light ray moves on 45 degrees,
the light ray moves on 45 degrees.
If the light ray moves in the plane,
it would be 45 degrees in the plane.
If we're moving out of the plane,
it would be 45 degrees out of the plane.
But there's only so much we can visualize
with a two-dimensional blackboard.
Okay, so that's the setup.
That's what space-time in this kind of
inflating, exponentially increasing world looks like.
Here it is.
Here's somebody.
You, me, I don't know.
And in the real world, of course,
people only get to live
for a certain amount of time.
But right now, we're going
to pretend we can live forever.
And so here's the world line of some observer.
And that world line, does it really end?
No, it doesn't really end because
there's an infinite amount of time
between any finite point in here.
But on the blackboard, we draw the,
the observer as just ending at that point over here.
That's the remote future.
What can that observer see?
Well, he looks back and he
sees light rays coming at him
from distant places.
And light rays move on 45 degrees.
I could, I can add one
more dimension to this if I,
I can fake a dimension by doing that.
All right, so he sees light rays coming,
but I can't get, I can't draw another dimension.
That's too many.
We would like x, y, and z,
but at least I can get
x and y on the plane,
on the diagram here.
So this observer looks back,
and as time goes on,
gets to see more and more,
but never gets to see more of the space-time
than is in the backward light cone here.
So in particular,
never gets to see anything out here,
or out here.
At least doesn't get to see
it in any sort of usual sense.
So there's a region,
most of space and time,
almost everything,
is totally inaccessible to this observer.
Now, of course, there may be another observer over here.
And that other observer sees something else.
There's some overlap.
Okay, there's some overlap.
But,
this person gets to see everything in here.
This person gets to see everything over here.
Let's simplify it,
and just study one observer at a time.
For all practical purposes,
his universe,
space-time universe,
is this backward light cone here.
Now, what does he see?
Does he see things,
a world which seems to depend on time?
You would think so.
You might think,
well, everything seems to be exponentially expanding.
But let's just do a very simple exercise now.
Let's consider this distance,
and compare it with this distance,
and this distance,
and this distance.
Basically,
this distance that I've drawn here,
is the distance from the observer to his horizon.
Let's see how that changes with time.
It looks like it's shrinking.
But let's just check that.
Here's the metric.
And let's put this point over here
at t equals minus one.
Let's put this point over here
at t equals minus a half.
This one over here at t equals minus a quarter.
Incidentally, that corresponds to uniform
ticking off of proper time.
Each unit of time,
would correspond to dividing this interval by half.
That's the way this transformation worked.
That's why there's an infinite amount of time in here.
And now let's calculate this distance.
To calculate this distance,
we just look at the metric.
This is the metric.
And so,
these two points are separated
by a spatial distance,
but no time distance.
So these two points
are separated by zero time interval.
That means in this formula here,
there should be an equal sign.
In some ways, there should be an equal sign.
Oh, yeah.
There is no time separation
at all between these two points.
So let's write it in a finite form,
not a differential form.
The square of the distance,
let's call it from a to b.
What is that?
No time separation.
What is the delta x between these two points?
Can you tell?
This is a 45 degree angle.
This distance is capital T.
This distance is also capital T.
In fact, let's not even bother
writing this t equals minus one.
Let it just be t.
This distance here,
the horizontal distance,
is also the same as the vertical distance.
So,
we get zero from here,
but from here we get plus,
and delta x is the same as T,
squared,
but now divided by T squared, h squared.
And what's the answer?
One over h squared.
In other words, the distance from here to here
is just one over h.
That's the actual real physical distance
that you would measure
with measuring devices.
But notice, the answer doesn't depend on T.
The distance between here and here
is exactly the same as
the distance between here and here.
The delta x is smaller,
but the T is also smaller.
So when you write up to here,
the delta x gets shrunk by a factor of two,
but T also gets shrunk by a factor of two.
So the distance of the observer
from the horizon is always the same.
The observer sees a horizon around him,
a sort of sphere,
and that sphere doesn't change with time.
In fact, you might suspect
that if you used coordinates
that were appropriate
to the observer inside one horizon,
you might discover that the metric had no time dependence.
After all, the distance to the horizon
doesn't have any time dependence.
It's always the same.
And in fact, many things don't change with time.
It just looks like they do.
You might expect that maybe there's some way
to rewrite this geometry.
And I'm simply going to tell you the answer.
I'm not going to work it out in detail.
But using coordinates like this,
spatial coordinates,
which are appropriate to the absolute interior
of this horizon region.
There is another way of writing
that's not symmetric,
but it's only good for this region.
It doesn't capture what's going on on the outside,
but captures everything on the inside.
I'm going to show you what it is.
And you look at it for a minute,
and it may look somewhat familiar.
Familiar, but not familiar.
These are coordinates
which are sort of built on the pattern
that I described here.
In other words, they're coordinates
in which the coordinate distance
between here and here is the same
as the coordinate distance between here and here.
This coordinate distance and the new coordinates
will be the same as this,
will be the same as this.
And I'll show you what the metric looks like.
ds squared equals minus dt squared.
That's no surprise.
It's actually proper time.
Actual proper time.
And then the rest of it is plus...
Oh, no, no, no, sorry.
I did it wrong.
Mistake.
I apologize for mistakes,
but the mistakes happen
when I haven't had my cookies yet.
Minus.
What?
Understandable.
Yeah, right.
Low blood sugar.
One minus h squared r squared dt squared
plus one over one minus h squared r squared.
The r squared plus r squared d omega two squared.
Remember what omega two is?
Right.
When you're sitting at the center
and you look around you,
you see an angular sphere around you,
and this is just one way
of not writing out the full spherical metric,
just simplifying it.
Does this look at all familiar?
Yeah.
Yeah, what's it look like?
It does.
Let me just remind you what Schwarzschild looks like.
Exactly the same,
except h there, or h squared,
is replaced by twice mg,
and then it's divided by r.
Everything is exactly the same
if you take the parentheses
and put this in here.
Likewise over here.
It has the same kind of form.
And in fact,
it looks awfully different
to have h squared r squared here,
but the important thing,
what was important?
Where is the horizon?
In the Schwarzschild black,
right.
But the horizon is where this thing
is equal to zero.
That's the place where clocks slow down.
It's the places where distances
are infinitely contracted.
And it's also the place which says,
where is the horizon?
It's also the place which separates
the inside of the black hole
from the outside of the black hole.
You can also write this in the form
r minus 2mg over r.
It doesn't matter how you write it.
The real importance of this term
is the place where it vanishes,
where it equals zero.
That is where the horizon is.
Likewise here.
Same idea.
The place where this thing vanishes,
which is r.
That's r equals one over h.
Where is it?
r equals one over h.
That's the distance to the horizon.
So this is another way
of writing exactly the same geometry,
except something really breaks down
if you try to make r bigger
than one over h.
Something goes berserk here.
You really don't get out past here.
The whole metric gets a little bit silly.
Space turns and turns into time.
Time turns into space.
We don't need to worry about that right now.
You let r go from zero
to one over h.
And this geometry covers
the entire cone there.
Everything that's inside that cone.
And it is everything that can be seen
by an observer.
By a single observer.
Yeah?
Why is it a nature function of time?
Well, because you weren't here
to begin with.
Because we're talking about
an exponentially expanding universe.
Right.
Where the scale factor is e to the ht.
So here's a series of lines
up there.
They're all length one over h.
These?
No.
Up there next to the drawing above.
Oh, here. The horizontal ones.
Yes.
They're all length one over h.
And therefore, they're like the distance
to the horizon here.
From r equals zero to one over h.
Alright.
It takes a little bit of mathematical trickery
to rewrite this metric.
A few coordinate changes.
There's a few transformations of coordinates
that you have to do.
And when you've done those
coordinate transformations,
you'll find that this patch
is called sometimes the causal patch
or the static patch.
And one thing you notice about this metric,
the most interesting thing about it,
or the many interesting things about it,
first of all, it has a horizon.
But second of all,
none of the coefficients here
depend on time.
They depend on r,
but they don't depend on time.
And in that sense, in this form,
the metric is completely time independent.
And it's another way of saying
that what an observer sees around him
just doesn't change with time.
It's static.
It always looks the same.
Distance to the horizon
is always the same.
Whatever the observer does at one time,
if he does the same thing at a later time,
he'll see the same thing.
Now, it is true that
if he takes two particles,
let's ignore any forces between them.
Let's suppose he takes two particles
and lets them go.
What will happen?
We're ignoring any attractive forces.
Space between them expands,
and so they go flying off.
So you say,
well, that doesn't sound time independent.
But the point is,
if he does the same experiment
at a later time,
he will see exactly the same thing.
Take the two particles,
let them go,
and they will slowly accelerate
apart from each other.
Take two particles at a later time,
do exactly the same experiment,
they will slowly accelerate away from each other.
Do those two particles see a redshift?
The other particle redshift?
Yeah. For sure.
Now,
once we get to this point here,
we can kind of see
that a black hole horizon
and a decider space horizon
are very, very close relatives.
The fact that
everything that you can say
about the near horizon region
of the Schwarzschild black hole
is pretty much the same
for the
decider space,
I'm not going to try to prove that.
But the similarity of the metrics
are pretty clear,
and they,
in fact, near the horizon
they're almost identical,
very close to the horizon.
But the whole global picture of things
is quite different.
Whereas a black hole is something
that we stand on the outside of
and look at
and emit Hawking radiation,
the whole picture here
is quite the opposite.
We are on the inside.
The black stuff is on the outside,
the stuff we can't see.
And yes,
there is Hawking radiation
being emitted from the horizon
for the same reason.
It's emitted and absorbed,
emitted and absorbed.
Sometimes a photon gets to us.
But we can also ask the question,
what is the energy of a photon
by the time it gets
from near the horizon to us?
And there,
there is a big redshift factor.
This metric,
just like the Schwarzschild metric,
has a gravitational potential.
This metric also has a gravitational potential.
I'll draw it for you.
As a function of r,
as a function of r,
there's a gravitational potential.
Let's see if we can draw it.
It's upside down.
It looks like this.
The meaning of that
is it takes work
to pull something from the horizon
to the center.
Equivalently,
an object emitted from the center
as it makes its way toward the center
will lose energy,
will lose potential energy.
It has to climb up out of this potential
and will lose energy.
Another way of talking about redshift.
You can work out the redshift
easily enough from the metric.
I'm not going to do it now.
But a photon emitted near the horizon
will lose energy on the way out here
such that the Hawking temperature,
the energy in the horizon
that's being emitted
is of order
Let's see.
What is it?
It's of order 1 over the distance
from the horizon
of order 1 over the distance
in Planck units.
How big is our horizon?
How big is the horizon
our horizon?
Our horizon,
that we think we know about on the
basis of the known expansion properties of the
universe, this distance 1 over h, 1 over
h is about 20 times 10 to the ninth
light years, 20 billion light years. The
redshift of a photon from the horizon
to where we are is by this factor of 1
over 20 times 10 to the ninth. That's a lot.
So the photons that we see coming from
the horizon are of incredible, basically the answer
is that the photons that we see have a
wavelength which is about 10 billion light years. So
those are not very energetic photons.
We are not likely to see them.
Right.
What kind of experiment would we do to
see them? Well, we would do the same kind
of experiment we do with the black hole, except
we do it from the inside. Alice takes her
fishing pole, and at the end of her fishing
pole, instead of a worm, she has a thermometer,
and she casts it out. They've
got a very long line of fishing.
Casts it out. The expansion of the universe
pulls on the thermometer, or tends to be accelerated
out away from her, and she waits 10 billion
years or so. It's not just a fishing line.
It happens to be a coaxial cable or
something that she can read off the temperature. And
she waits 10 billion light years and then
puts a thumb on the spinning reel to stop
it. She doesn't want it to go through the
horizon. So it stops over here, and she waits
until the signal comes through the horizon.
And then she waits until the signal comes
back. That's another 10 billion years. And
she reads off the temperature, and the temperature
she'll read off is high. On the other
hand, if she just sits here with her thermometer,
the temperature that she sees is redshifted, and
it's very, very, very low, far lower than
anything that can be produced in the
laboratory. It's not, in particular, the microwave background
temperature. It has nothing to do
with that. It's the de Sitter temperature.
And it's very, very low. That's the properties of
the world that we live in, as it will be
a couple of hundred billion years from now.
Empty, apart from us sitting at the center,
everything else having passed out through
the horizon. Some amount of stuff gravitationally
bound together might include our galaxy and
a couple of other galaxies that happen to
be not being dragged away with the ambient light.
I don't have any more questions.
So, if we have any questions,
go to the link in the chat.
Thank you very much.
Thank you.
expansion and everything else will be essentially
empty except for this very, very, very feeble
radiation, radiation from the horizon.
It's a sort of grim
prospect, as various people have noted.
The astronomers at that time will be confused.
They won't understand why they're
alone in a very big universe.
In fact, they'll have a very hard
time measuring how big the universe is.
There won't be anything out there to look at.
And the possibility of measuring this radiation,
well, that's not going to happen either.
Yeah?
Yes, Michael.
I think what you said last week
was that from our perspective, things don't exit
past the horizon.
Well, yeah.
Yeah.
Exactly the same as the black hole.
Here's the black hole.
From our perspective.
Yeah.
In a classical analysis, we would see things
getting closer and closer and closer and closer
and closer to the horizon.
You could say exactly the same thing over here.
Let's draw it.
Here's our observer.
Somebody falls through the horizon.
Our observer over here never gets
to see them fall through the horizon.
As time goes on for
our observer here, he looks back.
And as far as he can tell, as time
goes on longer and longer, Bob says, Alice is getting
flattened against the horizon.
So it's exactly the same as the black hole.
Basically, it redshifts and then basically disappears.
Fade away.
So if somebody else is getting pulled
through the exact same spot, what's the secret?
What's the secret?
Just to make it all clear, we're
going to be looking at the horizon Horus.
OK.
Classically, just without worrying
about any quantum mechanics.
OK.
Here is what he sees.
Sees may be the wrong term, since the wavelength
of radiation that they send out gets so long
that they'll never see it.
But here's their mathematical description.
Let's see.
Alright.
Here's the horizon.
And here is...
other one? Jane. You are Jane. Alice
falls towards the horizon and gets squashed.
Jane gets closer and is starting to
get squashed. Alice gets closer. Jane also
gets closer. In other words, a
kind of sedimentary structure forms near the
horizon that just gradually gets closer
and closer and skinnier and skinnier. Now,
that's a classical description. What
actually happens quantum mechanically is
more complicated and involves interaction with the emitted
radiation and so forth, which spreads
them all out over the place and
ionizes them, cooks them, does terrible
things to them. But from a classical
perspective, you would just lose track
of them as they get squashed
closer and closer in there and you'd
lose track of them because the radiation
from them would get more and more
and more redshifted as they get closer and
closer. Okay. But isn't it the case that
the horizons are only hot for things that get
close but don't cross over? If
you pass through, you don't get cooked.
Okay.
Alice has no problem with the
horizon. She sails perfectly happily through. Bob
just loses track of her, but if he
tries to do an experiment which sees what
happens to her, we come back
to this very strange situation, this Heisenberg
microscope situation, where the only way to
do an experiment is to shine some high-
frequency light on Alice. And as Alice
gets closer and closer to the horizon, the
wavelength of that light has to get smaller
and smaller. So the answer, I'm sure, by
now you know, is that the attempt to
look at her will cook her. So—Yes, Kevin?
Simplistically, all the effects of the Horizon at the Black
Hole were caused by That's simply not a fault of
The effects of the horizon of the black hole were caused
by the gravitational well, if you will, of the black hole.
What's the equivalent here?
Well, there is a gravitational... all right, good.
All right, let's do a little exercise.
For any kind of gravitating material, which we usually
call mass, but we could use the word energy,
for any kind of distribution of energy or mass, there is
around it or in its neighborhood or somewhere, there's a gravitational potential.
All right, the gravitational
potential is usually called phi.
Phi is such that its derivative, its gradient, is the gravitational force on
an object, on a unit mass, on a test mass, on a unit mass.
Now, phi satisfies an equation.
On the left-hand side of the equation,
there's something involving phi,
and on the right-hand side of
the equation is the mass density.
This is Newtonian physics.
Let's do Newtonian physics.
What's on the right-hand side?
Let's just say the mass density, which I'll call
rho, and it's a function of position in general.
It might just be a point source at the center.
What's the left-hand side?
I've just written phi, but
of course that's not quite right.
What's the... anybody know the right...
Not the divergence, but close, you're close.
Something called del squared,
which is basically the second derivative
with respect to the distance, r.
d second by dr squared of phi for a
radially symmetric distribution of mass is equal to rho.
This would give us, for example, for a point mass,
it would give us the usual Coulomb,
the usual...
Newtonian potential energy.
Now, vacuum energy is an interesting possible
candidate to put on the right-hand side,
and let's do so.
As my sign write,
is del squared phi minus rho or plus rho?
I can't remember, and I'm not
going to try to figure it out.
It's one or the other.
It's not important.
All right.
What would happen if there were vacuum energy
in addition to the pockets
of ordinary energy that sit there?
Well, you would put a constant on the right-hand side.
What would the constant be?
The constant would be the constant vacuum energy,
sometimes called cosmological constant.
Other times, it's just called h squared.
It's basically proportional to h squared.
In fact, that's where h comes from.
So here's a formula for the gravitational potential
of a space which is filled
with a uniform distribution of mass.
It's the vacuum energy.
Absolutely uniform.
Not only doesn't it change with position,
it doesn't even change with time.
What's the solution of this equation?
Nope.
Easier than that.
All right.
So what's the solution?
It's phi equals plus or minus.
We'll figure out the sign later.
h squared r squared.
Let's differentiate.
Well, maybe there's a factor of two.
What's the first derivative of this with respect to r?
h squared r.
What's the second derivative?
h squared.
That's this.
So look at that.
A uniform, absolutely uniform distribution of energy.
And there should be a minus sign here.
Yeah, there should be a minus
sign here if we do it right.
So what do we see?
We see that there's a potential, a gravitational potential.
You can think of it as being
due to this uniform distribution of energy
distributed all over space.
And what does it look like?
It looks like this.
It's a gravitational potential.
And it's going to be given by this.
It's going to be a gravitational potential.
It's going to be given by that.
And this is going to be the moment of
the energy that's going to be given by this.
Okay?
So what does this mean?
This means?
Okay, let's follow it a little bit.
That's the potential energy that I, at
the center of my geometry, I'm special.
I'm at the center of my geometry.
You may think you're special and you're at the
center of your geometry and that's fine with me.
But I know that I'm special and
I'm at the center of my geometry.
and I'm at the center of my geometry.
I make measurements.
I make measurements on test masses,
and I find they move in various ways.
And I find they move as
if they were in a potential
which went like this.
Incidentally, what does the force do to this potential?
No?
The force is the derivative of the potential.
All right?
So the derivative of the potential is just r.
So this is a force which increases.
It's repulsive.
That's the minus.
It pushes you down.
And the force increases linearly with distance.
So any two objects, if you
just start them out at rest,
they will start to accelerate away from each other.
And they'll eventually start picking up some speed.
How long does it take?
Does it pick up any appreciable speed?
That depends on h.
Basically, 10 billion years for it
to pick up any significant speed.
But if you wait 10 billion years, it
will be moving like a rocket.
OK.
So no, not like a rocket.
Like a photon, or close to a photon.
All right, so what does all this mean?
Supposing you start an object right up at the top,
literally at the top, what happens to it?
It stays still.
It stays there, right?
It's at a point of unstable equilibrium.
Well, that's another way of saying that me,
in my own frame of reference, if I
take an object which is located right where I am,
it'll stay there.
You don't have to be too sophisticated about it.
I am my own object, and
I don't move away from myself.
Well, not the, you know, sometimes, but not usually.
OK.
Now, what happens if I take an
object a little bit away from me?
And again, we are ignoring all other forces.
We can take into account the other forces we're ignoring.
So I start somebody out at
rest 100 meters away from me.
That's over here.
What happens to them?
They start moving away.
And in fact, in this kind of potential,
they will move with an accelerated motion that
will be, if we take into account relativity,
and everything, it'll be this exponential expansion.
So that's just a statement
that the space in between things
is expanding exponentially.
So this kind of picture
is a kind of Newtonian description
of the same physics as the exponential expansion
of the universe.
It is as though there was, number one,
a uniform distribution of matter around me,
and number two, a gravitational potential energy which
is pushing everything away.
Yeah?
Well, we do have to consider the other forces.
We certainly do.
The other forces, even a person, the islands
will disintegrate.
Yeah.
Right.
So if I took the, let's take the potential energy
between you and me, only gravity for simplicity.
There's another contribution.
I'm standing at the center, and I'm thinking about you.
And I see that you have an ordinary gravitational Newtonian
potential energy relative.
potential energy relative to me in addition to this.
All right.
First of all, what would the ordinary gravitational
potential energy look like?
It would look like that.
Pulling me toward the center, pulling you toward my center
would look like that.
One over r, one over r potential.
All right.
If I add that to this,
it would look something like that.
All right.
So if I'm close enough, if I'm close enough,
then I get pulled, you get pulled toward me.
If I'm right at this distance,
or you're right at this distance,
then you're in a kind of unstable equilibrium.
But if you're slightly farther
away than the top of this,
then you get pushed away.
So this is exactly the
situation that the Andromeda Galaxy appears
to be in here somewhere.
It's falling toward us.
A few galaxies away, they're accelerating out away from us.
Yeah.
So this is a model just
at the base in the expansion space,
and it acts as if it has this gravitational effect.
Yes.
Then we did talk in describing it,
we also talked about the vacuum energy,
which is a quantum effect,
has nothing to do with the,
and it behaves the same.
And so they both actually are there.
Which are both?
No, no, no, no, no, no.
There's one thing.
You can call it vacuum energy,
you can call it cosmological constant,
there's only one thing.
And if you want to mimic
it or model it in Newtonian physics,
you model it by a uniform mass distribution.
Right.
But it's one thing, it's not two.
Vacuum energy, cosmological constant, dark energy,
all the same thing.
And they all correspond, as I said,
if you want to model it in a Newtonian context,
you simply imagine a uniform, right.
But on the other hand,
we're saying this is also a
consequence of the simple expansion space
and the relativistic.
Well, you can either say it's a
consequence of it or a cause of it.
I mean, they go together.
Right.
Well, it's a little bit of expansion.
Say it again.
Pardon the time.
Pardon me.
I'll do it.
It seems that the same
phenomenon has a completely classical description
and a completely quantum description.
Well, the origin of the dark energy,
the cosmological constant, the vacuum energy,
is most likely quantum mechanical in origin.
Well, I think that's a good question.
I think that's a good question.
But once it's there, it's just energy.
In fact, I mean, you know,
the mass of the electron has a contribution to it,
which is quantum mechanical.
But once we know what the mass is,
we simply use it in classical physics
as if it were just an ordinary mass.
So, while it's quite true
that the dark energy cosmological constant
may ultimately be due to the quantum mechanical constant,
we don't really know.
It may ultimately be due to quantum fluctuations.
Nevertheless, by the time we
average over those quantum fluctuations,
what we see is a uniform distribution of energy,
very small, to be sure.
If it wasn't small,
then we'd be rocketing away from each other.
It's very, very small.
In natural units, in Planck units,
it's something like 10 to the minus 123.
It's a very, very small number compared
to any other natural scale in physics.
And it sets the scale for our...
And it's the reason, its smallness is
the reason that our horizon is so big.
What would the world be like
if that cosmological constant was much larger?
In other words, if h was much larger?
Here's the distance to the horizon.
Sorry, 1 over h.
What if h was much, much bigger?
Then we'd be surrounded by a smaller sphere.
We would be living in what
effectively looked like a much smaller universe,
even though it was, even though...
What do I say? H being big, right?
If h is big,
that of course means a more rapid expansion,
but it also means a smaller horizon.
So we'd be sitting in a smaller horizon,
but with a much larger repulsion between things.
If h were larger,
the repulsion would be larger,
and the size of the horizon would be much smaller.
So we'd be much more tightly restricted,
but we'd also be subject
to a force which would be,
you know, causing everything to explode.
So there is a limit
to how big the Hubble const...
the cosmological constant of the dark energy can be,
and we'd still be able to measure it.
We'd be able to talk about it.
It, uh...
Yeah?
Would that mean that there's a relationship
between Planck's constant,
which is related to butter fluctuations,
and the cosmological constant?
Yes.
In a sense.
There's a relationship.
The language to use is not Planck's constant.
Planck's constant is a thing which carries dimensions.
It's always good to talk about dimensionless things.
If you work in Planck units,
you're automatically talking about dimensionless things.
Um...
And, of course, knowing what the Planck unit is
does involve...
In ordinary, uh, measurement units,
does involve knowing what h-bar is.
But, um...
Yeah, there...
The answer is, in Planck units,
and that means everything is dimensionless,
it means that the Newton constant is one,
it means the Planck constant is one,
it means the speed of light is one.
In those units,
where all the fundamental constants of physics,
the most fundamental constants of physics
are set equal to one,
in those units,
the cosmological constant energy,
the dark energy,
is 123 orders of magnitude smaller.
So that's one of the great puzzles of physics.
What's the R of the equation?
The origin of that very, very small number.
Yeah?
Along those lines,
I have heard that not all theoreticians
share the idea that vacuum energy
should be identified with the cosmological constant
because of that 123...
If you go out in the world,
and you start asking people,
is the Earth flat or is it round,
you'll find 40% of Americans don't know that it's, uh...
Uh...
And I wouldn't say...
The situation is...
is...
Um...
Well, let's be a little bit charitable.
It's not quite as bad.
Yeah.
Now, there are some serious physicists
who question it, and, uh...
But...
And 10 years ago,
you might have reasonably questioned it.
10 or 15 years ago,
Um...
The bounds from experiment
get tighter and tighter and tighter.
What they mean by saying
that the cosmological constant isn't a constant
is the hypothesis that, uh...
Basically, that age varies with time
and decreases...
Uh...
Decreases?
Decreases.
And will eventually settle down to, uh...
Uh...
To zero.
The idea that the vacuum energy, whatever it is,
is a temporary transient thing
which will settle down.
All right.
Um...
And eventually not be there.
Just one quick question.
When they keep saying on these TV shows
about how everything's getting lonely and dark
and we'll be all by ourselves
and all that kind of stuff,
we wouldn't even notice a difference, would we?
Because you can't see galaxies
other than maybe a drama with the unaided eye...
No, with a telescope, you can.
Yeah, but I'm saying, without a telescope,
we wouldn't even be able to notice it.
Oh, that's probably true.
Yeah.
Without a telescope, uh...
Yep.
So who cares?
Yeah, who cares?
Yeah, yeah.
I think that's if you said it's perfectly flat.
If you took it perfectly flat and extended it forever
and you tried to pull it,
it would never fall off the edge.
Yeah.
So...
You know, it's a very interesting question.
I've thought about it myself,
and I've known other people who've thought about it.
How would astronomers of that distant time in the future...
Earth is still here.
They're still here.
You know, there's some questions and problems,
but nevertheless, we're all still here,
and we have our telescopes,
and we've lost our history books.
The Internet has failed.
We've lost our history books,
and we don't know very much.
Uh, how might we become aware of the fact
that there was a finite horizon out there,
that there was a dark energy,
that there was a galaxy,
that there was a galaxy that
was just vibrating away from each other,
and it's very, very hard to imagine any...
I can't think of any way
that they'd be able to tell.
Uh, the cosmic microwave background,
what would happen to it?
It would redshift away.
It redshifts to the
point where it's completely undetectable.
What about the galaxies that we count
in order to measure the Hubble constant and so forth?
They're not there anymore.
It's very, very difficult to
imagine how they could reconstruct, uh...
But would our new galaxies being born within the...
New galaxies are not born from empty space.
But we're adding to it with the dark energy.
No, the dark energy doesn't... won't create galaxies.
They would...
Actually, before we knew any of this astronomy,
there was something called Olper's paradox.
Right.
And so they would have to have some explanation.
No, there wouldn't.
There wouldn't be any stars out there.
No, there would.
There would be our galaxy and...
No, no, our gal...
Olper's paradox...
Let me remind you.
Olper's paradox was about the idea
of an infinite uniform density of stars out to infinity.
If you just take the stars from within our galaxy,
how much light do they give?
We know how much light they give.
Olper's paradox was a paradox of what happens
if the universe is filled with stars out to infinity
and they're not...
They didn't...
They didn't know about...
about expansion of the universe.
They're just sitting there.
No, but they wouldn't know about galaxies,
so they would just look out and see stars.
Yeah, but they...
Right, but they would see it into the stars.
They would see the galaxy have...
They would see the island universe
that the...
that the astronomers before Hubble believed in.
That would include Einstein.
Including Einstein.
But he stuck the...
the cosmological term in there just in case,
you know, to make it static.
Yeah, yeah.
So they make...
make that same mistake, so to speak.
No, they would just...
They would...
Yeah, right.
The stars in our galaxy would be smearing
against the horizon, right?
So they would go out in...
No, no, no, no.
They'll just be just where they are now.
They'll be...
Where are...
How far...
How big is the galaxy?
100,000 light years.
100,000 light years, right?
Small, tiny microscopic size.
No, I'm saying that the horizon will be shrinking until...
The horizon doesn't shrink.
It's...
Horizon doesn't shrink.
It's constant.
No, no, it's not constant yet.
It'll be another 20, 30 billion years.
Okay.
Right, but we're talking about 100...
Yes, yes.
And how big will it be
in 20 or 30 billion years?
Few galactic radii.
No, no, no, no, no, no, no.
It will not be a few galactic radii.
It will be about 20 billion light years.
From the dark energy that we know is there,
From the measurements of everything we know about,
the cosmological constant is a certain number.
How big? Big enough to put the
horizon about 20 billion light years away.
Now, tomorrow, basically forever.
So they'll be sitting in this big container,
20 billion light years across,
with 100,000 light year galaxy that they can see,
everything else having been swept clean,
and how do they detect the fact that
there is an outer boundary, let's call it?
Isn't there some rate at which
stars are ejected from the galaxy?
Yeah, stars are ejected from galaxies.
That's true.
You'll have some small number of
objects you can track for a while.
You can track them for a while,
but you won't be able
to track them out to cosmolo...
you know...
Well...
How do we know that that hasn't already happened?
Which? Stars evaporate from the galaxy?
That, you know, that edge of the universe,
the 20 billion light years away,
Yes?
is, you know, we're not able
to see the rest of it.
We can see it.
We can see it, we can see...
We can measure the expansion rate and reconstruct it.
Right?
Where there's enough stuff around to be
able to reconstruct it at the present time.
Suppose the event horizon would be just
outside the distance to the Andromeda Galaxy.
Wouldn't the...
That would be quite noticeable.
Yeah, then you'd be able, because the
Andromeda Galaxy wouldn't behave the way it would,
the way it behaves now, because the
component with the expansion is so large.
Yes.
But it's not...
The horizon is not going to shrink in.
The horizon is going to be at the place where...
Yeah, it's going to be at...
With the numbers that we have today.
With the numbers that we have today,
well measured, checked many different ways,
the prediction for the future is that the horizon,
will be at about 20 billion light years.
That's where it will be.
Yeah.
In other words, H is
constant during this kind of expansion.
And the distance to where you have to go,
to where you see the speed of light,
that's going to be constant.
Yeah.
Aren't there big, big bangs happening out there?
Not that I know of.
I thought that...
There were...
The...
What's it called?
Yeah, but we can't see that part.
That's out beyond the horizon.
That will not be visible to us,
or to our future descendants.
Now, what is true, there is something which is true.
They're called Poincare recurrences.
I'll tell you what a Poincare recurrence is.
First of all, your picture of...
That's the inside.
Your picture should be that there's some temperature here,
a very low temperature from our point of view,
a very high temperature out near the boundary,
but you should think of it as a thermal system.
It, in fact, has an entropy.
The entropy is just the area
of the horizon in Planck units.
It has an entropy, a certain finite entropy.
And so you can think
of it as a thermal system,
and so you can think of it
to a large extent as a cavity
with a finite amount of entropy
in it and some thermal gas.
The thermal gas is mainly out near the horizon
because of this effect.
It all tends to congregate out here.
And it's constantly fluctuating.
Now, a thermal system...
Let's talk about thermal systems, a box.
A box of gas with lots of molecules in it.
After it comes to thermal equilibrium,
and in fact, what will happen
is everything will come to thermal equilibrium.
When everything passes out through the horizon,
it will be in thermal equilibrium.
What is a gas, a box of
gas like when it's in thermal equilibrium?
Well, it's like nothing.
I mean, it's a big, dull box of uniform density.
Nothing much happens.
It just sits there and
sits there forever and ever, right?
A black body, right?
Yeah, if it's radiation in there, it's a black body.
If it's molecules in there, the molecules,
and they're fairly, let's say they're fairly dense,
then apart from tiny little fluctuations,
nothing ever happens.
Well, that depends on time scales.
There are time scales.
Basically, statistically, anything can happen.
There are no rules.
There's only statistics, only probabilities.
That's all there are are probabilities.
You can really ask, what is
the probability that all the molecules
suddenly come together in such a way that they
all wind up in the corner of the room?
There's an answer to that.
There's an answer to that, the probability.
It is basically E to the
minus the entropy of the gas.
The entropy is roughly the
number of molecules of the gas.
So if we have a box
with 10 to the 25th molecules,
this is E to the minus 10 to the 25th.
You weight a time of order
E to the 10 to the 25th.
It's called the Poincare recurrence time.
And basically, the Poincare recurrence
time is the time scale
for extremely rare and unusual fluctuations to take place.
Extremely rare and unusual fluctuation might be
all the molecules go off into the center.
Or it might be they all
assemble themselves into an elephant or whatever.
That time scale is of order,
what's called the Poincare recurrence time.
And it's normally extremely huge.
On that time scale, there's constantly things going on.
Fluctuations taking place which take
you far out of thermal equilibrium.
So far out of thermal equilibrium
that in the return to thermal equilibrium,
all sorts of complicated vortices and
other things might form in this there
before it returns to thermal equilibrium.
This is also thought to
be true for the sitter space.
That if you really wait long enough, how long?
E to the 10 to the 120.
What units?
It doesn't matter what units.
Believe me, it doesn't matter what units.
In any units you can think of, it will take
E to the 10 to the 120 of those units,
and let's say years, for a recurrence to occur.
And on that time scale, all
kinds of things will take place.
So, among other things.
Right.
But, you know, short of such
impossibly long time scales, nothing will happen.
It will just be heat death.
The same kind of heat
death that takes place in here,
when everything comes to equilibrium and
there's no more interesting things happening.
Well, more mild fluctuations could happen.
Fluctuations could happen, I'll give you an
example of a fluctuation that can happen.
We can even give a rough
estimate of how long between such fluctuations.
Instead of the whole world returning to
the original Big Bang, which might happen,
that would be this time scale here,
we could ask for a more modest kind of fluctuation.
A more modest kind of fluctuation might be a
fluctuation happens in which a solar system accidentally forms.
I told you an elephant could form.
Okay, yes, an elephant can form.
And the time scale for elephants to form is not
E to the minus the entropy of the whole gas,
it's E to the minus the entropy of an elephant.
What's the entropy of an elephant?
Roughly the number of molecules in it.
In the same way, if you wait
long enough, by accident, by pure thermal fluctuation,
a solar system might form here.
That might be the cheapest way of making an observer.
Right.
The cheapest way, probabilistically speaking, of making an
observer might be for a fluctuation to happen
and to create a solar system.
But I can think of something a little cheaper.
I can think of just the Earth forming.
That would be even cheaper.
The entropy of the Earth, well, you might
worry a little bit if there was no sun,
then you wouldn't have any warmth,
but let's not worry about that.
You might form an already warm Earth that
keeps itself warm for some period of time.
And you say, well, maybe it's
not enough time for people to evolve.
Don't worry about that.
The fluctuation involves the creation of people, too.
But you could even do cheaper.
If all you want is a single observer, you
could imagine a single observer or just his brain,
just his brain being nucleated by random fluctuation.
Such things are called Boltzmann brains.
And serious physicists worry about computing
the relative probability of ordinary observers
with a reasonable history like us versus Boltzmann brains.
They don't want a universe in which
the typical observer is a Boltzmann brain.
That's not a good thing if when
you calculate the properties of the universe
that you find out that the
overwhelming majority of observers are Boltzmann brains
that appear spontaneously out of nowhere.
And serious physicists worry about whether their
cosmology will be dominated by Boltzmann brains
instead of Darwinian brains that evolved.
I'm not kidding you.
It's a serious business.
Maybe a quicker way would be to send someone out.
Quicker way to do what?
To determine whether in the future,
when you follow your history books,
when the internet was crashed,
to determine whether or not,
if you just,
because it might be billions of years,
but then you might be able to see that there's...
No, no, you're right.
I should qualify my statement that it's impossible to,
it's impossible to do it except on time scales
which are big enough to explore such large regions.
Right, that's exactly right.
These forces are such
that they only become appreciable
at distance scales of let's say
some fraction of a billion light years.
So yes, if you could go out and explore,
yes, of course you're right,
that's a much shorter time scale,
you could go out and send out your explorers,
map out the geometry of,
with light signals,
measure the properties of space on large scale,
space and time,
and if you had your own,
you could give yourself a few
billion years to do it in,
and rockets that could get out
there and explore that large size,
yes, then you could definitely tell.
But if you're restricted to,
you know, the usual lifetime of an experiment,
well, just any kind of ordinary time scales,
you would have a much harder time telling,
and I'm not sure how you would do it.
Yeah, but they're absolutely right.
You could imagine sending out explorers,
to map out geometry,
and they would find this, yeah.
So the time scale of the experiments would be redshifted?
Well, no, the time scale of
the experiments would be of order,
a few billion light years.
I'm just saying that it
takes longer the more you wait.
It takes longer the more you wait.
Longer to do the experiments to
find out what we know now.
Yes, it would take much longer to do the experiments,
yes, that's right.
That's right.
But the observer,
sending out...
No, no, I think you're right.
It is a matter of redshift in a sense, yes.
The observer sending information back
sends a radiation that is modulated,
and that's redshift.
That's okay.
Don't even do that.
Don't even think about it.
Just send the observers out,
let them make measurements with light rays.
The light rays take a billion years
to get from one place to another.
That's okay.
We have a billion years.
And then just bring the observers back and...
And you're right.
There is a redshift factor,
but we face exactly the same redshift factor
when we measure it today.
We measure today the cosmological constant
by monitoring the cosmic macronutrient background.
That's been redshifted by a
factor of a thousand or so.
So what is the information content
of a highly redshifted signal?
You don't have to redshift that much.
If you want to explore
the universe on a scale of,
let's say, four billion light years on a side,
and that's enough.
Probably a billion light years
would be more than enough to detect the expansion.
In a billion light years,
the redshift is not a big deal.
It's a small fraction of one,
a tenth or something like that.
So you're not limited to one.
So you're not limited by redshift
in making these measurements.
If you were,
we wouldn't be able to do them today.
The planets and so forth...
Not the planets.
The stars and galaxies that we see out there
that we count
and which form our measuring rods and so forth,
those are out pretty far,
a few billion light years.
But we're not limited in detecting them
by their redshift from us.
Since we're talking about Fonker,
we're talking about Fonker ray recurrence probabilities,
and of course all this stuff is based on
quantum mechanics, quantum field theory...
No, no, that does...
Yeah, Fonker ray recurrences are not quantum mechanics.
They're classical...
I'm not saying...
That's true,
but all this is based on predictions
on the kind of laws of nature
that we are aware of today.
What's the probability that in the future
humans will discover laws about nature
that'll make all this wrong?
I'm not saying that we won.
Just mind the myth.
But, you know, I...
Yes, no, your point is well taken,
but it's also true that
the most single, robust set of rules
that has never been shaken at all
are the rules of thermodynamics and statistics.
So if I had to bet
on which laws would be most likely
to survive for a very long time
or an arbitrarily long time,
I would guess those which were based on
statistics, probability theory,
namely statistical mechanics.
But, do we know? No.
I would also make the point that
statistics and probability,
what they ultimately mean,
is also something that is quite mysterious
and we might have a different view of it.
Yes, I think we will
have a different view of it.
I was going to talk about...
Let's see, what time is it?
It's an hour and...
It's an hour what?
It's like 8.30.
Oh, I know, I know.
What time is it really?
All right.
All right, I...
Yeah, I thought I would amuse you
with some other things that physicists worry about today
that sound very bizarre.
I'm just going to ask
if this is a good time
to bring in the question that you brought up
about the ultraviolet redshift connection.
I mean infrared, ultraviolet infrared connection.
はい
Yeah, I never quite get to it, do I?
No.
Yeah.
It is the right time, but
I'm not going to do it anyway.
Maybe I could come back for another 10 years.
Yeah, ooh, someday we'll get to it.
Someday we'll get to it.
I was going to tell you about a puzzle that
has to do with probability theory that
is really sort of obsessing a lot of physicists.
And I'll tell you where it comes from.
The first thing, which we're
not going to talk about tonight,
is the idea of, except
I'm just going to mention it,
is the idea of eternal inflation.
I'll draw a picture of it for what it's worth.
And then I'll tell you what
the nature of the puzzle is.
First, we want to get a picture on the blackboard.
A picture of the Sitter
space or a expanding, inflating universe
looked like that.
Everything below here is the world.
Everything above there doesn't mean anything.
And this is the end of time.
OK, one of the things that
was discovered sometime in the 1970s
by a physicist by the name of Sidney Coleman
was that the Sitter space like this is probably unstable.
But it's unstable in a very specific way.
It's unstable with respect to
the fact that it's not stable.
It's unstable.
It's unstable with respect to nucleating little bubbles
in which the cosmological constant might be smaller.
I'm just going to draw
you what the picture looks like.
If a bubble nucleated over
here in which the cosmological constant
was a little bit smaller or maybe a lot smaller,
what would happen is a region would grow.
It would grow.
And eventually, it would be a new world.
And then it would fill up
a region of space like that.
This region of space in here,
this region of space-time in here,
is itself an entire universe.
Don't ask me why.
It's a bubble.
But it's an expanding bubble.
And that expanding bubble expands out
to something infinitely big up here.
And it corresponds, in some sense, to a universe.
With time, many of these bubbles will form.
And in fact, the problem is that
the bubbles are not going to form.
They're going to expand.
And they're going to expand.
And the population of them will exponentially increase.
Why?
It has to do with the exponential expansion.
The population will exponentially increase.
And this is a picture that cosmologists love to draw.
These different bubbles could be different from each other.
It's not really terribly important.
They might be different from each other.
Things go on in them.
And this process is imagined to
keep going and going and going.
Now, each one of these tiny little bubbles
is as big as the original one I drew here,
for the same reason that this line here
is as big as that line.
It's just that they occur later.
And they fill up all of future infinity
here with a kind of fractal structure of exponentially
increasing population.
And this is the same structure.
There could be people in there.
There could be whatever you like.
The populations exponentially increase.
There are some very funny puzzles about probability theory
having to do with exponentially increasing populations.
And they have really gotten in our way.
I'll give you some examples just for fun.
I'll tell you some examples.
And then I'll tell you how it applies to this.
Imagine the following.
A Gedanken world.
A thought.
It's not an experiment.
It's just a world.
In fact, it's not a Gedanken world.
It is our world.
It's a world in which the population is exponentially
increasing.
Unfortunately, this is approximately true.
Number two, it's a world with finite resources.
I think it's true.
But let's take it to be the
case that, for one, it's a world
where there's a total amount of resources.
And for one reason or another, nobody really
has the vaguest idea what the total resources are.
This, I think, is not true of all words.
Unless you're in Congress.
One half of Congress, anyway.
Right?
Yeah.
So we will take it.
These citizens who live in this exponentially growing
population.
And I think that's the point.
They don't have any idea
at all what the resources are.
But they are interested in the probability
that they want to know what the probabilities are
that their resources will last for another generation or so.
How can they give an answer to this
if they don't know what the resources are?
But we'll add one more postulate.
And the one more postulate is one
that we always make in science.
I'll give you some examples of it.
And it is that we who
are doing the experiment are typical.
Typical means the following.
It means that if there
are a great many possible outcomes,
but more, but by some large majority,
the observers who are doing this have a large probab-
well, let's see how to say this.
Yeah, okay.
Let's talk about coin flippers.
I hate to digress, but let's get into coin flippers.
We got zillions and zillions
of people who are doing this.
We got zillions and zillions of these people
who are obsessed with coin flipping.
And what they love to do is they
love to flip a coin a million times.
All of these people do this.
And they count how many heads they get,
and they count how many tails.
What they do with it, I don't know.
All right.
But a typical one of them, or one of them,
asks the question,
what bet should I make for how
many heads and tails do I get?
Not exactly, but, you know, within some reasonable bounds.
I'm going to do an experiment.
I'm an experimental physicist.
All experiments involve statistics,
especially in quantum mechanics.
And when we make predictions,
we're making predictions analogous to
the prediction of coin flippers
who flip coins.
Well, what's the answer?
The answer is there are some
coin flippers who flip all heads.
There are some coin flippers who flip all tails.
According to the standard theory of probability,
the overwhelming majority flip about, what
did I say, a million flips?
A million plus or minus
a thousand square root of n.
All right.
So if you're at all smart
and you're a good experimental physicist
and you know the rules of statistics,
you will put down your prediction.
Your prediction will be, what did I say,
half a million plus or minus a thousand.
I think I probably said it wrong.
Half a million plus or minus a thousand.
That'll be your best guess.
And if you're very far away from it,
you'll probably say there was something.
You probably won't believe that you are an outlier.
You're more likely to believe
that your theory was just wrong.
But there are going to
be those people who are outliers.
And they, of course, will believe their theory is wrong,
and they'll be wrong.
We always make the assumption that we are typical.
So in this expanding population,
let's make the assumption that we are typical.
We are like the majority
of all observers who ever lived.
Then what bet do we make
for how long the resources will last
after the present time now?
We're in the last one.
Well, not necessarily the last one,
but there won't be more than
two or three generations after us.
And the reason is,
in an exponentially expanding population,
like now,
about half the people who ever existed exist now.
About three-quarters of the people who ever existed
existed within two generations.
About seven-eighths within three generations.
So if we're typical
in an exponentially expanding population,
we are near the end of that expansion.
We're near the end of that expansion.
Now, that's a very puzzling conclusion.
It doesn't...
It sounds like there's something wrong with it.
How can you possibly know that
if you don't know what the resources are?
On the other hand,
it is true that no matter what the resources are,
the...
Most people will be near the end of the resources.
Right?
This is...
I'll give you another example
of this kind of exponential expansion.
You've all seen, I'm sure you've seen,
the...
It's my favorite drawing.
I come back to it over and over again
because it has some deep mathematical significance.
It's Escher's drawing called Limit Circle Number Four.
You've all seen it.
Angels and devils.
And I'm not going to
try to draw angels and devils.
But it has a big angel...
Let's just restrict ourselves to devils.
I prefer devils.
It has a big devil in the center.
It has smaller devils out here.
And so forth.
Now, in fact, the geometry is such
that they're really all identical to each other.
There are symmetries of this diagram
which move points,
which can move this point into this point.
It'll move this point into something small over here.
It's just the way that it's drawn.
Some things look smaller and some things look bigger.
It's completely symmetric.
But, of course, when Escher actually drew it,
he did have to draw the small things small
and the big things big.
Now...
Here's the question.
Let's define an angel...
devil, excuse me.
A devil which has been
drawn with a body part missing.
Let's call him an amputee.
Okay?
Definition of an amputee.
If a devil was drawn with some body part missing,
we'll call him an amputee.
Now, these devils go to sleep,
and they wake up in the morning,
and they wonder,
am I one of the unfortunate amputees,
or am I one of the whole devils?
Okay?
If you look at Escher's drawing,
and you extrapolate Escher's drawing
past the last visible devil,
and you believe that you can extrapolate it,
you look, you'll see Escher was awfully good at drawing.
He didn't draw any devils with missing body parts.
So your conclusion would be,
with very high probability,
you're not an amputee.
Okay?
On the other hand, Escher had finite resources.
Finite patience, finite time,
finite amount of ink.
And that means,
as he got tired out near the very, very edges,
surely very, very close to the edges,
you'll find that almost all of the angels and devils
will be slightly misdrawn, right?
Of course they will be.
They won't have heads,
or they won't have tails,
or whatever it is,
the ones out near the boundary.
Now, what is the ratio of the ones
which are adjacent to the boundary
to all of them?
Do you know the answer?
No.
There are about as many out near the boundary
as there are in the whole thing.
So,
there are about as many out near the boundary
as there are in the whole thing.
Obviously, there are fewer at the boundary.
A factor of a half.
And that's because the number of them
grows exponentially
as you make bigger and bigger circles here.
They grow exponentially.
And so if you actually count,
if you cut it off, let's say,
by putting a circle around here,
now count all the ones
that are adjacent to the circle,
and you put them inside,
you'll find they're about equal.
It's the same mathematics
as saying about half the population,
no matter how long into the past
the population had been growing for,
today, about half the population,
one generation,
constitutes about half the population
of anything that ever existed.
In the same way,
about half of the devils
are right on the edge,
whatever the edge is.
We don't have to know
how much resources Escher had.
It doesn't matter how much he had.
No matter how much he had,
as he draws more and more and more of them,
the ones near the edge
will always be about half of all of them.
And so, if you wake up in the morning
and you don't know whether you're a whole devil
or half a devil,
the chances are about 50%
that you're half a devil,
that you're an amputee.
And this is very puzzling,
because you could say,
well, how can I say that
when I don't know how much resources there were?
Well, the answer is it doesn't matter
how much resources there were.
Okay, now we come back to here.
We are again facing a problem
of exponential population growth.
In this case, population growth
is a function of little bubble universes.
Oh, let me come back to
angels and devils for a minute.
Come back to angels and devils for a minute
before we go on to universes.
Escher did have angels and devils.
Let's ask a different question,
the different question being,
when you wake up in the morning,
are you an angel or a devil?
50% probability, right?
There are as many angels as devils.
And the mathematics of Escher's drawing,
if it went on for infinity,
in some sense that would be true.
But we know that Escher had finite resources,
which means we have to draw an edge to this.
The answer for the ratio of devils to angels
is extremely sensitive to the way we draw that line.
It's extremely sensitive to the way
we could draw the line.
For example, every time we come to an angel,
let's go around it that way.
Every time we come to a devil,
we go around it that way.
And now we push this edge out further and further.
By a factor of about three quarters,
we will have more devils than angels.
It's all in the edge here.
It's all in the edge.
And so the assignment of probabilities
to angelness or devilness
is just extremely sensitive
to what Escher did
just as he was running out of resources.
It's ridiculous because, you know,
you simply don't know anything about his resources.
You would think that the answer was 50-50.
But if at the end he
had a little bit less pink paint
than white paint,
the answer would be many, many more white than pink.
Okay.
Same exact thing here.
You want to know the relative probability
of different kinds of bubble universes forming.
Blue ones, pink ones, and so forth.
The population is exponentially growing.
How do you decide?
You try to decide the same way.
You say, let's chop this off at some time
and count the number of blue ones versus pink ones.
But the problem is the answer is super hypersensitive.
You're hypersensitive to the exact way
that you draw this line.
And that has led to a problem
that cosmologists, physicists like myself
call the measure problem.
Measure as in probability measure.
How do you assign probabilities
in a world of exponentially increasing populations?
The answer always is it is extremely sensitive
to the way that you cut things off,
to the way you and your imagination
in the universe.
This is a very, very big problem for cosmologists
because they want to be able to use their theories
in a predictive way and make predictive predictions.
What other kind of prediction is there?
Or at best, if not predictions,
at least explanations of things.
And so in this kind of world,
if it's really true that there's an exponentially increasing
population, we run into new kinds of questions
about probability theory and about
how the use of statistics,
which really just have baffled, really baffled us.
My guess is, of course,
that we're asking the wrong questions.
We're probably asking the wrong questions.
But that doesn't help to say that we're probably
asking the wrong questions.
It doesn't help unless you can
say what the right questions are.
And, yeah.
Is there any connection to the renormalization
or to the odd and even strains?
To which?
Odd and even, I remember
it as odd and even strains,
but the, those, the fermionic strains
where the number of, as I recall it,
sorry, the number of quantum mechanical oscillators
varies the spin of the strain.
Well, there are, there are relations
with renormalization theory.
There are relations.
There are relations with renormalization theory.
Renormalization theory is also a situation where, again,
you start your picture of the
world as having a finite number
of degrees of freedom per unit volume,
and then you double the number of degrees of freedom
in each volume, and then you double it again,
and you double it again.
You don't double it really.
You double it in your
imagination and ask how things converge.
What we're talking about, of course,
is you start picturing the world as a lattice.
You can't handle a continuous
infinity of degrees of freedom.
So you start the world as a lattice,
and you make your calculations
based on one degree of freedom
per unit Compton wavelength of an electron
or something in quantum electrodynamics.
Then you say, I want more accuracy,
so I divide the world
in every cell in half again.
And I recalculate.
And in each case, I
ask the same kind of questions.
What's some relative population of regions of space
with this property or that property?
And again, not with respect to real honest time,
but with respect to your mathematical sequence
of descriptions, the population is exponentially increasing.
Again, you get infinite answers.
You have to deal with those infinities
and in quantum field theory,
there are techniques for asking questions
which are not sensitive to the,
let's call them the edge effects.
There are techniques for extracting out things
which are not sensitive to the details
of how you chop this up.
So yeah, there are correspondences and similarities
between questions in quantum field theory
and these kind of questions in cosmology.
And people are trying to exploit those similarities,
but not, I must say, with any great success yet.
That bubble, is that similar to inflation
going to the current universe or something like that?
Yeah.
Well, what's called eternal inflation creating,
yeah, it's deeply connected with inflationary theory.
So maybe it's the ultimate,
but that by looking at the
economic interaction of states
you would try to exercise
a small patch on the sky which
had a little colder or warmer temperature.
And of course you do see patches on the
sky with a little bit of warmer and colder temperature.
But to be more detailed, you'll have to
get really detailed to see that that's what they
are.
One of the details would be the
polarization of the microwave background around them.
It's kind of interesting.
If you saw one of these patches in the
sky, and there is one, it's called a cold spot.
It's a cold spot, and
nobody knows what it's due to.
It's a cold spot on the sky, a
cold spot in the sense of microwave background.
A cold spot is a candidate for a
spot where another bubble collided with our bubble.
It's a candidate.
What more can you say about
it other than it's a candidate?
Well, you can try to work out in
more detail what such a patch would look like.
So for example, you discover that light is polarized.
In particular, you discover that light is polarized.
This is the direction of polarization
around this in a particular characteristic way.
And people are doing this.
They're working out the consequences
of such a bubble collision.
Of course, should this be confirmed, that it
does look like a bubble collision and in
detail it does, this of course would
be a major, major revolution in cosmology, the
discovery.
But the detection of other bubbles which
collided with our bubble would be very, very
major.
The difference is that the inflation factor,
the H in these regions, that distinguishes
the bottom from the tops.
Is the bottom region expanding faster?
Bottom region typically is expanding faster.
And our region is somewhere in here.
And it had a history of different expansion rates.
So it's complicated.
It's a complicated story.
But it does include this
idea of exponential population growth.
So one could foresee a situation in
which we truly confirmed that there were bubble
collisions with our world.
We would have confirmed something like this
picture, at least a piece of it.
Then, it becomes a really serious matter
to try to get to the bottom.
to get predictive and to ask what
the relative probabilities of different kinds of bubbles
are. And that's where we run into
this trouble of exponential population. The answers would
be very dependent on the question of whether
they were finite resources or not. What is
a finite resources? I don't know what a finite
resource is. Just to say it comes to an end
somehow. And the details of the way that
it came to an end would determine what relative
probabilities were.
The bubbles collide. You just add
the dark energies of the two types.
No, it's more complicated than that. The
place where they collide, depending on details,
there's something called the domain wall,
which separates them. And the domain wall
on one side has one behavior.
The domain wall on the other side has one behavior.
The other side has another behavior. But the
point is the domain wall would be visible
to us, or could be visible to us.
We would need a bit of luck. Here
we are. Here's our observer. If the bubble collides
over here, some sort of bubble collision over
here, this observer doesn't get to see it.
If it collides over here, then he does
get to see it. So there's different scenarios,
different situations. But it doesn't seem totally
out of the question with the numbers
that we know that there could be bubble
collisions, that there could be visible bubble collisions.
And if so, they have a particular
signature, a particular behavior. They're fairly characteristic.
And if they're not, then they're not. And
if they're not, then they're not. And if they're
not, then they're not. And if they're not,
then they're not. And if they're not, then
they're not. And if they're not, then they're
not. And if they're not, then they're not.
If the cold spot is such a bubble collision,
we will know. We will know in time. What do
I bet? Well, I don't know what to bet, honestly.
Do the bubbles have four dimensions?
Yeah. Well, yes.
What about the curvature of expansion?
What about the curvature of expansion? Whether
it's convex or concave or flat? Will
that make that we see different things?
Oh.
The bubbles are usually negatively
curved, Friedman, Roberts, and Walker universes.
They have negative spatial curvature. The
bubble collision would certainly modify the
curvature in some characteristic way, but it
wouldn't turn the world from a world with
a negative curvature to a positive
curvature. That couldn't do. But yeah.
Kind of a romantic question, but is it
possible to assign a problem to a particular
population?
Well, I don't know.
And if you're going to assign a probability
to the statement that string theory is correct
or incorrect, given that we have
almost non-pure weather, one way or another?
I don't think so.
50-50 would probably do.
We'll do one stroke.
That's a matter of individual opinion for
which I don't think there's any value in
trying to assign a possibility.
OK.
So a probability.
No, I mean, is there any?
I'm not even sure I know what it means.
All right. I'll give you an answer that I've given
before. There is a mathematical structure,
a very precise mathematical structure, which
exists. It's mathematically consistent. Mathematicians have
won big prizes for proving theorems that
were...
I don't know.
First suggested by theorists on the
basis of string theory, which the mathematicians
didn't know. So the consistency of the
internal consistency of it has been extremely well
checked. There is a structure. The structure
has gravity, and it has quantum mechanics
in it. So in that sense, string theory
is a well-defined, exact... Now, of course, there's
a very remote possibility that somebody will
discover an inconsistency in it, but it seems
extremely unlikely, a mathematical inconsistency.
On the other hand, that part of it
which is mathematically precise, let's call it string
theory with a capital S, with capital
letters, string theory capitalized, it is supersymmetric.
It is...
OK.
It's supersymmetric. The world is not supersymmetric. The
world as we see it is not supersymmetric.
The mathematical structure which is well-defined and
for which we have a lot of confidence
that it really exists, you can call it
quantum gravity with supersymmetry, it is not the
real world. So in that sense, we know
now, no question, string theory is not the real
world.
It's not the real world. It's not the real world.
It's not the real world.
OK.
One hundred percent, we know it for sure.
The...
So you just can't break the symmetry?
Breaking the symmetry, nobody really knows how to
do. OK? It is not part of the mathematically
precise part of the theory. We all expect
that this thing that we call capital string
capital string theory. There it is, string
theory. It has many, many, many different
versions. A huge number of different possibilities lie
within this. We all expect that it's contained
within something bigger, something bigger that we
don't know how to analyze. It's more
or less like the situation where, maybe
it's like the situation, where physicists in the
time preceding Newton might have discovered the
formula F equals mA, and the formula,
the force is equal to m1, m2 times g
over r squared. But they didn't have the mathematical
tools to analyze anything but the simplest orbits.
So they said,
all right, we will use symmetry, the symmetry
of circular orbits. We need one little bit
of extra information. We need to know
the acceleration of a circular orbit. That's not
too hard. You can do it on the basis
of some simple symmetries, and you can therefore figure
out Kepler's, which one of
the laws is it that the...
One of the Kepler laws which tells
you the period is a function of radius.
Right.
You know that the theory that you're working
with, the theory of circular orbits, is not
correct. But you just don't have the mathematical power
to be able to go beyond it. I don't
know if that's what the real situation is, but
it could be like that. So we know that
the theory of circular orbits is contained
in something bigger, don't know how to analyze
it. We know that the perfectly idealized supersymmetric
string theory, the one that we really know how
to analyze, is not the real world. It looks
a little bit like the real world, but it's
not the real world. And the question is
whether it's contained in something bigger which we
could call string theory with a small s. But
the answer is we don't know very much about
this. We know a great deal about this. This
has been enough to tell us all sorts of things
about the combination of gravity and gravity. I
think the most important thing to us now,
and we don't want to talk about gravity
and gravity together, is that it's a very complex,
of gravity and quantum mechanics, things about black holes,
things about all kinds of things.
But to say one way or another, what's
the probability that string theory contains a,
or that there is an extension
of it, a bigger version of it
that contains our world right over here?
I don't know.
Of course, in some sense, well, of course that's true.
Our world is someplace.
Here's the theory of someplace.
If you add this to this, you get something bigger.
But that's not helpful.
We want to know whether, in some interesting way,
the theory of the real world is some extrapolation
from what we already know.
And that, there's no way to know.
Does it contradict the string theory?
Does it contradict the possibility?
Only capital string.
Does it contradict the possibility that what?
Does the capital string theory rule out the ?
Capital string theory doesn't rule out the presence of,
doesn't rule out the existence of small string theory.
But what it does say is that
nature is not, as we know it,
is not described by capital string theory.
So we know with certainty that
a bigger structure has to be
found.
And whether that bigger structure that contains our world
will sort of be contiguous with, connected
to the smaller structure of capital string theory,
this we don't know.
We can all make our bets.
ありがとうございました
You're saying that string theory has no symmetries
breaking like the eggs particles and things like that?
People write loads and loads of papers
about the symmetry breakings of string theory.
The symmetry breakings in particular
are the symmetry breakings of supersymmetry.
And we know a lot about the mathematics of supersymmetry,
but we don't know a precise version of how
to combine the breaking of supersymmetry with string theory.
That is outside the scope of what we know.
That doesn't stop people from...
You know, you make an approximation here and there, and
then you start rolling, and you can do some things.
The problem is that you're making approximations, but
you don't know what those approximations are approximations to.
You make some standard approximations, and
then you start doing some things.
You make standard approximations that we use
all the time, and you start calculating,
but there's no backbone to
the thing that you're approximating.
So at the present time, I think the safest
thing to say is string theory, as we know it,
and as we can... the rigorous version
of it, is certainly not the real world.
There's, in my view, lots of reason to think
that the part of it that we know about,
that we know about, is not the real world. There's, in my view,
lots of reason to think that the part of it that we know about,
that we know about, is not the real world.
And what that stirs is not the whole thing,
that it could be bigger.
It probably is almost certainly bigger,
but how to say whether the
real world is part of it,
that's very much a prejudice that
different physicists share in different proportions.
Smen- Does string theory, it contains gravity...
does it contain special relativity? Or is
special relativity a postulate for string theory?
It really does require special relativity.
Now, special relativity can be violated by the environment.
We're sitting here in a room where everybody's at rest,
and the world does not look Lorentz invariant to me.
Your presence here violates my sense of Lorentz invariance.
It also violates, we talked about this last time,
didn't we?
So you can have what physicists call a background, which
means stuff in it, which picks out
a particular frame of reference.
But the underlying rules for string theory
do have Lorentz invariance.
That's a prediction.
It's not a postulate.
Yeah, I would say it's a prediction.
But the most robust prediction is that it has gravity.
There's just no way for it to not have gravity.
It has gravity, but is it consistent with Einstein's theory
of general relativity?
It is.
I mean, the background independence, the general
is in the string theory also.
Yeah, this question about background independence
is a confusing one.
Yeah, it is background independent up to a point.
Up to a point.
Yes.
It's hard to change the asymptotic boundary conditions
continuously, but it should be hard to change
the asymptotic boundary conditions continuously.
How do you change asymptotic boundary conditions
continuously?
You can't do any operation that would change them.
But short of asymptotic boundary conditions,
changing the background locally in spacetime, yeah,
string theory does have that.
And you don't have to take my word for it.
This is something that's been long studied since the 1980s.
Works of people like Curtis Callan and other people
have studied that.
Do you have a last-ditch week for last try?
No, we're finished tonight.
This is the last?
Yeah.
OK.
Thank you.
For more, please visit us at stanford.edu.