This program is brought to you by Stanford University.
Please visit us at stanford.edu.
Here's space.
Let's concentrate on space.
No energy around.
We can take space-time to be flat.
But in particular,
if space-time is flat,
it's just ordinary Minkowski space.
We can certainly imagine that space is flat
by slicing through it in a flat way.
But now let's put a particle into it.
If we put a particle into it,
particles have energy,
and
the right-hand side is no longer zero.
At the point where the particle is,
and
only at the point where the particle is,
there's curvature.
Can you think of a geometry which has the property
that it is flat everywhere except at a point?
A cone.
Yes.
So the solution of the problem
of general relativity of a point mass
is that space is a cone,
and of course there's also time.
Space-time,
if we want to think about it,
we can think about it this way.
Time goes up.
And space,
instead of being just flat,
it is just flat.
But right where the particle is,
there's a conical deficit.
A deficit angle.
Just like when we make a cone by cutting
out with a scissor a piece of deficit angle.
Okay.
Now,
how big would you think the deficit angle is?
Well,
if there's no particle,
then how big is the deficit angle?
particle,
then there's no deficit angle.
What if there's a particle of mass m?
What would
you think?
Proportional to m.
Exactly so.
That's exactly right.
The deficit angle here
is proportional to m.
But the deficit,
and in fact,
it doesn't have to be a particle.
It could be any distribution of energy that's bounded.
It won't be exactly a cone,
but outside
the region where that energy is,
it'll have the same geometry as a cone.
So it might be
a cone with a sort of rounded surface to it,
but that's not so important.
All right,
now,
then comes the question.
How big does this mass have
to be before the deficit angle is
360 degrees?
There's nothing left when the deficit angle is 360 degrees.
The space has
essentially disappeared.
What has happened is it's closed up into a...thank you,
Michael.
The cone has gotten narrower and narrower.
The deficit angle eventually goes to a point
where there's no cone left.
At first,
it started as a big flat cone
when the particle at the center was light.
As the
particle got heavier and heavier,
the cone shrunk until there was no cone left.
There's
a maximum amount of mass that you can
put into three dimensions before it closes up
and just closes up and disappears.
How big is that mass?
Not very big.
The planet is
a clunk mass.
So we are not going...it's
the only mass in the problem.
So...well...
No,
it's dust grain.
Right.
So at most,
you could have,
in the way of life,
in three dimensions,
you could
have a single microorganism.
Right.
Not much room to develop an intelligence,
so forth and so on.
So space of two dimensions is clearly ruled out.
space of one dimension turns out to be even worse.
Gravity in one dimension,
one dimension space and one dimensional time is
so sick that it's not even worth thinking about.
Three dimensions,
three space dimensions,
one dimension space,
not twisty.
time dimension,
gravity behaves in the usual way.
What happens when you go to
four dimensions?
Well it's not just gravity,
it's gravity and also
electromagnetism,
which is sick.
Now first of all I'll
tell you in what way gravity
is,
gravity is not so much sick in four dimensions,
when I speak
about dimensions I'm speaking about spatial dimensions.
In four dimensions,
four plus one dimensions,
gravity is reasonably healthy,
but there is,
there
are some dynamical features to it which make it awkward.
The solar system would
not be stable,
the solar system would be very chaotic.
This is just a particular
fact about dimensions higher than
three that the Newtonian force law,
or the
force law that would derive out of Einstein's equations,
has bad
instability.
And so the solar system would be very
chaotic and the result of that is it
probably wouldn't take very long before
the planet got ejected out of orbit.
But
things are much worse than that,
that's not the worst thing,
that by no means the
worst thing.
Yeah?
Do you still get the Newtonian gravitation,
one over r squared?
No,
you don't get one over r squared,
that's why it's,
that's why it's funny.
You get one over r cubed.
As you go up in
dimensions,
it goes from one over r squared to
one over r cubed to one over r
to the fourth.
Now the real problem has to do with atoms.
Electrons are little
solar systems and it's not just gravity which
goes from one over r squared to one
over r cubed and so forth.
Electromagnetism also does.
It's governed by the same kind
of force law.
Coulomb's law and Newton's law have
the same form and that's true in
every dimension.
So what happens is you
go in higher dimensions is the
attractive force of gravity becomes
stronger and stronger at small
distances.
One over r cubed,
let's compare one over r cubed with one over r
squared.
One over r squared,
excuse me.
This is the force law when there are four space
dimensions,
this is the force law
when there are three space dimensions.
Well,
if I were to just
write this down,
I'm afraid we're going to run out of ink tonight.
One over r squared,
let's first plot one over r squared.
Now is one over r squared bigger,
is one over r cubed
bigger or smaller than one over r squared?
It's not well defined.
You have to tell me
where.
At r equals one,
they're exactly the same.
At r bigger than one,
r squared is one
over r squared because one over r
is equal to one over r squared,
right?
Ae całytto
is one over r squared.
Ok we've said one over n is
x то oxyto is one over n.
But the
question of r,
r plus u追ocratic is everybody saying that r
is less than 1 by 12 to the
whole n.
The question of r where r is less than 1,
r squared to t.
And this way you have
to have respect to the trace of intensity
because if a two pole is the same,
that means
r is higher than r squared.
So this is this kind
of elegant equation given by Newton.
Who are you asking to test it?
Why is that?
Why art you asking this?
I thought you could
do that?
I know this is the hearing settlement.
I know this was speaking to a lot of people.
the long distance Coulomb force which
holds the outer electrons in place would
be much weaker and there would not
be valence electrons and so forth they
would just fly off they would they would
fly off on the other hand the inner
electrons would be pulled in much more
tightly in fact in four space dimensions
the the Coulomb law when combined
with quantum mechanics would pull the
electrons right into the nucleus so
there wouldn't be atoms without atoms
there is no chemistry it only gets
worse in five dimensions and six dimensions
and so forth so we don't know really
why four dimensions what we do know is we
couldn't be sitting here if
the number of dimensions is higher
the number of dimensions that
the nuclear forces have seen larger
say it again
so is the number of dimensions in which the nuclear forces
is larger and therefore may exhibit one over rq to rq
I don't understand
I didn't understand
you asked me something about the nuclear
force right they would also be stronger
at small distances and would probably do real damage
to the theory of quarks and leptons quarks in particular
the theory of quarks would
not bind together properly into into
protons and neutrons
I've concentrated on atoms but much of
what I said you could also say
about the forces that held quarks together and
so forth lot so that would be bad
besides it's not entirely clear
that topologically that sex is possible
possible in higher dimensions.
This is important.
The conversation gets longer and longer.
Can you say anything about three spatial dimensions
and two time dimensions?
No.
That just boggles the mind.
I don't know
how to think about a world
with more than one time dimension.
No.
It seems like I have three time
dimensions to match the three spatial dimensions.
Yeah.
It's not clear.
Right.
It really isn't clear how to
think about what it would mean
to have more than one time dimension.
It's so confusing that,
no,
I have nothing to say
about it right now.
Okay.
So,
four dimensions does seem to be special.
As I said,
not for deep mathematical reasons,
as far as we know,
but there are certain features of basic
physics which seem to work in four
dimensions,
which for one reason or another
seem to be very thorny and problematic.
Atoms,
stability of the solar system,
the fact that in three
dimensions you can't have more than
a Planck's worth of mass before you close
the universe up into an infinitely narrow cone,
so forth and so on.
Any other questions?
I was saying,
why does time deserve dimensional status?
Well,
that I don't know what that means.
Dimensional status.
Why do we call it a dimension?
Well,
why not?
the real reason we call it
a dimension is because of Einstein,
whose special theory of relativity mixes
space and time together with transformations that
resemble,
mathematically,
rotations of space.
In other words,
there are transformations
which mix space and time together.
So it becomes natural to think of
time as a dimension of a four-dimensional space-time.
There's no unique,
in four dimension and space and time,
there is no unique time axis,
perpendicular to a space axis,
a moving reference frame as a
time axis which points in some other
direction.
The corresponding space is also tilted.
So there's no uniqueness to what the time axis is.
And they get mixed up with each other,
and it's quite profitable,
the mathematical structure of the theory,
space and time come in fairly symmetrically.
Or,
as you pointed out,
you can apply a boost and change energy.
For example,
an energy and momentum are time
and space components of four vectors.
Last week,
I think you said you would show us
where the cosmological constant went into the equation.
Yeah.
That's part of the lecture you're planning?
I actually hadn't,
but I'll tell you right now.
The question,
the more interesting question,
is what does the cosmological constant do?
But first,
let me tell you where it goes in the equations.
Just remember what's in the equations.
On the left-hand side,
we have something that involves geometry.
I told you that the only tensors that
we can make out of the gravitational field are,
that have two indices.
Remember,
on the right-hand side,
we're going to have the energy-momentum tensor,
two indices.
The only simple tensors that can be constructed,
or the simplest ones,
are r mu nu.
And whether I put the
indices upstairs or downstairs doesn't matter.
You can raise them,
lower them,
same thing.
r mu nu and minus some constant,
whether it's minus or plus,
we'll figure out later,
g mu nu times r mu nu.
Times r.
Now,
that's not quite right.
The coefficient here is determined by requiring,
well,
let's see,
we're going to put on the right-hand side,
t mu nu times a numerical constant,
8 pi times the Newton constant,
but sometimes just called k.
We expect and hope that energy-momentum will be conserved.
That means that the covariant derivative
del mu of t mu nu,
a kind of continuity equation for each component,
momentum and energy,
a separate continuity equation for each,
and if that's true,
then it had better be that the
left-hand side also satisfies the same thing.
Incidentally,
to make it satisfy the same thing,
we'd have to put the indices upstairs,
but that's no big deal.
And what Einstein discovered is that,
very generally,
no special assumptions about the geometry,
if he put a one-half here,
then in fact,
the left-hand side satisfies,
let's see,
this tensor as it stands is called g mu nu,
g for gravity,
or if we put the indices upstairs,
g mu nu,
it automatically satisfies,
for any geometry,
this identity.
So that fixed the form
of Einstein's equations with one ambiguity.
There is one more tensor that
you can form out of the metric,
which has the property,
which has this property,
this property is called covariant conservation,
there is one more tensor that you can form,
and that tensor is just the metric itself.
The metric itself satisfies del mu
g mu nu is equal to zero.
It's equivalent to the statement,
yes,
that's correct.
Why is that?
The reason is because the covariant,
all covariant derivatives of the metric tensor are zero.
The metric tensor is the one
tensor whose covariant derivatives are all zero.
One way to see that is
to go to a reference frame
where the metric and all of
its derivatives are equal to zero.
We talked about such a frame.
You can always choose coordinates
where the metric is constant.
Constant simply means its first
derivatives are equal to zero.
That means the Christoffel symbols are zero.
If the metric has no derivatives,
and the Christoffel symbols are equal to zero,
then the covariant derivative of the
metric must be exactly equal to zero.
The covariant derivative,
all covariant derivatives of the metric are equal to zero,
but in particular,
the one which corresponds to this continuity equation,
from here to here is just
replacing little g by big G,
and that's the one that's
going to be the largest derivative.
It's also true.
So that means there's one more thing that
we could have added into the left-hand side here,
plus some constant,
any constant,
lambda,
times g mu nu,
equals k t mu nu.
What's that?
Ooh.
Can't do that,
can you?
That's illegal.
Right.
That's the one ambiguity that
Einstein discovered in his equations.
Lambda is called the cosmological constant.
It can be positive or negative.
And we'll talk about it.
What it actually corresponds to is a modification of the,
of gravitational force law,
and depending on the sign of lambda,
it either adds an attraction or a repulsion.
But it's an attraction or repulsion which
is quite different than the Newtonian force law.
It's a force which grows with distance.
Instead of F equals one over R squared,
it's F proportional to R.
So we're going to talk about this later,
but for the time being,
it's just an ambiguity that was in Einstein's equations.
The numerical value of lambda
was known to be extremely small.
Einstein and everybody else at the time and for many,
many years
thought that there must be a
reason why this is not there.
Nobody knew any reason for it.
We know now that it is
there with a very small coefficient.
So this is called the cosmological constant,
but for the most part,
we're going to talk about
the theory without cosmological constant,
at least until we get to cosmology.
The reason is that the cosmological constant is so small
that the repulsive force that it creates
is completely insignificant until you go
out to distances which are cosmological,
until you go out to distances
of tens of billions of light years.
Billions of light years anyway.
Would it be fair to say that the first equation,
you start out by getting there by some
kind of tensor analysis of things that might work.
Then you must have to verify that.
This equation.
But you have to verify it with experiments.
That equation is not derived from first principles,
is it?
This equation.
Yes,
this equation.
I thought you were talking about Einstein's equation.
Oh,
this equation here.
No,
this is...
All right,
so let's go back a step.
What Einstein was looking to do
was to convert to tensor notation
equations which in certain
limits reproduced Newton's equations.
It was a guess.
Not that he had to
reproduce Newton's equations in those limits,
but that the right thing to
do was to look for tensor equations,
equations which would be true in any reference frame.
The left...
The right hand side here,
for very,
very slowly moving masses
and weak gravitational fields,
the right hand side here
is only significant
when you have two indices zero,
zero,
zero component,
and then it becomes the energy density.
The energy density on the right hand side here
with this kappa.
On the left hand side,
if you make the approximation that
the metric is not very distorted
from the flat space form,
that it's close to the flat space form,
and if you assume that
the metric of a static object
like a sun or something like that is static
and doesn't change with time,
then it's not hard to show that r zero,
zero,
what we're going to do is take the zero,
zero component,
of this equation.
Zero,
zero,
that means energy density on the right hand side,
and on the left hand side,
you work it out,
but what you find out
is that it's proportional
to some second derivative,
derivative with respect to x,
m squared,
space derivatives,
purely space derivatives.
In fact,
we can write it
in the form of
del squared,
it's got two derivatives in it,
of what?
Of g naught,
naught.
Now,
I'm probably missing a factor of two.
I always get the factor of two confused.
But if you remember,
g naught,
naught was very closely related
to the Newtonian potential.
So this just became the equation,
the Laplace equation,
or whatever it's called,
Poisson equation,
connecting the gravitational potential with rho.
Did he derive this equation
from first principles?
No.
He used a correspondence
with Newtonian gravity.
He made an assumption,
the assumption being
that the equations should have
the same form in every reference frame.
This was a big deal for Einstein.
He felt deep in his heart
that the equations should have
the same form in every reference frame.
You can't prove that.
You can postulate it
and see what you get.
What you got
was a tensor version
of Newtonian mechanics,
which would be true,
if it were true in any frame,
would be true in every frame.
Now,
it has,
of course,
empirical consequences.
It's not exactly Newton's theory.
It differs in various contexts.
It's empirical,
but the empirical consequences
are different when things move fast
or when matter
or the material that's gravitating
is so dense that it creates
very powerful gravitational fields.
Then it doesn't...
Newton and Einstein don't really agree,
and there Einstein wins empirically.
So...
Right.
You're perfectly right.
This didn't...
This wasn't entirely
just out of pure air.
It came from looking for
a particular realization
of tensor version
of Newton's equations.
Now,
let's...
Before...
Before we study
particular solutions
of these equations,
in particular,
the Schwarzschild solution,
which is a black hole,
before we enter into that,
which I want to at least start to do tonight,
I want to talk about
the way physicists today think
about the equivalence principle.
Remember I showed you
how Einstein thought about light falling.
He thought about light falling
by saying light in an ordinary reference frame,
an inertial reference frame,
moves in straight lines.
If it moves in straight lines
in an inertial frame,
then in an accelerated frame,
remember the elevator?
There's the elevator.
If it's accelerated upward,
then from inside the accelerator,
the light beam will seem to fall.
He wanted to generalize that idea.
That was a very simple idea,
good enough for a simple version
of elevator physics,
but he wanted to do much better than that.
What he realized is that
the equivalence principle,
what it said was,
first of all,
that physics should be the same
in all reference frames.
The equations should be the same
But beyond that,
he said if you choose coordinates,
now you can only do this locally,
remember you can't do this
over the whole space,
but if locally you choose coordinates
in which the metric is just equal
to the metric of special relativity,
in other words,
if you work with coordinates
which locally,
for which g mu nu
is equal to eta mu nu,
which is just equal to
one minus one minus one minus one,
then in the vicinity of that point,
the equations of physics
should have the same form
that they have in special relativity.
So here's what he said.
He said if we know equations
in special relativity,
we can take those equations
and try to make tensor equations
out of them so that they will be true
in any coordinate system,
and once we have those equations
in tensor form,
then we can just take them over
as they are into situations
where space might really be curved.
So what he was in effect saying
is that on small enough volumes,
small enough regions of space-time,
where curvature can't be detected,
same like the surface of the Earth,
a small patch of the surface of the Earth,
you can't detect curvature.
The motion of balls rolling
on the surface of the Earth
and so forth for small patches
looks exactly like the motion
of balls moving on a flat plane.
That's what Einstein said.
He said in space-time,
if you study regions of space-time
which are small enough
so that curvature is not important,
then the equations should have
the same form that they have
in special relativity.
Let's take the equations
from special relativity
and do something to them
so that they become tensor equations,
and then we'll know what equations
should be in general relativity.
Thank you.
Just the same tensor equations.
Let me give you an example.
We've already done that
with the motion of particles.
What's the law of motion
of a particle
in an inertial reference frame?
Well,
let's suppose there are no forces
acting on the particle.
No electric,
no magnetic forces,
just a force-free particle.
It moves in a straight line
with a constant velocity.
That's the same thing as saying
it moves in a straight line
through space-time.
It moves in a straight line
Einstein's generalization of that
is that particles move
on the straightest possible lines,
lines which locally look like
they're going straight ahead,
and that meant geodesics.
He didn't have to invent the force law.
He simply said,
I'll take what I know
from particles moving
without any gravitational forces on them,
that they move in perfectly straight lines,
and I will say locally,
along the trajectory,
as long as curvature is not important,
they'll just move straight ahead
exactly as if they were in flat space.
And that became his principle.
Particles move on geodesics.
From that,
we were able to
deduce the equation of motion
for particles,
the geodesic equation of motion,
and relate it to Newton's equation
for the motion of a particle
in a field of acceleration.
All right,
let me,
I want to go through another example
and show you how it works.
Wave motion.
We could use Maxwell's equations,
but Maxwell's equations
are a little bit complicated.
So let's take the wave motion
of a simpler field
than electric and magnetic fields.
A scalar field.
Last quarter,
when we did a little bit of
study of field theory,
we talked about the structure
in special relativity
of a scalar wave equation.
Was it last quarter?
I think it was
some number of quarters ago.
Right.
Maybe it was a half,
maybe it was a half ago.
Maybe it was three quarters ago.
I don't remember.
But we did talk about
wave equations.
Wave equations in special relativity.
Let's write down the wave equation
in special relativity
for a scalar field,
and then see what we can do
to turn it into a general relativity equation.
All right.
So let's start with waves
moving up and down one dimension.
Waves moving up and down
one dimension
with the speed of light.
All right.
Sometimes I'll use
the speed of light equal to one,
sometimes I won't.
For the moment,
let's let the speed of light
be general.
Anybody remember what the equation
of motion of a wave looks like,
a wave equation
for moving up and down a line?
It's got a field.
Let's call the field phi.
Just on a one-dimensional axis
to begin with.
Well,
it has some derivatives of phi,
time derivatives of phi
and space derivatives of phi.
And the form of the equation
is that the second derivative
of phi with respect to time squared,
this is the simplest possible wave equation,
that that is equal
to the second derivative of phi
with respect to,
let's call it,
the space coordinate x.
That,
no,
that's not quite right.
If we put the speed of light in,
let's see,
I think we have to put c squared here.
Is that right?
Yeah.
C squared here.
Then that describes waves,
two kinds of waves,
waves which can move to the left
or waves which can move to the right.
And the shape of the wave stays fixed.
That describes waves
which move sort of rigidly
down the axis,
preserving their shape,
either to the left or to the right.
Those are the two kinds of waves.
Of course,
and you can have
superpositions of them.
You can have wave,
you can have one wave moving to the right,
another wave moving to the right,
another wave moving to the left.
And what'll happen is they'll just pass
right through each other.
That's the wave equation
in one spatial dimension.
Now,
supposing I want my wave
to be moving not along the x-axis,
but along the y-axis.
What do I do?
Well,
I just substitute y for x.
What if I want my wave moving
in a general axis?
What do I have to do
to this wave equation
to describe
the general kind of wave
that can propagate
in three spatial dimensions?
And the answer is simple.
You just add d second phi
by dy squared
plus d second phi
by dz squared.
If I set c equal to one,
now let's set c equal to one
so that we go back to our,
uh,
notation that we're,
that we've become familiar with.
We set that equal to one.
We can then write this
in the form,
the second derivative of phi
with respect to x mu,
watch what I'm gonna do,
x nu
times
eta mu nu equals zero.
Let's see why that is.
Remember what eta mu nu is.
Its time-time component is one.
That means,
and of course this is contracted,
summed over mu and nu.
All right?
Let's start with mu and nu equal to zero.
In other words,
the time-time component.
Then what we'll get
is the second derivative of phi
with respect to t squared.
x naught is the same as t.
So,
eta naught naught,
that's one,
times second derivative of phi
with respect to t,
with respect to t again.
That's just second partial of phi
with respect to t squared.
Now,
what about eta one one?
First of all,
the off-diagonal terms are zero.
Eta,
just to remind you what eta is,
eta is the matrix
one minus one minus one minus one.
It has no off-diagonal elements.
So there are no terms here
in which,
for example,
contain a derivative with respect to x
times a derivative with respect to y,
or derivative sub t,
time,
no mixed ones.
All right,
now what about
eta one one?
What is eta one one?
Eta one one is minus one.
So,
let's see what we have.
From eta naught naught,
we have second phi
with respect to t squared.
And now what about eta one one?
That's minus one,
and it becomes second partial of phi
with respect to x one squared.
What about eta two two?
Same thing.
Plus the third term.
Well,
that's just this.
In particular,
if I transpose this to the other side
and set it equal to zero,
we've written the wave equation
in what looks like a nice tensor form.
But is it a tensor form?
It is not.
We have not yet succeeded
in making a tensor equation.
We've succeeded in making a nice formula,
but it's not a tensor equation.
So let's see why.
Let's see what this says more carefully.
Do it in two pieces.
First of all,
eta mu nu
is not a general tensor form,
but we might just want to replace this
by g mu nu.
That we can do.
So g mu nu,
we might put g mu nu here.
That looks more tensor-ish.
But it's still not a tensor equation.
And the reason is because
these are not covariant derivatives.
Let's write it this way.
We have g mu nu
d phi by,
let's start with d x nu.
Now,
I've obviously not written
the thing that's up above,
but let's multiply it
by d by d x mu.
Well,
that's clearly not the same
as the thing I've written here.
Why?
Because first of all,
g depends on position.
So when I differentiate
I'll get one term with
a derivative of g mu nu,
and another term of just
the type that I have here.
So I haven't re-
first of all,
this is not necessarily a tensor equation,
and second of all,
it's not this.
Okay?
But before I differentiate it
with respect to x mu,
let's erase this for a moment,
and let's forget g mu nu.
Is this a tensor?
d phi by d x nu?
Yes.
The derivative of a scalar
is a vector.
So the first step here
is a good tensor.
What happens if I multiply it by g mu nu?
Is it still a tensor?
Yeah.
It's a tensor now
with an upstairs index
instead of a downstairs index.
Now what happens if I differentiate,
and what is it?
It's a tensor,
but it's not a tensor.
But it's a vector.
In particular,
a vector
with one contravariant index.
Now what happens
if I try to differentiate it?
d by d x mu.
Is it a tensor now?
No.
What do I have to do
to make it a tensor?
Take the covariant derivative.
Incidentally,
I started with this equation here.
I could have taken the
d by d x mu outside.
Remember,
eta is a constant,
a bunch of constants.
You can differentiate eta
or not differentiate eta.
It doesn't make any difference.
But this as it stands
is not a tensor.
Incidentally,
how many,
well,
tensor or not,
how many exposed indices
does it have?
Well,
it's a tensor.
Zero.
Mu combines with this mu
and nu combines with this nu.
So if it were a tensor,
which it is not,
what kind of tensor would it be?
A scalar.
But this is not the right rule
for making a scalar out of a vector.
We have to replace this
by covariant derivative.
So we have to add to it
plus gamma mu.
Let's call this object here.
And we have to add
this vector here.
This is a vector,
let's call it v mu.
Yes,
We're covariantly differentiating
v mu with respect to x mu.
And so that means
we have to,
let's see,
we have to put another mu here,
a nu,
and a v nu,
I believe.
Which is just,
let's see if I've got it right.
And v is the phi,
I'm messing this up.
Let's go back.
You want the partial on the first one
and the gamma is
Yeah.
That's right.
We want partial on the first one
and then gamma mu.
v is the whole thing.
Yeah,
So then I should have
I should put v mu,
right?
Gamma mu,
no,
let's see,
I don't have it right.
We have to put some indices into the gamma here.
Gamma mu alpha alpha.
I think I have it right now.
Yeah.
The derivative with respect to x mu
gets replaced by a gamma mu.
The index mu is upstairs here,
an alpha and a v alpha here,
but then v alpha is what?
It is g alpha beta d phi by dx beta.
That's the covariant derivative.
We could write this in a very simple way.
We could write this in a very simple form.
Del mu,
covariant derivative
of g mu nu d phi by dx nu.
That's what it is.
But to work out what the covariant derivative is
means there's some Christoffel symbols.
This is a more complicated equation
than the equation that we started with,
but it's a tensor equation.
This is the wave equation
in curved coordinates.
In fact,
it's a wave equation
in curved coordinates
whether or not the space is flat.
It's a tensor equation.
If it's true in one frame of reference,
it's true in every frame of reference.
And this,
yeah?
Yeah,
it's equal to zero.
So,
all Einstein did
was he took
a standard wave equation,
Maxwell's equations,
rewrote them
in curvilinear coordinates,
and then said
I'm going to insist that I rewrite
them in a form in which
they have a tensor form
so that if they're true in one coordinate
system,
they're true in every coordinate system.
Right?
And how do they do it?
Basically,
the same rule.
Replace ordinary derivatives by covariant derivatives.
That's all.
Replace ordinary derivatives by covariant derivatives,
and that will give you
your equation.
Now,
the new equation
is more complicated,
and notice
in the equation,
the gravitational field appears.
Remember what gamma was.
Gamma played the role
of a kind of gravitational force.
When it was applied
to the motion of a particle,
gamma had
things like the derivatives
of the Newtonian potential in it.
So what appears over here
is a kind of gravitational force,
and the wave equation
contains
not only
what you might have expected,
namely some second derivatives of phi,
but it contains another term,
and that other term
is actually the gravitational force
on the wave field itself.
So,
that's how
ordinary,
simple waves
would interact with a gravitational field.
The effect of this,
of course,
is to bend waves.
This is a function of position.
The wave equation
now has a form
in which the various coefficients
are position dependent.
Do you know any situation
in which a wave equation
has position dependent coefficients
of various kinds?
Yeah.
Varying density,
varying dielectric constant,
and so forth.
And what is the effect
of varying density
or dielectric constant?
Well,
in particular,
it can bend the wave.
It can bend the wave.
When light enters water
non-perpendicularly,
it can bend the wave.
So the effect of
bending waves
And the effect of bending waves
is to change the frequency.
So,
we have a very simple equation
of bending waves
and the effect of bending waves
is to change the frequency
of the wave.
And what's the effect?
Well,
the effect of bending waves
is to change the frequency
of the wave.
So,
we have a very simple equation
and what is the effect
of bending waves?
Well,
the effect of bending waves
is to change the frequency
of the wave.
So,
we have a very simple equation
and what is the effect?
the effect of bending waves
is to change the frequency
of the wave.
So,
we have a very simple equation
of bending waves
and what is the effect?
Well,
the effect is to change
the frequency of
bending waves,
You see,
in technique you may have
already Hashimoto's
structure,
which is using
the way that the これ
I'm going to call the
I just wrote that V alpha is this.
So it's a hard to get
all of this in time-size conditions
that things ought to be independent of the coordinates,
right?
Yeah.
Right.
And more than that,
and more than that,
that locally in little patches in which are too small
for the curvature to be felt,
they should behave exactly
as if there was no gravitational field,
right?
So it's a little more than just what you said.
And a little more is
the content of the equivalence principle.
Yes,
sir?
Does covariant differentiation of a product have a little
rule?
Right.
So why,
I mean,
if you just write that in terms of
covariant derivatives,
the gene will be,
the mu goes outside,
doesn't it?
Yes,
it does.
Yeah.
So let's just write it in terms of covariant derivatives.
An obvious thing to write is that,
first of all,
that d phi by dx
mu is just del mu phi
for ordinary derivatives of a scalar,
okay?
And then what we had was
g mu nu del mu phi.
If you always
point out covariant derivatives satisfy the Leibniz rule.
The Leibniz rule being
that a covariant derivative of A times
B is equal to covariant derivative of A
times B plus A times covariant derivative of B.
Alright,
so the
covariant derivative of G times this is just two terms.
The first is G mu nu of X
times del nu del mu of phi.
And the second involves the covariant derivative
of G mu nu.
But what's the covariant derivative of G mu nu?
Zero.
So this is it.
This is the form of the wave equation.
But the reason I wrote it in a
more complicated way is I wanted to make very
explicit how the spatial variations of
G mu nu and the Christoffel symbols
enter into the equation and effectively
make it almost as though the curvature
of spacetime was a kind of
variable material that light was moving through.
That's not quite true,
but sort of like that.
Causes no trouble.
Let's leave that.
Okay.
Well,
I'm sorry...
That's basically just the state of gravity.
I'm gonna w咯 to the end
of this part of the lecture,
I don't have to point out questions,
But what weambles happened in this situation was important..
5-对
This driving equation is nice,
but it doesn't have any stresses at all.
We can use it in simple designer meow teste
What weambles happened in this situation?
it's equivalent to asking the question
supposing I have a scalar field that
satisfies such an equation with such a
property what do I put on the right-hand
side the right-hand side is energy
and momentum light has energy light has
momentum scalar wave fields have energy and
momentum so if I wanted to make a
nice little closed system of gravity
interacting with a wave field here I've
told you how gravity affects the wave field
now I have to tell you how the
wave field affects gravity okay so let's
see if we can figure that out let's
certainly what we're trying to do is tie
up the ends we have wave equations here
for Phi but we still need to figure out what
goes on in the wave field and we still
need to figure out what goes on in the
right-hand side if we want to figure
out how the wave field affects gravity
all right so that the the many many
ways to do this some sophisticated some not so
sophisticated and we're not
going to be sophisticated tonight
we want an energy momentum tensor that's made
up out of Phi now let's begin by
forgetting gravity altogether and just
imagine special relativity in other
words flat space-time and let's see if
we can figure out something about the
energy momentum tensor of a wave
field no gravity yet just ordinary flat
space-time special relativity we have a field Phi
and now we can go back to the
we can go back to ordinary
Cartesian coordinates in other words um Minkowski
coordinates and write the wave equation the
way that we had it before it really
can be written well we can write it as
what did we have before
eta mu nu no eta super mu nu
d mu d nu Phi equals zero right
that was the wave equation written in
a nice covariant notation but in flat
space no Christoffel symbols no varying metric
just a simple equation
just a mu nu can we guess what
the energy momentum tensor for Phi is well
first of all has to be a tensor so
it has to be a thing with two indices what
can we do to Phi to create and give
it some indices to give a to give an
expression involving Phi that would have
some indices well we can differentiate it
I'm interested in the thing with two
indices let's say team you knew so what
can I make I can make things like the
mu Phi the new Phi that's something I can
make what else
you
o
ou
by right okay one of the terms I'm
using something that I already know that I did
teach you previously let's see if I
learned that in grad in that course how
if you remember it.
Anybody remember what the energy
of a wave field is?
Just the energy.
What does the energy of a wave field have?
What's that?
Amplitude?
Take a look at this expression.
What does it do if phi changes sine?
What happens to this expression
if phi changes its sine?
It changes sine.
That means if I take a wave field,
if this were in the energy,
then a wave field which looks like this
would be a wave field
which might have positive energy
and a wave field which looks like this
would not have the same energy.
A wave field which is in every respect identical
except the sine of phi was changed
from phi to minus phi
would not have the same energy.
One would have positive energy,
one would have negative energy.
So one might expect then
that that is,
that is forbidden.
And it is forbidden.
The energy should be something
which doesn't change sine
when you change phi to minus phi.
It's like a harmonic oscillator.
Wave fields are very much like harmonic oscillators.
Harmonic oscillators have coordinates x.
The kinetic energy is x dot squared.
The potential energy is x squared.
If x changes sine,
nothing happens to the energy.
The energy is positive when the energy is positive.
The energy is positive when the energy is negative.
Whether you pull the spring out to the right
or whether you pull the spring out to the left.
The same is true of a violin string.
A violin string is a good example of a wave.
Would you expect a wave which looked like this
to have opposite energy from a wave
which looks like this?
No,
you wouldn't.
In fact,
they can go into each other.
They can vibrate into each other.
And so one expects on general grounds
that whatever the energy,
or in the energy momentum of a field phi is,
that it should not change sine
when you change the sine of phi.
Now what happens to this expression
if phi goes to minus phi?
Nothing happens.
It stays the same.
Why?
Hmm?
Because it's quadratic in phi.
If phi changes sine,
the mu phi changes sine,
the nu phi changes sine,
and the mu phi changes sine,
and the product doesn't change sine.
So a term like this is not expected
in the energy momentum tensor.
But these two terms are perfectly good.
We can add them together.
And we can add them together
with some unknown coefficient.
Let's put an unknown coefficient there.
What's a good number?
What's a good letter for an unknown coefficient?
C.
Thank you.
Good.
Now what I want to do
is I want to figure out
if there's any value of C
which will ensure that
that the continuity equation is satisfied.
The continuity equation is
d super mu,
t mu nu is equal to zero.
Now this is a funny looking expression.
Derivative,
you know what d sub mu means,
right?
That means derivative with respect to x mu.
And it's got a covariant index downstairs,
right?
d by dx mu.
What does a derivative differential sign
like this mean with an upstairs index?
You just raise the index.
What do you use for
the metric to raise the index?
Eta mu nu.
So this is a perfectly well-defined symbol
with an upstairs mu there.
It just means d super mu
equals eta mu nu d sub little nu.
The upstairs derivatives and the downstairs derivatives
are the same thing except for
some sign changes here and there.
All right.
So this is the continuity equation
or the conservation of energy momentum
in special relativity.
You can push the indices upstairs and downstairs.
I used to write it,
previously I wrote it this way,
but it's the same thing.
Indices can be moved upstairs and downstairs at will.
And here's my continuity equation.
We can also write this equation
in neater form.
We can just write eta mu nu on d nu
just turns this into d mu d mu phi.
One downstairs d mu,
one upstairs d mu.
That's what the eta mu nu does.
So here's what we have going for us.
Phi satisfies that equation.
And we want to find out
if there's a linear combination
of these two,
which is conserved.
If it is,
if there is,
it will give us a candidate
for the energy momentum tensor.
In fact,
it's unique.
Okay,
so let's just try it out.
Let's differentiate this.
Super mu.
T mu nu.
What do I get?
Apply it to the right-hand side here.
That gives me,
d mu,
d mu d nu,
now,
d mu phi d nu phi.
That's the first piece.
First term over here.
All right,
now,
this is a product.
Leibniz's rule can be applied.
What do I get?
I get d mu d mu phi.
Times d nu phi.
That's one term.
And what's the other term?
The other term is plus d mu phi,
d mu d nu phi.
That's when the d mu here
hits the second term.
Well,
what is this piece over here?
That's zero.
That's the wave equation.
So let's get rid of it.
Okay,
now let's,
we still have this term over here.
We still have to hit it with d mu.
d mu,
constant c,
eta mu nu,
d sigma phi,
d sigma phi.
What is that going to have?
Well,
d super mu,
eta mu nu,
what is that?
That's just d sub nu.
d sub nu.
What's it going to have?
It's going to have a term with d sigma phi,
and then a term with a mixed derivative,
d nu d sigma phi.
There'll be two of them.
Can you see why there are two of them?
One from hitting here,
and one from hitting here.
They're both the same.
You can juggle these indices upstairs and downstairs.
It doesn't cost anything.
So there are two terms,
each of which have the form d nu,
d sigma phi,
times d sigma phi.
Okay,
but this term is of
exactly the same form as this.
A derivative of phi,
and then,
here,
if I replace,
let's see,
if we replace sigma by mu,
they're exactly the same thing.
But we get two of these terms.
We get two of these terms,
and that means I want the factor of two someplace.
I want the,
let's see,
what are we doing?
What happened to c?
Hmm?
C,
you dropped it.
Yeah,
the question,
I know I dropped it,
but where did I drop it?
I think we want c equals a half.
With c equal a half,
just go through this,
go through it yourself.
With c equal a half,
this becomes an identity,
that this is equal to zero.
That's an identity for all phi,
oh,
for all phi which satisfy the wave equation.
I use the wave equation.
When I differentiated this term,
there was one term which was d mu,
d mu phi.
That was the wave equation.
Then there was another term,
and it canceled this.
It canceled the two terms from here,
that's why I had to put a half here.
All right,
go through that.
It's a little exercise,
not very hard.
If phi satisfies the wave equation,
then this object over
here satisfies the continuity equation.
Let's see.
Do I want a minus sign?
Yeah.
Minus sign.
Let's compute.
Now that we have it,
and it's unique,
there was no ambiguity.
It's quite unique.
Let's just see if we can recognize
what the energy density is.
Which term is the most important?
The energy density.
Zero,
zero.
Does it matter whether they're upstairs or downstairs?
It doesn't.
When you pull an upstairs index downstairs,
if it's a time index,
it doesn't change sign.
If it's a space index,
it does change sign.
But if we pull two time indices downstairs,
then certainly nothing happens to it.
So the energy density is either T naught naught
or T naught minus phi.
T sub naught naught.
Same thing.
And let's see what we get.
All right.
We have mu and nu both being time.
So what is this?
I'm now going to use the notation
X naught equals T,
time.
So what is this term over here?
Just the square of the time derivative of phi.
Not acceleration.
No.
It's just the square of the time derivative of phi.
Let's just call it phi dot squared.
Phi dot squared.
This is the energy momentum density.
Sorry.
It's the density of energy.
The density of energy.
Phi dot squared.
That's the first thing here.
Dot meaning derivative with respect to time.
And then minus one half.
And let's see what we have.
We have eta mu nu.
So we're interested in the time component.
The time component of it.
What is eta naught naught?
One.
So we just leave that alone.
And then we have phi dot squared.
Why phi dot squared?
If sigma,
the sigma is the same as
the sigma in the summed over.
If sigma is time,
then raising and lowering doesn't do anything.
Raising and lowering a time index doesn't change its sign.
Raising and lowering a space index does change its sign.
So we have phi dot times phi dot.
But then we also have
the space derivatives of phi here.
This could be x.
Then we would have derivative of
phi with respect to x squared.
But with a plus sign or a minus sign?
Minus sign.
Because.
Because pulling an index up and down changes its sign.
And then same thing with derivative of phi with respect to
y squared minus derivative of phi with respect to z squared.
Sorry,
derivative of phi with respect to z squared.
What do we get altogether?
We get.
We get phi dot squared
minus a half phi dot squared.
That's phi dot squared over 2.
And then the minus is here
and the minus here cancels each other.
And we get plus the derivative
of phi with respect to x squared.
Plus the derivative of phi with respect to y squared.
Plus the derivative of phi with respect to z squared.
And I think I left out a factor
of a half multiplying each one of these.
All times one half.
What is this?
This is the kinetic energy of the moving wave.
If we thought of it as a violin string,
it would be the kinetic energy of the violin string.
And this is the energy,
the potential energy in the violin string.
The stretching of the violin string away from
its equilibrium when the violin string is straight.
A straight violin string has no potential energy.
When the violin string has a derivative,
then it has potential energy.
So this is in fact the
correct expression for the energy density.
We could also work out all the
other components of the energy momentum tensor.
But why bother?
Here it is.
This is it.
You can go and figure out all of its components.
There is one ambiguity.
The one ambiguity is the
overall coefficient in front of it.
I could put a 10 in front of
it or a 100 in front of it.
And it would still satisfy the continuity equation.
Where is it?
It would still satisfy the continuity equation.
So there is an ambiguity.
But that ambiguity can,
and it is really there,
it's ambiguous,
but you can always absorb
it into the definition of phi.
Supposing I decided that the energy
momentum tensor should be 100 times this.
Well then I could redefine phi by taking
phi times 10 and calling it something new.
And then the new field would have an
energy momentum tensor which looked exactly like this.
So it's a matter of convention.
It's a bit of a matter of
convention about the definition of the field phi.
It is always defined so that the energy doesn't
have a factor of 100 or a factor of 7.
It's defined in such a way
that the coefficient there is 1.
Once you know it,
you can put it into the
right hand side of the equations here.
All right,
so you take this now.
Bodily.
Bring it over to here.
And it becomes the right hand side which tells gravity how
to respond to the energy and momentum in the wave field.
Yeah?
Maybe it's a real naive question,
but I read long ago that pressure
has something to do with general relativity.
Yes,
okay.
Pressure.
Pressure is simply defined in
terms of the energy momentum tensor.
Okay.
Right.
Okay,
I'll tell you what.
Pressure is a well-defined thing when a gas
or whatever it happens to be is isotropic.
If it's not isotropic.
Isotropic means you can't,
you know,
the molecules are moving as much this way as they
are this way as they are this way when it's isotropic.
If it's not isotropic,
then there are different components
of pressure in the various axes,
and you have to think about
something a little more complicated than pressure.
When a gas or a material or
whatever it happens to be is isotropic,
then the pressure is a well-defined thing,
the same in every direction.
And when the gas is isotropic,
it means that the energy momentum tensor,
it has a T00 here,
that's the energy density,
but then it has nothing in the off diagonals.
The off diagonals would render it not isotropic,
and the only elements it has are on the diagonal,
and those are called the pressure.
Or are they minus the pressure?
I think they're minus the pressure.
Oh.
The pressure or one-third the pressure.
No,
they're the pressure.
So the pressure is just defined
in terms of the energy momentum tensor.
Would a shear force be
an example of something off diagonal?
Yeah.
A shear force would be...
Right.
A shear force...
A stress,
a shear stress would be a non-diagonal component,
but it would be symmetric.
Right.
So you can see then that even in isotropic situations,
the pressure,
as well as the energy density,
really does enter into Einstein's equations.
Now,
when all the C's,
C's meaning the speeds of light,
not the C over there,
when the speeds of light are put into the equations,
the energy density is much,
much larger than the pressure.
Why?
Because energy density has C squared in front of it.
So typically,
unless you're in some situation where there
are things moving near the speed of light,
the energy densities are usually
much larger than the pressure.
Now,
for a box of photons,
where everything is moving with the speed of light,
pressures and energies can be
of the same order of magnitude.
But in any case,
in any case,
yes,
pressure enters into Einstein's equations,
as well as shear forces,
as well as...
What is a shear force?
A shear force is if you have a
block of material and you try to shear it,
you know,
you try to push one edge of it one
way and the other edge of it the other way,
that creates a kind of stress.
Right.
And that stress also enters into here.
It's non-diagonal elements of T mu nu.
So,
so,
yeah.
All right.
So that's,
in fact,
that's one of the things that Einstein discovered,
that energy,
momentum,
and stress and pressure are all parts
of the source of the gravitational field.
They're all sources of gravitational field.
Is it beyond more than it takes
a certain amount of energy to put right?
Let's say pressure into volume,
and you could just call that equal to a mass.
No,
it's more than that.
It is more than that.
Because it's off-diagonal.
Yeah,
for example.
Or,
for example,
if these coefficients were not all equal to each other,
different pressures in different directions,
they might add up to a given amount of energy,
but they would make the gravitational field do things which
were different than if they are equal to each other.
Right.
So that's the basic idea of the equivalence principle.
And,
you know,
like John Wheeler said,
well,
I'll just paraphrase what he said.
Energy and momentum tell the
gravitational field how to bend.
And the gravitational field,
well,
we,
yeah,
let's write it correctly now.
Del mu,
del mu,
which has all kinds of Christoffel symbols and other things.
The gravitational field tells the
wave field how to propagate.
That's how to propagate through space,
through the curve,
through the curvature of space.
And how does it do it?
It does it by Christoffel symbols and metrics.
And the metrics appearing within the equations here.
Okay,
any questions up until now?
Yeah.
I think I see how you
get an energy-momentum tensor from a potential,
from a stress.
From what?
From fluid motion,
from motion of charges.
How do you get an energy-momentum
tensor from a mass sitting somewhere else?
From mass?
From a blob of mass over here.
How do I know what the energy-momentum tensor is?
Einstein's equation exists at every point in space,
right?
Right.
It's a point equation.
Right,
but some energy over here creates an energy over here.
It doesn't create an energy over here.
I have a mass here
and mass is equivalent to energy.
So how do I calculate
all 16 terms of the stress,
of the energy-momentum tensor somewhere else?
There's zero.
If there's energy over here and only over here.
And a blob of mass here.
Yeah,
that's the energy,
then the stress tensor,
then the energy-momentum tensor is null.
non-zero where the mass is.
So there's,
the space can't be
curved.
No,
no,
wait,
wait.
That's two
different things.
Let's go back
a step.
Let's go back to Newton.
Or
not Newton,
but Newton a la place
en poisson.
Newton
a la place en poisson is
del squared phi
equals
4 pi,
4 pi
g rho
g rho.
Same equation as here,
at least in the appropriate
approximations.
Del squared phi is
r naught naught,
or something like that.
Alright,
now,
supposing there's some mass some place over here.
That's where rho is.
There's no rho over here,
there's no rho over here,
there's no rho over here.
But does that mean that phi,
that there is no phi over here?
No.
When you do this,
when you solve this equation,
you'll find
that there's phi all around
this object over here.
How do you see it?
Well,
one way to
remember it is to use Gauss's theorem
to tell you
that there's a gravitational
field.
You know,
you use Gauss's
theorem.
What this equation
is telling you is not that phi
is zero out here,
but that certain
combinations of its derivatives
are zero out here.
The fact that there's a source
determines a phi,
but it determines a phi in a way
in which this particular
expression vanishes outside.
And in fact,
what does it do?
It leads to the one over r squared,
or the one over r
force law,
one over r
potential energy law.
Same thing here.
This may be zero all over space
except it's a few points,
but the curvature
will be
distributed over space
in general.
Question?
If light has energy and momentum,
then it affects space curvature.
Does that mean that light
can affect the propagation
of light so they interfere and don't
obey superposition?
Yes.
Very good question.
Example.
Two light rays crossing each
other.
What do you call lines which are like this?
I forgot there's a word in elementary geometry.
Skew,
skew,
skew.
Two skew light rays going past each other.
They don't intersect,
but they would intersect if they,
you know,
just going past each other.
Each one causes
a gravitational field
which attracts the other one.
So instead of just going,
can I do this?
Let's see.
They go...
They attract each other.
Haven't they measured at very high energy levels
that photons do not interact
with other photons?
Yes,
yes,
yes.
Remember that Newton's constant is tiny.
It is very,
very hard in a laboratory
to measure the gravitational
interaction between
two
kilogram balls of iron.
A photon
or a light beam
has very,
very
little energy
and very,
very little mass.
Its energy divided by c squared
is its mass
and it's...
Remember,
it may be true that
E equals mc squared,
but it's also true that m
equals E over c squared.
So if you have some energy
of an ordinary kind,
ordinary magnitude,
the mass that it corresponds to is
minute,
very,
very small.
If you then say
that the gravitational interaction
between these two things
is their effective...
Let's write out what it would be.
It would be their effective masses...
This is terrible.
It would be their effective
masses m1,
m2
times Newton's constant
divided
by r squared.
r squared might be the distance of closest
approach of these two
light waves.
Now what is m1?
divided by c squared.
E of light beam
one times E of
light beam two
divided by c
to the fourth.
c to the
fourth.
c is three times ten to the eighth,
ten to the seventeen,
ten to the minus thirty-four
in the denominator.
Ten to the minus
thirty-four and
seven times ten to the minus eleven
in the numerator.
That's about ten to the minus ten.
Ten to the minus forty-four.
Ten to the minus forty-four
times the
energy divided by r squared.
So
in practice,
of course,
the interaction between
light waves is entirely completely
negligible.
You never have enough energy...
Yeah?
Maybe a historical question on the Cosmos
logical constant.
What you read in the
popular books is that Einstein was compelled
to put that in there to
keep the universe from collapsing.
As opposed to
how you described it earlier
where it fits right in
there.
Can you elaborate on that
maybe?
Yeah.
Okay.
Let's talk about the Cosmo...
Let's talk about the
Cosmological constant.
Okay.
So
we modify the equations
r mu nu
minus one half g mu nu
r
and then we add
to it
plus some lambda
times g mu nu
and we set that
equal to t mu nu
or k times t mu nu
or whatever.
One takes
the
constant of
r mu nu
and then we
multiply it by
the constant of
r mu nu
and then we
and then
we multiply it
by
the constant of
r mu nu
and then we
multiply it by
the
constant of
r mu nu
and then
we multiply it
by the constant of
r mu nu
and then we
multiply it by
the constant of
r mu nu
and then we
multiply it
by
r mu nu
because
is
the equation is telling me how phi out
here responds to the presence of a point mass.
But let's ask a different question.
Let's ask how phi responds to just a cosmological
constant.
What is phi like if there
was a cosmological constant with a Newtonian?
All
right.
The sine of lambda I'll figure out later.
Let's just be loose and sloppy with
the sine equals lambda.
I can find it.
Say it again.
Right,
right.
But look at it from
this point of view.
It's equivalent to just having a uniform mass density.
It's equivalent
to just having a uniform mass density.
It's equivalent to just having a uniform mass density.
It's equivalent to just putting a
uniform mass density spread all over space.
Now what's
the solution of this equation?
It's not phi equals zero.
It's not phi equals a constant.
For phi equals zero or a constant,
you would get zero on the left-hand side.
Yeah.
What
if I took the function x
squared plus y squared plus z squared?
What's its del squared?
It's a number.
Six,
right?
Differentiating x twice gives me two,
y twice gives me...
So this would be six.
So I think I want to
put a one over six lambda.
And then del squared of this,
if phi is equal to this,
del squared of this,
if phi is equal
to this,
then there would be apace space and that
there would be less space.
Right,
well got it.
One,
zero,
that's what it looks like
6 over lambda,
three times 10 to the recall.
Just to make it simple
as I did for the哈 knockingbox.
There would be no physics here,
there would be no
physics,
more of a lush sphere,
the quantoism to mansion,
liked it over MICAH's last word,
of which we are not familiar with yet,
but it gives us the component phi square
It's the gravitational potential.
What do you do with the potential?
You differentiate it
to find the force.
So let's find the components of force,
or strictly speaking
the acceleration of an object.
Phi has been defined
in such a way that its gradient is acceleration.
So here we are,
we have a particle over here,
here's the origin of coordinates.
What is the x component of force?
The x component of force
is the gradient of phi along
the x axis,
or maybe it's minus the gradient
of phi along the x axis.
Derivative of phi with respect to x is equal
to lambda over 6 times 2x,
right?
Or lambda
lambda x over 3.
What does that say?
That says that the x component
of force is proportional to x.
Pushing away,
well depending on the sign of lambda
and had I kept my sign
straight we would have gotten it right.
It's telling me that there's a component of force along
the radial direction.
The x component of force
is proportional to x,
the y component of force is proportional
to y.
And so it
corresponds to everything in the universe being pushed
away from the center by
a force proportional to the distance
and also proportional to the cosmological
constant.
Now you might ask,
wait a minute,
is there a special center?
The answer is no.
A force law like this where everything
is being pushed away from everything else,
if you sat at the center,
you would see everything being pushed
away.
But if you sat on one of
the particles that was being pushed away,
you would also see the original origin
being pushed away from you.
So in fact it's a force law which really
doesn't have a center.
It really just corresponds
to everything,
what it corresponds to is everything expanding.
Everything growing and the separation between all objects
accelerating outward.
So that's the cosmological constant.
And Newton
should have discovered it.
It shouldn't have taken Einstein.
Newton should have discovered it.
Well,
of course,
or maybe Laplace or maybe Poisson or whoever
it was who invented this kind of equation here.
They could have discovered it.
It was a possible thing in the equations.
They didn't.
But Einstein realized that there
was an ambiguity in the equations.
And
he,
for a while,
he entertained this.
Now notice you can put it
on the other side of the equation.
Minus lambda
g mu nu.
And you can therefore think of it
as part of the energy momentum tensor.
It's a part
of the energy momentum tensor which
is there even if nothing else is
there.
And so sometimes
the cosmological constant is a little bit schizophrenic.
It doesn't know which side of
the equation it wants to be on.
You can think of it as being on
the left side of the equation in which case
it's part of the geometry side of the equation.
Or you can put it on the
right hand side of the equation in which
case you can think of it as vacuum energy.
Energy that's
there when there's nothing else present.
You can either think of it as a
uniform distribution of mass or negative mass or positive
depending on the sign of
things which is pushing things out.
In other words,
a
funny form of energy.
Or you can include it on
the left hand side as a
funny piece in the geometry side of the equations.
That's up to you.
Yeah.
But it's numerical value in
the real world is extremely small.
Why is it so?
How do we know it's small?
It doesn't have any influence on
anything astronomically until the distance.
Remember it's a force which grows
with distance.
It only becomes
measurable and detectable
when the distance is out a billion light years.
A couple of billion light years then it becomes detectable.
My understanding was that if it was zero
that,
or put it another way,
that he introduced it
because if it wasn't present then he wouldn't
then the universe wouldn't
that his equation didn't have a static sign.
That's right.
Yeah.
There he did
make a mistake.
Here's what he said.
He said,
look,
the universe has been sitting here for a long time.
Why isn't everything crushing in?
Why isn't gravity pulling all the stars together and stuff?
There's got to be some compensating repulsive force.
So he introduced the cosmological constant
as a repulsion which would counteract
the attraction due to gravity.
And it was possible using the two of them together
to create an equilibrium
where the repulsive effect of
the cosmological constant would cancel
the attractive effect of gravity for just the right magnet.
It required a very delicate cancellation.
The cosmological constant
had to be just right.
But what he didn't realize was that it was an
unstable equilibrium.
That it was an
unstable and not a stable equilibrium.
Hmm?
Sort of an armistice.
Well,
it wasn't a very
an armistice.
It was a bad armistice because it had
had stability problems.
It was like you discover a rock
hovering above the earth somewheres.
What do you conclude?
You conclude there must be some
additional force to gravity which is holding
the rock from falling.
So you invent a linear force
which pushes the rock away
and there's some equilibrium point where
the attraction of gravity and the
repulsion of this new force
creates an equilibrium.
Now let's look at it for a minute.
It's interesting.
Gravity is attractive,
right?
Let's plot the potential energy.
Let's imagine.
Here's the earth.
Here's a rock.
The rock is noticed.
It's not hovering because
of centrifugal force.
It just hovers.
There must be some
repulsive force that's keeping it
from falling toward the earth.
Let's suppose it's of this kind,
of this cosmological constant
kind,
so that it has a force
which is proportional to distance.
Can everybody read that?
Force proportional
to distance?
Okay.
Let's plot the potential energy.
First of all,
there's the potential energy of the rock
due to the lump,
due to the earth.
What does that look like?
Potential energy.
Positive or negative?
Negative.
So it looks like
this.
Oops,
like that.
Now,
supposing this is a repulsive force,
then there's a potential energy associated
with it.
What does that potential energy look like?
Not a straight line.
The force is a straight line.
The potential
energy would be a parabola.
But would it be a
parabola going up or a parabola
going down?
Not if it's a repulsive force.
If it's a repulsive force,
remember,
things push toward lower energy.
It would look like this.
Now,
supposing your rock was right over here,
would it be in equilibrium?
It would be in equilibrium.
What if you gave it a little
bit of a push this way?
What if you gave it a
little bit of a push that
way?
That's exactly the situation that Einstein created
by balancing the cosmological constant
against ordinary gravity.
I don't know whether he noticed it or not.
It may be that he
didn't notice that it was unstable.
It may have been that he
noticed it was unstable and didn't care
or,
but,
he regarded it as his most foolish blunder.
But of course,
it was far from a blunder.
There really
is a cosmological constant.
What was a blunder was the
idea that it could be used to keep the universe
in equilibrium.
That was false.
But the idea that there should
and could be such a cosmological
constant in the equations,
that is certainly true.
Yeah?
Suppose the cosmological constant acted as an attractive
force.
Would that produce a specific origin?
No.
It would still be the same,
that there's no specific origin,
but what it would do,
it would enhance
the effect of gravity on pulling things together
and it would just create a crush.
Why wouldn't the forces
all act to direct toward a specific origin?
There's no specific origin,
but
we'll come to that.
That's why we're going to be studying
cosmology.
So that we can understand the geometry of a world
with such forces,
but without a center.
We'll come to that.
But not tonight.
Is it possible that the entire universe could be spinning
and centripetal forces causing things to fly apart?
No.
First of all,
we know experimentally that there's no
axis of rotation,
just observationally.
But even if there was some rotational axis,
when you go far enough out,
the universe can't be rotating with any very significant
angular velocity.
Why?
Imagine it had a fixed angular velocity.
When you go out far enough,
it will be exceeding the speed of light.
So you couldn't
have a global uniform universe
which was all in rotation.
At best you could have some small region in rotation,
and of course you do.
They're called galaxies.
But the galaxy
cannot act like an axis which drags everything
else with it,
just because of the speed of light constraint.
Unless of course the rotation is so small
that even out at the edges of the visible universe
the velocity is still so small that
it's well below the speed of light.
But that would really be observationally extremely small.
The angular frequency.
We would be unique,
wouldn't we?
Yes.
Yeah,
then that would place us
in the center.
Oh,
good.
Self-centered?
Going back to the energy momentum tensor,
can you talk about the consequences
of the off-diagonal terms?
Yeah.
I don't want to do that too much right now.
They create shear forces,
and they create
they're for example very
instrumental in creating gravitational waves.
Gravitational waves are kind of shear waves.
We haven't talked about them very much.
I'm not going to talk about them tonight,
but yeah,
they're extremely important
in creating gravitational radiation.
I'm not sure what to say about them.
Uh...
But for example,
you know,
there's no difference,
incidentally,
between
here is two things which sound entirely different.
Take a block of material and try to shear it.
Yeah,
so here it is.
We take a block of material
and we push this edge this
way and that edge that way
making sure,
well,
let's say we hold this edge down on the floor
glue it to the floor and push the top.
That creates some stress inside the block.
Now here's something that sounds entirely different.
Take the block
squeeze it this way and stretch it this way.
In fact,
they're identical to each other
except rotated by 45 degrees.
It's not hard to convince yourself that,
if you think about it a little bit
that
a squeezing this way and a
stretching this way is the same
as a shear along a 45 degree axis.
So what this means
is that off-diagonal elements
are the same as having
on-diagonal elements which are different from each other.
For example,
a positive and a negative on-diagonal element.
In any case,
we'll come back to that
shear and so forth.
It is important.
It does have all sorts of consequences
but it's not a good time for it now.
It requires a little more explanation.
Yeah?
Is there an intuitive solution to
these equations that sort of describes
a plan going around a sum that
gives us a little bit of sense
of the meaning of the
different matrix and what we sometimes feel like
Well,
okay.
The easy thing to do
is to work,
and we're going to do it,
it's not that easy,
but the
easier thing to do is to solve the equations
of gravity when the right-hand side here is
just a spherical mass,
the sun.
We can solve it.
We can find the metric.
We can calculate all the Christoffel symbols.
And we can calculate the motion of a small
planet traveling around the sun.
Absolutely.
The solution is called the Schwarzschild solution.
And it's the solution of a radially symmetric mass
outside the mass.
That's what we're going to do.
We're going to study that solution.
It is also the solution of a black hole.
The problem of solving
Einstein's equations for two masses,
both of which
are big enough to create a significant gravitational field,
you don't want to know.
I mean,
that's a job for a super computer.
Not for human equation solving.
Yeah?
It's kind of intriguing,
the idea of energy momentum
transfer for light being
very large.
So that skew beings would
light beings going past each
other would skew around each other.
You do that much better than I do.
Do it again.
Now you're on the spot.
But anyway,
doesn't that sort of imply that you could indeed
have high enough energy light density
so that...
I don't understand what I said.
...go in a complete circle the
way it does inside the Schwarzschild radius?
What I said was not that
light has a big energy momentum tensor.
I said it has a very small energy momentum tensor.
Yeah,
but...
Small because there are c-fourths in the denominator,
or c-squares in the denominator.
But in principle,
could you still have...
So you're asking the question...
...a bound ring of light or something like that?
Bound to what,
though?
Going in a circle.
For example,
around a star?
A black hole made out of photons.
Yeah.
You could certainly have a
light wave going around the
circular orbit around the black hole.
The trouble is,
the circular orbit
of a light ray
is unstable.
Again,
it's an unstable orbit,
so if it's...
If you have a mass,
a given mass,
and you consider a circular orbit
at a certain distance,
then the velocity of that circular orbit
is fixed by the distance,
by the parameter,
by the parameters of the mass and the distance.
So,
for example,
the Earth's distance from the Sun determines its velocity.
As you come in closer to the star,
or whatever it is,
the velocity gets larger.
If you have a real genuine black hole,
you can get in close enough to it,
not so close that you're trapped,
about three Schwarzschild radii away from it,
where there's a closed orbit of a light ray.
In other words,
a closed orbit where the velocity
is equal to the speed of light.
Um...
So there's one particular orbital distance
where a circular
light ray,
circular light,
circular path,
a light-like circular path can exist.
The problem is,
if it deviates just a little bit in toward,
then it gets sucked in,
and if it deviates a little bit outward,
So it's an unstable orbit.
So there's an unstable,
um,
orbit for a light ray outside a black hole.
What if you had two hypersonic...
If you were there,
would you just see a plane?
One of a kind.
If you were there,
would you just see a...
on that circle,
would you just see a plane
instead of the actual,
uh...
A plane?
You mean like an airplane?
The surface of the star would be...
It would look like a plane.
If you were in that circular orbit.
If you were on that circular orbit?
Well,
you wouldn't see any curvature
of that ceiling.
The star would just look like a different plane.
Well,
I'm not sure that,
I'm not sure that the light beams can see anything.
I would have to think
about what a very fast observer
moving around on close to that
light ray would see.
No,
say,
you didn't have to go as fast as you did
because the light that I'm taking,
you're just at that distance.
Then what it would look like is that...
If you're at that distance being supported
and kept from falling into the black hole,
you would just see in front of you
a great big horizon.
A big black...
A flash plane,
the surface of the star
would look like a flash plane?
Oh,
no,
not quite.
This orbit is not quite at the horizon.
It's,
uh...
The horizon
is,
uh,
it's three halves of the distance
to the horizon,
to be precise.
But I'm not...
Look,
when we get to the geometry of black holes,
you will understand a great deal about black holes
that you don't understand now,
and you'll understand
just how foolish your questions have been up till now.
That's my goal.
Okay.
I've got one.
I think that I'm using some stress-energy tensor
to have a special thing like this.
Um...
For ex...
Uh,
they do.
For example,
the sums
of the eigen...
the sums of the space-like eigenvalues
divided by three
is the pressure.
Um...
The time-like eigenvalue
is related to the,
um...
to the energy density
in a frame of reference,
moving,
moving with the fluid,
if it happens to be a fluid.
Uh...
If the eigenvalues
of the space-like...
You know,
it has four eigenvalues.
One in a time-like direction,
uh...
three in space-like directions.
If the three space-like eigenvalues
are all equal,
it means that in some frame of reference,
the fluid,
if...
Let's think of it as a fluid,
is isotropic.
Uh...
If they're different,
it means that there are some shear forces,
or squeezing and stretching.
Uh,
so yes,
they definitely do have meaning.
Um...
I mean,
they basically
characterize the,
uh...
the state of affairs.
Question.
Yeah.
The...
If you have an isolated
mass in space,
then you...
Do you adjust the...
Um...
the Riemann tensor
so that it's,
uh...
So the curvature is zero
at infinity?
Yes.
Then how do you do that
with the cosmological concept?
You don't.
No.
Good.
If you have a cosmological...
Excuse me.
If you have a cosmological
constant,
then the geometry that's associated
with it is not
flat at infinity.
It's what's called
de Sitter space,
or anti-de Sitter space,
and it's an entirely different kind of geometry.
So the answer is,
if there's a cosmological constant,
you don't adjust the geometry
so that the Riemann tensor is zero far away.
In fact,
if you have a cosmological constant...
Now,
okay,
let's go back.
Let's see...
Alright.
If we have a cosmological constant,
then we can set this equal to
lambda G mu nu.
I may have changed the sign of lambda,
but it doesn't matter.
Okay.
Now let's contract this equation
with G mu nu.
This becomes R.
This becomes minus
2R.
And what does this become?
4 lambda,
right?
Hmm?
4 lambda.
So we find that
minus R
is equal to 4...
or lambda is equal to...
or R is equal to minus 4 lambda.
In other words,
even if there's no matter around,
if all there is is cosmological constant,
then out to infinity
the curvature scalar is exactly
given by the cosmological constant.
If there is no matter around,
and only this,
then one would say that
that space
and spacetime
are uniformly curved.
Uniformly curved
because the Riemann scalar
is uniform everywhere
just given by the cosmological constant.
So,
I forgot what the question was,
but I think I answered it.
So,
I think I answered it.
You know,
are we assuming that
the universe is infinite?
No.
So,
we could have a model
of a finite universe
even with the cosmological constant
in the same context?
No.
Now,
yes,
you can have a model of one.
The question is,
real,
honest physics,
when everything is taken
into account,
what can you expect?
That's debatable.
But yes,
you can have a closed universe
with a cosmological constant.
Do we know enough now
to understand what the frame value is?
No,
not yet.
I think we need to...
Well,
we,
we need to...
No,
not yet.
Not yet.
Do we know enough to understand
what it is,
whether the universe is flat or not?
Space-time is flat or space is flat?
Space-time is flat.
Space-time is flat means it's just absolutely empty
and there is no energy or momentum
because if there were,
it just wouldn't be flat.
Not locally,
but at the universe.
At infinity.
Yes,
it just means
that,
yes,
it means that the geometry
or the metric
can be taken to just go
to eta mu nu,
far away.
That's all it means.
And it would be exactly the situation
whenever there are some concentrated masses
that create gravitational fields
that fall off
far away,
then space-time is
asymptotically flat,
is the right terminology.
Asymptotically flat just means
that the components of the metric
asymptotically
tend to eta mu nu.
But it's not obvious that that's true
because there's investigation...
You mean in the real world?
In the real world.
It's not true.
It's most definitely
not true.
Well,
I've found to be closer and closer...
What's that?
Investigation has shown that it's very,
very close to being true.
No,
no,
you're confusing the curvature of space
with the curvature of space-time.
Oh,
okay.
That's why I asked you,
do you mean space
or space-time?
Right.
Yeah,
we can...
I don't know
how much we're going to get into that this quarter
and how much we'll save it for next quarter.
But flat-space and flat-space-time
are two quite different things.
We will go through the Schwarzschild black hole
and the
Schwarzschild metric
and
and if I
have time,
a little bit about the
expanding universe.
But I think it will take a full two hours
to navigate through the Schwarzschild metric.
And really,
that's kind of the goal.
You know,
that's the real thing.
So I don't want to stop
before we do the Schwarzschild metric.
Right.
Okay.
So next week we...
No.
Yeah.
Next week,
yeah.
The preceding program is copyrighted by Stanford University.
Please visit us at
stanford.edu.