Stanford University.
I say,
okay,
let me read to you from the first paragraph.
Statistical mechanics is often thought of as a
theory of how atoms combine to form gases,
liquid solids,
and even plasmas and black body radiation.
But it is both more and less than that.
Statistical mechanics is a useful tool in many areas of science in which
a large number of variables have to be dealt with using statistical methods.
My son,
who studies neural networks,
uses it.
In fact,
about six months ago,
he called me up and says,
Pop,
do you ever hear of
this thing called the partition function?
And I said,
yeah,
I've heard of it.
And he said,
I'm just learning about it now because we
use it in the statistical properties of neural networks.
Free energy,
all those concepts that one often
thinks of in the context of physics.
But it's a much broader set of ideas than that.
So let me just continue with reading.
I have no doubt that some of the
financial wizards at AIG and Lehman Brothers used it.
So that was just to reinforce
what you asked me about derivatives.
Saying that statistical mechanics is the theory of gases is
rather like saying calculus is the theory of planetary orbits.
Really what it is,
is it's a mathematical structure.
It's a mathematical structure which,
of course,
has applications.
And if I had to put it in a nutshell,
in a very brief nutshell,
statistical mechanics is simply probability theory.
Now,
I personally have never understood
the difference between statistics and probability.
I'm so told there's some technical difference.
I guess there probably is,
but I don't know that difference.
But statistical mechanics is the application of probability.
Well,
statistical mechanics is probability theory.
It may be applied to
lots and lots of different situations.
But it's probability theory
under certain specific circumstances.
So I want to talk about
those circumstances a little bit first.
As I understand it,
the statistics is the purely mathematical part that doesn't
depend on whether or not the mapping to reality connects.
So the probability you are trying to
do something where you're predicting behavior of something.
Okay.
So if you're right,
and I have no reason to think that's true,
I don't think you're not,
and I understood exactly what you said,
statistical mechanics is a mathematical structure.
Okay?
So I suppose in that sense,
it's statistics.
The question is,
under what circumstances does it apply to reality?
And I want to talk about that a little bit.
But the real answer is very,
very difficult.
And I think,
to my knowledge,
it has never been completely sorted
out and proved in absolute rigor
that statistical mechanics as we define it
actually applies to any serious significant system
other than some very simple model systems.
But it's interesting to think about what
are the criteria and what are the circumstances
under which statistical mechanics,
as we normally think about it,
applies to systems,
to systems like a piece of chalk.
Let's hope,
let's hope,
pray.
Ah,
good.
It works.
So let's start with coin flipping.
Coin flipping,
you have a coin which has heads and tails,
and ordinarily,
under ordinary circumstances,
you would say that the probability for flipping is
that the probability of flipping a head is a half
and the probability of flipping a tail is a half.
They have equal probabilities,
and the probabilities sum to one,
so therefore it's a half and a half.
What right do you have to say that?
How can you prove that?
Well,
one simple argument,
which is rather convincing,
is that coins are symmetric,
apart from some little detailed differences
between the two sides of the coin.
And in fact,
of course,
because of the difference between
the two sides of the coin,
it's not absolutely true that the
probability is a half and a half.
One side may weigh a little more,
you know,
the mass distribution is slightly imbalanced
because on one side the carving is
a little bit different than the other,
but forget that.
Air resistance.
Yeah,
air resistance could have,
but if a coin was a really fair coin,
it means that it's so symmetric,
that you,
for the purposes of flipping the coin,
the two sides are exactly the same.
Somehow you can look at
it and tell which is which,
that's true,
but the paint that distinguishes the
two of them is so thin,
or the carving or whatever,
that it doesn't make any difference.
The symmetry between the two sides of the coin
ensure that the probabilities have to be the same.
And once they're the same,
it has to be a half a half.
Right?
Okay,
so that's straightforward.
There's a kind of mystery.
There's a notion of a priori probability.
A priori probability,
in this case,
because there is a symmetry.
Let me give you another example.
Let's take a die.
Die as in dice.
And let's color the faces of the die.
I want to color them rather than number them
for no important reason.
All right,
so there are six sides to a die.
And let's color them red,
yellow,
blue,
green,
orange,
purple.
Okay.
Now,
again,
the six sides of the die are symmetric.
There's a symmetry operation of just turning the die
through 90 degrees about various axes,
which takes any configuration of the die,
into some other configuration.
And that symmetry,
again,
ensures,
if you believe that the die is really symmetric,
if you believe that the die is symmetric enough,
then you're forced to believe that the answer is
that the probability of getting a,
let us say,
red,
or any other one of the colors,
is one sixth.
Right?
And that's a good argument.
But in most situations,
there aren't such symmetries.
So if there aren't such symmetries,
is there a notion to back
you up from where you can start,
your starting point for a discussion of probabilities,
a starting point which you can think of
as a priori probabilities?
The answer is not obviously,
but let's talk about it a little bit.
In particular,
let me give you a ridiculous kind of example.
Let's suppose I decided to take the die
and color it by replacing purple by red.
It now has five colors.
Red,
red,
yellow,
and so forth.
It now has five colors.
Now if I just write down the five colors,
and you stare at them,
you would have no reason to believe
that there's not a symmetry among them.
Just writing them down,
one after another,
of course,
one has more letters than the other,
but that's not the point.
You could number them if you liked.
You would say,
you might say,
look,
I have five possibilities.
Red,
yellow,
blue,
green,
oh there it is,
green and orange.
So what's the probability of flipping a red?
And the answer by the same logic,
or illogic,
would be one fifth.
But you know perfectly well that's not the answer.
Yeah?
Can't information theory make this rigorous
by defining the entropy functional?
Well,
we're going to spend a
lot of time doing exactly that.
But,
no.
In principle,
yes.
But in fact,
systems are too complicated
to easily prove that the conditions
for thermal equilibrium,
and so forth,
really apply.
Most systems are too complicated.
There's a few model systems
that you can actually prove the theorems about,
but in principle,
you can state the conditions,
but it's very,
very hard to prove them.
In any case,
here you have five colors,
and if you didn't know any better,
and you didn't know very much about the dye,
you would say,
that's one in five.
But of course,
the answer's not one in five.
The answer is two in six for red,
and one in six for yellow,
blue,
green,
and orange.
So,
what's going on?
Well,
the answer,
of course,
is that the real symmetry of the system
acts on the six faces,
not on the five colors.
But it's very easy to imagine
that a dye doesn't have a symmetry,
doesn't have any symmetry at all.
It could be weighted in some way
that's sort of off balance.
It could be an unfair dye,
weighted,
with extra weight in one corner,
or something like that.
And then,
where would you get your a priori probability from?
Well,
of course,
one way of getting the a priori probability
would just be to flip it a zillion times,
and after a zillion flips,
you could count how many of each kind you got.
But that's not what we're going to do.
We're not going to try to
study this air in this room
by doing a zillion replicas of the room.
I mean,
we will do that mathematically,
but not physically.
And so,
someplace else,
we have to get the basic ideas
of a priori probability
from.
You might go back a step
and say,
if the dye
is not really a fair dye,
then the probability is going to depend,
or may depend,
on all kinds of things.
It may depend on details,
such as the way the hand flips it,
the air currents in the room,
the nature of the surface,
that it may or may not bounce off,
all kinds of details
which are extraneous to the system itself.
In other words,
it may depend on the environment
as well as the system.
So,
the idea of an a priori probability
for the dye
may not be such a good idea after all.
You have mentioned the fact that you have
implicitly assumed a time symmetry
in which you can...
We are going to implicitly assume
time symmetry,
and in fact,
we're going to talk about that
sort of right now.
Let's add a dynamical element
to the idea,
which may help us get a handle
on this idea of a priori probability.
The cube here,
the dye,
let's think of it as a dynamical system.
A dynamical system means
one which changes with time
under some law of motion.
A law of motion
is simply an updating process.
It tells you if you
know the state of the system
at one instant of time,
it tells you what the instant...
what the state will be
in the next instant of time.
That's the idea of a law of motion.
An updating from one instant to the next.
Now,
of course,
with the motion of particles
and things like that,
the motion is nice and smooth
and continuous,
and you can subdivide the time
into infinitesimal elements.
But if we're talking about a dye,
the closest thing we could imagine to that
is that the dye executes operations
one per...
Now,
per what?
Per elementary time in it.
Per interval.
In other words,
we imagine dividing up time
into equal segments.
We will not take the limit.
And at each instant,
the dye rearranges itself
in a way that only depends
on what's showing at the top of the dye.
Okay,
so we could represent that law
and in this...
in previous versions of this class,
we have talked about this kind of thing
several times,
but you can represent
the motion of the dye
as a rule.
Okay,
so let's see.
I have some rules written down here.
Let me give you some rules.
Here's the first one.
If the top of the dye is red,
then in the next instant...
Let's see,
where is it?
Yeah.
Red goes to blue.
If it's blue,
blue goes to yellow.
If it's yellow,
yellow goes to green.
If it's green,
green goes to orange.
And if it's orange,
orange goes to purple.
And if it's purple,
purple goes back to red.
We could represent this
as a kind of diagram.
We could put six colors down.
Red,
blue,
yellow,
green,
orange,
purple.
And then just draw some arrows.
Red goes to blue,
blue goes to yellow,
yellow goes to green,
green goes to orange,
orange goes to purple,
purple goes back to red.
Okay?
That would be a complete dynamical theory
of a very,
very simple system,
the dyes,
the dye.
Okay?
Now,
supposing the motions occurred quickly.
Let's suppose they happened fast.
So fast that they happened,
let's say,
in less than a blink of an eye.
And now we ask,
I don't care whether the dye is weighted funny
or not weighted funny.
It doesn't matter.
This is the rules.
This is the rules of motion of the dye.
And it spends equal amounts of time
in between each successive motion.
Then it's pretty darn clear
that if I just randomly sample it
at an instant of time,
as it's going from one to the other very fast,
if I randomly sample it,
it's pretty darn clear that I will have
an equal probability of getting any one of the six,
one,
two,
three,
four,
five,
one,
two,
three,
four,
five,
six colors.
Right?
Just because they each spend
the same amount of time,
or each,
the dye spends the same amount of time
being in each one of these states.
So it's pretty darn clear,
I don't think I need to prove it,
that this would be a situation
in which
the probability would be one sixth,
as you would expect.
Now this is fairly robust.
We could replace this law by other laws.
Let's see,
I have another one.
I think I have two others written down.
Well,
we could just replace blue by green,
and green by blue,
and maybe change some other ones.
It wouldn't make any difference.
So there are many possible laws like this,
all of which would lead to the same one sixth.
So it's fairly robust in a sense.
But is it completely robust?
No.
I'll give you an example of a law
which gives a different answer,
or which doesn't give an answer altogether,
really,
that's the point.
Okay,
so here it is.
Red goes to blue.
Blue,
let's see,
what do I have here?
Blue goes to green.
And green goes back to red.
Yellow goes to purple.
Purple goes to,
what have I left out?
Orange.
And orange goes back to yellow.
All right,
now at every stage,
whatever the state of the system is,
it tells you what to do next.
There's nothing wrong with this rule.
It does have a funny property
relative to this one over here.
What is that funny property?
Well,
maybe the easiest way...
It has two orbits.
This has one orbit.
This has two orbits.
Or two cycles.
You might say cycles.
In fact,
if you graphed it,
you graphed it,
you might have red,
blue,
green,
back to red,
and yellow to purple,
to orange,
back to yellow.
Two distinct cycles.
Now,
there's no way that you can say,
there's no way a priori
to know what the probability is
that you're on this cycle or that cycle.
If you're on this cycle and
you know you're on this cycle,
and you whip around it real fast,
then obviously the probability is
one-third to be red,
blue,
or green,
and zero to be yellow,
purple,
or orange.
But on the other hand,
all you may have is also statistical knowledge,
where it came from,
let's not worry about now,
about whether you're on this cycle or this cycle.
And in that case,
it would be more complicated.
I'll leave it to you to calculate if it was,
of course,
if it was a half a half,
probability of a half of
this and a half of that,
then you would reduce yourself back to one-sixth.
But if it was probability
one-third to be on this cycle,
and two-thirds to be on that cycle,
then it would be more complicated.
I'm not going to work it out right now.
Okay,
so this is a counterexample
to the statement that there's equal a priori probabilities
for all configurations.
But this system,
or with this law of nature,
this law of motion,
there is something called a conserved quantity.
Let's define a quantity z.
Z is for zilch.
This is the zilch.
The zilch has a value either one or zero.
It's equal to one
for red,
blue,
or green.
And zilch is equal to zero
for yellow,
purple,
or orange.
Two distinct orbits
with two distinct values of the zilch.
The zilch is conserved.
What does it mean that it's conserved?
If it starts at a particular value,
it stays at that value endlessly.
So a conservation law,
in this context,
and really in all contexts,
means that the system breaks up into different orbits
with different values of the conserved quantity.
There may be many conserved quantities
for a complicated system.
And you have two possibilities.
One is to fix the zilch.
You measure it.
You know what it is.
If you know what it is,
then you just throw away all the other values
and you go back
to a somewhat smaller system,
in this case a system with three states,
but just repeat the story
and there will be equal a priori probabilities
of all of the states
with the same value of the conserved quantum number,
with the conserved quantities.
And as I said,
the other possibility is
you may only know statistical information
about these things,
in which case
you use that statistical information,
but statistical information
about the values of conserved quantities.
What's the most important conserved quantities in physics?
Well,
energy is going to be
the most important one for us.
Momentum is not going to play such a big role.
And the reason momentum doesn't play a big role
is because usually we're thinking about systems
which are contained
within containers.
In statistical mechanics,
we're usually thinking about gases
or liquids or whatever it is
contained in containers.
And of course,
when a molecule hits the wall,
it bounces off.
Of course,
it gives a little bit of momentum
to the box,
but we don't care that much about the box.
We don't try to keep track.
If I throw a tennis ball against a wall,
we don't have to remember
that the earth recoils a little bit.
It doesn't play any role
in what goes on with the tennis ball.
It's not important.
And so if we ignore the recoil of the box,
then momentum is not conserved
by virtue of hitting the sides of the box.
So momentum is not so important.
Electric charge can be a very important conserved quantity.
Angular momentum is much like
linear momentum,
also tends not to play a big role in general.
But it could.
I mean,
it could under certain circumstances.
So the rule is,
you take,
or a simple rule would be,
you take all of the conserved quantities,
you take all the conserved quantities,
and you fix them.
In other words,
you measure them
or some other way,
you know what they are,
and then you simply study
and you calculate them subject to the constraint
that the conserved quantities have certain values.
Okay?
That's essentially the structure of statistical mechanics.
Calculating probabilities of things
subject to constraints,
and those constraints usually take the form
that some quantity is fixed.
Some conserved quantity is fixed,
one or more.
Alright,
let me give you an example
that we could make up using dice.
Die,
one die.
No.
Well,
okay.
Let's make up an example involving two dice.
Now I'm going to number the sides.
One,
two,
three,
four,
five,
six.
Of course,
this one also has a four,
five,
and a six,
but you can't see it.
And this one also has a one,
two,
and three,
and you can't see it.
And the rule is now,
they interact with each other.
Interacting with each other means
that when one flips,
the other is also forced to flip.
And the rule is,
they flip in such a way
that the sum of the numbers
on the two of them doesn't change.
For example,
in this case,
we start with two and six.
From two and six,
we can flip in a way
that can bring us to what?
It can bring us to four and four.
It can bring us to one and seven,
except there is no seven.
It can bring us to three and five,
but it cannot bring us to one and two.
So that's a rule,
and we can write that as a conservation law.
For each value of the total number,
there would be a number,
and we would have a closed cycle.
Because you can't get off the cycle,
you can't change the total...
I don't know what to call the number here.
That's another generalized zilch.
The generalized zilch here cannot change,
and so therefore,
the...
Let's see,
how many possibilities are there
for the conserved quantity?
You can have one and one,
you can have two.
Conserved quantity can be two,
it can be three,
and what's the largest value it can have?
Twelve.
Okay.
Then it has to be seven in order to...
Well,
if it was seven,
then you could...
If any one,
two,
three,
four,
five was back in,
subtracting from seven would give you the other...
No.
You'd still use all sides of it.
Two is just very constraining.
Two is very constraining,
yeah.
There's only one configuration.
It happens there's only one configuration.
Could you argue there's two?
Hm?
Could you argue there's two
because there's two guys?
No,
they both have to have one.
That's one configuration.
This one being one and this one being one...
I was thinking of like 11,
where one's five and the other's six,
but they switch.
That there are two.
There are two ways of making that.
Yeah,
there's two ways of making 11.
But only one way of making 12.
But in rotational symmetry.
No,
okay.
Just the only thing that
counts is the number on top.
All right,
you get the point.
so I haven't told you what
the multiplicity of each value is.
This is only one here,
only one here,
one configuration.
Here,
what's a three?
You can do with a one and
a two or a two and a one.
I think those are the only two ways.
Is that right?
Right.
What about a four?
I think that's right.
So there's a multiplicity of ways of doing it,
but each one of these numbers,
has associated with it a cycle.
Let's,
for example,
the two cycle.
The cycle associated with two.
What is that?
It...
Yeah,
you know it.
Okay.
Yeah,
11 goes to 11.
That's all that can happen.
In other words,
it stays the same.
Stays the same.
What about the three?
How many possibilities are there?
What are they?
Let's see.
One two goes to one two.
Or one two goes to two one.
Both of them are possible.
So I think there's two,
yeah.
So I think...
What do we say?
Oh,
sorry.
This is the two cycle.
There are three states of the three cycle.
What are they?
No,
no,
no.
Two states of the three cycle.
Yeah.
So it's one of these jobs like that.
One goes to the other.
The other comes back to it.
Two possible cycles.
Or...
You just come back to the same thing.
Okay.
One of the other.
And so forth.
There are a bunch of different disconnected orbits.
The orbits in this case would be characterized
by the value of this number.
And once you fix it,
then you can throw away all the others
and concentrate on the little subsystem which is...
which has a particular value of the conserved numbers.
All right.
Is that clear?
The most important...
Quantum...
I keep saying quantum number.
The most important conserved quantity is energy.
And that's the one where most
of our focus is going to be.
There are others.
For example,
in chemistry,
there are a lot of conserved things.
The amount of each or
the number of atoms of each...
The number of atoms of
each element are conserved in chemistry.
Okay.
In nuclear physics,
of course,
that's not true.
But the total number of protons plus neutrons is conserved.
So there are other conserved quantities.
But as I said,
for the most part,
energy will be our most important...
Oh,
oh,
sorry.
Sorry,
sorry,
sorry.
Let's go back a step.
Let's go back a step to information.
Information plays a very important role in what's going on.
I gave you a counterexample to the...
To the robustness of this,
namely the existence of conserved quantum numbers,
conserved quantities.
But obviously it's not really a counterexample.
You just have to generalize a little bit.
But let me give you now
an example which is really much worse.
And the much worse example goes like this.
Red goes to red.
Yellow goes to red.
Blue goes to red.
What do you think green goes to?
Red.
Orange goes to red.
Is there another one?
Yeah,
blue.
Blue goes to red.
Purple.
Yeah,
purple,
purple.
Good.
Purple goes to red.
That's a perfectly good deterministic law.
It tells you what happens next.
No matter where you start,
you just get red.
All right?
You start the system.
You start the system out somewheres.
Okay?
There are no conserved quantities here.
No conserved quantities.
There couldn't be.
If there was any conserved quantity,
it's very quickly...
There's obviously no conserved quantity.
They all have the same value because they...
Or whatever quantity you pick because
they can all get to red.
So they have to have the same
value of whatever it is as red does.
So there's no conserved quantity.
That's not the problem here.
On the other hand,
it's certainly true that at
least over reasonable lengths of time...
Remember,
this thing happens fast.
Blip,
blip,
blip.
If you intervene with the system,
what's the most likely thing that you find?
Red.
In fact,
not only is it the most likely,
it's overwhelmingly more likely.
It's infinitely more likely.
You will simply find red.
You won't find any of the others.
Here's an example where there are no conserved quantities,
but it is not true,
nevertheless,
that there is equal a priori probability
of all of the different
values of the color index here.
What's wrong with this example?
Well,
there's nothing really wrong with it.
It's a possible world,
but it doesn't behave the way real dynamical systems do.
Real dynamical systems have something that
I always call the conservation of information,
but you could equally well
call it the conservation of distinctions.
What it says in this simple context
is that distinctions between configurations don't disappear.
Distinct beginnings always give you distinct outputs.
Distinct starting points always give you distinct...
...different outputs.
And not only that,
if you trace backward,
first of all,
it's deterministic,
which means no matter where you start,
you get to a very definite place after each instant.
And distinctions don't merge.
In other words,
what this would look like would be red goes...
Let's see how to draw it.
Red goes to red,
yellow goes to red.
Obviously what happens here is
the different trajectories all merge.
They all merge and come together with red.
No matter what you start with,
red,
yellow,
whatever,
you get out red.
So in this case,
the trajectories just merge together,
and because they merge together,
initial distinctions are lost.
You can call that loss of information.
You can call it loss of distinctions.
You can call it the
violation of the conservation of information.
How about irreversibility?
You can call it irreversibility,
but irreversibility,
it is a form of irreversibility,
but I don't want to
confuse it with thermodynamic irreversibility.
Thermodynamic irreversibility is a different thing,
and so I didn't want to call it that,
but it is...
It's sort of the deepest form of irreversibility.
Laws of physics which lead deterministically to outputs,
but the output doesn't determine the input.
You can't get back to the input.
Loss of information.
In this case here,
it's quite obvious that the a priori probability
of the different starting points is not equal.
So that is not equal.
Yeah,
the initial...
The a priori probability.
So that's another counterexample,
and that's a more dangerous kind of counterexample.
Dangerous in the sense that if
you had a system like that,
it would not satisfy the rules of statistical mechanics.
The rules of statistical mechanics are fundamentally based
on the idea that the microscopic laws of physics,
laws of physics which govern...
At the deepest level,
and we're going to be
mainly talking about classical physics here,
at the deepest level,
the molecular level,
or the atomic level,
or the elementary particle level,
or whatever level we have to
get to to understand the system,
that the laws are consistent
with the conservation of distinctions,
or the conservation of...
Are we saying that the sample
size is not going to change?
The sample size is not going to change.
No.
Okay.
If you mean by the sample size,
the volume of the system,
no.
Yeah?
Can you describe this as saying it's a one-to-one function?
Yeah.
Okay.
Is this going to be a strong restriction?
Absolutely.
Without it,
we would get nowhere.
And what about its physical...
Is it a good physical assumption?
Yes.
It's not only a good physical assumption,
it's a consequence of the
basic principles of classical mechanics,
and all classical physics.
All classical physics is dependent on it.
So does that mean that if
you're outside of the realm of classical...
No,
no.
There's a quantum mechanical version of it.
There is a quantum mechanical version of it.
In classical physics,
it's called Leoville's theorem.
I'm going to tell you what it is.
In quantum mechanics,
it's called unitarity,
but we're not going to
be doing very much quantum mechanics.
If we do any quantum mechanics,
we'll probably do some,
but we'll do a sort of seat of the pants.
We won't use the real principles of quantum mechanics,
but...
But the classical version of it,
I will basically tell you right now.
I have a question.
Yeah.
So that's either way,
right?
You do one tempo to two different states?
Yeah.
I mean,
as somebody said back there,
the conservation of distinctions means
that the mapping is one-to-one.
So that example of the summations
of the die is not a lab?
Oh,
yes.
The summation of a...
Well,
because one state...
That may or may not.
Because one state of one,
two,
that should go back to the same
state if we go to a different state.
You have to postulate a law,
all right?
Now,
if in each sector,
each sector means each value of the conserved quantities,
if the diagram in that sector
is a closed loop like that,
then you're in business.
That conserves distinctions.
If you start here,
you get to here.
You can tell not only where you're going,
but where you came from.
That's the characteristic of
a system which conserves distinctions.
If you know where you are,
you not only know where you're going to be next,
but you know where you are last.
Okay?
Now,
in this case,
if you know you're at red,
you can ask,
where am I going next?
The answer is red.
Where did I come from?
Beats me.
I don't know.
No way to tell.
So,
yeah?
You started off by talking about coin flipping.
And this seems to be a very interesting topic.
It seems to be going quite a different way.
We're not talking about random outcomes of something.
We're talking about quite deterministic rules.
Yes,
we're talking,
yes.
The world,
at least the classical world,
is deterministic.
It's only apparently statistical.
It's apparently statistical,
and we're going to talk about
the conditions why it is apparently statistical.
But I will tell you right now,
it's apparently,
a system is apparently statistical,
typically because it's coupled.
It's coupled to a much,
much bigger system about which you know very little.
And a heat bath,
in other words.
And you don't know enough about the
heat bath to specify the details of it.
But that's always the case.
I mean,
that things are random.
Not always the case,
but it's the case in
classical physics that things are random,
not because there's any intrinsic
randomness in the laws of physics,
but because you simply don't know enough.
You don't specify.
We're going to talk about that.
That's the basic idea of entropy.
All right,
in any case,
this principle of the conservation
of distinctions is so important.
It's rarely mentioned because it is so
deeply assumed by everybody who does classical physics
that it is rarely mentioned as
one of the laws of thermodynamics.
I would call it the zeroth law of thermodynamics,
except the zeroth law of thermodynamics
is also used for something else.
So we could call it
the minus first law of thermodynamics.
And it is the most central fact that must
be true for thermodynamics or statistical mechanics to make sense
and for it to predict the consequences of thermodynamics,
the theory of heat.
So it's a...
It's,
as I say,
built into the structure of classical mechanics.
What is the relevant statement about classical mechanics?
Classical mechanics,
of course,
does not deal with these very,
very trivial...
I use these as illustration,
illustration of a concept.
But of course,
classical mechanics deals with continuous systems,
systems of coordinates and momenta.
For our purposes now,
momentum can just be mass times velocity.
And each coordinate of a system
has associated with it a momentum,
namely its time derivative times the mass of the object.
And...
But of course,
there is a deeper,
more profound meaning to the idea of a momentum.
We've talked about it in classical mechanics.
For the purpose of this class,
momentum can just mean...
It's a very,
very simple definition of momentum.
And it's a state of momentum with conventional momentum,
although there may be situations where you want to
keep track of a more profound definition of momentum.
All right.
So what is the state of a system?
The state of the system for this simple example
of a single die was just a label color,
state the color.
If you know the color,
you know it comes next
and you know it comes before.
If it's a case of two dice,
then it's a pair.
The state of the system is
labeled by a pair of colors.
What about a single point particle?
A single point particle is
labeled by a collection of coordinates,
x,
y,
and z,
or x1,
x2,
x3,
x,
y,
and z.
That's the coordinates of the
particle and the corresponding momentum,
the x,
y,
and z components of the momentum.
Equivalently,
the x,
y,
and z components of the velocity.
But for reasons that go
into the depths of classical mechanics,
the momenta are the right things to describe it by.
The symbol for momenta,
the historical symbol for momentum,
is p,
and the historical symbol for coordinates is,
of course,
x.
There are three p's and three x's for each particle,
so I draw it as just
a p and an x plane.
But,
of course,
for an ordinary particle,
there would be a three-dimensional p space
and a three-dimensional x plane.
So it gets complicated fast.
The picture of the phase space,
this is called the phase space,
the phase space of a classical particle is six-dimensional.
What is the x space called?
Just x by itself,
without worrying about p.
It's called a configuration space.
So the configuration space is the space of x's,
the phase space is the space of x's and p's.
But what constitutes a state of
a particle is not an x,
but an x and a p.
And the reason is that in order to
say where a particle is going to be next,
you not only have to know where it is,
but you have to know how it's moving.
You have to know both its position and its momentum,
or the position and velocity.
So for a single particle,
the x's and the p's,
are like the color of the surface of the dice.
It labels a state of the particle.
For many particle systems,
there are many x's and many p's.
If there are ten particles,
how many x's are there?
Thirty.
x,
y,
and z for all ten particles.
px,
py,
and pz for all ten particles.
So what do we say?
There were thirty x's,
thirty p's,
so for ten particles,
sixty coordinates to the phase space.
And so it gets complicated fast.
For a system of ten to the twenty-third particles,
I won't try to draw it.
It's six times ten to the twenty-third dimensional space.
But now,
what does it mean to say,
well first of all,
what is an orbit?
What is a history?
A starting point,
which could be like the analog of starting with red,
is just a starting point in this phase space.
And then the equations of motion,
either Newton's equations or whatever
equations are governing the system,
allow you to follow it.
So you follow it with time.
These little ticks here could be microseconds.
But of course the motion is continuous,
but you could nevertheless,
you could divide it up into microseconds if you like,
or what's smaller,
nanoseconds,
or whatever you want to do,
and draw the trajectory.
And that's the trajectory in the phase space.
It's not the trajectory of the object in space,
it's the trajectory through this phase space.
Wherever you start,
oh,
there are various kinds of situations,
and we can talk about them.
In some of them,
the trajectories just wander off and go to infinity.
For example,
just for a free particle,
a free particle,
if you give it a shove,
it just goes off to infinity.
Its momentum doesn't change,
so p is constant,
but x just goes off to infinity.
But for the kinds of systems we're interested in,
the systems which are contained within finite boxes,
as a rule,
the system will,
will not leak off to infinity,
but it will somehow usually wind up coming back,
or perhaps not coming back to exactly the same point,
but it's,
that's a bad drawing.
That's not a good drawing,
because it illustrates something exactly
the thing which doesn't happen.
It illustrates exactly,
the problem,
the problem is two dimensions,
it's too low a dimension to draw a good picture.
Okay,
what doesn't happen,
and now this is a theorem of classical mechanics,
and it has several pieces to it.
The first statement is that trajectories don't merge.
Never happens.
All right?
This is the analog of saying,
that distinctions are preserved.
Distinctions are conserved.
The two different starting points never
lead to the same end point.
Okay?
And also the opposite is true.
Of course,
this wouldn't make any sense at all.
A given starting point splits in two.
What on earth would that mean?
You start at some given starting point,
and you,
that would mean it's not deterministic.
It would mean you don't know where you go next
when you get to this point over here.
Those things don't happen.
Trajectories don't cross.
Number one,
they don't cross.
And number two,
they don't merge.
So a trajectory doesn't cross like that.
They never do that.
And they never merge.
Now there can be conserved quantities.
In other words,
the trajectories can be labeled,
for example,
with values of energy.
The energy doesn't change along a trajectory.
It's much like the zilch.
It doesn't change along the trajectory.
And so the different trajectories in general,
whatever they do,
may be labeled by the energy.
And that energy doesn't change.
You pick it once and for all,
and it stays that way.
So that's,
again,
what is that called?
That's called the conservation of energy.
Yeah?
Does the orbit include what happens
if you go back in time also?
Yeah,
well,
of course,
that's up to you
how you want to define it.
But yes,
you can think of it
as going backward in time also.
There really is no starting point.
No,
no,
no.
But you could,
for convenience,
say,
let's consider all the motions
that start out at time t equals 0.
Of course,
that allows you to start
anywheres.
It allows you to start anywheres.
And so there's lots and lots of trajectories.
But yes,
they can all also go backward,
and you could label a whole thing by,
not label a whole thing,
but you could draw the whole entire trajectory,
both going backward and forward.
An example,
just as a simple example,
which is too simple for any interesting
statistical purposes,
a harmonic oscillator,
where you have momentum,
let's see,
position,
which did I do?
I guess I did momentum and position.
For a harmonic oscillator,
the trajectory is just a,
it's not a very good ellipse.
It's intended to be an ellipse.
The center of the ellipse
is at the center of the diagram.
And the object,
and the point in phase space
just goes around an ellipse.
If you projected it onto the x-axis,
the motion would just be going up and down
as an oscillator.
If you projected onto the momentum axis,
which is the same as velocity,
it would also be going back and forth.
But there are many trajectories.
And what distinguishes the,
yeah,
what distinguishes these different trajectories?
The energy.
The energy of the oscillator.
And also where you started them.
But,
where they were at time t equals zero.
But these are the different trajectories.
And as you can see,
they don't cross.
But that's a general principle.
So,
first of all,
there's the principle from classical mechanics
that trajectories never cross or merge.
Now that's not quite good enough for us.
Here's a situation that still could happen
even though trajectories don't merge or cross.
You could have a situation
which in practical,
in a practical sense,
is as bad as merging.
Namely,
where the trajectories very rapidly come together.
They don't quite ever merge,
but perhaps they get exponentially closer and closer.
All trajectories getting closer and closer.
Then for practical purposes,
you would lose distinctions.
No matter how good your resolving power was,
wait long enough and you lose the distinction
between these different trajectories,
at least from a practical point of view.
That doesn't happen.
Trajectories don't merge like that.
Either really merge in this sense,
or do this kind of thing,
which may look to you or
to your eye the same as this,
but you can imagine the difference.
Here trajectories are just coming together asymptotically.
That doesn't happen.
The theorem,
this is called Leoville's theorem.
We're not going to prove it.
I don't remember if we proved
it in the classical mechanics class.
It's called Leoville's theorem.
Not Louisville,
but Leoville.
L-I.
Leoville's theorem.
Leoville's theorem says the following,
that if you start with all of the points
in a patch of phase space,
take all the points in a patch of phase space,
start out the system at time t equals zero,
and follow each one of them
for a certain length of time,
the volume of the patch of
phase space doesn't change with time.
The volume stays the same.
That says that even if
the points in the phase space
might contract in one dimension,
they will spread out in the other dimension,
in the other direction.
And in that sense,
distinctions are preserved.
The volume in phase space is conserved,
and that's another,
that's the continuous version
of the idea that convergence of trajectories doesn't happen.
That,
if you like,
that information is not lost.
Or that distinctions are not lost.
Yeah?
Could you preserve the area,
but have it such that,
it's so complicated that it fills up a huge...
Yes.
That's the second law,
yes.
That's exactly right.
That is the second law of thermodynamics.
That that,
well,
the increase of entropy is exactly that.
But is that the reverse of this merging?
I mean,
you say that it's not going to merge,
it's over the top.
Well...
If it merged,
picture backwards,
would that give you the...
We will come to this.
This is an important point,
that,
and let me state it for
the rest of the class here.
The question was,
can it happen,
and the answer is it almost always happens
for interesting systems of sufficient complexity,
where can it happen that the volume of this region
does stay conserved,
but it sort of branches out in some horrible,
fractalated...
I don't know how to draw it.
I mean,
I'm not very good at drawing fractals.
In such a way that it eventually,
apparently,
fills up the whole phase space.
And the answer is yes.
The answer is yes,
that does tend to happen.
No.
That cannot happen.
It preserves its topology.
Yeah.
There are no mergers,
but chaos happens.
This is called chaos when this happens.
What's required for the...
This is a theorem.
What's the requirement?
Say it again.
What are the possible axioms to prove the theorem?
The Lagrangian form of classical mechanics,
either the Lagrangian form,
the Hamiltonian form,
or the principle of least action.
Okay?
So it all traces back ultimately
to the principle of least action,
or if you like,
Lagrange or Hamilton's forms of equations
of classical mechanics.
Does the volume correspond to a known physical
certain quality?
Yes.
Well,
yes and no.
It's connected with entropy,
but entropy is a...
is a subtle thing.
All right.
Let me stay with the bottom line is.
The bottom line is that
if we have a system
which is enclosed
so that it doesn't escape away to infinity,
and it has the property,
shares the property
with these kinds of systems,
the kind of systems that are represented by cycles,
namely,
that there are no mergers
and no splittings
and that sort of thing,
conservation of information,
then,
if the system moves through the phase space fast enough,
or in other words,
or equivalently,
if you wait and average over long enough times,
then there is equal a priori probability,
subject to the constraints,
subject to the constraint
of the conservation of information,
subject to the constraint of energy,
which means that you study only
surfaces in this phase space
which correspond to fixed energy.
Fixed energy might correspond to
a surface in the phase space,
moving around the subspace of the phase space,
then a priori probabilities are simply uniform
in the phase space.
It's another way of saying that
if you time average
things over times long
by comparison with some appropriate time,
then the average over time
is simply the average over the phase space,
or equivalently,
equal a priori probabilities
to every point on the phase space,
subject to the constraints.
So that provides you,
Leoville's theorem provides you
with kind of the
um,
basic notion of a priori probability,
equal statistical weights
to every point in the phase space,
um,
measured by the volume,
or every volume of phase space
of the same volume has equal probability.
So in some sense it doesn't have a different density.
Yeah,
that's right.
The density is uniform
on the phase space.
The sort of a priori probability density
is uniform on the phase space.
Question.
Yeah.
Are you saying that Leoville's theorem
is either inherent or,
I mean,
are you saying it's ergodic?
I'm,
yeah,
I'm assuming that the system is ergodic.
Okay,
so ergodic means,
all right,
so,
yeah,
I'm assuming that.
And it's true for almost all systems.
Well,
actually,
I am,
I'm actually not assuming it's ergodic.
If it's not ergodic,
it means that there are extra conserved quantities.
When a system is not ergodic,
that means that the phase space divides up
into different pieces
which carry different conserved quantities.
Then you have to pick
a value of the conserved quantities.
So,
for example,
for the harmonic oscillator,
that's not ergodic.
What does ergodic mean?
I'll just tell you very briefly.
Ergodic is,
fairly closely related to chaotic.
It's not exactly the same thing,
but it means that the phase point
wanders around rather thoroughly
throughout the phase space
and pretty much touches every point
on the phase space,
very much like this touches every point
by the time it gets back.
Okay,
if it doesn't touch every point,
then that means that there are closed sectors
which have conserved quantities
which correspond to chaotic.
So,
what does that mean?
It means that there are conserved quantities.
For example,
this phase space is not at all ergodic.
This point doesn't get to every point inside here.
It only gets to the points on the same ellipse.
But that just tells you
that there are conserved quantities.
There's a conserved quantity
which takes on a value on every ellipse.
If you fix that conserved quantity,
then you stay on a given ellipse.
If you calculate the time average
as the phase point moves around that ellipse,
that average quantity will be the same as
calculating the average over the ellipse.
The time average will be the same as
averaging over points on the ellipse here.
So,
in fact,
really,
I have not so much assumed ergodicity
as I've assumed when you say
there are no additional conserved quantities
besides energy,
that really is the statement of ergodic behavior.
Okay.
Yeah.
In your statement of Leibovitz's theorem,
you talk about the volume of the points in the...
In phase space,
not in ordinary coordinate space.
Not in...
Okay,
so let's just remember.
What a volume in phase space means
is it's a thing with units
of,
let's say,
let's say it's a simple particle,
one particle.
Then a volume in space has units of length cubed.
A volume in phase space has units of length cubed
times momentum cubed.
It's a six-dimensional little volume element.
And it has units of length times momentum,
which is called action.
Okay.
Length cubed times momentum cubed
is called action cubed.
So it's volume in phase space,
not volume in ordinary space.
I was going to say,
a point doesn't have to be volume.
Right.
Well,
that's true.
No,
no,
no.
What I'm saying is
you start with a little volume in phase space,
little or big,
it doesn't matter.
And you track all the points.
And you see where they go.
This had a volume.
This has a volume.
And it takes time.
Yeah.
It has to take time.
Right.
But the volume of this will be exactly the same
as the volume of that.
In the case of the harmonic oscillator,
just the ellipse just stays the same.
So therefore,
would that be an example of that?
Don't you need an infinite number
of points to have a VOP
to show that there's a volume?
Otherwise,
how can you...
Yeah,
an infinite number of points,
a volume.
Are you,
are you,
are you fooled by the fact
that I drew some points here?
Oh,
no,
no.
I just,
you know...
You need it at least in count of the ints.
No,
no,
no.
It's a continuous infinity.
It's a volume.
It's a volume in the phase space.
I just,
I could crosshatch it,
okay?
Does that make it better?
Yeah.
Okay.
Better?
No.
So is that kind of related to
the fact that you have one-to-one mapping,
so if you have a point in one state,
eventually...
Yes,
yes,
yes.
Again...
Again,
the motion of dynamical systems,
the initial state at one time is
related to the final state at another time
as a one-to-one mapping.
Right.
As a one-to-one mapping,
and in that sense,
it is like this.
All right?
And just as this,
if you cycle around here long enough,
you will average over all these
points with equal a priori probability,
uh,
and the same is,
the same is true of following points in phase space,
and the right statement at the
end is that the a priori probability,
the a priori measure,
whatever you would like to call it,
for a dynamical system is volume in phase space.
Volume in...
Well,
let me just point out that you can map
the unit circle to the circle of radius 2,
and that does not preserve area...
Right.
But it does...
It is one-to-one.
You're right.
That's,
uh...
Okay,
good.
Good.
It's...
Yeah.
That's right.
It's more than one-to-one.
Um,
it's volume preserving,
or,
uh,
phase space volume preserving,
which is better than one-to-one.
So how do you factor in
certain parts of one of those?
Well,
you don't.
I mean,
we're doing classical physics.
Now,
if we were doing quantum mechanics,
we would subdivide the phase space into little boxes
of order h-bar on a side,
and,
uh,
we would think about little boxes in phase space,
which were no better defined than,
uh,
than,
the uncertainty principle allows.
So it actually,
from a quantum mechanics perspective,
it's actually a finite number of points.
Well,
a finite number of points.
the density of them,
in any case.
Yeah.
Right.
Good.
And,
uh,
as I said,
that's why I don't,
uh,
at this point,
want to...
Now,
the ultimate justification,
in fact,
for this principle that,
of equal a priori
probability on phase space,
really is quantum mechanics,
um,
because it's only in quantum
mechanics where the states of a system are discrete,
and where you can actually count.
You can actually count states and so forth,
and,
uh,
make it more like this situation here.
All right.
That,
uh,
in any case,
that's an important principle
that equal a priori probabilities,
or uniform a priori probability distribution.
Um,
let's talk about probabilities and get to entropy.
Okay.
So,
we've discussed energy.
Energy is a conserved quantity.
We fix the conserved quantity called energy for a system,
and then within the space of
a particular value of energy,
the system may hop around from one state to another,
all
with the same energy,
and as it hops around,
if it hops around fast enough,
you get to
average the energy.
Now,
you get to ask about probabilities by
asking how much time does the system spend
in each one of its particular configurations,
and that,
by Liouville's theorem,
will pretty
much be guaranteed to be
just average over the phase space.
Okay.
The next concept is entropy.
Now,
you might have thought the next
concept in thermodynamics would be temperature.
Temperature is much more intuitive than entropy.
Well,
is it?
It's really not.
Um,
you have,
of course,
a body sense of what temperature is.
Uh,
things are hot and things are cold,
and so you have an,
I don't think you have an
intuitive sense of what temperature means,
but you do have an intuitive sense of what
hot and,
or at least a biological sense
of what hot and cold is.
But it's really energy and entropy
which are the more basic concepts.
So let's start,
let's talk about entropy.
Okay.
Before we talk about entropy,
let's talk about probability distributions.
If we have some variable,
and that variable could be the numbers on a die,
or it could be a continuous variable,
such as x or p.
Okay.
Or something else.
Then you may have a probability distribution of some kind.
Where you got it from,
let's not worry about where you got it from.
This is some variable,
it may be a collection of variables,
it may be more than one of them,
but let's just take a one-dimensional thing.
Here's the probability,
p goes this way,
and the probability distribution,
I don't know,
it might be like that.
And every value of the
coordinate or the set of coordinates,
by coordinates I now just mean any
parameters which describe the state of a system.
As I said,
it could be the numbers on a die.
If it was the numbers on a die,
they would be discrete.
And instead of having a
continuous function for the probability,
you would have just a sort
of set of numbers for the probability.
The only difference between the
discrete system and the continuous system
is whereas you might add,
whenever you add for the discrete system,
you're probably going to wind
up integrating for the continuous system,
but we'll come back to that.
Alright.
What does it take to be a probability,
a possible probability distribution?
Two things.
p must be positive everywheres in both these cases.
Negative probabilities have no meaning.
It could be zero,
of course.
When I say positive,
I could also mean zero.
And the other thing in this
case is the sums of the probabilities,
let's call it p .
i now is which particular state you're talking about.
Sum of p is equal to one.
So a sum of positive things,
a bunch of positive things whose sum is one.
Clearly each one of the p's
has to be less than one.
Less than or equal to one.
The sum of positive things adds up to one.
Each one must be less than or equal to one.
The only way any one of them can be
equal to one is if all the others are zero.
The analogous situation for a continuous variable
is that the integral of the probability,
let's call this variable x,
p dx,
is equal to one.
And of course,
the way we use a probability distribution is we don't
talk about the probability of a specific value of the coordinate.
We talk about the probability that the coordinate
x lies between x and x plus dx.
We talk about the probability that the
coordinate lies in a little interval here.
And that naturally is zero.
And that naturally brings us to
the idea of a probability density.
A probability density is a thing that we integrate.
A probability for a discrete variable
is a thing that we sum.
Next concept,
another important concept,
is the concept of the average value of a quantity.
Now I'm going to assume,
of course,
that everybody knows a little bit of statistics.
Let's take this case here.
The discrete case.
Suppose that there is some function of i.
Let's see,
what could we take it to?
How about the square?
Hm?
I squared.
That could be I squared,
yeah.
Just some function of i.
Well,
i could be an integer.
i,
of course,
could be many,
many variables.
I've drawn it as one variable.
But it could be a multi-dimensional space.
Some function,
some quantity,
which depends on the state of the system.
Could be the energy.
It could be anything that you like.
Any property of the system which,
if you know i,
you know the value of that property.
What do we call that?
Let's call that,
let's call a quantity the property f.
And f also depends on i.
If you know the state of the system,
then you know f.
What is the average value of f?
And we'll label the average value
of f by just a notation,
standard notation for averages,
standard physicist notation,
bracket around it.
That's the average of f.
What's the definition of the average?
The definition is to sum up over all i,
f of i,
but weighted with the probability.
For that value of i.
Remember that p's add up to one.
That's the definition of the average value of a quantity.
And it is the standard average.
It's the ordinary average,
except weighted by the probability,
not just by a flat measure,
not just adding up the f sub i's and dividing,
but weighting them according to p of i.
Why do you weight it according to p of i?
Well,
you can imagine a situation,
for example,
where you had only one non-zero probability.
You wouldn't want to,
if you wanted the average value of f,
it's quite clear the average value of f
is just the value of f at that point.
If you look at this formula,
that's what you'll get.
All the p's are equal to
either zero or one in this case,
and you'll only get one contribution.
So that's called the average.
And now what I want you to imagine,
as I said,
I do want you to keep in mind
that there could be,
this space here could be
a multidimensional space of some kind,
but I've enumerated all of
the states of the system here,
enumerated them all,
laid them out here,
and let's suppose now that
all we know about the system,
the only thing we know is,
that it's in one of m possible states.
Let's suppose there are n states altogether,
m is less than n,
and all we know about the system is
that it's in one of these m states,
so it could be this
set of m states over here.
That's all we know.
What is the probability,
out here?
Zero.
So the probabilities of zero out here,
what about out here?
And what about in here?
Not one.
One over m.
Remember,
they have to add up to one.
So this is m states in here,
all we know is that it's in this range here,
and the probability in here is one over m.
Question?
They're equally probable?
When I say we know nothing but,
that's another way of saying they're equally probable.
Yeah.
If we know nothing but the fact
that it's in one of these m states,
that means,
and we really just don't know anything else,
that it's equally probable that it's
in any one of these m.
If it's equally probable that it's
in any one of these m,
a statement of a complete ignorance
is equivalent to the statement
that all things are equally probable.
So a statement of complete ignorance,
other than that we know that the
system is in one of these m states,
is equivalent to saying that
we have a probability distribution,
let's draw it over here,
which is zero everywheres except in this range
where the probability distribution is one over m.
Right?
Okay.
This m here is a measure of our ignorance.
The bigger m is,
the bigger our ignorance.
Now,
why might we be ignorant?
There may be many reasons for being ignorant,
but the usual reason is because
the number of degrees of freedom,
first of all,
they're very microscopic,
second of all,
they're very numerous,
and so typically there's lots and
lots of ignorance about a system,
and all you know is some restricted information.
Now,
in this case,
I've drawn a very,
very idealized version of that idea
where I know nothing except that it's
in one of these one over m states.
m is a measure of your ignorance,
but is it the only possible measure of your ignorance?
No,
you could take m squared,
you could take m cubed,
you could take any monotonically increasing function of m,
and that would also be a measure of your ignorance.
The one which is correct,
which is called entropy,
is the logarithm of m.
Logarithm is a monotonically increasing function,
log m,
and it's called s.
s for entropy.
Why is s entropy?
I don't know.
It's logarithm of m,
for this particular case over here.
or if you like,
it's within this,
well,
it's logarithm of m,
which is also equal,
incidentally,
notice that it's equal to
minus logarithm of one over m.
The only reason I'm writing
in terms of one over m
is because the probability distribution happens
to have height one over m.
So this is writing it in terms
of logarithm of the probability distribution in here.
Logarithm of the probability where it's not zero,
in a non-zero range.
That is a measure of your ignorance.
Yeah.
This matter of the base of the logarithm,
is it natural logarithm?
Yeah,
we're gonna,
in fact,
you could,
you have your choice about
how you want to define it.
And in different branches of science,
it's defined in different bases.
In physics,
it's always log to the base e,
natural logarithm.
In information theory,
it's usually log to the base two.
But the conversion factor is just
a factor of logarithm of two.
The logarithm of a,
yeah,
so it's a trivial relationship.
In information theory,
people like using binary digits,
and they like taking powers of two.
An entropy of logarithm of two is called,
well,
logarithm of two in this sense,
and then natural log two,
is called one bit.
We'll come to why it's called a bit,
but,
but in any case,
this is the entropy.
Now,
why take the logarithm?
I'm not gonna tell you right
now why we take the logarithm.
The answer is because it's useful
to take the logarithm.
What's that?
You just told us.
Yeah,
I'm not gonna tell you why it's useful.
Yet.
We are certainly gonna find out why.
All right,
I will tell you.
Yeah,
all right.
Let's,
let me,
I will tell you by example.
Let's do an example.
Supposing I have a bunch of coins.
N coins,
big N coins.
N coins.
Each of which can be heads or tails.
That's my system.
My system is not a single coin.
My system is N coins.
Heads,
tails,
heads,
and so forth.
Okay.
And supposing I know nothing about it.
Let's take the most extreme example of ignorance.
I don't know nothing.
Okay.
What's the entropy?
Well,
how many configurations are there altogether?
Two to the N.
What's the logarithm of that?
N log 2.
Notice that the entropy now is
proportional to the number of coins.
It makes sense now to
talk about the entropy per coin.
The entropy per coin is logarithm of 2.
By taking the logarithm,
we reduce entropy to something which is additive,
which adds up over the system,
which is proportional to the size of the system,
for example.
The entropy in this room is proportional
to the number of molecules in the room.
But the only reason that it's proportional to the number
of molecules in the room is because I've taken this logarithm.
So here's an example.
If the molecules are just replaced by coins,
and the only question was,
is the coin a head or a tail,
you can see that by taking the logarithm,
you make something which is proportional
to the number of degrees of freedom.
So entropy,
like energy,
is something which adds up for systems.
Yeah?
And in base 2,
that's just n.
Say it again?
In base 2,
that's just n.
Yeah,
in base 2,
that would just be n.
Good.
In base 2,
it would just be n.
In base e,
it's n log 2.
But in any case,
in either case,
we're going to have a system that's just n.
So one bit of information means
either when we're talking about base e,
it means a entropy of log 2,
or when we're talking about to the base 2,
it just means an entropy of one unit.
The entropy of a single coin,
if we didn't know whether it was heads or tails,
that's called a bit.
So entropy is measured in bits.
Yeah?
Is there a precise definition of degree of freedom?
I mean,
I still don't know what you mean,
but...
A variable.
How many degrees of freedom something has means...
Well,
you ask how many variables are
there that you have to know.
In this case,
the variable is either head or tail,
head-tail,
and you need to know any of them.
I imagine we can concoct some more official definition.
But I can't think of a right or a wrong.
Isn't it more or less in your example,
you're giving a number of particles?
Because that's kind of a loose flow.
Well,
in the case of a single particle,
of course,
it's six.
The three coordinates in the...
Right.
So more or less,
yes.
Wait a minute.
You said we know zilch in this case,
but you didn't take that into account.
Yeah,
in this case,
we don't know zilch.
In this case,
Right.
In the case of a few of all,
if you double the number of coins,
then you double the entropy.
So that would be an argument for using the law.
Yeah.
That's the idea.
Right.
Now,
an exercise you could ask is
supposing you did know the zilch.
Then what would the entropy be?
Right.
Then there would be some states...
Then you take averages.
Then you do one more thing.
If you know something in addition,
you know the probabilities,
you take an average of that long quantity.
Absolutely.
That's called...
Yeah,
absolutely.
Well,
we're going to take an average of this quantity.
Yeah.
Precisely.
But you got me so excited with that
remark that I forgot my train of thinking.
No.
It was a tremendously important point,
and I forgot what it is.
Well,
I don't remember what it is,
but let's just do one...
Well,
a couple more examples.
Again,
supposing...
Oh,
oh,
one...
Yeah,
I remember what the important point is.
Supposing we know everything about the system.
Knowing everything would mean,
in this case,
we know exactly which configuration we're in.
That would mean that one
of these states has probability one...
...and all the others have zero.
What's the entropy then?
Zero.
It's just log of one.
Log of one is zero.
Okay?
E to the zero is one.
So,
this is a kind of interesting fact.
When you have complete information
that's equivalent to zero entropy,
when you have no information,
that's when you have the maximum entropy,
incidentally.
You cannot have an entropy bigger than this.
This is easy to prove.
Sorry.
Logarithm of n.
This one is the largest entropy
you can have for that case.
So,
entropy is a measure of ignorance.
Now,
this is interesting.
Notice that with this definition of entropy,
and this is the real definition of entropy,
it is not really a function
of the properties of a system.
It's a function not only of the system,
but your state of knowledge of the system.
Now,
that sounds a little bit ridiculous,
because entropy is something we're going to treat as
though it were a quantity associated with the system.
And we'll come to why.
But really,
it's a joint question of
the system,
its probability distribution.
In fact,
it's a function of the probability distribution,
is what it is.
Okay,
so that's the simple-minded notion of entropy over here.
Now,
let's try to find a definition going exactly in
the direction that you pointed out a moment ago.
Let's imagine some probability distribution.
I don't mean it to be conditional.
I just don't want to
draw a bunch of vertical lines.
A probability distribution now,
which is not flat and then zero,
but may have some width,
maybe that it's close to zero in some region,
in some range,
and then close to one for some other range,
and then close to zero,
but it's not exactly zeros and ones.
It's a more complicated or arbitrary,
in fact,
probability distribution.
Can we generalize this idea so
that we have a measure of ignorance,
which is in some sense approximately
a notion of the number of states
that we've included under the probability distribution here,
which have non-negligible probability,
the logarithm of it.
All right,
so here's the usual definition.
It's actually the average.
The average.
Here it is.
Log of one over m.
It's the average of logarithm of the probability.
The average of logarithm of the probability.
Now,
wait a minute.
Minus.
Remember that the probability is
always between zero and one.
What does that mean about the logarithm?
Negative.
Just like the logarithm of
one over m is negative here.
So that means that this is positive.
It's the average.
It's the average of the logarithm
of the probability of the ith configuration.
How do we calculate that?
Well,
we just use the formula for averages.
Where do I have the formula for averages?
I think I lost it.
So let's write it down.
The average of a function of i is equal to the
sum over i of f of i times p of i.
Let's apply that.
Let's calculate the average of
the logarithm of the probability.
That's equal now.
For f of i now,
we just substitute minus log p sub i.
So what is it?
It's just summation over i of minus p sub i.
That's this one times the log of p sub i.
Okay.
That's called,
this is it.
This is the final definition of entropy.
Let's look at it for a moment.
Supposing we have one of these distributions,
which is flat and zero,
equal to one over m up on the top,
and it encloses m states all together.
What is this quantity?
Well,
outside,
when we start adding up the contributions to it,
there are contributions from the regions where p is zero.
They give zero,
because p is equal to zero.
On the other hand,
there are the contributions from within this range.
And what are they given by?
They're given by,
let's see what they are.
p sub i is one over
m for each one of those states.
Then there's logarithm.
So we have a minus sign of one over m.
A minus sign.
And now we have to sum over i.
But each one of the states in
this bin here gives the same answer.
So what do we do with it?
We multiply it by m.
We multiply it by the number of states here.
That just cancels out this.
And gives us minus log one over m,
which is the same as log m.
So this formula,
the average of the log of the probability,
reproduces this formula for a square distribution like this.
But it's more general.
And it is kind of a
measure of the width of the distribution,
or the number of
configurations with non-negligible probability.
More or less equal non-negligible probabilities.
But it is what it is.
p sub i log p
sub i is called the entropy.
As I said,
it reproduces this answer when the
conditions are applicable for this answer.
And otherwise it gives a general answer.
Any questions?
No.
So what is the coefficient of Boltzmann's
constant to make it consistent with classical thermodynamics?
Boltzmann's constant.
Absolutely.
Yeah,
I always forget about Boltzmann's constant.
Right,
okay,
so let me,
let me,
right.
Boltzmann's constant traces back
to the definition of temperature.
Energy and entropy together determine temperature.
In the early days,
when physicists,
or whoever they were called themselves at that time,
steam engineers,
whoever it was,
were interested in temperature,
they really didn't know what temperature was.
All they knew was how you measure it.
Measure it with thermometers.
In the beginning,
they didn't even have the idea
of an absolute zero of temperature.
But today we know temperature is a form of energy,
or is measured in units of energy.
The appropriate idea of,
for example,
the temperature of a gas is a
measure of the energy of individual molecules.
Not exactly,
but that's roughly what it is.
The conversion factor between energy,
which was measured in joules,
and temperature,
which was measured in degrees,
what,
Celsius or degrees Kelvin or whatever,
the conversion factor was not known.
It wasn't known how much energy per molecule
there was in a gas at a certain temperature.
So there was an unknown conversion factor.
Boltzmann introduced it.
He was the one who realized,
Boltzmann and Maxwell,
realized that at least for a gas,
or an ideal gas,
temperature is a measure of
the kinetic energy of the molecules.
But the unknown conversion,
why was there an unknown conversion factor?
Basically because they didn't know how many
molecules there were in a mole of gas.
They knew how much energy,
they could measure how much energy does it take
to heat up a mole of gas one degree.
But what they didn't know,
they didn't know how much energy it would take
to heat up a mole of gas one degree.
But what they didn't know,
they didn't know how many molecules were there.
So Boltzmann's constant,
which was a measure of the energy per molecule,
that was unknown.
If we use,
today we know of course how many
molecules there are in a mole of gas,
and we can work if
we like with units of temperature,
which are really just units of energy.
We can measure temperature in joules.
It's just the energy needed,
the energy of a single particle,
roughly speaking,
the energy of a single particle
in a gas at that temperature.
So that's just a historical fact.
Boltzmann did not know his own constant.
Boltzmann was so depressed by the fact that he
didn't know his own constant that he committed suicide,
and I think the next year
Einstein figured out what Boltzmann's constant was.
From the Brownian motion.
I don't think that's
the reason Boltzmann considered suicide.
I don't know why he did.
Newton also didn't know his own constant.
Yeah.
It took many years for Newton's constant to be measured.
It took a few years
for Boltzmann's constant to be measured.
Did Plyton know his?
Yeah.
Plyton knew his.
Absolutely.
Can we partition the constants?
Those constants where the person whose name is
attached to it knew what the constant was.
That's a constant.
How many constants are there?
Let's see.
There was a...
One of the hard ones that took a
little bit of time was the electric charge.
What was known and easy to measure
was the ratio of the charge to mass.
And then it took some time until...
What's his name figured out?
Michael...
No,
not Michelson or Morley.
Millikan.
Millikan figured out how to measure
the charge separately from the mass.
So whoever thought of the idea that electrons had
electric charge didn't know the value of the charge.
Right.
Who was that?
Who was the first one
who postulated that electrons had charge?
Well,
that they were electrons and they had charge.
Yeah,
I think it was Benjamin Franklin.
It wasn't Robert.
Hmm?
Didn't...
No.
I think it was Benjamin Franklin.
I don't think it was Ronald Reagan,
I don't know where that came from.
Back to the experiment?
Yeah.
What?
You said gore,
I can understand that.
Gore invented the electron.
All right,
so we have now the concepts of temperature and entropy,
and I've introduced the idea of a probability distribution.
Now,
we're going to go further next time,
but for today,
let's just postulate something called
thermal equilibrium for a system.
Now,
let me first explain when a system
can be said to be in thermal equilibrium.
These are not necessary and sufficient terms.
This is not sufficient conditions.
This is necessary condition,
but for many systems,
it's sufficient.
For lots of systems,
this is good enough.
Thermal equilibrium is not a property of an isolated system.
If you have a truly isolated system,
it's not in thermal equilibrium.
It has an energy.
It has a definite value of the energy.
You may not know what it is,
but it has some energy,
and that energy is fixed.
Thermal equilibrium is a property of a system in contact.
I'll tell you what contact means in a minute.
A system A in contact with a much bigger system,
B.
A doesn't stand for anything.
This is not Alice and Bob.
This is A and B.
A just stands for the system under consideration.
B stands for heat bath.
It's a very big system with many,
many more degrees of freedom.
And the whole system,
the whole combined system of A,
the thing of interest,
and B,
the heat bath,
has a given total energy.
That's an assumption.
For our purposes,
the bigger system can be thought
of as a closed and isolated system.
Let me say what closed and isolated means.
It means there's no way for energy
to flow into it and out of it.
Either it's contained within insulating walls that
don't allow any heat energy in or out,
or it's just an isolated region in space
that nothing can come into or out of.
The bath is a system.
A plus A can be an isolated system.
But A is not an isolated system.
Now,
if the bath is big enough,
basically in the limit.
Oh,
oh,
one other thing.
The bath plus A is isolated,
but neither A nor the bath themselves are isolated,
but they weakly interact.
Weakly interact means that the energies of interaction,
whatever the interaction between A and B are,
it's governed by some energies of interaction,
the energies of interaction are very small compared
to the energy of either A or B.
But the interactions,
whatever they are,
allow energies to go back
and forth from A to B.
They allow energies to be transferred back and forth.
From B to A.
From A to B.
The whole system has a definite energy.
So the whole system has
a definite value of the zilch,
the zilch being energy in this case.
That whole system will move around in its
phase space on a surface of constant energy,
but it'll move around and hop around
from point to point to point to point.
And among other things,
the different points will correspond to different
ways of partitioning the given amount of energy
into the energy of the heat
bath and the energy of A.
So under these circumstances,
neither the energy of the heat bath,
which we're not terribly interested in,
nor the energy of A,
which we are interested in,
will have a definite predictable value.
It will fluctuate.
It will have a probability distribution.
A probability distribution,
if you wait long enough,
until,
just wait long enough,
that's it.
I mean,
there's some time scale.
Of course,
if you start the system in some arbitrary way,
it won't be in thermal equilibrium.
But if you wait a long time until it equilibrates
and energy is hopping back and forth between them,
in a long time average sense,
there will be a probability for the energy of A.
Okay?
Let's,
and in other words,
in other words,
the various configurations of A,
let's plot them.
Here are the various states,
the energy states of A,
values of the energy,
this is energy now.
They may be discrete,
they may be continuous,
not important for us at the moment.
These are all the various
values that the energy of A,
this is the energy of
A that it can take on.
We start with a given total amount of energy.
Okay?
The energy of A will
be a small fraction of it,
but as a function of the total energy,
as a function of the total energy,
there will be some probability distribution.
And we can also think of it as
a function of the average energy within A.
Whatever the energy of the whole system is,
there will be,
the bigger the energy of the whole system,
of course,
the bigger the energy,
the average energy of A is likely to be.
So we can parameterize the behavior,
the nature of the system,
by the average energy in
A or by the total energy.
If we know one,
we know the other.
The total energy,
in principle,
we should,
if we know how to calculate,
calculate the average energy of A.
We'll learn how to do that.
So the average energy of A or the total energy,
either one,
but let's say the average energy of A,
this is the average energy of A,
or just the energy of A,
just the energy of A,
has some probability distribution,
and this probability distribution is a function
not only of the energy of A,
but also the average energy of A.
If you give me an average energy of A,
then there will be some probability distribution.
So let's just think of a probability distribution
which is parameterized.
In other words,
it's a whole sequence
of different probability distributions.
The different probability distributions correspond
to different values of the overall energy.
Yeah?
The average of A is taken over time?
Yes,
it can be taken over time.
it's taken over time.
The average energy of A is taken over time.
Alright,
so it's parameterized.
You have a probability distribution,
which,
in fact,
we can just say
it's a function of the state of the,
of A,
and the total energy,
if you like.
The total energy parameterizes
the probability distribution.
Change the energy,
you change the probability distribution of A
over its states.
The states of A are I.
Alright.
Here are two things you can calculate
if you know the probability distribution.
You can calculate the average energy of E,
of A,
and you can calculate also the entropy.
Given a probability distribution,
you can calculate the entropy of A.
Just entropy of A.
Which happens to be the average of the log
of the probability of A,
with a minus sign.
In other words,
you can calculate the average energy
and the entropy.
Now I'm going to tell you what's going to happen.
Let's see what temperature is.
What temperature is.
If you increase
the energy of the system,
of the combined system,
if you increase it,
needless to say,
and obviously,
the energy in A will increase a little bit.
If you increase the energy of
the whole system a little bit.
In general,
the entropy will also change.
The entropy in A will also change
if you increase the energy of the whole system.
And you can ask,
how much energy,
how much change of energy
in A does it take
to change the entropy by one bit?
How much,
how much
change in E A,
how much change in the energy of A
must you make
in order to change S by one bit?
What is that?
That's the change in energy,
the derivative of the energy,
with respect to the entropy,
times that one bit,
which is logarithm of two or something.
That's not,
this is not the important thing here.
That's how much energy
you have to add to A.
And how do you do it?
You add the energy to A
by adding it to the whole heat bath here.
That changes the average energy E A.
And how much must you change E A
in order to change the entropy by one bit?
In other words,
to hide one more bit of information,
to increase your ignorance by one bit of information.
How much energy do you have to put into A?
This derivative,
the change in energy per unit entropy,
is called the temperature.
That's what's called temperature,
T.
It's the energy change needed,
if you like,
to state it colorfully,
to hide one more bit of information.
But technically,
it's the change in the entropy
per unit entropy of the system.
Okay.
So from an information-theoretic point of view,
it's the change in the entropy
if you hide an extra bit of it.
An example of it,
incidentally,
is Landauer's principle in computing,
that if you want to erase a bit of information
from a computer,
now remember,
you can't destroy information.
You can't destroy information
because it's conserved,
because of the principle of
conservation of distinctions.
So if you try to erase a bit of information
from the computer,
you wind up putting it into the heat bath
surrounding the computer.
All right.
How much heat or energy
do you put into the heat bath
by taking one bit of information
out of your computer
and putting it in the heat bath?
Well,
it's the temperature times the temperature
times logarithm of two.
That's the amount of energy that-
that's the amount of heat energy
that you put into the environment
when you erase a bit of information.
That's an example of it.
And that's why you can't erase information
from your computer
without putting heat into the environment.
Why?
Because when you erase a bit of information,
you change S a little bit.
Well,
you can see why.
You can see why.
There are people working on reversible computers.
Yeah.
But if you're-
Yes.
Right.
That means you do your computation
without erasing.
Right.
But if you erase,
you will heat the environment.
You can stop global warming
by never deleting anything.
Yeah.
Right.
That's already .
Or you can heat your house
by erasing .
What's that?
I missed the...
You can heat your house by erasing your information.
What you can't do is cool
your house by opening the refrigerator.
But a bit is really a small amount of
energy in terms of like an environment that you'd
be in.
Yeah.
Right.
Okay.
So let's say now where the smallness comes in.
The smallness comes in for exactly the reasons
that were asked to me a few minutes ago.
What happened to Boltzmann's constant?
The answer is really strictly speaking,
Boltzmann's constant goes here,
Kb.
I'm inclined to work in units.
Just like when I do relativity,
I work in units in
which c is equal to 1.
When I do thermodynamics and statistical mechanics.
I always work in units in which
the Boltzmann constant is equal to 1.
But in ordinary units,
ordinary units,
which are what?
They're joules per degree...
K is joules per degree Kelvin?
Yeah.
Right.
It's a terribly small number.
What is it?
Anybody remember?
10 to the minus 23.
Right.
Like Avogadro's number.
No.
Inverse of Avogadro's number.
Right.
So it's a very,
very small number.
And this means when you erase one
bit of information at a temperature T,
this temperature incidentally
is the temperature of the surroundings.
When you erase a bit of information,
you change the energy of
the surroundings by a very small
amount.
So K is a small number.
And yes.
And it's also true that entropy...
The standard thermodynamic definition of entropy...
Let's see.
What I call entropy differs from the standard
entropy also by a factor of a Boltzmann constant,
but is it upstairs or downstairs?
I forget.
Isn't that a little bit of a
circular definition since you're talking about entropy?
Yes.
So that's the answer.
So it's a little bit of a
circular definition since you're talking about entropy.
And it's also true that entropy is a
little bit of a circular definition since in order
to define S,
you have to enumerate the states.
What's that again?
Isn't it a circular definition that one
bit of information is erased under that situation
since in order to define S,
you have to enumerate the states,
which means that you enumerate
the bits?
Well,
I don't think it's a circular statement.
It's a little bit of a circular definition.
It's a little bit of a circular definition to
say that if I erase a bit of information
from the computer,
it heats the atmosphere by a certain amount.
Well,
in order to define S,
you've got to...
In order to find F,
which is F?
S,
the entropy.
Which?
S.
Yes.
Great.
And if you enumerate the states,
then you enumerate the bits.
You don't have to know anything about the computer.
You don't have to know anything.
You don't have to enumerate the states.
You don't even have to know what the states are.
The system is.
The systems are.
It's just a general fact that if you
erase one bit of information from any computer,
no matter what its states are,
and no matter how it's made,
and what company it's made
by,
it will always heat the atmosphere by that much.
So is it a circular statement?
No,
I don't think it's a circular statement.
Look,
statistical mechanics is,
in a certain sense,
a bunch of tautologies.
It's mathematics.
When we apply it to physics,
we're adding something else in.
And we're adding in this idea
of averaging over times and so forth.
But I didn't want to get into Landauer's principle
of what happens when you erase a bit of information.
I simply wanted to give you the definition of temperature.
Temperature is the change in the energy that
you must add in order to change the atmosphere.
the entropy by one bit,
which means divided by log 2.
When we were thinking about the dye and thinking,
well,
we're only interested in one face,
we were making a choice about what information
was considered relevant.
And it's not necessarily the same thing
that the computer user thinks of as a bit that
causes the chip to get hot.
So that's a different bit.
They're probably related by some constant.
I think it'd be gross energy.
I'm saying that chips that
have lots of cells get hot.
There's a certain amount of energy
that we would call an amount of entropy.
But that's not the same
thing as what in the computer
you would call a bit.
Because there's a lot of energy.
There's a lot of other stuff going on.
Yeah.
No,
the actual statement,
the correct statement
of Landauer's principle is you will heat the atmosphere
by at least this much.
There's a very idealized situation
where only this very,
very simplest thing happens,
namely without disturbing it any other way,
you eject one bit.
Landauer's principle said that's the absolute minimum
that the energy of the atmosphere will change by.
If you erase a bit of information.
So yeah.
Is the numerator E the average energy?
Yeah,
the average energy of A.
Of A,
so it shouldn't really have a bracket.
Yes,
it should.
And I'm going to get tired of writing the average.
From now on,
whenever we think about a quantity associated
with a subsystem here,
I will often neglect to write average.
But when we're thinking about the subsystem in equilibrium
with the bath,
what we mean by the various quantities
associated with it is the averages.
And they fluctuate.
They do fluctuate.
And we're going to talk about calculating fluctuations.
Fluctuations are an important thing.
In fact,
it's what Einstein realized.
Einstein realized that the
quantities of thermodynamics fluctuate.
He realized that those fluctuations
would have effects on small,
little impurities in the system and knock them around.
And what he did was essentially calculate the fluctuations
using statistical mechanics,
fluctuations of various quantities
like pressure and energy and so forth.
And he did that.
And he demonstrated how they would affect small impurity
in a system.
OK.
We've done quite a bit.
We've gotten energy,
entropy,
temperature,
phase space.
All right.
The next time,
we will work out and derive the Boltzmann
distribution.
The Boltzmann distribution is the probability distribution
for the states of A in the heat bath.
And it's obtained statistically by using some probability
arguments about energy being transferred back and forth
between the system and the giant heat bath.
OK.
For more,
please visit us at stanford.edu.