Stanford University.
Well,
I think what I'm gonna do is
take roughly a half an hour or
something like that and
just discuss some elementary mathematics.
Now,
I want you to learn this mathematics
and if need be to look it up.
It's three simple pieces.
See,
three simple pieces of mathematics,
all
elementary,
and I suspect most of you either
know this or knew it at one time,
but it's so central that I think we
need to lay it out and use it.
Lay it out for future purposes.
Okay,
the first piece of mathematics is
called Lagrange-Rogge.
How many people here have seen Lagrange multipliers?
How many of those people
remember what a Lagrange multiplier is?
So roughly half the people have seen it
can use it.
Would that be fair to say?
How many people have never seen a Lagrange
multiplier or can't remember what it is?
Alright,
so the answer is the majority of
you have,
but I'm going to remind you
anyway because it is absolutely central.
We're constantly
minimizing or maximizing things subject to constraints.
What is the thing that
we're likely to minimize incidentally or maximize,
sorry?
Entropy.
But we'll get to
why entropy,
not tonight,
next time I suspect,
but why we maximize entropy.
But
yes,
thermal equilibrium is a state of
maximum entropy and that means we want
to maximize something as a function of something else.
We want to maximize a
certain function as a function
of the variables that define it,
number one.
Number two,
there are constraints.
We don't just want to maximize a function,
but we want to maximize
a function subject to some constraints.
What might
the constraints be?
Well,
a particular function明
constraint might be that we know the
total energy of the system or we know
the average energy of the system for
some reason we may know the average
energy of the system for example we
might have again a container full of a
lot of molecules we break it up
into small pieces we're going to study one
small piece and I tell you that
the total energy in that container is
whatever it is 20 zillion joules okay I
also tell you that it's composed of a
bunch of identical parts how many
identical parts 10,000 of them what's
the average energy in each one well you
take the total energy and you divide it
by the number of parts and that tells you the
the average
the average energy in each part
now I want to focus on this part
and say I know the average energy
and I want to maximize the entropy
subject to the constraint
that the total energy is fixed
that's a problem
that's the kind of problem
that emerges time and time again over and over
another example is we may know
the total amount of electric charge
in a region and we may
want to maximize the entropy given
the total amount of electric charge
or the total amount of angular momentum
or whatever
so we constantly face problems
of minimizing or maximizing mathematical
subject of minimizing and maximizing are
equivalent to each other or the same
we constantly want to maximize functions
of several variables
subject to constraints on those variables
what does that mean?
example
a function of two variables
let's literally take an example
I want to minimize
minimize or maximize?
minimize I think
x squared
plus x squared
plus y squared
now anybody can minimize x squared plus y squared
what's the minimum value of x squared y squared?
zero
it can't be less than zero because
x squared and y squared are both positive
and x equals 0 and y
equals 0 it is equal to 0
but it's not equal to 0 anywhere else
so the minimum is right
at x equals y equals 0
and the function is equal to 0 at that point
but now supposing I tell
you I want to minimize it
subject to a LA dalla Make sure
that you memorize all its taken coefficients
to a constraint.
I want to know where x
squared plus y squared is minimum given
that,
I don't know,
let's say x plus 2y is equal to 1.
To draw a picture,
we
can plot on the plane here the
contours of x squared plus y squared.
X squared plus
y squared,
the contour map,
right at the center.
It's minimized and as we move
away it forms a bowl,
a valley,
and the contour map would look like this.
On the
other hand,
and of course the minimum of
the function is right at the center,
on
the other hand,
I really want to minimize it
subject to a constraint and that
constraint is x plus 2y equals 1.
That's a straight line and I don't know
what's a straight line,
maybe it looks something like that.
So what I'm really
asking is where along this line is
x squared plus y squared minimized given
that you're on the line?
Well that's certainly not at the origin here,
it's
somewhere along here.
Looks like it's about over here,
doesn't it?
x squared plus y squared of course is
just the squared distance from the origin and so
you're kind of asking along this line where is the
line closest to the origin?
That's the geometric problem that corresponds to it
but the mathematics problem is to
minimize x squared plus y squared
subject to a constraint that x
plus 2y is equal to 1.
How do you do that?
Well,
one way would just be to eliminate,
let's do it,
we could eliminate one of
the variables,
plug it into here,
and then minimize the remaining function.
For
example,
what does that mean?
We could solve for x and
find that x is equal to 1 minus 2y
and then plug it into here and we would have
1 minus 2y squared,
that's x squared,
plus y squared.
Let's just call this f.
f on the line,
on the red line,
f would be given by this
and then the next step is
just to minimize f with respect to y.
We don't have to worry about the constraint
anymore because we've already
taken the constraint into account.
So that's one
way of doing the problem.
Now in many cases the constraint is just too
complicated to solve.
It might be some stupid complicated function that's just
too complicated to solve,
but there is another way
to do the problem and the
problem is called the method of Lagrange multipliers.
Maybe I'll,
perhaps as we go
along,
I will prove that it works.
For a simple,
well not for this example,
but maybe a little more general example,
but
let me just tell you what the method is.
I'm going to tell you the rule,
then we can try
to see maybe why the rule is true.
Alright,
what you do,
here's our problem.
We have a function of some variables,
in this
case just 2,
function of x and y,
and we want to minimize
it given that some other function
g of x and y is equal to 0.
g of x and y in
this case over here just corresponds to,
what was it,
x plus 2y minus 1.
x plus 2y minus 1 is equal to 0.
That's the constraint.
Alright,
here's the trick that you do.
You take the constraint and you multiply it by
a new variable.
A new variable is often called lambda,
usually a Greek letter,
and it's called a Lagrange
multiplier.
You add that to f.
Add or subtract,
it doesn't matter.
You add it to f,
and now
you have a new function of x and y
that also depends on this auxiliary variable which we're
going to get rid of soon enough.
We're going to get rid of it in a moment.
But we have
a new thing.
We're going to get rid of it in a moment,
but we have a new thing.
And,
we have a new thing,
which is f and lambda g.
And then what we do is we just minimize
f plus lambda g with respect to x and y,
ignoring the constraint.
Forget the constraint and
just think of this new object here and
minimize it with respect to x and y.
Okay,
how do you
minimize a function of two
variables with respect to its variables?
You differentiate with respect to the variables
and you set the result equal to zero.
So,
that
would say we differentiate df by dx plus lambda.
Lambda is treated as just a constant,
times
dg by dx.
And we set that equal to zero.
That's one equation.
And the other equation is df by dy.
Okay.
Plus lambda dg by dy is equal to zero.
Those are the two equations for minimizing this particular
object over here.
Alright,
here are two equations for two unknowns x and y.
Both of them depend
on x and y.
x and y.
And we can solve them for x and y.
But wait a minute.
We have an
this thing lambda there.
What do we do with that thing lambda?
The answer for x and y
will depend on this parameter lambda.
What we do with the parameter lambda at the end,
after we have solved this problem over here,
implicitly in terms of lambda,
is that we
set lambda to whatever value is
necessary in order that the constraint,
the original
constraint,
g equals zero,
is really satisfied.
I'm going to give you an example.
I'm going
to show you how it works by example.
In fact,
we might as well do that example,
and then
I'm going to show you why it works.
I'll show you how it
works and then why it works.
Incidentally,
you could imagine having more variables,
x,
y,
z,
w,
and have several constraints.
I'll tell you later on.
I'll show you later on
what you do with several constraints,
but let's just do it as a function
of two variables for one constraint.
Okay,
so let's solve this problem up here.
Here's
our problem.
Minimize x squared plus y squared subject
to the constraint that x plus 2y minus
1 is equal to zero.
Well,
we add this quantity,
x squared plus y squared,
plus lambda,
which
I'll sum up as y squared plus z squared,
times the constraint,
x plus 2y minus 1.
In this
case.
The 1 is not going to
be very important to this calculation.
That's a new object,
and now we minimize it.
How do we minimize it?
We differentiate it with respect to x
and set the result equal to 0.
What's the derivative of this?
That's 2x plus lambda
x equals zero.
Mens for unjust hermit,
who's got a limited number of terms,
and we firing
with respect to...
Oh,
sorry,
plus lambda.
Good.
Thank you.
Plus lambda equals zero.
2x plus
lambda equals zero.
And then
same thing with y,
2y
and in this case it's plus
2 lambda,
extra
2 here,
equals zero.
Now we can
solve for x and y in terms
of lambda.
We don't know what lambda is yet,
but let's solve for
in terms of x and y.
Let's solve
for x and y in terms of lambda.
x is equal to minus
lambda over 2.
That's
this equation.
x is minus lambda
over 2.
And y,
I
think,
is just equal to minus lambda.
Everybody agree with that?
Right.
Okay.
So we
solved that problem,
except we don't know what
lambda is.
What we do now is we choose
lambda so that the constraint
is actually satisfied.
Let's do that.
x plus 2y minus 1
is equal to zero.
Let's
plug in the solution.
The solution
is x,
which is minus
lambda over 2,
plus 2y,
which is minus
2 lambda,
I believe.
2y is
minus 2 lambda.
Minus 1
is equal to zero.
Sorry,
is equal to 1.
Is equal to 1.
I just transposed the 1 over to the other side.
And now,
what does that mean
in terms of lambda?
Excuse me.
2 is 4 over 2.
Okay.
So this is what?
Minus 5 halves lambda?
Minus 5 halves lambda
equals 1,
or lambda is
equal to minus
2 fifths.
And now we solved our problem.
Lambda is equal to minus
2 fifths,
which means
lambda over 2 is
minus lambda over 2 is 1 fifth,
I think.
Let's see.
Lambda over 2
is
1 fifth,
and y
is equal to
2 fifths.
I've just plugged in what lambda is.
Minus lambda is 2 fifths.
Minus lambda over 2 is 1 fifth,
and we have now found out
where
this curve,
or where
this line
achieves its closest
distance to the origin.
That was the mathematics problem.
Minimize x squared
plus y squared,
which is 1.
This is just the square
of the distance of a point
to the origin.
Minimize it along this line,
and that means find the point along the line
which is closest to the center.
Now,
we could check independently,
of course.
We could do the calculation the other way
by eliminating the constraint,
by solving the constraint for one of the variables
and plugging it back in,
and we could do it that way.
Of course,
we'll get the same answer.
Now,
let me show you why
this works.
So just a little bit of algebra.
It just takes a little bit of algebra
to see why it works.
And it's very general.
It's extremely general.
It's not
x squared plus y squared
was just an arbitrary function that I picked.
Pick any other function.
The fact that I chose the constraint
to be a straight line,
a linear function,
again,
nothing special about that.
Okay,
let's do the next one.
Let's look at the problem,
not this problem,
but a general problem in both ways
and see that we get the same answer.
So let's start by the method of eliminating
one of the variables from the constraint.
Here's our problem.
We have f of x and y.
We want to minimize it,
subject to the constraint that g of x and y
is equal to zero.
g of x and y equals zero is some curve,
and it means we're minimizing it,
minimizing f along that curve.
All right.
Here's the way I'm going to do it.
I'm going to imagine,
this may be too hard to do,
but it doesn't matter.
All I have to do is imagine doing it.
Solving this equation
for one of the two variables.
Which one?
All right,
let's imagine solving for y.
If we solve this equation for y,
it will tell us what y
is as a function of x.
In other words,
this was some curve.
It corresponds to a curve.
That represents y as a function of x.
Let's not worry right now whether it's single-valued,
not single-valued.
That's not an important issue here.
It gives us a y as a function of x.
Then we plug that back into here.
And we say what we're really trying to minimize
is f of x and y of x.
This is now a function of a single variable.
It's only a function of x
because y is a function of x.
So f of x is
now a definite function of x.
f of x and y becomes
f of x and y of x.
Next step.
What's the next step?
Differentiate this with respect to x
and set the result equal to zero.
That will find us the minimum of x
subject to the constraint.
So let's see.
Let's do that.
We have to differentiate the x dependence.
That's df by dx.
But then we have to add to that
the derivative of f with respect to y
times dy by dx.
This is an ordinary derivative.
dy by dx.
Alright,
this is the change in f
when we change the first argument here
of the function.
And this is the change
due to the change in y.
But the change in y is not
the same as the change in y.
The change in y is
determined by the change in x.
And we set this equal to zero.
Okay,
that's an equation.
But what about dy by dx?
What do I know about dy by dx?
Let's see what we can
figure out about dy by dx.
This curve here
is a curve of constant g.
Let's imagine moving along it.
Imagine moving along it
and making a small differential displacement.
A small differential displacement
along the curve of constant g
will not change g by definition.
If we're moving along the curve of constant g,
then g doesn't change.
So I can write the following equation.
Along this curve,
the derivative of g
with respect to x
times dx
plus the derivative of g
with respect to y
times dy
is equal to zero.
That says g doesn't change
when I make a small differential displacement.
The reason I did this
is because this allows me to solve
for dy by dx
in terms of things involving the constraint g.
Alright,
so dy by dx,
which is divide by dx,
and what do we get?
We get dy by dx
dy by dx
is equal to minus
dg by dx
divided by
dg by dy.
Alright,
very simple.
We just use the statement
that the constraint,
along the constraint,
g is constant,
and that tells us something about
the derivative of y with respect to x
along that curve.
And now we plug it in.
We plug it into here.
Let's see what we get.
dy by dx
might as well write it over.
We get
df by dx
Now there's going to be a minus sign
from the dy by dx,
so let's put the minus sign here.
df by dy
and now,
dy by dx,
except I already took into account the minus sign,
this is dg by dx
divided by dg by dy
Let's put it in there.
dg by dy
equals 0.
Let's multiply by dg by dy.
So we get dg by dy
equals 0.
That's not a bad looking equation.
Alright,
so now we're going to
do the same thing.
That's the equation
after we've eliminated
y,
this is the equation
which solves for the minimum
of f subject to g.
What I want to show you,
I don't want you to use this,
we're not going to use this.
What we're going to do is show that you get
exactly the same relationship
from the method of Lagrange multipliers.
So let's go to
the method of Lagrange multipliers.
Here are the two equations
that followed
from the method of Lagrange multipliers.
But now,
let's eliminate
lambda from the equation.
How can we do that?
We can solve for lambda in one equation
and plug it into the other.
Alright,
so let's see.
Here,
lambda,
it says lambda
is equal to
minus
df by dx
divided by
dg by dx.
Is that right?
Let's see.
Yeah.
Minus,
because I've got to transpose,
and then lambda will be
df by dx
divided by dg by dx.
Now let's plug it into here.
Alright,
let's plug
lambda into here.
So we have lambda
minus sine
df by dx
divided by dg by dx.
But instead of dividing
by dg by dx over here,
let's just multiply
by dg by dx over here.
Alright,
it really was
divided by dg by dx,
but then I just multiply
the right hand side of zero.
Hopefully it's the same equation.
So,
I'm not even going to look.
I hope it's
the same equation.
Is it the same equation?
Hmm?
It's got a minus sign.
They both have minus sign.
minus d by dy
They're both equal to zero.
I don't know.
Right.
We have to multiply
by minus one to get them to be the same.
But they are the same.
So this was just a simple illustration
that the method of
there's an intuitive geometric
picture of it,
but
it takes longer to explain
than just to do the arithmetic.
The method of Lagrange multipliers
is completely equivalent
to solving the constraint
and then plugging
back in.
And as you
can see,
it's usually easier.
Okay,
so what are the rules again?
You take the constraint,
you multiply it by lambda.
You add it to the
thing that you're trying to make minimum or maximum.
You then differentiate
as if you were trying to
minimize the whole thing.
You get two equations.
Let's see.
Or however many
equations there are
variables in the problem.
Doesn't have to be two.
But you can do it.
Okay,
so the other one is df
by dy
plus lambda
dg by dy
equals zero.
You solve those two equations.
They're two equations for two unknowns,
x and y.
But then,
after you're finished,
you choose
lambda so that the constraint
is actually satisfied.
So that the constraint g equals zero
is satisfied.
So I gave you some
example.
Make up your own examples.
Work out,
I don't know,
instead of
x squared plus y squared,
take
x cubed plus y cubed
and the constraint is
that sine of x plus y is three.
I don't know.
No,
sine of x plus y can't be
three.
e to the x plus y is equal to three.
Right.
Alright,
just make up an example or two.
Try doing it by
eliminating one of the various
variables and you'll quickly discover
that it's usually easier
to just use the method of Lagrange
multipliers.
But one of the nice
things about the method of Lagrange
multipliers,
it doesn't force
you to single out one of the
variables for special
treatment.
The method of,
that I
used here,
singled
out x
as opposed to y.
It wasn't special,
but
I singled it out to solve
for it.
I solved for y,
actually.
And so I didn't treat
the variables symmetrically.
No problem,
there's nothing wrong with that.
But it's a nice feature of the
method of Lagrange multipliers that it
treats the variables symmetrically.
Let me just
tell you without
proving.
Supposing I had a
function of several variables.
Function of
x1 dot
dot dot dot
xn.
Whatever
they happen to be.
And now I have a collection
of constraints.
Not
just one constraint.
For example,
I may have two constraints.
One of the constraints might be that the total
energy is fixed.
Another constraint
might be that the total charge is
fixed.
Or the energy
and the angular momentum.
They would be two
separate constraints.
And so I would have a
set of constraints.
g1,
let's call it,
is equal
to zero.
g1 is
a function of the same set of variables.
g2 is equal
to zero.
However many I have.
It's important that there not be
more constraints than variables.
Otherwise you can't solve it.
If you have more constraints than
variables,
in general there is no solution.
But
fewer constraints
than variables.
Then what you do is you introduce a Lagrange
multiplier for each of the
constraints.
So you write
f
plus the first
Lagrange multiplier times g1
plus the second
Lagrange multiplier times g2.
And however many Lagrange multipliers
you have or however many constraints you have.
And then you minimize
or
differentiate
the result with respect to the
x's.
Set them equal to zero.
The f
plus the sum
of lambda i gi
with respect
to
each one of the x's
and set it equal to zero.
Solve it
and then
choose all of the
lambdas.
How many lambdas
do you have?
One for each constraint.
Choose all of the lambdas
so that all the constraints
are satisfied.
That's
the method of Lagrange multipliers
and as I said it is
central to statistical
mechanics.
We will use
it over and over again
and if you're not familiar
with it just look it up on
I'm sure you can find it easily on
the,
just google it
Lagrange multipliers
it's probably a Wikipedia article
and try it out,
work with it
a little bit and become familiar with it.
I will not explain it again
but I will use it again
over and over.
What is the thing that
we're typically going to minimize?
The entropy.
What are the constraints?
Constraints such
as we know the total energy,
we know
the total whatever it happens to be.
Okay,
next
little theorem.
These things are too small to really be called
theorems.
Stirling's approximation
to the factorial function.
Everybody know what
Stirling's approximation is?
Anybody not know?
Oh no no no
but I mean you know how to prove it.
好
謝謝
where it comes from.
Alright,
so let's just review very quickly
Sterling's approximation.
N factorial occurs over and over in all sorts of
probability contexts.
Every time you calculate permutations and combinations
in order to calculate probabilities,
N factorials appear all over the place.
Okay,
generally the N's which appear are very large numbers.
They have to do with
how many ways there are arranging
or rearranging a large number of variables
in some large number of ways,
and so it's important to have an approximation of a
reliable approximation which becomes better and
better as N becomes large for
the factorial function.
N factorial.
Equals 1 times 2 times 3
dot dot dot dot up to N.
That's the factorial function,
right?
Alright,
now I want to find a good estimate for it.
What I'm going to begin
with is by taking its logarithm.
I'm going to calculate,
I'm going to estimate
it.
I'm going to calculate the logarithm.
I'm going to estimate the logarithm of N factorial.
Once I've estimated the
logarithm of N factorial,
how do I estimate N factorial?
We exponentiate the logarithm.
Right.
So it's just as good to...
Alright,
so let's calculate,
let's estimate the logarithm of N factorial.
Log N factorial.
That's equal to log of 1 plus log
of 2 plus log of 3 plus and so
forth and so on.
Log 1 happens to be 0.
But nevertheless,
write it down.
Plus log 2 plus log 3
dot dot dot plus log N.
Alright,
so what do I have?
Let's plot N in this direction.
Let's plot logarithm of N.
Now what does the logarithm function look like?
It looks like it's 0 at N equals 1.
And it looks something like this.
And basically what we're doing
is we're adding up the areas.
N equals 1,
N equals 2,
N equals 3,
dot dot dot.
We're adding up the areas under this
logarithm curve here.
Alright.
When N becomes large,
it's a good
approximation of N factorial.
breakfast
Since the least possible approximation to the
sum to replace it by the integral.
Right.
The integral.
So let's consider picture 2.
So let's consider then instead of considering the sum here,
this is sum of log
of N from N equals 1,
N equals sorry it's log of,
let's
call it log of X.
Log of X from X equals 1.
1 to x equals n and we're going
to replace that by integral dx logarithm of x
Okay,
so we have the problem of integrating logarithm of x
It's easy to do,
you just look it up in a table of integrals
That incidentally means find the function
whose derivative is logarithm of x
I'll tell you how I would think
about it if I didn't know the answer
I would begin by saying,
well logarithm,
at least for large x,
is a very slowly varying function
It practically doesn't vary at all
Logarithm is terribly slowly varying
So I might just try saying,
well what if this logarithm were a constant
Then what would be the integral dx of a constant?
x times the constant,
right?
x times the constant
Okay,
so let's try x times log x
x times log x
If log x were a constant,
and it's very very slowly varying
If we replaced it by a constant,
then the right answer would be x times the constant
So this shouldn't be too far off
Now let's differentiate it and see
if we really get logarithm of x
So what's the derivative of x log x?
Well,
it's got two factors
So the derivative of the first
factor is 1 times the second factor
That gives us,
good,
that gives us log x,
right?
But there's another term,
what's the other term?
It's x times the derivative of logarithm of x
But the derivative of logarithm
of x is 1 over x
Okay,
so what do we get?
Plus 1
Not log x plus 1,
but log x
1 plus log x
So that's not so good,
we wanted to get log x
We didn't want to get 1 plus log x
Okay,
but all we have to do now is
We have to subtract something from this
Whose derivative is 1
Which is x
That,
my friends,
is the integral of log x
x log x minus x
Differentiate it,
you'll get x,
sorry,
you'll get log x
So we now know that this,
oh,
this integral goes from 1 to n
And the answer is
n log n minus n
I've just substituted for x,
I've just
Integral from 1 to n
One end point just gives 0
The other end point gives n log n minus n
This is Sterling's approximation for the logarithm
Of n factorial
And actually this is the way
we're going to wind up using it
n log n minus n
Because we're generally going to be
interested in the logarithm of n factorial
But just to
Just to,
hmm,
I don't know what's going on
Just to complete the calculation,
we now want to exponentiate it
Alright,
so we want to take
e to the n log n
e to the minus n
We have the sum or the difference of two terms
When we're going to exponentiate it,
I will get
e to the n log n
That's,
what's e to the n log n?
That's n to the n
Same as n to the n
n to the n is the same
as e to the n log n
Times e to the minus n
This is Sterling's approximation
Sterling's approximation to the factorial function
It grows very fast
n to the n grows very rapidly
But not quite as rapidly as n to the n
It's modulated by a decreasing
function e to the minus n
Okay,
so that's a second little lemma or theorem
That you must know in order to do statistical mechanics
And the third one
Is a combinatoric fact
Simple combinatoric fact
But one
And once we do it,
we won't do it again
Or we won't explain it again
But let's do it anyway
I'll tell you what the
problem that we're really interested in
Supposing I have
n copies of the same system
Now you can just think of this as n boxes
n boxes
And each box can be in a state
The states of a single box
I'll label them over here
They actually correspond to the energy states of the system
But here they are
Vertically is energy
This is the i-th state over here
And each one of these boxes
Can be identified with a state in here
In other words,
each box is in a state
Or has a particular state
Labeled by one of these i's
We could draw a picture
Or we could draw a figure
If the first box happens to
be in this state over here
I'll put a line over there like that
If the second box happens
to be in the same state
I'll put another line over here
Supposing the third box is
in a different state over here
And the fourth box is
in a different one over here
And the fifth box
Let's put a fifth box
in just to add one more
Just happens to be in the
same state as this one over here
So a diagram like this
Is a description of the states
Of n copies
There are n copies here
Of a system
N copies
Each with its own state
Now
Here's an interesting quantity
Oh
What should we label
Yes,
we labeled the states i
Notice that i does not stand
for which box we're talking about
It stands for the possible state
Within a box
The possible configuration within a box
And I'm taking them to be discrete
Alright
I can ask how many boxes are there
In the first state
This is i equals one
How many boxes are there
Well in this case there are
no boxes with i equals one
But in general the answer will be an integer
N sub one
That's the number of boxes
In state number one
The number of boxes
In state number two
Is n sub two
N sub three
And so forth
What do these n's have to add up to
I wonder if the lecture is
supposed to be in here tonight
It's supposed to be in the other room,
no?
Yeah,
okay
Okay
What must these n's add up to
Begin
The number of boxes in the first state
Plus the number of boxes in the second state
Plus the number of boxes in the third state
And so forth have to add up to n
But the question I want to ask is
How many ways are there
Of choosing a state for each box
Such that there are n one
Boxes in the state one
N two boxes in the state two
N three boxes in the state three
And so forth
How many ways are there
Of getting a given set of n's
Okay
Anybody know the answer?
Oh I wrote the answer down in the
Yeah,
the answer was written in the notes
So you do know the answer I presume
Okay
Let me write the answer down
And then if we have time
I'll try to explain why it's the answer
The answer involves a bunch of factorials
And is the primary reason
Why
Why I bothered
Giving you an approximation
For the factorial function
Alright,
the answer is very simple
It's simple but subtle
It's capital N factorial
What should we call this thing?
I think I just called it
I don't remember
Did I give it a name in the notes?
The number of ways
Of distributing a state to each box
Such that
There are n one boxes
In state number one
N two boxes in state number two
And so forth and so on
I'll just call it number
Number
Alright
It is equal
To capital N factorial
Divided by a product
And the product
Is
N one factorial
N two factorial
N three factorial
Dot dot dot
What happens if some of the states
Are unoccupied altogether
For example
This state over here
Doesn't appear in any of these boxes
Let's call this the forty second state over here
What is N sub forty eight?
Zero
That looks a little odd
Zero factorial downstairs
But what's zero factorial?
One
That's the definition of a factorial function
So
All of the unoccupied states
Just give a bunch of ones
One times one times one times one is just one
So you only get something interesting
From the states which are actually filled
And if there are three boxes
In the first state
Then there's a three factorial
Four boxes in the second state
Then there's a four factorial
And so forth
Alright this is the answer
To the question
Of how many ways there are
Of making a configuration
Where there's a given number of boxes
In each state
Let's see if we can
At least motivate the answer
I wonder if we should just go in there
And get some seats
Yeah
Yeah I think that's the thing to do
If we come in a little early next time
I'll finish up the derivation of this
Ten minutes early
But you can also look it up again
Wikipedia
For more
Please visit us at
stanford.edu
Thank you