Stanford University
We did not talk about Helmholtz free energy,
did we?
We did?
What did I say about Helmholtz free energy?
Just the definition,
that it's related to the logarithm of the partition?
That's all?
Yeah.
Okay,
good.
I believe the last time was next time,
ideal gas.
Oh,
we never got to the ideal gas at all?
No,
we didn't.
My problem is I'm teaching this
course both in graduate school and here,
and I'm completely far.
Did we prove the following identity?
You were going to do yt equal one over theta.
We didn't do that either?
That's right.
Okay.
Let's assume that for now.
Oh,
I thought we had done the ideal gas.
Okay,
before we do the ideal gas,
I want to get to the
ideas of volume and free energy.
We'll need it.
So,
let's define a concept.
I think I told you last time
that the logarithm of the partition function
or is there a minus sign?
I think there's a minus sign.
T times the logarithm of the partition
function is called the Helmholtz free energy,
A.
Okay.
The Helmholtz free energy has an important meaning,
but before we get into its important usefulness,
before we get into it,
did we count,
did we prove,
all right,
you're going to have to help me out.
Did we?
Did we prove the relationship between energy,
free energy and entropy?
We did.
Oh,
good.
So,
we don't have to do that.
Okay.
In particular,
temperature times entropy minus the energy
is equal to the free energy?
Yes.
Okay.
We did that.
Good.
I'm all bollocked up because of
my confusions about what I'm teaching where.
Okay.
So,
we don't have to do that.
Did we talk about control parameters at all?
We did fluctuations.
Oh,
we did fluctuations,
but we did not do control.
We did fluctuations in ideal gas.
Okay.
Before we do the ideal gas,
I would like to introduce
the concept of pressure and how
you calculate the pressure in a system.
This is still more theory and less application,
but still,
if we want to do the ideal gas,
I think we'd better know what pressure is.
Okay.
The definition of pressure is,
of course,
through the definition of force on the walls.
We could imagine,
if you like,
a cylinder with a piston,
and we could measure the force
on this piston due to the
collisions of the molecules with the piston,
and that would
define the pressure.
The pressure is the force divided
by the area of the piston,
force divided by area.
I don't even think I'll bother writing that down.
We all know that.
So the question is,
how do we calculate the force on a system?
Well,
we could try to calculate the collision with the molecules.
Every time a molecule bounces off,
it makes a sudden force on here,
an impulsive sudden
force.
We could average the force over enough time
so that the actual force is a very,
very wiggly
function that jumps around a lot.
We could average it over time
and define a pressure in that way.
That is not a particularly
convenient way to define pressure,
nor is it a very general
way.
So,
molecules hitting walls are not the
only way that you can get pressure.
Another way,
for example,
you could get pressure is there might be direct forces,
not just
collisional forces,
not just contact forces of the molecules with the walls,
but there
might be a potential energy,
a long-range force of some kind,
maybe not long-range,
but semi-long-range force.
So,
you could get a lot of
energy between the molecules and the piston,
and they might
push or pull on the piston.
And that would not have to do with direct collisions.
So we need a more general definition,
both of force in general,
but in particular force
on the piston in this particular setup.
Now,
let me remind you what the
definition of force is in mechanics.
The definition of force in mechanics is the two things.
The definition of force is the change in
the potential energy of a system with respect
to position,
or the change in potential
energy with respect to some coordinate.
Let's write down the formula just to remind you.
The change in the potential energy,
let's write potential energy,
let me call it U,
with respect to a coordinate actually is minus the force.
Okay.
Now,
that suggests that we define the pressure
or the force on the cylinder here,
on the
piston,
as the change in energy of the
system with respect to motion of the piston.
We can either think of the change...
Yeah.
That's a good way to think about it.
The change in the energy of the system,
how much does the energy of the system change
when we move the piston a little bit?
Another way to think about it is the
work done on the piston per unit position change.
The work done.
So if we can calculate the change in energy,
now what will that be?
That will be the change in energy minus.
The change in energy of the gas
in here as we change the volume.
We change the volume a little bit,
the energy in there will change,
and that is the work
done on the piston.
It's also minus the work done
by the piston on the gas.
Energy conservation tells us that the work done
on the piston by the gas is the same
as the work done on the...
Oh,
the minus sign.
The work done on the piston by the gas.
We'll have a little definition of the
work done by the gas on the piston.
So...
And we'll focus on the work
done by the piston on the gas.
So we could imagine squeezing the gas a little bit,
changing the volume,
or changing the
coordinate of the piston,
and the work done on the gas,
or the change in energy of the
gas with respect to a small motion
of the piston is a force of gravity.
course called the force on the piston.
Is that clear?
Alright,
so that's a
definition.
The change in energy,
called delta E divided by delta X,
where X could
be the position of the piston,
X.
That's the force on the piston.
It's
important in this context that we move the piston slowly.
Why?
Let me give you a
crazy example.
Supposing,
let's move the piston outward.
Okay?
The formula is still true,
the change in energy of the gas with respect
to the location of the
piston is related to the force.
Supposing we change
the position of the piston really fast.
So fast
that
the
we were moving the piston faster
than the velocity of the molecules.
What would be the force on the piston
when it receded very quickly away from the molecules?
Zero.
Why?
Because no molecule would bang into the
piston and so there would be no force.
So it's important that we move the piston slowly.
Slowly so that some average of
the collisions can be averaged over.
So we move the piston slowly,
adiabatically is the word,
we move the piston adiabatically,
and we calculate the change
in energy with respect to position.
Now if we multiply this
by the area of the piston,
I shouldn't call it A because
that's going to be free energy,
let's call it little a,
this becomes the force divided by little a,
the area of the piston,
and what's little a times delta x?
Delta x.
That's the change in volume.
The area of the piston times the change in
position of the piston is the change in volume.
So we could write that the change in energy divided
by the volume is the force divided by the area.
What's the force divided by the area?
The pressure.
Now I have a feeling I have
the sign wrong and I'll tell you why.
It's just a question of keeping clear in your head whether
we're talking about the change in the energy of the gas
or the change in the energy of
the position of the piston when it's pushed.
All right.
If I squeeze the gas,
do I increase or decrease
the energy of the molecules inside?
You increase it.
So just to check which the right sign is.
I'm thinking of E now
as the energy of the gas,
not the energy of the piston.
All right.
If I move the piston inward,
I decrease the volume.
Is that correct?
All right.
But the pressure is positive.
Delta E is positive.
Delta V is negative.
So delta E divided by delta V would be
negative if I squeeze the gas a little bit,
but that must correspond to positive pressure,
so there must be a minus sign here.
All right.
And there is.
So the change in energy per
unit volume is minus the pressure.
That minus sign always seems a little peculiar to me,
but it's right.
And as I said,
that's the way to think about it.
Squeezing the gas decreases the
volume but increases the pressure.
Okay.
Now,
again,
we must do it slowly.
Otherwise,
the point is that pressure is
a concept that is a good idea.
Again,
an average concept,
averaged over some time.
So you can't do it instantly fast.
You better do it slowly.
And what's more,
what's also important is that in
this formula that the only changes
in energy are due to the motion of the piston.
I can imagine other changes.
I can imagine that while I
move the piston a little bit slowly,
I could heat the gas
by putting a flame under it.
Okay.
Let's see.
What?
Or cool it.
Or take energy out of it.
Then this formula would not be right.
For example,
I could squeeze the gas a little bit,
which would tend to increase the energy,
but at the same time remove heat from the gas,
all right,
by connecting it to a refrigerator.
All right.
I could decrease the energy.
By removing heat,
but squeeze the gas,
which would tend to increase the energy.
The net effect being,
if I tuned it correctly,
to not change the energy at all.
Then I would have a change
in energy and a change in volume,
but it wouldn't give me
the right answer for the pressure.
In fact,
it wouldn't necessarily need any pressure.
To do that.
Okay.
You just change the volume,
remove heat.
You don't need any pressure to do that.
In fact,
if you remove heat,
the volume will naturally change by itself.
So it's important also that you not have
any other sources of energy coming into and
out of the system other than
the work done by moving the piston.
Okay.
No heat allowed in and out.
You move the piston slowly.
What is such a process called?
Adiabatic.
Could you also just say that,
well,
there's a pressure term and then there's another term?
Sure.
We'll do that.
But we want to first define pressure.
Before we write that there's
a pressure term and another term,
we've got to define pressure.
Okay.
Now,
adiabatic also means a constant entropy.
Have we discussed that or not?
I don't remember.
We haven't.
All right.
So let me explain to you why an adiabatic process,
that means one done slowly,
why that
is a process at constant entropy.
This really ultimately comes from quantum mechanics.
It can be phrased in terms of classical mechanics,
but it's easier to phrase it in terms of,
well,
we don't even need quantum mechanics.
We don't need quantum mechanics.
All we need is the idea that there are
energy levels and that the energy levels are discrete.
Now,
this is the energy levels of a system,
but let's plot horizontally the volume of
the system.
So,
here we are.
There's a system.
It has a collection of possible energies.
The energies just being the sums of
the energies of all the particles in there.
If we were doing quantum mechanics,
the energies would be discrete.
If we're not doing quantum mechanics,
then we have to be a little more careful,
but in
quantum mechanics,
we have discrete energy levels and
we can label the i-th energy level.
Horizontally,
we have the volume of the system.
The energy levels are not independent
of the volume of the system.
If we change the system by changing the volume,
the energy levels will change.
For example,
if you slowly change the volume of the system,
then the values of,
I don't
mean the energy itself,
I mean the values of
the possible values of the energy,
the
energy levels of the system,
the possible values of the energy,
they will also change.
For example,
if you have a box of a certain size,
if the size of the box is a certain
size,
if the size is very small,
the energy levels are very,
very well separated.
This is a quantum mechanics fact.
A small box,
it takes a lot of energy
to jump to the next level,
the next energy level.
A large box,
it only takes a small energy
to jump to the next energy level.
So as the volume changes,
the energy levels themselves,
the individual values of the
energies of both a single
particle or just a whole system,
they also change.
So let's imagine plotting them as they change.
The energy levels evolve.
Typically,
as you make the system bigger,
the energy levels decrease,
so I've indicated
them by a decreasing function.
And so forth.
No,
not particularly.
No reason for that.
On certain situations it might be,
but in general,
it's typically,
again,
it doesn't
have to be any particular kind of function or volume.
But there are two important properties.
They are connected to the
issue of conservation of information.
You can think of the changing of the volume,
the slow changing of the volume,
as if you
were to change the volume,
as the time evolution of a system.
What do we know about the time evolution
of systems in both classical mechanics and quantum
mechanics?
Number one,
the levels,
no level disappears.
The energy levels just evolve
and they don't disappear or reappear.
No new energy levels appear as you
change the volume or any other control parameter.
A control parameter means the
thing that you can dial slowly.
As you slowly dial a control parameter,
I'll give you other examples of control parameters,
but the volume is the most familiar one,
the energy levels don't disappear,
and number
two,
they don't cross each other.
They don't cross and they don't disappear.
They stay in the same order.
So the lowest energy level stays lowest,
the next one stays second lowest,
and so forth.
That is a property of
both quantum mechanics and quantum mechanics.
And there's an analog of it in classical mechanics.
Now,
supposing we start our system at a given
energy level and we slowly vary the control
parameter.
What happens?
There's a theorem about this,
and the theorem is called the adiabatic theorem.
It's a quantum mechanics theorem.
There's an analog of it,
as I said,
for classical mechanics.
The quantum mechanics theorem says that the
system is a system of quantum mechanics.
The system,
as you change very slowly,
change the control parameter,
the system will remain
in a state of definite energy,
and it will just track along these lines.
So if you start the system over
here with this precise value of the energy,
and if you
know the shape of these curves,
you vary the volume slowly,
you know that you'll wind up
over here,
again,
in a precise energy level.
What happens if we know,
let's suppose our state of
knowledge in the initial state is
such that all we know is that
we start in one of these three levels.
One of these three levels.
That's all we know.
Then,
after a period,
we know that we're still
in one of these three levels.
That's all we know.
Okay?
What happens if we know that the probability
for being in one of these three levels is
one half,
one quarter,
and one quarter?
One half,
one quarter,
and one quarter.
That does sum to one,
doesn't it?
Yeah.
One half,
one quarter,
and one quarter.
What will the probabilities for being
in the different levels over here be?
One half,
one quarter,
one quarter.
What happens to the entropy?
If we start with a given entropy here?
It does not change.
Why?
Because the probability distribution doesn't change.
The probability of being in the ith level doesn't change.
So we can say that P
of I is an adiabatic invariant.
That's the terminology.
An adiabatic invariant means a very slow change.
The probability of being in
the ith state is one half.
Okay.
Even though the energy of the ith state may change,
the energy of each of these states
change,
how can that be consistent with energy conservation?
Because we do some work by changing the parameters.
Exactly.
We do some work by changing the parameters.
So the levels change,
meaning to say the energy levels change,
the energy that they have,
but the probability of being
in the ith level doesn't change,
and that assures that the
entropy,
which is after all just a summation
of P of I log P of I,
you know what I mean,
P of I,
but that doesn't change.
So the entropy is an adiabatic invariant.
Let's come back now.
Now this is really central that energy is an adiabatic,
sorry,
entropy is an adiabatic,
energy is not an adiabatic invariant.
Entropy is an adiabatic invariant.
And the ultimate reason for it is information conservation.
Without it,
we could have energy levels running into
each other and all sorts of funny things
happening,
and the probability distribution would
not be an adiabatic invariant.
Okay,
let's come over to here now.
We said that the pressure was the rate
of change of energy with respect to volume with
a minus sign.
In an adiabatic process.
We now know that that means at fixed entropy,
at fixed entropy,
so the definition of pressure,
let's write it as a calculus equation,
minus the pressure is the derivative of the energy
with respect to the volume keeping fixed the entropy.
Now keeping fixed the,
not keeping fixed the temperature,
certainly not keeping fixed
the energy,
the derivative of the energy with
respect to the energy is what?
One.
It's certainly not the derivative
of energy with respect to energy.
Sorry,
sorry,
I forget what I said.
The derivative of energy with respect to
volume at fixed something defines the pressure.
The something is the entropy.
Okay.
Think of fixed entropy as first of all,
again,
meaning do it slowly so that you have time
for things to average,
but also without adding other forms
of energy to the system that you
haven't accounted for,
then that's not having to do with this pressure,
then this is the
definition,
and that is the definition of pressure.
There's a more general concept,
which I might as well tell you.
There are other kinds of control parameters besides volume.
Let me give you an example.
External magnetic field.
Again,
you could imagine a dial that
ramps up current or external electric field,
which
is a dial that ramps up the
charge and capacitor plates or anything like that.
Those are also control parameters.
And those control parameters also,
when you change them,
do work on a system.
Same kind of formula,
and you could write it more generally.
Instead of volume,
we could introduce a control parameter x.
Volume,
replace it by x,
whatever x is,
magnetic field or anything else.
Instead of pressure,
let's define the variable y that goes with x.
Okay.
The definition of y is simply minus y
is equal to the derivative of energy with respect
to x,
whatever x is,
at constant entropy.
So there are lots of things like this.
The most familiar,
and we'll mostly work with this,
the most familiar being volume and pressure.
These variables come in pairs.
They come in pairs.
y,
which is the general force of the current,
is the force of the current.
The force,
if you like,
the derivative of energy with respect to x,
and x.
They're called conjugate thermodynamic variables.
The most familiar,
again,
pressure and volume.
The question is,
how do we calculate the pressure?
Well,
that's not so hard.
All we have to do is figure out
the energy as a function of the entropy.
And the volume.
And energy as a function of energy,
of volume and entropy.
And then we can differentiate keeping the entropy fixed.
But calculating the entropy of
a general system is usually difficult.
It's usually a pain in the neck,
frankly.
You can do it.
But there's a simpler formula for the pressure.
And the simple formula involves not the rate of
change of energy with respect to volume at fixed entropy,
but something else.
This is also equal to the rate of change
of something else with respect to volume at fixed temperature.
Why is it easier to be
able to deal with fixed temperature?
The reason it's easier to be able
to deal with fixed temperature is very simple.
When you write the partition function,
everything goes back to the partition function.
You calculate the partition function.
It's handed to you.
It's a function of temperature.
That's the natural variable.
That's the variable that the partition function is
directly presented to you as a function of.
And if you can differentiate the appropriate
thing with respect to volume at fixed temperature,
it's usually much easier than
first having to calculate the entropy
and then trying to differentiate
something keeping the entropy fixed.
It's usually much more difficult.
This is easier.
What is the thing that you differentiate?
The Helmholtz free energy.
And the Helmholtz free energy?
That's not so hard.
Once you know the partition function and its logarithm,
you multiply it by the temperature,
and then you differentiate the Helmholtz
free energy with respect to the volume.
Now,
I haven't told you why that's true.
So,
since I don't like leaving loose ends,
we should prove the theorem that says,
let's see what it says.
It's a little mathematics theorem,
not very hard.
Well,
it says that the derivative
of energy with respect to volume
at fixed entropy is the same
as the derivative of the free energy
Sorry,
there should be a minus.
Yeah,
same thing.
No,
sorry.
It's the derivative of the free energy
with respect to the volume at fixed temperature.
All right.
In order to prove this,
we need a little bit of a theorem.
It's a small theorem.
It's a calculus theorem.
It's practically not a theorem.
It's just a simple identity.
And let's see what the theorem is.
Let's plot two independent...
Any questions?
No questions.
All right.
So,
let's plot horizontally the volume...
or it could be any other control parameter.
The theorem I'm going to teach you,
which is in the notes,
you can apply to any control parameter at all.
But let's take the volume as our special case.
And vertically,
let's see,
what did I plot vertically?
I think the temperature.
Yeah,
the temperature.
Now,
let's imagine drawing the line...
Let's see,
we need the lines.
Let me see what lines we need.
Well,
let's first start with a point.
All right.
Now,
this point,
at every point,
is a value of energy and also of entropy.
The temperature,
if you know the temperature and you know the volume,
you know everything about the system,
and you can compute the energy and the entropy.
Let's see.
I want to make sure my diagram
looks consistent with the one in my notes.
So...
Uh...
Yeah.
All right.
We can also draw lines of constant entropy and energy.
What do they look like?
I don't know what they look like,
but let's draw in just some arbitrary lines.
Here's a line of constant energy.
And let's put in a line of constant entropy.
Right through that point.
Okay?
So the entropy along this line is constant,
and the energy along this line is constant.
S equals constant.
Energy equals constant.
Now,
what do I want to compute?
I want to compute...
the rate of change of energy
with respect to volume
at fixed entropy.
That's the pressure.
That is the pressure.
Minus the pressure.
All right?
But I would like to compute it
in terms of derivatives with respect to temperature.
I want to compute it in a different way.
All right.
So what are we computing here?
Let's take a differential change in volume.
Here's a differential change in volume,
dv.
This is the change in energy
when I change the volume a little bit,
keeping the entropy fixed.
So it's the difference between the entropy at the energy
at this point and this point.
Is that clear?
If that's not clear,
we might as well not go any further.
The rate of change of energy
when we change the volume a little bit
is the difference between the
energy here and the energy here,
divided by dv,
of course.
Divided by dv.
Here's how I'm going to calculate it.
I'm going to calculate the change in the energy
when I go horizontally.
That's at fixed temperature.
And then when I drop down vertically.
So the change in energy
in going from here to here
is the sum of two terms.
The first is the change in energy at fixed temperature.
Okay?
This is the change.
This should be partial derivative.
Partial derivative of energy
with respect to volume
at fixed temperature.
That's this change here.
And then there's the vertical change.
Okay?
What is the vertical change?
Well,
in going from here to here,
the entropy changes.
Why does the entropy change?
Because the entropy is different over here
than it is over here.
The entropy was constant along here.
It has a different value.
Let me use a different color.
The entropy has a different value over here.
And so we can compute
the change in the energy going from here to here
as the change
in the energy with respect to the entropy.
We're changing the entropy a little bit.
Times the change in the entropy
when we go from here to here.
The change in the energy with respect to the entropy
times the change in the entropy
will give us the change in the entropy.
So we have to multiply this
by the change in the entropy
when we change what?
When we go from this curve to this curve.
It doesn't matter whether we go
from this curve to this curve
from here to here
or from here to here.
Why?
Because the entropy is constant along these lines.
So the change in the entropy,
The entropy is a
times the change in the entropy
in dropping down vertically.
What's the change in the entropy
in dropping down vertically?
It's the change in the entropy dropping down vertically.
Change in the entropy
with respect to the temperature at fixed volume.
Fixed volume is vertical.
What's that?
The s by the...
We're not changing the volume going down.
You said that it's the same whether
we go down or we go left.
Yeah.
It's the same whether we
go down or we go up.
We go down or we go left.
What's the question?
The question was,
then both of them would have fixed the temperature.
You could use either one.
We can use either one.
Okay.
No,
okay,
good.
What is this?
This is dE by dS at fixed something.
dE by dS at fixed x.
Sorry,
at fixed volume.
Oh,
okay.
Yeah,
at fixed volume.
The e by dS at fixed volume
times the s by dt at fixed...
No,
no,
I've got something wrong here.
The s by dx at fixed temperature.
The s...
The s by...
The temperature's going down.
Oh,
yeah.
The e by dS at fixed volume,
dS by the volume.
I'm sorry.
The s by...
dE...
You can only fix one of them.
Wait,
dE...
I just think...
dE by dS at fixed volume times the
change in s in going from here to here.
The change in s from going from here to
here is the s by d volume at fixed t.
I have too many variables in my formulas.
All right.
The change in going from here to here in the entropy
is the change in entropy with respect to volume at fixed temperature.
That's the formula that we want,
I think.
Yeah,
that's the formula that we want.
Okay.
Now...
Would you make that clearer again?
Yeah.
I will.
All right.
The substrates are...
Yeah.
We have this,
which is dE by d volume at fixed temperature.
Okay?
Well,
better yet,
let's just write dE.
Let's not even write dE dV.
The change in energy in going from here to here is the derivative of energy with
respect to volume at fixed temperature times the change in volume in going from here to here.
Right?
That's one term.
That's in going from here to here.
And then vertically going downward is minus the derivative
of energy with respect to a change in the entropy.
The entropy here and the entropy here is different.
At fixed volume...
That's because I've dropped vertically.
I've dropped vertically.
At fixed volume is minus the
times the change in the song p.
And that goes along to A.
It's
All right.
It's stuff.
Okay,
you just finished this.
For some reason,
if we look at our first Vegetations here,
you can see that we
now have thisAS SOLV in here.
And then pancakes for thisSX whose patron
value in go from A to A.
Sort of the same thing.
Well,
that's when the same thing
is going to change in volume.
Yeah.
You know what?
of energy with respect to volume keeping temperature fixed,
that's horizontal,
then
derivative of energy with respect to
entropy at fixed volume times the change
in entropy in going from here to here.
In this formula you can think of
the energy as a function of volume and
entropy.
Yeah,
yeah,
but whatever it is it's the
change in energy with respect to
volume keeping the temperature fixed.
That's the coefficient that goes with
volume and the other one is derivative
with respect to entropy times the change
in entropy.
Why?
Because you're going from here back to here rather than
from here to here.
You're going from here down to
here and so the sign is negative.
Sign is negative.
You just spend some time with it
and you'll see why the time is negative.
Okay,
now what is the change in
entropy in going from here to here?
That's this over here.
The change in entropy in
going from here to here is
also the change in entropy of
the energy with respect to volume.
Now that's the same thing as I say.
Oh God.
But if you look at the logic,
you're going from here to here.
I want you here.
Which is the same as the change
in entropy in going from here to
here.
This if you want to get the right
answer,
I just have to make it clear to you.
It's the same.
See,
there's an segurism is right and theاهhi.
Yeah.
It's the same thing.
The?!?
just not here.
is the change in entropy and
going from this point to that point
which is minus the change in entropy
of going from that point to that point
okay what's the change in entropy
of going from here to here?
it's the derivative
of the entropy
with respect to the volume
at fixed temperature
that's the change in entropy going from here to here
at fixed temperature,
yeah
times dv
no,
it's not equal to zero
it's the change in energy going from here to here
that's what it is
now if I divide it by the volume
then I get
the derivative of the entropy
of going from here to here
and I get the derivative of energy
with respect to volume
along this line
which is constant entropy
that's equal
derivative of energy with respect to volume
at fixed temperature
dv
minus the derivative of energy
with respect to entropy
at fixed volume
say it again
dv goes
dv after d divided by dv
minus the volume
yeah,
yeah
take the dv out
I have a certain threshold
when the symbols just get too many
I just really lose them
the edv at fixed temperature
minus the e ds at fixed volume
ds by dv at fixed temperature
that's your first line
that's my first line,
yeah
I just rewrote it
okay now why is it interesting?
this is the thing
oh incidentally this is a calculus theorem here
I haven't done it
I haven't used the interpretation of these variables yet
this is a calculus theorem about
relationships between derivatives with
respect to two different variables
so it's not a deep theory
theorem about energy and entropy or anything else
it's just the calculus theorem
okay now
now let's apply it
okay now let's apply it
to the real thing
what is the derivative of the energy
with respect to the entropy at fixed volume?
now at fixed volume we're talking about a system
with no change in the control parameter
it's just the same kind of system we
studied before we even talked about control parameters
do you remember before we introduced control
parameters to do work on the system
do you remember what the e by ds was?
temperature
so now we use some physics
now we're going beyond calculus
and we can write that
dE by dV at fixed s
which is the pressure
which is minus the pressure
that's the thing we're trying to calculate
that's equal to dE by dV at fixed temperature
well it's a lot easier to calculate things
at fixed temperature than it is at fixed energy
so that's a good sign
I just rewrote this over here
and then minus
but this is just the temperature
dE by dS at fixed volume
temperature
times dS by dV
at fixed temperature
all I'm doing
is using a little bit of physics
the physics wasn't saying that
dE by dS at fixed volume
was temperature
and a little bit of calculus
to write down this theorem
and I have succeeded
in writing the pressure in terms
of derivatives with respect to temperature
instead of with respect
sorry
derivatives at fixed temperature
instead of at fixed entropy
that
is an advantage
because it means you don't have
to go and calculate the entropy
and keep it constant while you're varying the volume
alright but this is even simpler
this over here
is the same as
the derivative of Ts
with respect to the volume
at fixed T
why is that?
because the derivative of T with respect to T
uh
yeah
okay
so I can pull this out
I can pull the T inside the derivative
and this is just the derivative of Ts
with respect to volume at fixed temperature
and this
is the derivative of energy
with respect to volume at fixed temperature
the result is
that this is equal to the derivative
with respect to the volume
at fixed temperature
of E minus Ts
E minus Ts
and that's the
and that's minus the pressure
okay
these two terms combine together
to just say
derivative with respect
they're both derivatives with respect
to volume at fixed temperature
and the result is derivative of
E minus Ts at fixed volume
well what is E minus Ts?
it's A
the Helmholtz free energy
so we now have
a lovely theorem
that says that pressure
is equal to
let's rewrite it
pressure
is equal to minus
not the derivative of the ordinary energy
but the derivative of the Helmholtz free energy
no,
isn't that minus the Helmholtz free energy?
hmm?
this is the Helmholtz
it's minus
no,
that is
you got the minus on that
that's the volume that's in it
it is minus the derivative
it should be minus the
derivative of the Helmholtz free energy
with respect to the volume at fixed T
I think I've got it right
yeah
okay
and that's an enormous simplification
because the Helmholtz free energy
is just simply related
to the logarithm of the partition function
you don't even have to differentiate it
to get the energy
you have to differentiate the partition function
and to keep the entropy fixed
you have to calculate the entropy
so you have to do two procedures
one of which can be rather complicated
you have to
if you wanted to use energy and entropy
you have to differentiate
to get the energy
and then you would have to keep the entropy fixed
and believe me,
that's a nuisance
on the other hand,
the Hall theorem simply tells you
to calculate the pressure
all you have to do is differentiate
the logarithm of the partition function
at fixed temperature
with respect to the volume
so if you can calculate the partition function
as a function of temperature and volume
you're home,
you have the pressure
so that's what we're going to do
we're going to do that now for the free gas
should we take a five minute break?
this is our fundamental equation
there's a more general version of it
but
where things like pressure
are derivatives of the Helmholtz free energy
with respect to other control parameters
but this is the basic one we're going to use
at least for today
what we're going to calculate is the pressure
energy,
and all the various properties
of the ideal gas
we now know enough to do that
and we can apply it to a simple
statistical mechanical system
we'll take five minutes
alright,
we want to apply our tools
now we have a lot of tools
partition function,
free energy
real energy
entropy
we have all these tools
theorems of various kinds
we'd like to apply it to
a simple system
the simplest interesting system
well
an interesting simple system
is the ideal gas
the ideal gas is a system of point particles
which are non-interacting
no structure to the particles
we can modify that later
we can allow them
to have some internal structure
but without any internal structure
point particles
filling a volume V
the object
is to calculate all the thermodynamic properties of it
by computing the partition function
and then applying the various tools that we have
alright,
now
we have to
in order to do the partition function
we have to sum over states
sum over states
of a system
here's our system
the states of a classical mechanical system
are the same as the states of a system
are not discrete things like that
they're continuous
they're characterized by positions and momenta
that means that the sum over states
is going to be replaced
by an integral
I'm not going to spend a
lot of time explaining that procedure
but
what are we going to be integrating over
all of the things that
characterize the state of the system
so
if the system has n particles
capital N particles
then
its state is described by 3n coordinates
namely the 3n positions
of the molecules
and the 3n components of momenta
that means that the sum over
states will be replaced by an integral
integrals and sums are of course
the same thing in some limit
in quantum mechanics it would literally be the sum
in classical mechanics we have to
bend our definitions a little bit
to include the possibility of continuous sums
and to characterize the state of the system
momenta and position
alright so what do I replace the sum by
an integral over the position of every particle
that means d3nx
3n x integrations for each particle
sorry 3n x integrations for each particle
integration for each particle
the 3 coordinates of space x y and z
and the 3
components of momentum
I'll just indicate it that way
those are
that replaces the sum
now what do I sum
normally I sum e to the minus beta
times the energy of the ith level
instead
we're going to have e to the minus
the energy
but not the energy of the ith level
but the energy of a state
with particles at position x in momentum p
so what do we write here
we write
the energy
is the sum over all the particles in the system
is a contribution to the energy from every particle
let's write it sum over little n
to indicate the particles
and what's the energy
if there are no forces between the particles
and let's also assume that there's no gravitational field
or anything like that
it's just particles in a box
then the only energy is
the kinetic energy of the particles
so it's the sum over n
of p sub n
that means the nth particle
squared
divided by twice the mass
and that's it
let me write that all on one line
not two to the m but
momentum of the nth particle squared
and that of course means px
squared plus py squared plus pz squared
so this is the sum over all the squared momenta
all three n of them
divided by twice the mass
and I'm assuming all of
the particles have the same mass
now that's it almost
there's one other thing that
needs to be taken into account
that's the following idea
here's a
we're going to assume that
all of the particles are identical
you can't tell them apart
so let's imagine we have a state
I'm going to draw the particles as little discs
they're really point particles
but you won't be able to see
them if I draw them as points
little discs are particles
now supposing I interchange these two particles
is that the same state
or is it a different state
well now it's a matter of interpretation
not interpretation
in fact it actually doesn't matter in the end
but if they're really identical particles
and there's no difference between them
then interchanging two of them
is the same state as before
so supposing there's only two particles
and I integrate over all possible states
I'm double counting
I'm double counting because
I'm counting each configuration twice
if I call this the
first particle and the second particle
this is the same configuration
this is not a q this is just a particle
this is the same as particle two over here
and particle one over here
so that means I would have to divide by two
what if there are three particles
what do I divide by
if there are n particles
n factorial
so to keep track of the fact
that the particles are all physically identical
that an interchange of two of them
is a trivial non-change of the state
we put a one over n factorial
in front of it
this is what we want to calculate
that's the partition function
and it's z of beta
but it's also a function of the volume
where does the volume come into this
well the x integrations
are done over some range
and the range of the x integrations
is the interior of the box of gas
so implicitly
there's also a dependence
in fact I mean in
principle there could be a dependence
not just on the volume
but the shape of the box
however in this particular case
it's really only the volume that comes in
the temperature and the volume
now the integrand here does
not depend on x at all
so that means I can do the x integrations
immediately
and what does each x integration
supposing I focus on a particular particle
let's say the first particle
dx1 this is d3x1
what is that integral
it's just the volume
I have n such integrals
and so I get a factor
which is volume to the nth
volume to the nth
divided by n factorial
incidentally volume to the nth over n factorial
can be re-expressed
in a neat way
I'll write it out here for you
but for the moment I'm going to
leave it in the form that it is
but let me just re-express it for you
volume to the nth
without the n factorial you couldn't do this
volume to the nth over n factorial
now what's sterling's approximation to n factorial
for large n
n to the n
not the large n to the n
e to the minus n right
the other way
no
which is equal
to e to the n
v to the n over n
to the n
which in turn
e to the n that's just
it's there but
it's
e times the volume
over n
to the nth
now
what is v over n
or n over v
density
n over v is the density
so in fact
this is
e divided by the density
rho
to the power n
in other words
for each particle in the system
there is a factor
of one over density
in the partition function
we'll use that another time
I'm not going to use that today
but it's interesting to notice
that this thing combines itself in together
in such a way as to give
a factor of one over the density
for each particle
alright
that's a useful fact
that'll come up another time
but for the time being
let's just leave it this way
the reason I want to leave
it in terms of the volume
because later on I want to differentiate
with respect to the volume
to calculate the pressure
okay
here's the entire dependence on the volume
there is no other dependence on the volume
and the rest of it
is just this p integration
so we have to figure out
how to do the p integration
and the p integration is just this p integration
so the integration is actually easy
there are three n identical integrals
in other words
it's the three nth power
of a basic integral
the basic integral is a one dimensional integral
e to the minus p squared
now p squared
does not mean px squared
plus py squared plus pz squared
it just means a one dimensional variable
e to the minus p squared beta over 2m
and the integral is just this
integrated dp
alright
I don't remember if we discussed
did we discuss Gaussian integrals?
we did not
not this quarter
alright let's discuss Gaussian integrals
quickly
we'll do it quickly
this integral
let's not call it p
let's just call it l
e to the minus p squared beta over 2m
or y
e to the minus y squared dy
from where to where?
from minus infinity to infinity
these momentum integrations go
can momentum be negative?
yes
it just means going in the negative direction
this integral is just a number
it's a convergent integral
and it's just a number
anybody know what the number is?
it's just square root of pi period
square root of pi
how the hell do you get a
square root of pi in a formula?
well since the answer is square root of pi
if you want to do the integral
it's smart to do the square root of the integral
the square root of the integral will be pi
I'm not kidding that's right
that's the way you do the integral
square it
then you can do the integral
you can't do the integral the way it is
you can do it if you square it
alright some other time I
will do the integral for you
but not today
ok so to do this integral here
it's sort of of this form
but there's an extra coefficient
in front of the y squared
namely beta over 2m
all I have to do is change variables
let me change variables so that
p squared times beta over 2m
is y squared
that just means
you've changed variables
that p
is equal to the square root of 2m over beta
times y
that's all
then p squared will be
2m over beta times y squared
and what's in the exponent here
will be 2m over beta times y squared
it will just be simple
it will be what
e to the minus y squared
but what happens to dp
dp is not dy
but rather dy
times 2m
let me put it on the outside
2m over beta
to the power one half
and now I've done the integral
the integral is the square root of
2m over beta to the power one half
and I've got the square root of pi
that's this
times this factor here
oh yeah
y
y?
isn't that a y-thumb?
where?
where is your y?
p is
did I do this right?
yeah
I replaced dp by dy times
the square root of 2m over beta
which is the same as 2m
over beta to the one half power
and now the integral is
just the square root of pi
and so this all together is 2m
pi over beta
to the one half power
that's it we've done the basic integral
how many such powers
how many powers of that integral are there?
3n
one for each component of the momentum
so the whole partition function has now been done
it is 2m pi
divided by beta
to the power n
twice n divided by 3
no just
sorry 3n divided by 2
3n divided by 2
I can't think without my pants
notice the whole thing is something
yeah even the n factorial
is approximately the nth power of something simple
if we were to have plugged back
in the density and all that stuff
this is just the nth power of something
In other words,
there's a factor for each particle.
We could have done it for one particle
and then just taken the nth power of it.
And that would pretty much give us the right answer.
Okay,
so this is the partition function z.
It depends on the volume,
and for fixed volume,
it depends only on the temperature.
Volume is a control factor,
and beta is the temperature.
Now,
first of all,
let's calculate the energy per particle.
Oh,
before we do that,
let's take the logarithm of it.
I want logarithm of z.
The logarithm of z...
is equal to...
well,
it's minus logarithm of n factorial...
over here.
Then there's plus log n log v.
n log of the volume.
That's from here.
And then...
there is minus 3n over 2...
log beta...
that comes from here.
It's minus because the beta was in the denominator.
And then there's plus 3n over 2...
log of what?
2m pi?
That's it.
We could write this...
I'll leave this as an assignment to you...
to rewrite this in terms of the
density instead of the volume in n.
You'll find that it's basically
n times logarithm of the density.
The n factorial and the v combined
together to give you logarithm of the density,
but I'm not going to do that now.
Okay.
That's it.
That's log of the partition function.
Let's first calculate the energy per particle.
All right.
Let's calculate the energy before the energy per particle.
Notice that all the interesting terms...
Well,
we'll see what's interesting in a minute.
Let's calculate the energy per particle.
What's the formula for the energy?
General formula...
doesn't depend on the fact that it's a free gas...
just very general formula...
minus the derivative of log
of z with respect to beta.
Energy...
is equal to minus the derivative of log z...
with respect to beta.
Well,
it's all laid out for us.
That's equal...
to plus 3n.
The minuses here and here cancel.
And we get plus 3n over 2.
And the derivative of log beta with respect to beta...
is just 1 over beta.
What's 1 over beta?
Temperature.
So,
the total energy of the gas is...
3 halves T...
times the number of particles.
And the energy per particle...
energy per particle...
is just...
3 halves the temperature.
If I were to change units...
and use the standard textbook unit convention...
I would replace capital T...
by kT...
by Boltzmann's constant times...
let's say Boltzmann's constant times little t.
3 halves kT...
I won't do that.
I'm not going to follow that convention.
But I just wanted to point out...
3 halves kT...
is the textbook answer.
Where did the...
first of all,
where did the 1 half come from in the formula?
The 1 half came from the
square roots in the Gaussian integral.
Right?
It came from the square roots in the Gaussian integral.
Or it came from the...
from the Gaussian integral.
Where did the 3 come from?
The 3 dimensions of space.
So basically,
there's a kinetic energy per direction per particle...
which is 1 half T.
Right?
Per direction per particle.
The 3 directions of space...
If there was 26 dimensions of space...
then it would be 26 over 2.
I picked 26 at random.
It had nothing to do with string theory.
I just...
Huh?
We believe you.
Yeah.
No.
26 is the letters of the alphabet.
Okay,
so E over N...
is 3 halves the temperature.
Or 3 halves kT,
if you like.
If you wanted to plug in numbers...
and use 300 degrees at room temperature...
you'd want to plug in...
the Boltzmann constant...
which is 10 to the minus 23 or something.
And you would find the energy per
particle is 10 to the minus what?
21 or something like that in joules.
So it's pretty small.
Okay,
so that's the first step...
or the first little thing we can calculate.
Next,
let's calculate the pressure.
That's an interesting thing to calculate.
To calculate the pressure...
we first calculate...
we want to calculate the derivative...
of the energy with respect to volume...
at fixed entropy...
but that's too hard.
So let's calculate the derivative...
of the free energy...
with respect to the volume...
at fixed temperature.
That's a lot easier.
Okay,
so let's do that.
First we need the free energy...
A.
A is equal to minus T log Z.
And we want to...
and we want to differentiate A...
with respect to volume...
minus it is pressure.
Okay,
the only term which is going to contribute...
only the terms which depend on the volume...
are going to contribute to this derivative.
We might as well throw away everything else.
Nothing else will give us
a derivative with respect to volume.
Remember we're doing this at fixed temperature.
This is at fixed temperature.
So at fixed temperature...
this is just a constant...
when I'm differentiating.
This is a constant.
The only thing which depends on the volume...
at fixed temperature...
is this volume term.
That's it.
That's how easy it is.
Okay,
let's see what we get.
The derivative of T...
this is minus...
T...
times the derivative of log V...
with respect to V.
Now,
do I have a...
Yeah,
N log V.
And that's just...
So what am I writing?
I want to write the derivative of the free energy.
That should be on the next line here.
On the next line...
This is equal to...
N...
over V...
period?
I think that's it.
No.
Times T.
The T over here.
No minus sign...
because...
there are two minus signs.
Can everybody see this minus sign over here?
Yeah.
There's a minus sign right where my finger is.
Minus the ADV is P.
But A is minus T log Z.
So the two minus signs go away.
And when I differentiate,
I just get N over V...
times the factor T.
There we have the ideal gas law.
The ideal gas law P...
is PV equals NT.
Pressure times volume...
is the number of particles...
times the temperature.
That's the standard ideal gas law.
Of course,
in textbook notation,
this would be PV...
equals NKT.
And then we could write that,
if we like,
as pressure...
we divide by volume,
if we like,
and we can write that...
N over V is the density of particles...
rho...
rho KT.
So it tells us that pressure...
is proportional to density...
times temperature.
Okay,
forget the K.
And...
my units...
in which temperature has units of energy...
its pressure is equal to density...
times...
temperature.
That's the ideal gas law.
That's the particle density.
Not the mass density,
but the particle density.
Right.
So...
And as you see,
we don't need...
any...
we don't need to think about the molecules,
we don't have to think
about the collisions with the walls,
we don't have to...
we just mechanically...
we mechanically carry out...
the statistical mechanical definition of pressure,
the statistical mechanical definition of energy,
all in terms of the...
the most fundamental variable,
which is the...
partition function.
Yeah?
How do we get rid of the mass?
Good question.
How did we get rid of the mass?
The mass...
Where was the mass in the partition function?
It's over here.
Differentiating it,
it's just a constant.
Right,
you just have an overall constant there.
Yeah.
Isn't that remarkable?
That the pressure doesn't depend on the mass.
It is remarkable.
Neither does the average kinetic energy.
The average kinetic energy is gotten
by differentiating with respect to beta.
So if you put a...
bowling ball in a gas,
the kinetic energy of the bowling
ball will be exactly the same
as the kinetic energy of the...
of a single molecule,
of any single...
or if you make...
Yeah.
The bowling ball will have the same kinetic energy
as the energy of any other molecule.
It will have a much smaller velocity.
Right.
So...
Yeah,
so that's a good point,
that the energy...
that the mass cancels out of these formulas,
oddly.
What else is interesting about this formula?
In your notes,
you carry on an H-bar.
Oh,
oh.
Right.
The H-bar is just a convention.
It's a convention.
I'll tell you what the convention...
why there's a convention.
The original definition of the partition function as a sum
was a dimensionless...
Let's talk about that a little bit.
Was a dimensionless quantity.
In the exponent,
the thing in the exponent was dimensionless.
E to the minus beta...
beta has units of one over energy,
times energy.
This is dimensionless and it's just a sum.
So,
the usual definition of the partition function...
the partition function is dimensionless.
On the other hand,
with this definition here,
the partition function has the dimensions
of whatever x times momentum to the 3n power are.
Now,
x times momentum is not dimensionless.
It has units of what is called action.
All right?
It is not dimensionless.
To make it dimensionless,
what we do is...
and it won't change any answers.
I'll show you why in a minute.
But to make it dimensionless,
what we just do is divide each
factor of an x times a p
by a physical quantity,
by a constant of nature
with the dimensions of x times p.
It doesn't matter what constant...
it doesn't matter what we divide it by,
in fact.
But just to give it the right dimensions,
we divide by Planck's constant.
Every time we see an x by a times p,
And that gives us some factors of Planck's constant.
What will it do in the partition function here?
It will give us another
minus n logarithm of Planck's constant.
Okay.
It doesn't make any difference to anything
because we're always differentiating the partition function.
It makes no difference to anything.
Differentiating the partition function
to calculate various quantities
or differentiating a logarithm of the partition function,
this just doesn't contribute.
So it's a convention.
There's only two terms that are important for the...
That's right.
There's only two terms in this expression here.
Which are being differentiated.
Right.
Say it again.
No,
I think it's .
there's a .
Yes,
thank you.
It's .
Okay.
In fact,
it's kind of interesting.
If we really did do quantum mechanics
and we did...
If we did the quantum mechanics of the free gas,
the free ideal gas,
this term would actually appear there naturally
just by summing over states.
We would discover it.
Yeah.
So this is a quick and dirty and shorthand way
of calculating the effects of quantum mechanics.
Does it come into anything?
Not really.
Nothing interesting.
So at least not until
we start to think about it.
We start exploring quantum mechanics.
Then it does have an interesting consequence
or an interesting point about it.
What does it do to the entropy,
incidentally?
It does contribute to the entropy.
If we go back to the connection between...
Remember,
there's a connection between beta times the energy,
the free energy.
Well,
it would add a constant to the entropy.
But again,
adding constants to the entropy
doesn't change anything.
Okay.
That is the ideal gas,
the ideal gas law.
It is interesting to calculate the entropy.
How would we calculate the entropy?
It's interesting to calculate it for no other reason
than to see that it's fairly complicated
and that you would not want to try to calculate
derivatives of anything to the entropy.
So,
let's start by keeping the entropy fixed.
Let's just look at the entropy.
Let's see.
There's a formula for the entropy in terms of...
I think it's A minus E,
and then there must be a beta.
I think that's right,
huh?
All right.
So let's calculate that and see
what kind of nasty thing we get.
First of all,
A is 1 over beta log Z.
That's easy if I know the partition function.
In other words,
beta times A just gives me log Z.
Minus...
Now,
what's E in terms of log Z?
The derivative of log Z.
All I think times beta,
right?
I think it's E minus A.
Is it E minus A or A minus E?
E minus A.
E minus A?
Yeah.
I can never remember.
Okay.
All right.
So it's the sum of two terms.
The sum of the two terms,
S.
S is first of all equal to minus log Z.
That's not too hard to calculate.
Plus beta...
Or minus,
I guess.
No,
minus or plus.
Plus beta d log Z by d beta.
Okay.
Now,
that's not so bad.
But if we actually go and calculate it,
we're going to find out
that it's kind of a mess.
Not too bad a mess.
But just for the free gas alone,
for the free gas alone,
it has logarithms in it.
And logarithms are sort of hateful.
It has things which are logarithms
and things which are not logarithms.
So let's see what it has.
It has logarithms of Z,
which is all this stuff.
In particular,
the important pieces of it
are N log V minus 3N over 2.
Log beta plus this constant stuff over here,
which is not important when we differentiate it.
And then beta d log Z by d beta.
But this is just the energy.
D log Z by d beta is minus the energy.
So this is minus beta.
I think it's minus beta times the energy.
And what was the energy?
The energy was 3 halves.
3 halves.
N times T over beta.
Sorry.
The betas cancel,
I think.
Did the betas cancel?
I think the betas cancel.
Why did the betas cancel?
Yeah,
the betas cancel.
So this is the entropy.
And the entropy involves logarithm of,
logarithm of beta.
And so if I try to calculate,
well,
it's just a little bit complicated.
In this particular case,
if I try to calculate the pressure
as the derivative of the energy
with respect to volume keeping entropy fixed,
I would have to remember to keep log beta fixed.
That's a little bit of a nuisance.
It's more complicated than just differentiating
the free energy with respect to the volume,
keeping beta fixed.
Keeping the energy fixed,
sorry,
keep differentiating the energy,
keeping the entropy fixed is a more complicated process
and we have to remember to keep this fixed
as you differentiate the energy with respect to the volume.
This is the tip of the iceberg
because this is an extremely simple system,
the free gas.
Normally the entropy is a rather complicated
and nasty function.
And keeping it fixed while you differentiate the energy
can be very hard.
On the other hand,
if you can calculate the partition function,
all you have to do is differentiate the volume,
keeping the free energy,
keeping log z fixed,
and that's your,
that's the,
fewer steps.
So,
Helmholtz free energy is a good thing.
It has all sorts of applications
and its main advantage
is that the things that you calculate
are generally at fixed temperature.
Any questions?
Yeah?
Why is it called a partition function?
I don't know.
I really don't know.
I think it has,
I suspect it has to do with,
well,
there is a thing in mathematics
called a partition function,
which is the number of ways of summing up a,
I don't know the origin of it,
but it probably has to do with
partitioning the energy into these bins there,
how many ways are there of partitioning the energy,
but I don't know for sure.
Why is it free energy?
What's free about it?
Don't know.
Again,
I don't know.
This terminology is historical
and I do not know what's free about it.
I don't know.
Nothing.
And it's not the only kind of free energy.
It's the Helmholtz free energy.
What does it have to do with Helmholtz?
Again,
I don't know.
There's also a Gibbs free energy.
Question,
the free energy,
Helmholtz free energy,
since tip here is in there,
does that imply it's an equilibrium,
it only pertains to an equilibrium state?
Yeah.
Because it has the temperature in its definition.
Well,
the whole idea of a partition function,
now again,
it's one of these things,
if there are very slow variations,
you can ascribe a free energy
to small volumes,
as long as things are varying slowly
over distance and time.
So,
another example,
or another general way
in which free energy is important,
if you have a,
well,
let's first take the,
Supposing you have a movable partition,
this is just an example,
movable partition
with gas on both sides,
and the partition is,
is free to transmit energy
between the two parts of the system,
then .
.
it will have pressure on it from both sides
what is the equilibrium configuration?
the equilibrium configuration of this partition
is when the pressure from both sides are equal
in other words when the net force
on the partition is equal to zero
that means that the derivative of
the free energy of the left side
with respect to
the volume of the left side
must equal
the derivative of the free energy
of the right side
with respect to the volume of the right side
but a small change in
the volume of the left side
will give you the negative of the small
change of the volume on the right side
so if we referred everything
let's say to the left side
this would become
much more
minus
the derivative of the right side of free energy
with respect to the volume of the left side
in other words
we would write that the derivative of the free energy
left plus right
just transpose to the other side
with respect to the position of the partition
is equal to zero
okay we just put this on the other side
let me walk through a few boxes
we were we see a lot of no surface pode
so i don't think that's practical
again i want to say that
the repetition of less than and minus
nothing else
you need to be born
don't forget you do
denim
is in a heat bath,
if the whole system is in a
heat bath which keeps it at constant
temperature,
as the changes happen,
the heat bath is enormous.
So as changes happen,
assume
the temperature of the heat bath doesn't change.
If the system is in a gigantic heat bath,
and we want to find out
the equilibrium position of this partition,
it's where the free energy
is stationary,
not where the original ordinary energy is stationary.
So equilibrium,
in a
situation where the temperature is held constant,
temperature typically is held constant by
being in a big heat bath,
if the temperature is being held constant,
then the mechanical
equilibrium happens not where the energy is minimum,
but where the free energy is minimum.
That's a bit of a surprise.
You might have expected where
it's where the energy is minimum.
It is not.
It's where the free energy is minimum.
Now of course,
in saying that you're in a
heat bath,
it's assumed that energy can flow
back and forth into the system here.
So that's
a big advantage of free energy,
that it establishes where equilibrium
is in a system where there's
no energy,
and we can't go back and forth
between temperature and what's in the system.
What we derived under those circumstances,
under the adiabatic circumstances,
is that
you do use the ordinary energy.
We've swapped ordinary energy for free energy,
and you use
it in an adiabatic for isothermal.
Adiabatic is harder as a general rule than isothermal.
Isothermal means fixed temperature.
So actually,
you would get a different equilibrium position
if you had adiabatic walls,
which didn't allow energy into and out of the system.
Then the
temperature would not be kept constant
and the partition model would move on.
Because it won't let the water into the system.
I don't get it,
but I'ming in with that.
If you healed up energy eventually and you can't
nothing to do with partition function,
the partition here would move in a way
which would minimize the energy.
But if you're keeping it at constant temperature
with energy flowing into and out of the system,
then the equilibrium is when the
free energy is minimized.
So that's an important distinction and sometimes it's
really important for some problems.
Because free energy,
you get a different answer.
You get the wrong answer if you minimize the energy.
Any other questions?
Okay,
mostly what I wanted,
well I wanted to impress on many of you,
many things.
First of all,
the ideal gas is a
interesting system by itself,
but the main thing I
wanted to impress on you is
the power of knowing the partition function.
The power of knowing the
partition function,
once the partition function is calculated,
a series of
almost mechanical steps will derive for you energy,
pressure,
entropy,
fluctuations.
We haven't talked about fluctuations in pressure,
but that's an interesting thing
in a sense.
The power of knowing the partition
function itself has the pressure fluctuate,
and just about every
thermodynamic relationship,
every thermodynamic quantity can
be computed from the partition
function by a relatively simple thing
of usually differentiating the partition function.
So it's a powerful tool.
Okay.
For more,
please visit us at
stanford.edu.