Stanford University.
All right,
I want to come to a new class of systems.
It was a very interesting class of systems.
They're usually called magnets,
magnetic systems.
But they may or may not
have anything to do with genuine magnets.
What is a magnet?
A magnet is a collection of little magnets.
And little magnets have the property that they point along,
they tend to align themselves along magnetic field.
But the important thing about them
is that they're little systems which can
point in any direction.
Furthermore,
whatever they are,
whether they're little magnetic grains,
or are they iron atoms,
or something else.
They are themselves little magnets.
And it means they're like,
what do you call those things
that mariners use to figure out
which way they're going?
Compasses,
yes.
They're little compasses,
except they can point in three dimensional space.
They have interactions between them.
And the interactions tend to favor parallel neighbors.
The interactions between them are fairly similar.
They're fairly short range,
which means that roughly speaking,
each magnet affects
its nearest neighbors and tends to make
it want to align in the same direction.
That's the energy function will tend to
be lowest when the magnets are aligned,
biggest
when they're anti-aligned.
You can have the opposite incidentally.
You can have the situation
where the little magnets are favor,
the energy favors anti-alignment.
Then,
it's not called a parallel magnet.
A ferromagnet is a situation where they align.
It's called an anti-ferromagnet,
and it tends to make anti-alignment.
But real magnets,
ferromagnets,
iron magnets,
are systems where the little magnets tend
to align each other.
But they only align their nearest neighbors.
Nevertheless,
even though they only align their nearest neighbors,
at sufficiently low
temperature,
it may be the case
that the fluctuations are weak enough.
At very high temperatures,
they fluctuate like mad.
At very,
very low temperatures,
only the lowest energy states are important.
And the lowest energy states all have
the magnets aligned along the same direction.
Which direction?
Well,
any direction,
but along the same direction.
So a ferromagnet is a
system certainly which at zero temperature,
when there are no fluctuations,
tends to align.
And it aligns by the
first one aligning the second one,
second one aligning your third
one,
third one aligning the fourth one,
and so forth.
Or really,
we're not thinking about a line of them.
We may be thinking about a three-dimensional block of them,
each one aligning its neighbors,
and the whole thing in some collective way,
all pointing in the same direction.
As I said,
at high temperatures,
they tend to fluctuate wildly.
And so it's not likely that at high temperatures,
this phenomena of alignment will persist.
We make models.
We make various kinds of models of magnets,
mathematical models.
The real thing,
the real genuine thing,
a bunch of interacting iron atoms,
is much too
hard to solve.
If for no other reason than the interactions are not...
If for no other reason than the
interactions are not between just nearest neighbors,
there's
a tendency for the interaction to
slop over to second nearest neighbors,
third nearest
neighbors.
And this makes a nightmare of a mathematical system,
too complicated to solve in detail.
So we make simplified models.
The first kind of simplified model is called an...
Well,
the first kind of simplified model is
even so simplified that it doesn't have any
interaction between its neighbors.
All right.
The first kind of magnet we're going
to study is not even really a magnet.
It has no interaction between its neighbors.
But the special simplifying feature of it
is this is a magnet whose little individual
magnets can only point in one of two directions,
either up or down.
It's called a Z2 magnet.
Why Z2?
Z2 is the group of two elements,
up and down,
basically.
But that's not important to us.
All right.
So we're going to study a Z2 magnet.
It's called a Z2 magnet.
And most studies,
or most of the early studies of magnets,
were about Z2 magnets.
All right.
So that means we're building our magnet out
of little elements which have only two possible
states.
Either they're up or they're down.
And we're making an array of them.
We might study different kinds of models.
We might study models in which it's a one-dimensional array.
We might study two-dimensional arrays of them,
and so forth and so on.
We might even study very high-dimensional arrays.
Not because anybody can build a high-dimensional magnet.
It's because the mathematics of high-dimensional
magnets turns out to be especially simple,
for reasons I'll tell you later.
All right.
So we have these systems which are
composed of these elementary magnets which are very
simple.
They either point up or they point down.
And in the examples that we're
ultimately going to want to study,
we're going to want
to look at the energy state of these magnets.
And in the example that we're looking at,
there's an energy function which,
let us
say,
favors neighbors being in the same direction.
All right.
So a high-energy state would
be neighboring magnets in opposite directions.
A low-energy state would be
neighboring magnets in the same direction.
And so at zero temperature,
which will pick out the lowest energy state,
there are only
two of them.
Either all magnets pointing up or all magnets pointing down.
All the little elementary magnets
pointing up or all pointing down.
I'll assume for the moment that the system
is symmetric with respect to up and down.
If it's symmetric with respect to up and down,
then the energy function,
whatever it is,
between two neighboring magnets,
will be one thing if the two are parallel.
In other words,
the same energy if they're
both up or they're both down.
All right.
So if the two are parallel,
then the energy function is one
thing if they're both up or
And a higher energy if one
is up and one is down,
or one is down and one is up.
That's a simple system that we can try to study.
An array of them,
one-dimensional array,
two-dimensional array,
three-dimensional array.
In fact,
we could just study two atoms like this.
We'll call them spins.
What they have to do with spins,
nothing is spinning.
It's just a name for them,
spins and spins.
And the spin is the same thing.
The spin is either up or down,
and the energy favors having them parallel.
So at zero temperature,
they will all line up,
either up or down.
Which is it going to be?
Is it going to be up
or is it going to be down?
The answer is both are low-energy states.
So we can say they're,
well,
technically we would say the ground state is degenerate.
Two possible equal-energy ground
states are lowest-energy states.
But that means whether it's up or
down is going to depend on minute effects,
such as,
for example,
a tiny,
tiny stray magnetic field.
A tiny,
tiny stray by a tiny,
tiny stray magnetic field,
I mean some almost infinitesimally small magnetic field,
extremely small,
which might even be too small to measure,
but still might favor one direction or the other.
There are so many of these little magnets.
And they're all in
this infinitesimally small magnetic field.
And so they all line up in that direction.
If we changed this infinitesimally small
magnetic field from up to down,
all the spins would want to be down.
No matter how small that magnetic field is,
the ground state will either
be all up or all down.
And if we imagine a limit in
which that background magnetic field gets smaller,
and smaller,
the magnetization,
the magnetization means the tendency for all the spins
to be up or all the spins to be down,
it doesn't go away.
It just stays there until
the external magnetic field reverses sign,
and then they might all simultaneously reverse sign.
This is called spontaneous symmetry breaking.
The system has a symmetry.
What is a symmetry?
You take all the spins and you flip them.
You turn all ups to downs.
If you turn all ups to downs,
the energy stays exactly the same,
ignoring this little stray field.
All ups have,
I mean,
they don't have to all be up.
Whatever the configuration is,
it might be one up and one down.
If you turn them both over,
you get one down and one up,
same energy.
So this system has a symmetry.
The symmetry being,
let's give these degrees of freedom a name.
Let's call them sigma.
Sigma of I,
the ith spin.
And it's either plus or minus one.
Plus one if it's up,
minus one if it's down.
That's our system,
a collection of these simple degrees of freedom.
The symmetry,
here's the symmetry.
All sigmas,
sigma of I for all I,
goes to minus sigma of I.
All spins flip.
Everything about the system is exactly the same.
But,
if you put on the tiniest magnetic field,
it will tend to line it up in that direction.
And that direction is not symmetric.
It's all up.
So that's called spontaneous symmetry breaking.
Spontaneous means that it doesn't,
it doesn't go away as you shrink the bias.
We can think of the
bias being the tiny magnetic field,
which might bias it in one direction.
We let that magnetic field get,
external magnetic field get smaller and smaller and smaller.
And eventually,
we take it away altogether,
and the spins are left all up.
If we started with the
magnetic field in the opposite direction,
the external magnetic field in the opposite direction,
and then gradually removed it,
all the spins would be down.
So there would be two possibilities,
but either of them would break the symmetry.
Breaking the symmetry means that the configuration
would not have the symmetry of up goes to down,
but would be biased in one direction or another.
That's the phenomenon we want to study.
Now,
another reason for studying it,
magnets are kind of interesting,
of course,
they're lovely little toys to play with,
but another reason for studying these kinds of systems
is because you can model an enormous number
of statistical mechanical systems as magnets.
Let me give you an example.
A gas,
a fluid.
A fluid is a collection of molecules.
Okay?
But I can try to represent that collection of molecules
in the following way.
Break up the container that contains them
into cells,
where the cells are about as big as a molecule.
Let's suppose these molecules have hard cores
and that we can't stick
them on top of each other.
Then if the cells are
about as big as a molecule,
then we can't get two particles
or two molecules into a box.
And so either a box is empty,
or it has a molecule in it.
Again,
two possible states for each molecule.
Each box.
It's either got a molecule,
or it don't got a molecule.
We could call having a molecule up.
We could call not having a molecule down.
And then this system of molecules moving around,
let's just put molecules in various boxes.
This would correspond to a spin up,
a spin down,
down,
up over here,
down everywhere else.
And we map the mathematical problem
of the gas of molecules
into the mathematical problem
of the magnet.
That's a very,
very fruitful avenue of exploration.
It has been a fruitful avenue of explanation.
And for example,
let's pursue it.
Let's pursue it before we actually
get into the mathematics of it.
Let's,
let's think about it a little bit.
What would correspond to the configuration
in which all the molecules were up?
Full.
We absolutely chock-full this system.
We make the gas extremely,
the gas,
we make the system extremely dense.
What corresponds to all the spins being down?
Empty.
So,
the configuration with all molecules up
is the high density limit.
The configuration with all molecules all spins down,
that's the low density limit,
or the vacuum to be specific.
But let's just call it the low density limit.
Okay?
What corresponds to a configuration
where there are equal numbers of ups and downs?
For the magnet,
we would call that unmagnetized.
We would call it unmagnetized
because on the average,
every spin is equally likely to be up and down.
So it's perhaps the situation
where there's enough fluctuation to,
to,
to make on the average every spin be zero.
What would that correspond to,
to this,
to this system here?
Half full.
It would correspond to the density half full.
Okay?
Now,
let's,
let's think about what happens
to the magnet
when we have a little bit of a magnetic field.
We have a little bit of a magnetic field,
and let's suppose it's at some finite temperature.
It's at some finite temperature,
and we put a little magnetic field
which tends to make it point down.
Okay?
All right.
If it's at some finite temperature,
there will be some fluctuation.
All the molecules will not literally point down.
There will be some fluctuation,
but on the average,
they'll point in the direction of the magnetic field,
but maybe with only a weak bias.
As the temperature goes up,
of course,
the bias goes away,
and they tend to fluctuate more.
So at low temperatures,
but not zero temperatures,
what we'll find is that on the average,
the magnets will be down,
but not with a full hundred percent magnetization.
And now we start changing
the magnetic field a little bit,
and we vary it.
It gets smaller and smaller and smaller,
the external magnetic field,
and finally becomes zero,
but then we turn it
on with epsilon amount of it,
tiny amount,
in the opposite direction.
What happens?
Well,
if the magnet had spontaneous magnetization,
in other words,
if this phenomena of
spontaneous symmetry breaking was active,
then there will be a sudden jump in the magnetization,
a sudden jump from more
spins down to more spins up.
What does that mean for the fluid?
Well,
the density.
The density makes a sharp jump.
As we vary some parameter,
let's not worry about now exactly what parameter to vary,
but as we vary some parameter,
whatever the natural analog of the magnetic field is,
we'll find it's the chemical potential in fact,
but as we vary some quantity,
there's a sudden change from a biased situation
where more spins are down,
what does that mean about the density?
Less than half.
To a jump where the
density is more than a half.
What do we call that?
A phase transition.
And it's a phase transition from a less dense configuration,
we might give a name to that,
we might call it a gas,
to a more dense configuration,
we might give another name to that,
a liquid.
Okay?
So,
just as an example,
many,
many systems can be modeled
as these simple magnetic systems,
we call them magnetic systems,
but they stand for a
lot of different kinds of systems,
and that's why they're so useful.
They're useful for magnets,
but they're also useful for fluids.
The magnetic transition
where sudden spontaneous magnetization happens,
that's also the gas-liquid phase transition.
So that's why we study them.
And we don't just study them because they're magnets,
which are interesting in their own right,
but because they are a broad brush description
of many,
many different kinds of statistical mechanical systems.
I've given you two.
The magnet on the one hand,
and what's called the lattice gas on the other hand.
The lattice gas is incidentally a,
not always a gas,
it can be a liquid or a gas,
depending on which phase it's in.
Let's,
let's,
before we actually study such systems,
let's talk about them broadly first.
Let's make a plot.
And on this plot,
let's plot temperature on the horizontal axis.
Low temperature,
everything fluctuates a minimum amount.
At zero temperature,
it just picks out the ground state.
At high temperatures,
it fluctuates maximally.
And on the vertical axis,
let's imagine an external magnetic field.
Let's see,
we can put the whole thing in a magnetic field.
How can I represent the magnetic field?
Um,
by an arrow with a different color.
Incidentally,
we're restricting ourselves to magnetic fields
which are either up or down.
Not,
not pointing sideways.
So we have an external magnetic field.
Let's call it H.
Little h.
Why H?
I don't know.
It's a traditional name for the magnetic field
in these spin systems.
H.
Let's start at zero temperature.
No fluctuations.
What happens if H is pointing up?
Well,
H will point up.
It will bias all of these spins.
And it will say they're not fluctuating.
So push them into their ground state.
But there are two ground states.
The low temperature will make them,
make sure they're in their ground state.
But there are two ground states.
All up or all down.
Which one is going to be favored?
Well,
that will depend on the direction of this magnetic field.
This magnetic field adds a little bit of energy
which is different for an up and a down spin.
And so if they're all up,
that might be the lowest energy.
So when H is positive,
the,
let's call it the average magnetization,
the averages of the spins,
it will be
magnetized upward.
I don't know.
Let's just say the average of sigma,
is greater than zero in this region.
Magnetized up.
And in this region where the magnetic field is down,
oh boy,
I don't have my bag.
Sigma is less than zero.
Now it may or may not be,
but generally it is,
that if the temperature is low enough,
this state of affairs persists
right up to
almost zero magnetic field.
And then across here there's a jump.
A jump,
sigma less than zero here,
and sigma greater than zero here.
So,
there's a phase transition across here.
Let's just put a
bold line there of some kind.
And if we go across here,
in other words,
if we fix the temperature,
low temperature,
and vary the external magnetic field,
there will be a jump of the magnetic field.
And then there's a jump in magnetization across here.
That jump in magnetization,
as I said,
corresponds to a jump in the density of
the analog fluid here.
Now,
this situation typically persists,
as we'll see,
out to some finite temperature.
And then beyond that temperature,
the fluctuations in the system are so strong
that it destroys this tendency
for the spins to align themselves
when the external magnetic field goes to zero.
They'll be aligned down here
only because of the presence of the external magnetic field.
They'll be aligned up here
because of the external magnetic field.
But right on the axis here,
the net magnetization,
the net tendency to be up or down,
the net expectation value of
sigma will be zero along here.
And so this jump will disappear
and everything will be completely consistent,
completely smooth as you go across here.
Again,
this here corresponds to the liquid phase,
high density.
This corresponds to the gas phase,
low density.
If you fix the temperature,
you have a jump.
Now,
I'm going to tell you what this H is.
This H is actually the chemical potential.
Corresponds to the chemical potential.
It's the thing that you use to vary the density.
Of course it's the thing that
you use to vary the density.
The more you vary the external magnetic field,
the more you'll bias it
to either greater or lesser density.
So H is the chemical potential in the analog.
And if you want to vary the density,
you vary H.
But it varies discontinuously at some point,
and that's the gas-liquid phase transition.
So you can go from gas to liquid,
by crossing this boundary,
and having a sudden jump in the density.
That's just the usual thing that happens
when there's a transition from vapor,
which is very low density,
to liquid-water,
which is higher density.
But you can also do something else.
You can go around here,
and go from gas to liquid,
without passing through any transition at all,
without passing through any discontinuity at all.
That's called going around the critical point.
And some of you who are familiar
with the properties of the gas-liquid phase transition
know that you can go from water to steam
without passing through a sudden abrupt change,
by going around the critical point.
So that corresponds to going around the critical point.
I'm pointing these things out just to show you that
there's a lot of different ways to do this.
These lattice systems have a lot of physics in them.
A lot of familiar physics,
and sometimes some unfamiliar physics.
Okay,
we're going to study these lattice systems a little bit.
In the case where you're talking about the magnetic system,
you change that external magnetic field a little bit.
Let's say you're at very low temperature.
Is there kind of a hysteresis effect,
when you're right at zero field?
Is there a hysteresis effect?
If you go around,
then a loop.
Well,
no,
not if you go around,
then a loop.
But if you just keep the temperature
down below the critical point there.
Do you have to,
because you've got some interactions
between all these spins,
do you have to put
a little extra field on there?
You're asking whether there's a metastable phase.
You're asking whether you can have metastability,
the analog of what happens
if you were to lower the temperature of steam
below the temperature of the transition,
and you're very,
very careful,
can you keep it steam?
I think that's what you're asking.
Yeah,
I think that's the issue of metastability.
Can you vary this h and go down to here,
keeping all the spins upward?
And the answer is typically yes,
but if you sit there,
it's not true equilibrium.
It's not true equilibrium.
If you take a system,
let's take these little magnets.
Now,
we've ignored the question of what causes
the magnets to change their direction.
All we've done is talk about their orientation.
We haven't talked about the kinetic energies
which might cause them to actually move.
But let's imagine that there was something in the system
which caused them to move.
So you start with a magnetic field downward.
They point downward.
And then you very,
very carefully increase the magnetic field.
And you will come to a point,
if you're very,
very careful with a magnet,
where the magnet will be pointing in the wrong direction
relative to the field.
That's called a metastable situation.
But if you sit there
and you wait there long enough,
sooner or later,
a fluctuation will happen.
A fluctuation will happen.
One of the spins will return.
And then you realize,
or a group of them,
a small group of them will realize
that they can find lower energy configuration
by flipping themselves over.
And once they flip themselves over,
that thing starts spreading out
and creates a bubble of spins
which all then right themselves
and get themselves oriented in the right direction.
So it's called metastability.
It's not really equilibrium.
It's out of equilibrium.
But it can take a long,
long time
for equilibrium to set in.
And that's the root of metastability.
Yes,
that can happen.
And it's closely connected to the phenomena
of metastability in the gas-liquid system,
where you can cool or otherwise change
the parameters of a gas-liquid phase transition,
gas-liquid system,
where you might be able to,
one way or another,
very carefully,
change the liquid or change the parameters
so that you move into
what should be the gas region,
but nevertheless the system not budge and stay liquid.
But if you sit there and wait a little bit,
sooner or later,
a little bubble of gas will form
and then the bubble of gas
will take over the whole system.
Is that super cooling or super heating?
Yeah.
It's connected with hysteresis.
The question is,
in the case of,
you said this is Z2,
but in the case of these magnets,
would the normal magnet radiate energy
where we are ignoring that aspect?
Yeah,
we're not asking about the kinetics of the system.
Right.
But I'll tell you,
all right,
but you can ask what really does happen for magnets.
Now,
real magnets are of course not these Z2 magnets.
They are...
Right.
So you could imagine trying to
orient the magnets with a magnetic field,
change the magnetic field to get into an unstable situation,
but then typically what will happen is after a while
they'll start to slosh around and,
yeah,
what they'll radiate away is spin waves.
Spin waves are sort of waves of wiggly magnetization.
But there are no spin waves for this situation
because they're either all locked up,
well,
everyone is either up or down
and nowhere is in between.
So,
yeah,
they could flip,
for example,
by emitting sound waves.
They could flip by emitting light waves,
but that would be unusual for a real magnet.
A real magnet doesn't flip itself over.
When a compass changes direction,
it usually doesn't emit a lightning bolt.
I mean,
it might emit a little
tiny bit of sound into the...
Not much.
Well,
very...
Even that would be hard,
so...
Yeah,
since the...
very,
right.
Very,
very low frequency radio waves.
Right.
More likely just some sound waves or something,
which are easier to...
But...
Or some pressure waves.
Who knows?
I don't know.
Anyway,
this is what we want to study.
I'm not going to study these things
in as much mathematical detail
as I do in the
notes that I've distributed to you.
I'm going to study them in a different way.
I'm trying to decide...
Yeah,
I think what I'll do
is give you an illustration
of the phenomena...
Phenomenon of spontaneous magnetization
in an approximation
which is called the mean field approximation.
This is one of the many approximations...
I'll tell you the various approximations
that we apply to these kinds of magnetic systems.
There are approximations
which are called low temperature expansions,
where you begin with the system at zero temperature
and you expand your way
in powers of something involving the temperature.
All right.
There are high temperature expansions
where you start the system at the infinite temperature
where it fluctuates like mad
and then you expand about one over the temperature.
High temperature expansions.
They're not very hard
and they're not very difficult,
but it's not where we're going to go.
Then there's another kind of method
called renormalization group.
That's a method that I will maybe tell you
a little bit about as we go along,
but not tonight.
And the other method is called
mean field approximation.
And mean field approximation
is a nice physically intuitive picture
of how this phenomena
of spontaneous magnetization takes place.
That's what I want to do tonight,
is show you the mean field description of this.
And mean here doesn't mean nasty.
It doesn't mean cheap.
It means average.
Okay.
Mean field approximation.
Now,
what we're going to imagine
is that we have a lattice.
And it might be a three-dimensional lattice,
which might be the case we're really interested in,
or it might be a two-dimensional lattice.
I don't want to deal with the one-dimensional lattice
for reasons that perhaps we'll discuss.
But let's start with either a two-dimensional lattice
that I can draw on the blackboard
or a three-dimensional lattice,
or better yet,
a D,
D like David,
a D-dimensional lattice.
And the reason I say a D-dimensional lattice
is because this approximation works best
when D is very large,
for reasons that I'll explain.
The reason is very simple.
The reason has to do with the fact
that the higher the dimension,
the more neighbors that any given atom has,
or any given site has.
In one dimension,
each site only has two neighbors.
Okay?
In a thousand dimensions,
how many neighbors does a thousand have?
A thousand.
Two thousand neighbors.
Yeah.
Two thousand neighbors in a thousand dimensions.
In two dimensions,
each one has four neighbors.
In three dimensions,
two more,
six neighbors.
So,
two D neighbors.
Now,
the reason it's good
to have a lot of neighbors
is because you can average over the neighbors.
You can do an average over the neighbors
and say this molecule at the center
sees the effect of a large number of neighbors,
and it doesn't matter much
if one neighbor is a little bit different.
You can average over the neighbors.
You can use the laws of large numbers,
so to speak,
statistics,
to average over the properties
of the nearest neighbors.
So,
it's as if we in this room
form the lattice,
which you do form sitting there in your chairs,
although it's a rather irregular lattice.
And you're interested in the properties
of your neighbors
and what your neighbors are doing to you.
Well,
if there are enough neighbors,
you can average over them and say
the effect of my nearest neighbors on me
is to have this particular effect,
which is the average over large numbers of neighbors.
If there's only one or two neighbors,
then averaging over them
might be a less effective thing to do.
And this is true for this kind of system.
So,
the mean field approximation
becomes accurate,
infinitely accurate
or perfectly accurate,
in the limit of large numbers of dimensions.
But we're not really interested
in the limit of large number of dimensions.
Well,
it turns out numerically
that two is a little bit large
and three is large already.
In other words,
mean field approximation
works pretty well for three dimensions.
But more important than that,
than whether it works numerically well,
is it gives you a picture of what happens
that leads to this magnetization.
All right,
now,
we're going to invent now
an energy function.
An energy function
which is the energy function,
well,
for this system of atoms.
Each one is either up or down.
Let's represent an up by a dot
and a down by a cross.
The energy only depends on the orientation configuration
of nearest neighbors.
All right?
The energy is low when they're parallel
and high when they're anti-parallel.
So,
here's an expression which does that.
Let's take the energy
to just be,
let's call it sigma of i,
sigma of j,
but now i and j represent
neighboring points on the lattice.
As you range over i and j,
I really only want you to imagine
that you're ranging over nearest neighbors.
Nearest neighbors are on the lattice.
And let's put a minus sign in here.
Now,
if sigma i and sigma j are the same,
in other words,
if they're both plus one or minus one,
then sigma i,
sigma j is one,
and the energy is negative.
Negative is low.
All right,
so this favors or lowers the energy
when they're parallel.
What about when they're anti-parallel?
When they're anti-parallel,
then the energy is plus one.
And so there's two units of energy
stored in every bond
if the bond is a broken bond.
Now,
what do I mean by a broken bond?
Let's say an unbroken bond
is a bond where the spins are parallel.
Here's an unbroken bond.
A bond means a nearest neighbor link of the lattice.
Here's another bond which is unbroken.
The spins are parallel at the two ends of it.
A broken bond would be one
like this one over here,
where the spins are anti-parallel.
Broken bonds cost you energy.
How much energy?
Each broken bond costs you two units of energy.
So energetically,
it's profitable
to keep the number of broken bonds to a minimum.
But on the other hand,
as you raise the temperature,
because there are so many possible configurations
with broken bonds,
raising the temperature will tend to create
a population of broken bonds there.
All right,
so that's the picture.
Now,
we're going to do
an interesting approximation,
which really captures some of the interesting physics.
Let's focus on one molecule.
Let's focus on this molecule right over here.
I don't know whether it's up or down,
so I haven't biased it,
but let's focus on this one over here.
And let's write the expression for its energy.
Its energy,
let's call this sigma z.
That's sigma zero right at the center.
The spin that I'm focusing on is called sigma zero.
It's plus one or minus one.
And it interacts with all of its nearest neighbors.
So its energy,
the energy of sigma zero,
let's call it little e.
Little e represents the energy of this spin
in the background of all of its neighbors.
And what is it?
It's minus sigma zero times.
The sum of all the
spins of all the nearest neighbors.
Sum of the nearest neighbors of the nearest neighbor spins.
I'm not going to try to make too much,
that's enough terminology,
enough indexology.
Okay?
Let's suppose that the spins have an average value.
An average value that the system has magnetized.
Let's suppose,
it may not be,
we'll find out if it's not.
In other words,
let's suppose that on the average,
each spin has the same value as each other spin.
And let's suppose on the average,
the average of any spin is called s.
Now,
s is a number between minus one and one.
The average of a thing which
can only be one or minus one
must lie between one and minus one.
So,
whatever s is,
the average spin,
is between one and minus one.
s is the thing which is called the mean field.
The average field,
the average value of all of the spins.
And now,
each one of these spins sees around it
a whole bunch of spins.
If the dimensionality of the system is high enough,
it sees loads and loads of spins around it.
And so it has some average energy in the background.
This one has an energy in
the background of all of these.
And what is its energy?
It's just equal to minus sigma naught
times,
now on the average,
each one of these sigmas is equal to s.
So,
that's n,
or sorry,
that's twice d
times s.
Why twice d?
That's because that's the number of nearest neighbors.
Twice d is the number of nearest neighbors.
So I've replaced each one of these by its average.
There are two d of them.
And so that particular spin,
right at the center,
is experiencing a bias
or a effective energy
which is proportional to that spin
with a minus sign,
whatever it is.
Now,
s can either be positive or negative.
We don't know offhand whether s is positive or negative.
They may all be,
they may have a tendency,
maybe zero,
maybe on the average s is equal to zero.
Then,
this would not be magnetized.
It's magnetized if s is not zero.
And s can either be positive,
or it can be negative,
or it can be zero,
and that's what we want to find out.
But,
let's assume that there's some finite value of s.
Now that we know the energy of this particular spin
in the background of all the others,
let's just do some statistical mechanics
for this one spin
in the background of all the others.
We're freezing all the others.
Well,
we're not freezing them,
we're freezing their average value.
And we're going to think of sigma
0 as a little system all by itself
at temperature T.
And let's see what we can learn about it.
Let me not call it sigma 0 anymore,
let me just call it sigma.
It's just the one spin that I'm focused on now.
And it has an energy,
it's energy,
e stands for energy now,
which is equal,
as I wrote over there,
twice the dimensionality of space,
s,
that's not ds,
that's just d times s,
it doesn't stand for the differential of s,
times sigma.
And let's write the partition function and the stati-
Yes.
Let's write the statistical mechanics for that spin.
The probability function for it
is e to the minus beta
times its energy.
But its energy is just this.
So that gives us a plus 2 ds times sigma.
That's the Boltzmann weighting factor.
Next,
let's calculate the partition function.
Okay?
The partition function is the sum over
the two possible configurations of the spin.
We're just doing the probability
distribution for the single spin
in the field of all the others.
And so let's just write that this is equal,
this is the sum over sigma,
sigma equals plus or minus 1.
And so what do we get?
We get that the partition function is
just equal to e to the twice,
let's,
twice beta ds plus e
to the minus 2 beta ds.
I've just added the two configurations,
and this is the partition
function for this very simple system
in the field of all the others.
Okay?
That's z.
How do I calculate the average energy of this spin?
Well,
we first have to take a logarithm.
Right.
All right.
This is also twice the
hyperbolic cosine of 2 beta ds.
Okay.
That's that step.
Let's take its logarithm.
Log of z is equal to,
first of all,
log of 2 plus log
of cosh of 2 beta ds.
What about the minus 2?
Well,
the minus 2 log of z is,
of course,
just this.
Now,
what is the energy?
The energy is the derivative of
minus log z with respect to beta.
That's the thermodynamic identity
or the statistical mechanics identity
we've used over and over.
So the energy,
but not the energy of the whole system now,
just the energy of this one spin.
I'll just call it,
what shall we call it?
Well,
this is the energy of the whole system.
So basically,
it's the average value of little e here.
The average value of this little spin is,
or it's the average value of
the energy of this one spin.
What is it given by?
It's given by the derivative of minus log z.
Let's see.
So what is that?
That's minus 1 over hyperbolic cosine of 2 beta ds.
And then we have to differentiate
the hyperbolic cosine with respect to beta.
That gives us hyperbolic sine,
2 beta ds.
And then we have to differentiate
what's in here with respect to beta.
So that gives us another factor of 2d times s.
Okay.
This is the important factor over here.
It has another name.
It's minus the hyperbolic tangent
of 2 beta ds.
Okay.
That's the answer for the average energy.
But what about the average value of the spin itself?
What about the average value of sigma itself?
Well,
the energy of sigma is sigma
minus sigma times 2d times s.
If I wanted the average of sigma,
I would just take the average of the energy
and divide it by 2ds.
Spin and energy just differ
by a factor of minus 2ds.
So if I simply divide the average energy by 2ds,
I will find the average value of the spin.
What is that?
Here's 2d.
Here is,
well,
let's see.
I think I left out something.
Yeah,
here it is,
2ds.
2ds times 2ds.
If we just cancel this 2ds,
then we have the average value of the spin.
I think I also want to cancel the minus sign.
That's the average value of that spin
by doing statistical mechanics on that spin.
Hmm.
Incidentally,
if you plot hyperbolic tangent,
the function hyperbolic tangent,
if we plot beta this way
and hyperbolic tangent vertically,
it looks something like this.
It goes to 1 at this
end and minus 1 at this end.
What does this correspond to?
The maximum value that tanh takes on is 1.
The minimum value that it takes on is minus 1.
This just corresponds to the statement that at,
that the maximum value the average
of the spin can take on
is 1 and minus 1.
This end out here,
or both ends actually,
are low temperature.
When beta goes up,
it's 1.
When beta goes to 0,
so when beta goes to 0,
sorry,
when beta goes to infinity,
that's low temperature.
And don't ask me about this side over here.
I'm going to come to that side over here.
It's a little weird,
isn't it?
What does that mean?
Negative temperature.
Weird,
huh?
Yeah,
okay.
We'll come to negative temperature,
but let's focus on...
But this is the average value of the spin
as a function of beta.
The spin as a function of beta.
All right.
Yeah.
It's interesting to relabel the x-axis s
and get the same shape.
Yeah,
yeah,
yeah.
We're going to do that in a minute,
right.
Good.
All right,
so this is the average of the spin.
But now,
this only makes sense
if the average value of the spin
over here is the same
as all of the other spins.
After all,
we're assuming
that every spin is like every other spin,
and so we have a consistency requirement.
The consistency requirement
is just that this average value of the spin here
be equal to the average value of the spin,
s.
And this becomes an equation
for,
if you like,
the magnetization.
The magnitude of the magnetization,
s itself.
s is the average of the spin.
It's the amount of magnetization.
And this becomes a self-consistency equation.
Let's just go back.
What did we do?
We said,
look,
in the limit of a large number of nearest neighbors,
we can average over the nearest neighbors.
And just think of an average behavior
of the nearest neighbors.
Assume that the nearest neighbors on the average
have a spin,
s.
Then the energy of our friend at the center here
will be minus sigma times 2 ds.
And now knowing that,
let's use the statistical mechanics
to calculate the average value of s.
And once we've done it,
consistency requires that it just be the same
as the input s in the first place.
So here we are.
What do we have to do?
We have to satisfy this equation.
On the left,
we have s.
Let's draw the graph of just s.
On the right,
we can put s over here.
Tangent to beta s is...
We'll put s on the horizontal axis.
What is the significance,
in terms of this graph,
of changing beta...
Let's say d is fixed.
d is three dimensions now.
What's the significance of changing beta?
It changes the slope at the origin here.
That's all.
It just spreads the curve out or shrinks it together.
What happens when beta is very small?
It spreads it out like this.
So this is beta small.
Well,
that's not the axis.
This just stands for small beta.
What about large beta?
Supposing beta was enormously large?
Yeah.
That means it looks almost like...
this.
But this curve and that
curve are related to each other.
They're just shrinking along one axis.
Squeezing it along...
Well,
I didn't quite do it right.
The height of this should have been
the same as the height of this.
This corresponds to one unit over here.
This is one unit over here.
All right.
So I didn't draw it well,
but that's the picture.
Now let's draw s as a function of s.
On the left-hand side,
we have s.
On the right-hand side,
we have this tanh.
We want to set them equal.
That just means superimposing on this diagram...
a straight line.
At the point where they intersect,
s will be equal to tanh to beta s.
All right.
What about here?
Where do they intersect?
They only intersect at the origin.
That's the only place where they intersect.
It's at the origin.
And the implication of that is
there's only one solution of the equation.
And that one solution of the
equation is magnetization equal to zero.
Okay?
That's what happens at small beta.
And small beta means high-tech.
And that's the temperature.
Now you start lowering the temperature.
And as you lower the temperature,
this curve migrates to this curve.
And what happens over here?
Now there are actually three solutions.
There are three solutions.
And to calculate which solution
is actually the right solution,
you have to calculate the entropy
and see which one corresponds to the highest entropy.
All right.
So these two have the same entropy.
And this one has some higher entropy configuration,
which actually corresponds to
some kind of metastable configuration.
Here is the solution.
Another way you can do it is to
imagine that there is this little weak magnetic field.
If there was a very tiny,
small magnetic field,
it would bias you to one of these two solutions,
depending on which way.
Incidentally,
these two solutions correspond to
the two possibilities for the magnetization,
either on the average up or the average down.
They correspond to S equals
something positive or something negative.
All right.
If you were to bias the system
with a little bit of external magnetic field
and really work it out carefully,
you would find out that only these two solutions persist.
That's all that's there.
And that's what happens.
So what happens now?
You start changing the temperature.
And at some point,
at some point,
the slope of the tanh function here
gets to be equal to the
slope of the straight line here.
And after that,
there's the intersection
that corresponds to the magnetized phase.
Where does that happen?
That happens when the slope of this function
becomes equal to one.
That's just when twice dS,
sorry,
twice,
when twice beta d is equal to one.
When twice beta d is equal to one,
then the tanh curve here
becomes equal to one.
So we have an equivalent slope
to the straight line.
And beyond that,
it has this new intersection over here
and over here.
That's where the magnetization happens.
So,
in effect,
we have found the temperature,
the beta,
at which this phenomena first happens.
It happens,
let's see,
what is it?
It's when beta is bigger.
we have spontaneous magnetization,
this is spontaneous magnetization,
yeah,
when
let's see beta which is 1 over the
temperature times 2d is equal to 1 or
temperature equals twice the dimension of space,
twice that the temperature
equal to twice the dimension of space,
whether in space would be 3 for
three-dimensional systems or the temperature
of six units and six units
in what unit well we would need to
put some units in here by putting a constant
into this formula over here
this is not dimensionally consistent,
sigma is either
plus or minus 1 and energy has units
of energy we have to throw in another
constant over here to give it units
that other constant would appear over here
now let's call that constant J
I always call that constant J then it
would appear over here and has units of
energy
ok the main point is you see what
the pattern is that as you vary the
temperature from high temperature to low
temperature or from low temperature to
high temperature
let's start at the low
temperature situation at the very lowest
temperatures at the very lowest temperatures
this is a sharp jump here
and what does it say it says
the magnetization is either plus 1 or
minus 1 so a temperature equal to 0
it's just temperature equal to 0 T you jump
well you jump as you go across here
from magnetization minus 1 to plus 1 two
possible solutions and then as you increase the temperature
let's see what happens as you
increase the temperature if you increase the
temperature to a high enough point
beyond to a temperature higher than this
there's no more solution other than the solution at 0
ok so that means as you increase
the temperature at some point at some point
the spontaneous magnetization disappears
the spontaneous symmetry breaking
disappears and there's only the solution with
sigma equal to 0 no no magnetization over
here but up to that point there is
magnetization so we have exactly the
situation that I described when we began
and we have a jump jump
in the magnetization are that's associated with
a jump from here to here if we buy
us the system a little bit with a little
bit of external magnetic field one of
the two of these will be the lower
energy configuration
and it will dominate the physics
Alright,
so that's the phenomenon of spontaneous magnetization
One other point,
notice what happens to the intersection over here
as you go to this point over here
As you go to this point over here,
let's track it
So let's start with...
Okay,
so here's very low temperature
and now we raise the temperature
this curve starts to move over to this,
like that
this point moves down
and as we lower the temperature,
we eventually come to this
first point where the crossover is
and the crossover,
the crossing of the temperature
between these two curves migrates
continuously to the origin here
and the meaning of that is
that there's magnetization all along here
in other words,
there's non-zero average of the spin
but as you move toward this point here
the average magnetization goes away
and disappears at that point and then it's gone
Okay,
what's this point called?
Anybody know?
Critical point,
Curie point,
yeah,
critical point
T critical,
right
What would it mean for a fluid?
What does it mean for the gas-liquid phase transition?
It means that as you move to the critical point
the density difference between the gas
and the liquid goes to zero
Over here,
more spins down
more spins up
There's a gap,
a separation in the value of the density
as you jump from here to here
but as you go above the critical
point or right to the critical point
right at that point,
the liquid and the gas density are exactly the same
and then beyond that,
there is no liquid-gas distinction
Temperature's higher than the critical temperature
So that's the mean field approximation to
the critical point of the Ising magnet
I didn't tell you this is called the Ising magnet
It's the Ising magnetic system,
Ising,
I-S-I-N-G
Ising didn't invent it
He solved the one-dimensional version of it
which takes about a quarter of a line of paper
It's very trivial
His thesis advisor asked him to study
it as an example of phase transitions
and he did,
and he discovered
that there's no phase transition in one dimension
Now,
that doesn't seem consistent with this
When d equals one,
there still seems to be the same phenomena
but the point is,
in one dimension,
it's a poor approximation
There aren't enough nearest neighbors to average over
He solved it correctly and
found there was no phase transition
and from that,
he concluded that there are no phase transitions,
period
He was quite wrong
but he did get his neighbor to
think that there was no phase transition
He was named to be the
most famous name in statistical mechanics
because his thesis advisor happened
to give him the right problem
Anyway,
the Ising model,
these are called the Ising models
and in dimensions higher than one
the mean field approximation is a good approximation
and says that there's a critical point
magnetization up to that critical point
no magnetization after that
and the magnetization smoothly goes to zero
as you go to the critical point
Alright,
so that's a...
I,
uh,
this took shorter than I expected it to
so let's have some questions
and I don't want to start a new topic now
What was J?
Oh,
J is just a constant
Let's just go back to where it came from
I wrote that the energy of the system
was minus sigma i sigma j
Now,
sigma is a dimensionless variable
It takes on magnitude one and minus one
So it's dimensionless
So this is not dimensionless,
dimensionally consistent
if I wanted to restore some dimensions
So what I would do is
I would put a constant here
with units of an energy
Alright?
J
I suppose J for Joule,
I don't know
And then it would reappear over here
because it always multiplies the dimensionality of space
Right?
Could you go to the logic again
for S equals the tangent hyperbolic to beta dS?
Well,
what we find
when we isolate this one spin
and think of it in
the background of all the others
is that its average in the background
because of thermal fluctuations
will be tan 2 beta dS
Alright?
Now that's just one spin out of all these others
What we've assumed
is that there's an average spin
for every spin on the lattice
which are all the same
Every spin is like every other spin
and we've assumed that the
average spin is equal to S
That was our starting point
We replaced all the nearest neighbors by S
But then this is only consistent
if when we calculate the average
of any one of the spins
it's equal to the average
that we assumed in the beginning
So we assumed an average value
for all the other spins
We then calculated the expectation
or the average value of the
one spin that we treated honestly
All the others we just
treated as something we can average
This one spin we treated honestly
in the background of the others
And we found out that
at a given temperature it has an average
which is equal to this
The only consistency
The only way this can be consistent
since we assumed that the average
of a spin is equal to
We called it S
is for these two to be equal
So it's just the consistency of
the original assumption
that the average of the spin is equal to S
And this is a,
incidentally,
this method of mean field
is a common method in physics
where when you have a lot of degrees of freedom
you focus on one of them
and you assume the average value for all the others
Then,
using the average value for all the others
you study the dynamics of
the one additional degree of freedom
And then in the end
when you've calculated the averages for
that one additional degree of freedom
set them equal to the averages that you assumed
for all the others
That's called the mean field approximation
And as I said,
it's a widely used approximation
And it is most effective in situations
where any one degree of freedom is in direct contact
with a large number of others
that you can average over
In terms of the dimensionality of space
it means that the,
what's called the coordination number
the number of nearest neighbors is large
The way you can get the
number of nearest neighbors to be large
is only one way
and that's to let the
dimension of the lattice get large
So then you have the perfect right to ask
Okay,
you've convinced us about something
in the limit of very large numbers of dimensions
We might believe it for a thousand dimensions
We might even believe it for a hundred dimensions
We might even believe it for ten dimensions
But where should we start to disbelieve?
And the answer is,
you should start
It depends of course on
the degree of accuracy you want
But if you want something like 20% accuracy
or you just want 20% accuracy for the critical temperature
Okay,
d equals 3 is fine
It's a good approximation for d equals 3
It's a so-so approximation for d equals 2
I'll tell you the exact numbers
If you calculate the critical temperature
Here's the critical temperature
Where was it?
Setting j equal to 1
Here it is
Alright
For two dimensions
t is equal to 4 in some appropriate units
The correct answer if I remember is about 2.7
So it's not good and it's not horrible
For three dimensions I don't remember the exact numbers
Of course I can do 2 times 3
That I'm pretty good at
It's 6
But I don't remember the exact
Let's see
The critical temperature is always lower
The real critical temperature is always lower
Than the mean field approximation
So I don't remember the exact numbers
But it's within 20% or 15% of the right answer
And by d equals
Well,
we're not interested
We're really not interested in 4 dimensions
5 dimensions or 6 dimensions
It's reasonably accurate for d equals 3
It gives you the right general picture
And is even quantitatively within about 15%
I can't remember the exact number
d equals 1
It completely breaks down
Well,
it completely breaks down
It says t equals 2d
The actual answer is t equals 0
The critical temperature is 0
In other words,
you never even really get started
At temperature 0 it's true
That there's a magnetized phase
Either all up or all down
But the smallest amount of temperature
Will disrupt it
Incidentally,
I can tell you the physical reason for that
There's an interesting simple physical reason
Why you can't have this kind of spontaneous order
In one dimension
And why you can have it in higher dimensions
Let's think about all of the configurations
Of the one-dimensional theory
Let's start with all spins up
So what we're starting with
Is a little bit of bias
Which makes all the spins be up
And now let's look at all the configurations
That we can build on top of that
What can we do?
We can start flipping spins down
What happens?
How much energy is stored
In one spin flipped down?
Can anybody figure that out?
Hmm?
Four
Each bond,
each broken bond
Costs you two units of energy
You have to go from minus one to plus one
So each broken bond costs you two units of energy
This costs four units of energy
How about flipping two spins down?
Are they next to each other?
Very good
Are they next to each other or are they not?
What if they're not next to each other?
Then the answer is eight
But what if they are next to each other?
Four again
What if they're three apart?
Four
There's an infinite number of configurations
Which cost you no more in energy
Than just one flipped spin
Whole big blocks of them
Flipping them over
Cost you no more energy than one of them
That's the main reason
Why the magnetized phase is unstable
When you increase the temperature a little bit
There's just a lot of configurations
Which cost the minimum amount of excess energy
What happens in higher dimensions?
Let's take higher dimensions
Let's take two dimensions
Again,
start with all spins up
And now flip one of them over
How much energy does that cost?
Eight units of energy
How about two units?
How about two spins flipped?
Sixteen if they're far from each other
But how much if they're next to each other?
Twelve
Let's see which are the broken bonds
Here's a broken bond
Let's just color green the broken bonds
One
Two
Three
Four
Five
Six
This is not a broken bond over here
So that six times two is twelve units of energy
That's more energy than just one flipped spin
Okay
Here's the way you can count
Draw a perimeter around the islands of flipped spins
Imagine flipping islands of spins
Imagine islands or groups of them adjacent
Flipped
And draw
A boundary around them
Like that
And then count how many bonds this boundary passes through
How many?
Well,
it's proportional to
But the main thing is
There's no way to flip a lot of spins
Without costing a lot of energy
The cheapest you can do
If you want to flip a hundred spins
The cheapest in energy
Is to have them form
A compact group of them
Well,
probably not a square
Probably,
yeah,
maybe a square
Maybe a square
And then
The number of broken bonds is proportional to the surface
Well,
it's proportional to the boundary
It's in one dimension
Boundary is just two points
And so when you flip whole blocks of spins
It just breaks two bonds
But in higher dimensions
Trying to flip large numbers of spins
Becomes costly
Because you'll have to break a lot of bonds
The number of bonds does not grow
as fast as the number of spins
But it does get bigger and bigger
And that's why there's this stability
To the higher dimensions
To the magnetization in higher dimensions
Than there is in two dimensions
Because
Every island of spins is surrounded
By a bunch of neighbors
Which are holding it fixed
And to flip large numbers of them
Becomes costly
Whereas in two dimensions
Big blocks of spins are only held in place
By two bonds
Not a very stable situation
The technical mathematics of it
We can postpone to another time
But that's the intuitive physics
Of what's going on
So in fact
You could conclude from this
That there's no gas-liquid phase transition
In one dimension
And there isn't
There is a gas-liquid phase transition
In two dimensions
Now who's interested in one dimension and two dimensions?
Well
It turns out that there are lots of systems
In solid state mechanics
Solid state physics
And condensed matter physics
Which are approximately in some sense
Either one-dimensional or two-dimensional systems
Systems of
You know
Long chains of molecules
Or planes or flat planes of molecules
And
These
Lower dimensional systems do have a real
Utility,
a real application
But as I said
In one dimension and two dimensions
One dimension there is no
Gas-liquid or magnetic phase transition
In two dimensions and higher there is
And in very high dimensions
Mean field approximation becomes extremely accurate
So this is like
This is only for lattice systems?
Well
The tools that I showed you were for lattice systems
There's more general systems that we could study
Incidentally it's kind of fun
To try to do a better approximation
Than the simple mean field approximation
And here's the game
You again pretend that all
the spins are equal to s
But then you unfreeze two of them
Not just one of them
You unfreeze two of them
And you study the statistical mechanics of pairs of them
Two of them free to fluctuate
Two adjacent ones free to fluctuate
And you calculate in the background of all the others
The average value of any one spin
Of either of the two of these
You do that
And then you set the average value
Of either one,
they'll be the same
Equal to the background spin
And you get a better approximation
You get a better approximation because you've allowed
One nearest neighbor to each one of them to fluctuate
And you get a better approximation
It's an improvement
You can go further
You can study three spins at a time
In the background of all the others
You get an even better approximation
Okay
Eventually you can study all the spins
In the background of no spins
And you get the exact answer
But it is fun
I once worked out the two spin case
In the background of the others
And you do get a numerically quite a good answer
For the three dimensional case
Yeah
I'm wondering if you said
negative temperature is an interesting
Oh,
well,
yeah
Let's come to negative temperature the next time
Yeah
How do they figure out these things?
We didn't have to think of this as negative temperature
We could just think of it as negative s
Okay
Right
That was the right way to think about it
How do they get the exact number?
You said they had an exact number
This is an exactly solvable
Oh,
okay
All right
Comparing high temperature expansions
And low temperature expansions
And discovering that they are very close
Well,
something called lattice duality
Which you will find written up
in the notes that I distributed
On the internet
The lattice duality argument
And it's a very elegant,
beautiful mathematical observation
About these systems
But I didn't want to do it here
But this two dimensional system
The two dimensionalizing model is exactly solvable
It has enough symmetry and enough special structure
That it is exactly solvable
Is there a name for the two free element solution?
This?
No,
you mean the mean field with two spins unfrozen?
Is that what you're asking?
Yes
Not that I know of
There's something called the beta approximation
Which?
The beta approximation
Beta,
beta
Hans beta
No,
that's not
That's got nothing to do with this
That's got
That is one dimensional systems
But not the Ising model
The Ising model is too simple
I mean,
if you apply the beta approximation
It would be like hitting a peanut with a sledgehammer
No,
the
It's for one dimensional systems
And it's for one
The one dimensional systems
With more complicated kinds of interactions
Which cause them to
What are called Heisenberg magnets
Not this Ising magnet
He first worked out
The beta approximation
Not the beta
The beta method of solution
Is applicable to something called Heisenberg ferromagnets
Not to the Ising ferromagnets
So,
um
要
You described this in terms of gas-liquid phase transition.
Is it equally applicable to liquid-solid phase transition?
No.
The liquid-solid phase transition is a transition from
a homogeneous configuration to one which is crystallized,
where all the molecules line up in a definite lattice.
And it's a sharp transition where the
system goes from a disordered liquid phase
to a sharply ordered lattice configuration.
Now the problem with this system,
and the reason that it can't
exhibit that kind of phase transition,
because it's already biased by having its own lattice,
and there's no sharp transition between
a lattice symmetry and no lattice symmetry,
because it's already got its built-in lattice structure.
So no,
there is no notion of a
solid-liquid phase transition for this system.
Okay.
We've got a related question for gas-liquid.
Does that mean if you put
a liquid through a very small capillary,
you can't tell whether it's a liquid or a gas?
Because that's effectively the one thing.
I would have said if you
put it above the phase transition,
above the critical point,
you can't tell if it's a liquid or a gas.
Okay.
No,
I think,
okay,
I think you're right.
If you take a small enough sample,
you can't tell if it's a liquid or a gas.
Phase transitions are things that
happen in the infinite number of,
in the limit of infinite number of particles.
Phase transitions never happen for
finite number of degrees of freedom.
For finite number of degrees of freedom,
there are never sharp phase transitions.
There are sharp discontinuities.
And the way you can see that is you
can look at the structure of the partition function.
The structure of the partition function,
when you have finite number of degrees of freedom,
the partition function is a
finite sum over finitely many particles,
and if it's a spin system like that,
over finitely many configurations of e
to the minus beta times the energy.
Each contribution from every single state,
from every single state,
is a finite number of degrees of freedom.
So the partition function,
the final state,
is an analytic smooth function of beta.
And when you add up a
finite number of analytic or smooth functions,
you get a smooth function.
Phase transitions are singularities,
places of discontinuity of some
sort as a function of temperature.
So for finite number of degrees of freedom,
you never get phase transitions.
There are never,
the partition function is always completely analytic.
It takes an infinite number of degrees of freedom.
Basically,
these sums have to be infinite sums,
and if the spins only take
on values of one and minus one,
well,
you'll have to have an infinite number of
spins before this can add up to something singular.
So,
right,
so in fact,
you cannot tell the difference between a
gas and a liquid at any temperature,
except maybe zero temperature,
but let's forget that.
At any temperature,
you can't tell the difference.
You can't tell the difference between a gas and a
liquid or any of these things by looking at small samples.
It takes large samples to...
And then even if the sample is very,
very large,
its magnetization is not
infinitely stable unless it's infinitely,
infinitely big.
It just requires an infinite background
to hold the whole thing together.
So there's two different ways,
two different situations where you can't tell
the difference between a gas and a liquid.
One of them is just studying small samples.
The other is when you have a critical point
like this and you go around the critical point.
There's no sharp place where
you go from gas to liquid.
The properties sort of smoothly
go from one to the other.
I wonder if you could remind us
exactly how the thermodynamics of this particle is.
We've got,
going back to like the baths,
each particle is thought of as one
of the baths which is in equilibrium.
Well,
I wouldn't call the rest of these heat baths.
I would just call it the mean field.
The reason I wouldn't call it heat bath...
Well,
I mean field bath,
which still has to...
In order to apply the Boltzmann statistic,
so we have to exchange energy
with the surroundings in some way,
don't we?
Yeah.
So what does that mean exactly?
Okay,
it means that there are other
little terms in the energy which cause,
when you put them into the
equations of motion of the system,
cause transfer of energy back and forth.
Now,
we haven't talked about this,
but I will discuss it for a moment now.
If you have a system whose energy...
Let's use the language of quantum spins now,
okay?
Language of quantum spins.
If...
So,
sigma then has three components.
Sigma 1,
sigma 2,
and sigma 3.
The sigma that we've been talking
about here could be the z component,
the third component of the spin.
And there would be a term in the energy which would just be
proportional to sigma 3 of one particle times sigma 3 of another particle.
What a minus sign.
Alright.
From the point of view of the mechanics,
of the quantum mechanics of the system,
sigma 3 will never change with time.
There's nothing in...
Think of this as a Hamiltonian.
There's nothing in this Hamiltonian
which doesn't commute with sigma 3.
In fact,
the only things in the Hamiltonian are sigma 3.
There's nothing which doesn't commute.
Now,
I'll remind you,
because I know you've studied quantum
mechanics at least a little bit,
that the time derivative of something...
Do you remember the formula for
the time derivative of a quantity?
Yeah,
it's the commutator.
The commutator with the Hamiltonian.
Do you remember that?
Okay.
So the commutator of I times the commutator...
Is it A with H or H with A?
I don't remember.
But that's good enough.
There's nothing in this system here
which does not commute with sigma 3.
So what this means is that this system,
if you were to lay it
down and lay down a given configuration,
it would never change.
It's completely static.
There's nothing in it which would allow it to change.
Of course,
that also means it would never come to thermal equilibrium.
You need a little bit
of interaction of a different kind,
something which doesn't commute with these sigmas.
So,
you could add something like a tiny,
tiny little number,
epsilon,
times the first component of sigma 1,
sigma I times first component,
sorry,
sigma 1,
sigma 1 of J,
and maybe another one with sigma 2 and so forth.
You'd have to add something in
that doesn't commute with the sigma 3s
to give it time dependence.
As it is,
it doesn't have any time dependence,
but you always imagine in the back of your mind
that there are tiny little interactions
between things which can cause them to change.
This system as it stands doesn't have anything in it
which would tell you how things change with time.
You know what it's like?
It's like having an expression
for the energy in classical mechanics
which only had potential energy,
no kinetic energy.
If a system didn't have any kinetic energy,
it wouldn't move.
It would have energy depending on its position,
but it wouldn't have anything,
it would have nothing in its dynamics
which would cause it to move from point to point.
So you can think of this here,
the term that we included,
as the potential energy of this lattice of molecules,
ignoring the kinetic energy which causes things to change.
Somehow or another,
that additional kinetic energy
is going to allow these things
to get into some sort of equilibrium.
Yeah.
It allows them to get into equilibrium,
it allows them to change with time,
to approaching equilibrium,
but interestingly enough,
it has no effect whatever
on the phase diagram,
on the nature of phase transitions.
That's all determined by potential energy.
And surprisingly,
kinetic energy doesn't play any
role in these phase transitions.
The system finds the configuration,
well,
the potential kinetic energy doesn't play any role.
Only,
no,
kinetic energy doesn't play any role.
So in the end,
we find the thing up with the probability
to beta ds and down with the...
But you must always imagine,
as you say,
you must always imagine there's
a little more to the system
which must be very weak in order that the energetics
is mostly dominated by the things you've kept,
but you must always imagine there's a little more
which brings the system to thermal equilibrium.
I guess what I'm wondering about is,
are there some systems that you
might think you could model this way,
but you'd go wrong if you did?
I can't think of any offhand.
In other words,
you're talking about quite a general class of...
Well,
if we tried to use this
to describe how a fluid flows out
of a little hole in a container
and how the fluid goes from inside the container
to outside the container,
it would never do that.
We could never,
yeah,
we could never study
the approach to thermal equilibrium
or the approach to anything.
So we would completely fail to study anything
that involves the time dependence of the system.
All we can study is the equilibrium properties.
But I think you're asking whether there are systems
whose equilibrium properties wouldn't
be correctly described this way.
Well,
I'm sure we can invent them,
yes.
We can certainly invent them.
Any mixing in the Hamiltonian
between kinetic and potential terms,
between position and momentum,
will...
The reason we get away
with this is because the energy
consists of two pieces,
one which is completely potential
and only depends on the positions,
and the other which is completely kinetic
and only depends on the momenta.
Remember,
the partition function is an
integral over positions and momenta.
The potential energy doesn't make...
The integrations over the momenta
don't care about the potential energies.
And they just factor off completely.
They just factor off and they're exactly the same
as if the molecules weren't interacting with each other.
The potential terms are the things
which know about the interaction between molecules.
The other term,
the other factor doesn't.
And so all of the properties
of the gas which are interesting
with respect to the phase transitions and so forth
have to do with potential energy.
Crystallization has nothing to do with potential energy.
All it has to do with
is finding the configurations of molecules
which form crystal lattices,
and that's got entirely to do with potential energy.
Minimizing a certain combination
of potential energy and entropy.
Yeah,
a couple of weeks ago you
were describing coarse and fine-grained entropy.
And I think I remember that you said coarse-grained entropy,
that the...
The Leuville theorem is violated?
No,
I didn't say that.
The Leuville theorem is never violated.
No,
it's a theorem.
Theorems can't be violated.
Theorems are either wrong or right.
The theorems are never violated.
That's why...
What if you say that when
the loose grains get really skinny
and you have a delta-p,
delta-x that's wider than that,
that it doesn't violate the...
No,
because the Leuville theorem
is not about coarse-grained entropy.
It's just not about coarse-graining.
It's about fine-grained system.
It's just not a theorem about the coarse-grained entropy.
It's strictly a theorem about the fine-grained entropy.
So how could coarse-graining violate
the theorem about fine-grained entropy?
Let's try to understand the relation,
but let's take a look.
Okay.
But you might have imagined a wrong Leuville theorem
which says that the fine-grained entropy doesn't change,
that the volume of...
Sorry,
the coarse-grained entropy doesn't change.
That would not be a theorem.
It's violated,
but it wouldn't be a theorem.
And nobody ever thought it would be a theorem.
Right.
Okay.
But...
So if I announce the new theorem,
this is the Schmeierville theorem or the Leuville theorem,
the Leuville theorem...
The Leuville slugger who invented the Leuville theorem
said that the volume and phase of the...
and coarse-grained phase space is constant with time.
Well,
that would have been violated.
Yeah.
Could you explain what happens when the...
phase space...
the area turns into a very wavy kind of...
you know,
cotton candy kind of thing?
And then you have...
We're talking about coarse-grained...
Well,
okay.
So I say,
take that cotton...
cotton candy...
and look at the volume actually...
occupied by the candy.
It's very tiny.
Very tiny.
But on the other hand,
if you were to take every little...
spot along the fibers
and put on that spot
a little ball about that big...
Of course,
they would crash into each other,
but if they crash into each other,
just let them overlap.
And to take the volume that would be carved out
by this coarse-grained version of the cotton candy
where every point is blurred over a certain size,
it would fill up the area that you...
that you...you know,
the pink...
the pink cloud of...
Right.
So there are two different descriptions of volume.
One of them is the coarse-grained volume where you...
you know,
where you...
I don't know what the right word is.
Coarse-grained is the word.
But where you let each little piece of the cotton
be replaced by a little sphere,
and the spheres...
eventually the cotton will get so close together
that the little spheres will begin to overlap,
and those little spheres will fill up the volume
that visually you would see
in this cloud of cotton candy.
Much bigger volume.
So as the cotton candy is spun out,
it starts as a little glob of sugar that big,
and if you coarse-grain a
little glob of sugar that big,
it's that big.
Not much bigger.
And now it starts to spread
out its tentacles in all directions
and create this cloud of cotton candy.
But now you replace each point along that fibrous structure
with a little sphere,
it'll occupy a volume which is much bigger.
So as you spin out the cotton candy,
it seems to grow,
although the actual volume of sugar
is exactly the same.
That's what happens.
Cotton candy,
that's a good example.
Right.
That's a very good example.
I will use it next time.
For more,
please visit us at stanford.edu.