Stanford University.
The subject this quarter is a collection of things,
but
mostly special relativity and field theory.
We're coming back now,
not quantum field theory.
We're not prepared for quantum field theory yet.
We've learned classical mechanics,
those who have participated up till now.
Classical mechanics,
the general structure of classical mechanics,
what it is,
how it works,
the action principle,
Hamiltonians,
Lagrangians,
all that kind of stuff,
and I assume you know it.
We also learned some elements of quantum mechanics.
I can't believe I taught
a whole quarter on quantum mechanics
and we never got to the harmonic oscillator.
That's...
When I tell people that,
they say,
what did you do?
And I tell them,
and they say,
oh,
that's good.
But we learned the principles of quantum mechanics,
but we didn't spend much time on examples.
In order to go forward with
quantum mechanics and quantum field theory,
we're going to have to do
some more quantum mechanics for sure,
but not this quarter.
No quantum mechanics this quarter.
We're back to classical physics,
but now back to the relativistic end of things.
We've studied non-relativistic mechanics,
motion of particles,
mostly motion of particles,
F equals m a,
Newtonian physics.
We have not studied anything about light,
and that's because light
basically is a relativistic phenomenon,
a phenomenon that has to
do with special theory of relativity,
and that's going to be our goal this quarter,
the special theory of relativity.
And classical field theory.
Classical field theory means electromagnetic theory,
basically electromagnetic theory,
waves,
forces on charged particles,
all that sort of thing.
But in the context,
very definitely in the context
of the special theory of relativity.
So that's where we're going to begin.
Special relativity,
that's tonight.
I said this before.
I suspect that most of you
have at some point in your lives
learned the elements of special relativity.
How many people would not fall into that category?
So I'm right then.
Just about everybody has
learned special theory of relativity.
How many people feel that
I could completely dispense with it
without losing any,
without that I...
Is it...
Do you feel that you would
like to go through special relativity?
Yes.
All right,
so I'm getting the rough
answer that the answer is yes,
and that's what I had prepared to do tonight.
But I had also been prepared that if everybody said,
we really understand special relativity completely,
can you move on to the next thing?
I would have said yes.
But I'm glad you didn't because I...
但是
I like the idea of teaching from the beginning
okay so let's come to
special relativity let's first talk about
relativity
well let's even go back a step before relativity
the idea of a reference frame
the idea of a reference frame you know
what I'm not going to spend a lot of
time on
the basic philosophy and everything
you know what a reference frame is
we talked about reference frames in classical
mechanics
it's a set of spatial coordinates x y and z
usually based on cartesian coordinates
to specify the coordinates
you will want to specify
where the origin of coordinates is
there's ambiguity in that you can
translate it from one place to another
and you will also want to
specify the orientation of the coordinates
in other words by orientation I
mean they're free up to some rotation
you want to pick the x-axis that way
and you want to pick the y-axis that way
the y-axis that way
the z-axis that way
or change it
but specify it to begin with
and that's part of picking a reference frame
a spatial set of coordinates
in addition to a set of coordinates
which could be measured by meter sticks
if you like
if you want to think physically or concretely
about what a coordinate system means
think of space as filled up
with a lattice of meter sticks
so that every point in space can be specified
as a certain number of meters to the left
certain number of meters up
certain number of meters in and out
and that's a coordinate system for space
and in order also to specify when something happens
not just where it happens
you have to specify a time coordinate
so a full coordinate system or a full reference frame
consists of an x a y and a z
and a t
in other words a time axis
and that's a reference frame
now you can have different reference frames
apart from the ability to
rotate from one thing to another
you can also consider moving reference frames
reference frames that are moving
relative to some specific reference frame
we could speak of our reference frame
by our I mean yours and mine
now let me think let
me not say yours and mine
your reference frame
you're sitting still
I will assume that for the most
part you will continue to sit still tonight
but I will move around from time to time
I may march past you like this
or I'm going to march past you like that
and we will
if I think of my coordinates
as a coordinate frame a set of meter sticks
that I carry with me and move with me
as I move
so that at every instant I personally
am at the center of my own coordinates
then my coordinates are different than your coordinates
you will specify an event by
an x y z and t
I will specify it by a different
set of x y z's and t's
to account for the fact that
I may be moving past you
in particular we won't agree about the x's
if I'm moving along the x axis relative to you
my nose I will always say relative to me
is uh six inches in front of my face
I think it's probably less than that
and I will say my
nose is at x equals six
you will say my nose
is not at x equals six
you will say my nose is moving
and it's at some position that changes with time
and so you'll give a different coordinate to it
um
in ordinary time
pre-relativistic physics,
we will also specify times,
pre-special relativistic
physics,
we will also specify times,
and in pre-relativistic physics we would
assume that we all have watches,
our watches are synchronized,
we go through
some operation to synchronize them,
we'll talk about operations to synchronize
watches,
but we'll assume they're synchronized so
that at the given instant of time
all of your watches agree with each
other and they agree with my watch.
My watch agrees with your watch.
That was an assumption that was made in all of
pre-relativistic physics,
that time is time is time is time,
and there's no
ambiguity associated with moving reference
frames about what the time is
at a given instant.
What does relativity mean?
Relativity means that for all coordinate systems which are
related to each other by uniform velocity,
all reference frames related to each other
by uniform motion,
the laws of physics are the same.
The laws of physics are the same
in every reference frame,
the word is inertial reference frame,
you know the term
inertial reference frame.
If one frame is inertial,
then any frame moving with uniform
velocity relative to it is inertial.
What is an inertial reference frame?
What is the first inertial reference frame
that you start with?
Let's just make it simple and
say it's a frame of reference
in which Newton's laws are correct,
and in particular where particles which have
no forces on them move with uniform velocity.
That's a reference frame.
Every
frame moving uniformly relative to it,
not rotating
relative to it,
not accelerating relative to it is another inertial frame.
And it's a feature of Newtonian
mechanics that the laws of physics,
F equals M A,
that
together with Newton's law of
attraction or Coulomb's law of attraction,
they're the
same in every reference frame.
So if you like,
the way I like to describe
this is go to the proverbial railroad
train moving down the x-axis with uniform velocity,
and think about you in the,
or me,
I'm in the train,
you're standing still.
You'll have
a set of laws,
and the way I like to
think about it is laws of juggling.
Juggling is a
good thing that makes a
lot of use of classical mechanics,
inertia,
forces,
all the good stuff.
And if you know how to juggle at rest,
you juggle exactly the same way in the moving
reference frame.
You cannot tell.
Another way to say it is
if you're in a moving reference
frame.
If I'm in a moving reference frame,
I'm in a moving reference frame.
If I'm in
a moving reference frame and everything is
sealed so that I can't see outside,
I cannot
tell that I'm moving.
I try to find out by doing some juggling,
and I find out that my
standard laws of juggling work,
and I assume,
therefore,
that I'm at rest.
But that's not
right.
All it tells me is that I'm in uniform motion.
So the principle of relativity is that the
laws of physics are the same in every reference
frame.
That principle existed before Einstein.
It was not invented by Einstein.
Sometimes
it's attributed to Galileo.
I don't know if he said it or not.
Newton would have recognized
it.
And it is called the principle of relativity.
What did Einstein add?
Einstein added one
law of physics.
The law of physics is that the
speed of light is the speed of light,
c,
that the speed of light is 186,000 miles per second,
or that the speed of light is
3 times 10 to the 8th meters per second.
That's a law of physics.
Now,
if you combine
the two things together,
that the laws of physics are
the same in every reference frame,
and that it's a law of physics
that light moves with a certain velocity,
you come to
the conclusion that light must move with
the same velocity in every reference frame.
Why?
Because the principle of relativity says the laws
of physics are the same in every reference
frame.
And Einstein announced that it's a law of
physics that light moves with a certain velocity.
That is puzzling.
And let's quantify and
make precise why it's so puzzling.
Let's try to be very,
very almost pedantic about
it.
Let's start with a reference frame.
A reference
frame is a coordinate axis in space.
Now,
for our purposes now,
space is just one dimension.
It's irrational.
I don't care about y and z.
I care only about x.
So let's draw an x
axis.
Here's x.
And also a time axis.
Here's t.
Let's call this your reference frame.
And
in your reference frame,
light moves with the speed of light,
with the standard speed
of light.
And so if a light ray is
sent out
from the origin,
time t and position x,
it will move with a
trajectory given by x equals ct
That's the motion of the light beam
And what does that look like on this map here,
on this map of space and time?
It looks like a straight line,
x equals ct,
it looks like a straight line like this
Now the faster the light moves
The closer to horizontal that line will be,
in other words in a given amount
of time the further it will move
So c is some number,
if I actually put in
186,000 miles per second
That line would be practically so horizontal
That you couldn't see the difference from horizontal
It would mean that this light ray
goes 186,000 miles in only one second
That would be a very horizontal line
So I will use some other units
for the speed of light
Units in which I can see
explicitly that the light ray is moving.
It moves a certain distance in a certain time.
That's its velocity
Okay,
now let's add a second reference frame
A second reference frame moving relative to the first
The second reference frame has an x prime axis
Its axis is called x
prime and the center of it,
just like the center of me,
is moving relative to you
So because it's moving it means me,
the center of my coordinate system,
is moving also with a straight line
It's not a very good pen.
Let's just try another one
Also moving with a straight line,
it's not a very good pen,
let's just try another one
So I'm moving with a straight line
And that straight line is x equals vt
Where v is my velocity relative to u
Okay,
so I'm moving with x equals vt
My position relative to u keeps increasing as a
function of time and that's the trajectory x equals vt
Now I don't call this x equals vt.
I just call it x equals 0.
That's me
But I don't want to call it x equals 0.
Let's call it x prime equals 0
That's x prime.
I will agree that to call my coordinates primed
All right,
I call my coordinates x prime and t prime
Next
What about,
yeah,
what's the relationship between
your coordinates and my coordinates?
Well,
that's pretty easy
So I'm going to call my coordinates
x prime is equal to x minus vt
This distance here is vt
My coordinate is called x prime your coordinates
called x my coordinate is your coordinate less
The distance between us which is vt
So that's x prime equals minus
vt and what about our clocks?
Well,
if we make the assumption that Newton made
Newton made the assumption that all clocks can
be synchronized with the clock in the same order
And that the time that a clock registers
has nothing whatever to do with how it moves
then we can
Before I even started to move we could synchronize
our clocks and now I can start to move and
The rule will be my time
is the same as your time
this would be the transformation of
coordinates between your coordinates and my coordinates if I
know when if you know when an event happens
You can tell me and my coordinates when it happened
Okay.
Now let's take this light ray the light ray that moves with
x equals CT in your frame and ask how it moves in my
frame
Alright,
so I want to find out how
the light ray moves in my frame.
It's going to be x prime is
Going to be X but along that
light ray X is equal to CT
All along this light all along this
light ray X is equal to CT.
So that means along the light ray X prime
Is equal to CT minus V T,
which is the same as C minus V times T
So in my referring oh
Which is also the same
as C minus V times T.
Prime
That's important
That's important.
So according to my watches and my
clocks and my measuring sticks that light ray
Which was emitted from here does not
move with the speed of light C
but moves with X times X
goes with the speed of light c minus v.
That's bad.
Something's wrong.
At least if Einstein
was right,
something's wrong,
because Einstein announced the rule that all light rays move
with the same speed.
What about a light ray going the other way,
incidentally?
The light
ray going to the left
would be x equals minus ct.
If you plug that in to x prime is equal
to x minus vt,
you get x prime is equal
to minus c plus v times t.
In other words,
a
light ray going,
if I'm moving to your right,
a light ray going that way looks to me like
it's going a little bit slower by this amount.
A light ray going in the other direction appears
to me to be going a little bit fast.
That was the first example.
That was what Newton would have said,
and that is what Galileo would have said,
and
it's what everybody would have said until the
end of the 19th century when people started
measuring the speeds of light extremely carefully and
found out that no matter how things were
moving,
the speed of light always appeared to be the same.
The only way to reconcile
this is to say something is wrong
with the transformation law between your coordinates
and my coordinates.
Something is wrong with
this simple-minded coordinate transformation here.
So the first
step of special relativity is to
figure out how this has to change,
your coordinates versus
my coordinates,
in order that the speed of light
be the same in every reference frame.
Okay,
I'm going to take you through that first,
through the steps.
Even before that,
we should
go back and ask about perhaps
assumptions that we made which were unwarranted.
Well,
there's a zillion assumptions we made,
obviously,
a lot of them,
but the most important one
and the one which is most at risk and
in fact the one which is wrong is that simultaneity
in every reference frame is the same.
That if we begin with our clocks synchronized,
and now I start to move,
will my clocks remain synchronized?
Is this synchronized with your clocks?
In other words,
is this the right transformation between
moving clocks and stationary clocks?
And that of course,
in hindsight,
is the one that we
know was wrong,
that the correct relationship is different
and in fact that the whole idea
of simultaneity is frame dependent,
is reference frame dependent.
Here's what I want you to
imagine.
Each one of you has a clock.
All right?
Okay.
Your clock,
your clock,
your clock.
You synchronize them by whatever means you synchronize your
clocks.
I have an equivalent collection of friends
who are spread out exactly the same
way relative to me as the front
row is here relative to this gentleman here.
Each one
of my friends has a clock.
I've made sure that our
clocks are synchronized and now we're
moving.
We're moving relative to you.
Okay?
As we go past,
we check each other's clocks
and we check whether they're synchronized.
And we check whether they're synchronized.
And if so,
if not,
excuse me,
how much out of whack is each clock depending
on how far down the line you are?
Equivalently,
we're asking what is the,
we could ask the
same thing incidentally about our meter sticks.
We could ask as I pass you,
is my x equals
1,
1 unit of your position relative to you?
If you get my point.
And of course,
this is where Einstein made the great leap.
He
said we have to be more careful.
We have to be much
more careful and define very carefully
what we mean by synchronous
and what we mean by lengths,
what we mean by times.
All right.
So he said,
okay,
look,
let me think about experimentally
how I would synchronize two
clocks given his postulate.
His postulate was the speed of the clock.
And he said,
okay,
the speed of light is
the same in every reference frame.
How do you go about synchronizing your
clocks and how should I go about synchronizing my clocks?
I said,
well,
if light goes that direction with
speed c and that direction with speed
c in every direction,
it will do a little trick.
A little trick is if we have two clocks,
let's say this gentleman at the end over
here and that gentleman at the end over there,
and they want to synchronize their clocks,
they don't want to get up out of their seats.
They're lazy.
They don't want to get out of their seats.
They want to stay where they're
sitting.
Then they find somebody right in the middle.
Now,
how do they know the person
is in the middle?
They measure with meter sticks.
I'm afraid you'll have to get out
of your seats if you want to do that,
but you measure with your meter sticks and you
find that that's five meters
or four meters to the center.
You'll find that's four meters
to the center.
Go back to your seats and now check your clocks.
All right.
To check your clocks by,
we could also have somebody sitting
in the middle there if we
could check the clocks by when your clock
reads 12 noon and when your clock reads
12 noon,
each send out a flash of light,
a flash bulb.
If the two flashes arrive at the
center at the same time,
then your clocks were synchronized.
You each said you're going
to send out your light beam
when your clock reads 12 o'clock.
If the light at the center
arrives at the same time,
then your clocks were synchronized.
That's the way Einstein decided to define synchronicity.
Now what about me who's moving?
I'm moving.
I get to this point over here.
When I get
to this point over here,
let's say that just happens to
be the point that you emit your
simultaneous light rays.
All right.
At 12 noon,
according to your clocks,
you each emit
a light ray,
but it doesn't quite get
to the center at 12 noon.
It gets to the center
slightly later according to your clocks,
by which time I'm over here.
Since I'm over here,
your light ray will arrive at me
a little bit late relative to your light
ray.
So I will say you guys are out of synchronous.
You made some mistake.
You didn't synchronize
your clocks because the light arrived
at me at two different times.
I can either say that
or I can say that the meaning of synchronicity...
is different in the two frames of reference.
Okay,
so let's go back to our
two coordinate systems and be skeptical
about exactly what synchronous means
in the moving reference frame.
In the stationary reference frame,
we'll assume that synchronous means
two points on the same horizontal,
at the same horizontal level here,
at the same T.
But what about the moving frame of reference?
The moving frame of reference,
we'll find in a minute,
that this point is not synchronous with this point,
but is synchronous with some other point.
And in fact,
that the whole surface here,
that the moving reference frame
calls synchronous,
not here,
that's the wrong place,
that's light.
It's someplace else.
We're going to map out,
what the moving observer calls synchronous.
And how are we going to do it?
We're going to do it by
synchronizing the clocks according to Einstein's rule.
Okay,
so what we need now is a better drawing.
Whenever you encounter a relativity problem,
draw a picture.
That's the first thing to do.
You first draw a picture.
The picture is always the same.
It's X and T.
X and T can be a reference
frame that you can think of as stationary,
in your frame of reference.
The other frame of reference,
think of the railroad train moving down the axis.
But the next thing to draw in,
before you draw anything else,
draw in light rays,
how light rays move.
So draw in X equals
CT and X equals minus CT.
In particular,
X equals CT.
We'll worry about X equals minus CT later.
But as I said,
if we were to use C equals 186 times T,
we would draw a practically horizontal line.
We don't want to do that.
So we choose the speed of light in
some units where it's easier to draw the picture.
And in particular,
the natural choice of units is
to make the speed of light one.
How do you make the speed of light one?
Well,
you use length units,
which are defined relative to your
time units in an appropriate way.
If your time units are seconds,
use your length units to be light seconds.
How big is a light second?
Well,
it's 186,000 miles,
but never mind.
One light second is a unit of length.
And how fast does light go
in units of seconds and light seconds?
It goes one light second per second.
That means that on a diagram like this,
where X measures light seconds and T measures seconds,
light moves at 45 degrees.
I'm sure you've seen this before,
but I'm just spelling it out.
It moves backwards at the same 45 degrees.
So that's the trajectories of light rays.
Next,
let's draw in another observer,
another reference frame,
a moving reference frame.
And again,
the reference frame is going to be
moving X prime equals X minus VT,
exactly like it is here.
Same picture,
superimposed on the light ray.
This is X equals VT.
What is X prime along here?
Zero.
This is also X prime equals zero.
So let's put X prime equals zero.
That's because X prime is X minus VT,
and if X is equal to VT,
X prime is equal to zero.
So that's the moving reference frame.
And let's try to figure out where T prime is,
where the T prime axis is.
All right.
We begin by putting in three people.
The one on the end,
the one in the middle,
and the one at the other end here.
All right,
so at the initial time,
right over here,
we're going to put in a moving person.
Not a stationary one,
I should have said,
not you people.
My friends.
My friends who are separated by equal distance,
there's me,
there's the one in front of me,
and there was the one yet in front of him.
Let's put in the first one.
And he moves with the same velocity.
That means he moves parallel.
Let's suppose that he's one unit ahead of me,
but measured with your meter sticks.
That means that this distance right over here
is one unit.
What does that say about the
equation of this second blue line here?
It says that it's x equals vt
plus one.
It's one unit ahead in the stationary coordinates.
What about the next person who's two units ahead?
Like that.
And his equation is x equals vt plus one.
vt plus two.
Now person one over here has a watch.
And as it happens,
his watch says,
time zero,
what is time zero?
That's not a time on my watch.
I'll take time zero to mean 12 noon.
Time zero occurs right over here along his trajectory.
That's time equals zero.
In other words,
the moving observer and the stationary observer agree
by assumption on what time t equals zero means.
The stationary observer,
t equals zero all along the horizontal axis.
That's essentially the definition of the horizontal axis.
All times from the stationary
observer are the same along here.
But let's see if we can figure out
where time zero is along this second axis.
Along,
let's give these people names.
Fred,
Mary,
and Seymour.
Is that the way you spell Seymour?
Yeah.
All right.
Fred,
all right.
So the way this is going
to work now is at this point,
Fred is going to send
out a light signal to Mary.
And at some point,
I don't know what point yet,
Seymour is also going to send
out a light signal toward Mary.
But they're going to send it in such a
way that they arrive at Mary at the same instant.
Okay.
So Fred sends out his light signal along here.
Where does Seymour have to
send out his light signal from
in order that it arrive at exactly the same time?
Well,
if I start in this end,
and I start shooting light rays up at 45,
I'm likely to miss this point.
So I'll be smart.
I'll work backward 45 degrees to here.
Each light signal in the stationary
reference frame moves at 45 degrees.
You can see,
because the second reference frame is moving,
the second reference frame is tilted
relative to the first reference frame,
that the point occurs above what
the stationary observer calls t equals 0.
This point over here,
the moving observer,
will call t prime equals 0.
Why?
Because in the moving frame of reference,
these two points sent light rays
to the central observer over here
that arrived at the same instant of time.
So Mary will say,
you guys sent me the light signal
at exactly the same instant of time
because it arrived at me
at the same instant of time,
and I happen to know that you're equally spaced.
Now it just becomes a little exercise
to figure out where this point is.
So I'm going to take you through that exercise.
I'm going to do it in detail.
It's very easy.
Let's give these points names.
This is a and this is b.
And what we want to
figure out is what the coordinates
of this point b are because we
know b is synchronous with the origin
in the moving reference frame.
That will give us some information.
In other words,
b must be a point,
t prime,
one of the points for which
t prime is equal to 0.
Okay,
what about point a?
How do we find point a?
We find point a by recognizing that
it's at the intersection of two lines.
What is this line over here,
the green line?
That's x equals ct.
This line is x equals ct because
it's a light ray moving to the right.
We've decided to set the
speed of light equal to 1,
or I decided.
So it's really just x equals t.
The motion of a light
ray is just x equals t,
and here's the light ray.
That's this line.
And the other line is this line.
And the other line along there that this point
a lies on is x equals vt plus 1.
How do we find the intersection?
We substitute one equation into the other,
and it just says t
is equal to vt plus 1.
In the first equation,
I just said x equal to t,
or t times 1 minus v is equal to 1,
or,
even better,
t is equal to 1 over 1 minus v.
So we now know where the
time of this point a is.
This is point a.
What about the x of this point a?
I would like the full
set of coordinates of this point.
So let's put a box around it.
What's the x of that point?
vt plus 1.
Well,
you can write it as vt plus
1 and plug in what t is,
but you can be smarter and you can say,
look,
this line is x equals t over here.
The green line is x equals t.
So all along the green line,
x is equal to t.
In other words,
x is equal to 1 over 1 minus v.
Now let's go to line a,
b.
The next thing to do
is to figure out line a,
b,
which will ultimately figure out where
it intersects x equals vt plus 2.
It's a few steps.
There's a few steps,
but they're fun to do.
So we'll go through them.
And I don't know a shortcut for this.
I don't know any shorter way to do this.
What about the line a,
b?
Okay.
Every line which is at 45 degrees
but pointing downward to the right,
in other words,
45 degrees but going upward to the left,
is a line that has the property that
x plus t is constant along that line.
Every line moving upward to the right with
45 degrees is x minus t is a constant.
Lines which are at 45
degrees but upward to the left
are lines x plus t equals a constant.
All right.
Let's take this one.
It's x plus t is equal to something.
What thing?
Well,
one easy way to find out what
I should put on the right-hand side here
is just to take one point on that line
and plug in the value of x plus t.
x plus t is the same all along this line.
And in particular,
at point a,
x plus t happens to be twice 1 minus v,
twice 2 over 1 minus v.
It's just this plus this.
x plus t.
So all along line a,
b,
a,
line a,
b,
x plus t is equal
to 2 over 1 minus v.
So we've now found line a,
b.
All right.
We want to find point b.
So there's one more step.
And that step is to
find the intersection of line a,
b
with x equals v,
t plus 2.
So we take x plus t
equals 2 over 1 minus v,
and we combine it with x minus v,
t equals 2.
That's this equation over here.
x minus v,
t equals 2.
And we solve the two simultaneous equations,
and that will tell us
what the coordinates of b are.
All right.
So how do we do that?
Well,
the first step we can just
solve by subtracting the two equations.
That will get rid of the x.
All right.
So let's subtract.
On the left-hand side,
we have t minus minus v,
t,
which means t times 1 plus v.
That's equal to 2 over 1 minus v minus 2.
All I've done is subtract.
All right.
I want to subtract 2 from a fraction,
so the best thing to do is
to put them over the same common denominator.
t minus 2 times 1
minus v over 1 minus v.
I've just multiplied and divided by 1 minus v.
Okay.
If you look at this carefully,
you'll see the 2s cancel.
2 minus 2.
The term with v here will become plus.
This whole thing becomes twice v over 1 minus v.
That's equal to t times 1 plus v.
One more step to calculating t.
It's just to divide by 1 plus v.
So what happens if you divide by 1 plus v?
Well,
you divide by 1 plus v.
1 minus v times 1 plus v.
Too many steps.
I hate doing algebra on the blackboard,
but I don't see any way around it.
I could tell you to go home and do it,
but...
What's 1 minus v times 1 plus v?
1 minus v squared,
right?
So we can just write
this as 1 minus v squared
and get rid of the 1 plus v.
That's t.
But it's not really t that I want.
I want x and t at this point.
So how do I find the x of point B?
This is the t of point B.
We could call it tB.
What about the x of point B?
Well,
all I need to do is substitute into this equation.
t is equal to tB,
so let's see what it is.
xB is equal to 2 divided
by 1 minus v minus tB.
Right?
I'm subtracting t from this equation minus tB,
and tB is 2v over 1 minus v squared.
Looks ugly,
but it's not.
When v is plus or minus 1.
What's that?
What happens when v is plus or minus 1?
Then bad things happen,
right?
Right.
When v is plus or minus 1,
that means that the observer here
is moving with the speed of light,
and we get into a kind of degenerate situation.
Well,
you just plug in.
What does happen?
Let's see.
First of all,
this one over here.
When v is plus or minus 1,
tB becomes infinite.
So the...
Yeah.
See what's happening.
When v gets to be plus or minus 1,
let's say plus 1,
this blue line is tilting over
to become horizontal with the light curve.
Not horizontal,
parallel with it.
And when it's parallel with it,
they never intersect.
So the intersection is at infinity.
Part of the game here,
of course,
is to realize that we
will eventually disallow things moving faster
or as fast as the speed of light.
For the moment,
that's a fair question,
and something bad happens.
So it begins to smell bad to
have somebody moving with the speed of light.
All right.
We can simplify this.
Multiply by 1 plus v in
both the top and the bottom.
Now use the fact that 1 minus v times 1
plus v is the same as 1 minus v squared,
and we get everything over the same denominator.
And let's see what we have.
We have a 2v.
We have another 2v with a minus sign.
They cancel.
And we just have a 2.
The remaining thing is a 2.
So it's not so bad.
xB is equal to 2 over 1 minus v squared.
The only difference between them is that
there's an extra factor of v in tB.
Now why did I go to all that trouble?
I went to all that trouble because I wanted
to figure out where the surface of a line
— it's a surface in higher dimensions —
where the surface,
when there's also other space dimensions like y and z,
where the line is which corresponds
to being simultaneous with the origin here.
And it's a line.
Which passes right through that point.
We could have found the other points in the line
by using smaller or bigger intervals for the same argument.
Same argument,
but with smaller or bigger intervals.
And we would have found that all
the places which are simultaneous with the origin
lie on the line which passes through the
origin and which passes through the point B.
What do we know about that line?
We know that it has a constant slope.
What is the slope?
The slope,
of course,
is the ratio of t
to x all along that line.
And what's the ratio of t to x?
It's just tB over xB.
Which is just v.
The ratio of tB to xB
is the ratio of this to this,
and it's just plain v.
That's all.
So the slope is just v.
The slope of this line here is v.
Another way to say it is
that this line is t equals vx.
t equals vx.
All along this line,
the moving observer says everything is simultaneous.
So however the clocks,
however the moving clocks work,
all the clocks along here,
if they're synchronized,
if they've been synchronized by Einstein's procedure,
they will all read the same time.
They will all read t
prime equals zero all along here.
Why?
Because this operation here was exactly
the operation to synchronize these two clocks.
If this one reads t prime equals zero,
so does this one.
All along here.
All right,
now look at the diagram.
Let me simplify the diagram.
Let me make it,
get rid of a lot of the stuff on it.
We have,
first of all,
a light ray moving at 45 degrees.
We have x equals vt.
That's the moving observer,
the center of the moving observer.
And then over here,
we have t equals vx.
Notice the symmetry of these two.
x equals vt and t equals vx.
The meaning of this symmetry is that this line
over here is just the reflection of this line.
They're just related by interchanging t and x,
flipping about the green line here.
Another way to say it is
that they're at the same angle.
This angle here is the same
as this angle here on this diagram.
So we've discovered something interesting.
If Einstein is right,
and if the speed of light
is the same in every reference frame,
and you use light rays to synchronize clocks,
then what's synchronous in one frame is not
the same as synchronous in the other frame.
That's the first thing.
And the second thing is we've actually found
what synchronous means in the moving reference frame.
It corresponds to surfaces which are not horizontal,
but which are tilted a little bit.
Tilted by slope v.
That solves the problem of
what simultaneous means in different frames,
and they're not the same.
Okay,
next.
Can we say more about the relationship
between xt and x prime and t prime?
Let's,
uh,
all right.
We don't need this.
Oh,
we can just lift it up.
Now,
here's what we know.
We know that x prime
equals 0 whenever x equals vt.
That x equals vt is the
same as x prime equals 0.
So let's begin writing x prime
is equal to x minus vt.
But we don't know that that's correct.
All we know is that
when x is equal to vt,
x prime is equal to 0.
This could be incorrect by some factor.
Let's call it f.
That factor could depend on the velocity of
the relative velocity of the two frames of reference.
So let's write f of
the velocity between the two frames.
And I mean the magnitude.
How fast is it going?
The magnitude of the velocity.
I use script v here to
indicate the magnitude of the velocity.
The velocity v can be positive or negative.
The two reference frames could be moving.
The moving frame could be moving backward.
It could be moving forward.
So v could be plus or minus.
But the function that would go here,
we might guess,
is just a function of the magnitude of the velocity.
Let's leave that.
Let's assume that for the moment.
And that's the general answer for what x prime is,
although we don't know yet anything
about what the function v is,
the function f of v is.
What about t prime?
Well,
we know that t prime is equal
to 0 whenever t is equal to xv.
We know that x prime
was 0 when x equals vt.
We know that t prime
equals 0 when t equals 0.
equals 0 when t equals xv.
Just invert x and v.
So it must be then that this is equal to
t minus vx times some other possible function of v.
These two equations tell us that x
prime is 0 whenever x equals vt.
And it tells us that t prime
is equal to 0 when t equals vx.
In other words,
it's just reflecting the equation.
This relationship that t prime is 0 when this is
true and x prime is equal to 0 when that's true.
Okay,
now we use some physics.
We use the physics that Einstein said that the
speed of light is the same in both reference frames.
What does that say?
The speed of light is
1 in the stationary reference frame.
So it must also be
1 in the moving reference frame.
What that says...
is that whenever x equals t,
x equals t is along the green line,
it must also be true
that x prime equals t prime.
If we have a light ray,
and the light ray moves with velocity 1,
this goes right back to
the first thing that we demonstrated,
that when we took a light
ray that went like x equals ct,
and then we transformed from one frame to another,
remember what we got the first time around?
We got c minus v and cp.
c plus v.
Alright,
let's do the same thing now and say,
supposing the light ray satisfies x equals t,
then it must also be true
that x prime equals t prime.
How can we arrange that?
Well,
it's actually very easy.
Let's suppose x equals t.
Then for that curve,
we can write this as
x times 1...
Oh,
let's write it.
What do we have to do
to make this equal to this
when x is equal to t?
If x is equal to t,
these two will be the same.
These two will be the same.
So what's in the bracket here will be
the same as what's in the bracket here
when x is equal to t.
If we want x prime to equal t prime,
there's only one choice.
That's to make f equal to g.
That's the only way.
f must be the same as g.
If f is not the same as g,
the motion of the light ray in moving coordinates
will not be with velocity 1.
So,
we come to the conclusion,
Einstein's rule tells us,
that whatever the connection between these coordinates is,
it involves the same function here.
What more do we know?
What more do we want to know?
We want to know what this function of v is.
We would dearly like to know
what that function of v is.
Once we know it,
we know completely how the coordinates
in two reference frames are related to each other.
So,
we use one more ingredient.
Incidentally,
I'm practically regurgitating Einstein's
first paper on the subject.
I haven't read it for probably 50 years,
but it has left,
obviously,
a very lasting impression on me.
This is basically what he did in that first paper.
Well,
this and a lot more.
Okay.
So now he said,
wait a minute,
who's to say which frame was moving?
Who's to say if my frame is moving relatively,
relative to you with velocity v,
or your frame is moving relative
to me with velocity minus v?
Whatever the relationship between the
two frames of reference are,
they should be symmetrical.
We could take the entire argument,
and instead of starting with the x and t,
and drawing an x prime and t prime,
we could do exactly the opposite.
The only difference would be that,
as far as I'm concerned,
you're moving with velocity minus v,
as far as you're concerned,
I'm moving with velocity plus v.
So we can immediately write down
what the relationship between
x and t are in terms
of x prime and t prime.
Here it is.
I'll write it down for you.
Let's write it over here.
It must be that x is equal
to x prime,
now,
what shall I write?
Minus vt prime?
Plus vt prime.
Why?
Because the velocity,
the relative velocity has the opposite sign,
times function of the same magnitude of the velocity.
The magnitudes of the velocity,
if I'm moving relative to you with velocity v,
you're moving relative to me with velocity minus v.
Let's assume this function is
just a function of the magnitude
of the velocity,
which is the correct answer in the end,
and t is equal to,
what is it?
t prime plus v x
prime times same function of v.
The question is,
are these two equations,
or these two sets of equations,
compatible with each other?
After all,
I didn't really need to guess the relation
between
x and t over here.
I could have just solved this equation
for x,
these two equations for x and t.
So I want to make sure that
this equation and this equation
are compatible with each other.
I'm going to do it in a fancy way.
Of course,
that will determine what f is.
The compatibility,
here's the way you would do it.
Here you have x prime and t prime,
in terms of x and t.
Now supposing you take the x
prime and t prime from here
and plug them in over here.
What will you get?
You'll get x in terms of x and t,
and t in terms of x and t.
How can that make any sense?
It can only make sense if what you get is
x is equal to x
and t is equal to t.
That's going to involve choosing f carefully.
Okay,
but I will show you
more than one way to do this.
Maybe we should just do it,
just by plugging in.
Yeah,
let's do it by brute force.
Let's just do it by brute force.
I have a fancier way to do it.
Okay,
let's do it.
x is equal to x prime,
which is what?
Somebody got to read it off to me.
x minus vt
times f of v.
That's this guy over here.
And plus v times t prime,
which is t minus vx,
also times f of v,
all times f of v,
right?
All times f of v.
So that will square f of v here.
Right?
Now,
as I told you,
the only way this can make sense
is if it just reads x is equal to x.
That's the only way it can make sense.
And if I did the same thing for t,
I would do the same thing for t here,
plugging in t prime and x prime,
and I'd better just wind up being
t is equal to t.
But let's look at it.
What does it take?
Let's combine things.
We have x,
um,
x times f squared over here,
and then we have plus v squared
x times f squared.
That's from here.
And then what about the t dependence?
Minus?
Minus.
But more important is the t dependence.
The t dependence is minus vt here,
minus vt times f squared,
and here we have vt times f squared.
This is minus vt times f squared,
this is plus vt times f squared.
Good sign.
The t's cancel automatically.
We've done something right,
because the t's cancel automatically,
leaving only the x's.
And the x's have x times f squared
minus v squared f squared x.
Or in other words,
x times 1 minus v squared times f squared.
And that,
by damn,
has to be equal to x.
How do we arrange that?
Well,
we arrange that just by choosing
1 minus v squared times f squared to be 1.
In other words,
it tells us what f has to be.
And it tells us that f has to be
1 divided by the square
root of 1 minus v squared.
In other words,
we cancel out the x,
so we have 1 is equal to
1 minus v squared times f squared,
f is equal to 1 divided by this square root.
That's it.
But what about the other root?
That's probably some interchange of
plus velocity and minus velocity.
Let's see.
So that would be minus .
.
It sounds like it's an
inversion of coordinates or something.
It's probably an inversion of coordinates.
I don't know,
I never thought about it.
Um,
yeah.
That's .
.
That corresponds to the
possibility of reflecting the coordinates.
x goes to minus x.
Good question.
I'm not sure what the answer is.
Let's ignore it for the moment.
It's got two roots.
I'm not sure what it says.
Okay,
so now we have the answer.
Oh,
I know what the answer is.
Okay.
Square root of 1 minus v squared
over square root of 1 minus v squared.
All right,
now I'll tell you what the answer is.
First of all,
which root you pick,
plus or minus,
should not depend on the velocity.
There shouldn't be some point in velocity
at which you suddenly jump from
one root to the other root.
That would be a very discontinuous thing to do
as a function of the velocity.
So you say,
what do I know?
Well,
what about for velocity v equals 0?
Certainly for velocity v equals 0,
in other words,
when there's a constant,
the two frames are not moving relative to each other.
We want the two frames to be the same.
So that says that x prime equals x,
not x prime equals minus x.
The two roots here would
correspond to the two possibilities,
x prime equals x or x prime equals minus x.
Surely,
when the frames of reference are
at rest relative to each other,
we want the solution to just be x
prime equals x and t prime equals t.
So that says,
pick the positive.
The positive root plus square
root of 1 minus v squared.
Okay,
let me write this more completely.
Let me write it again.
Let's write it in the usual way.
And I assume you recognize this.
t prime is equal to t minus vx
over square root of 1 minus v squared.
Notice they have the same
form except x and t interchanged.
x prime is x minus vt,
t prime is t minus vx,
all divided by square root of 1 minus v squared.
Okay.
These are,
of course,
the Lorentz transformations.
These are the Lorentz transformations,
and they've been cooked up to make sure
that in every frame of reference,
the speed of light is 1.
Okay.
What do you do if the speed of light
has not been chosen to be equal to 1?
What if it's just c,
where c is whatever you choose it to,
however you choose your units?
Then,
to figure out what's going on here,
all you have to do is say,
well,
if I'm going to use other units,
I must have these equations be dimensionally consistent.
I must have these equations.
Now,
velocity is a length over a time.
Well,
an x is a length,
a time is a time,
this is a length over a time,
so the numerator here,
the two terms are consistent with each other.
That's fine.
No problem.
But what about the square
root of 1 minus v squared?
The units of 1 are just 1.
They're dimensionless.
The units of a velocity
are a length over a time.
So,
and,
that does not have units 1.
So this velocity squared here
must not really be velocity squared.
The only way to make it dimensionally consistent
is to make this v squared over c squared.
In other words,
had we kept the speed of light in everywheres,
this v squared really would have meant
the velocity in units of the speed of light
by setting the speed of light equal to 1,
equivalently,
we said velocities are measured in
units of the speed of light.
v equals a half would
mean half the speed of light.
So,
the only way to restore the dimensions
and get the dimensions right in this equation
is wherever you see v squared,
put v squared over c squared.
Now,
this equation is not quite right.
What's wrong with this equation?
The left-hand side is a time.
The denominator is okay.
The right-hand side starts with a time,
but is v times x a time?
You need to divide by c squared.
v is a length per unit time,
but if I multiply that by a length,
I get a length times a length over a time.
That doesn't sound right.
So this v must be v over c.
A simpler way to say it is
the way I said it a moment ago.
v over c squared.
Yeah,
Right,
v over c squared.
That's the only way to restore the units.
And now,
this is the recognizable Lorentz transformations.
Notice that as long as the velocity is very small
compared with the speed of light,
so that v squared over c squared is even smaller,
if v is a tenth the speed of light,
v squared over c squared is one one-hundredth.
If v over c is
a tenth to the minus four,
or a tenth to the minus five,
this v squared over c
squared is truly a small number,
and the square root just becomes one.
What do we get?
We get x prime is equal to x minus vt.
That's the good old Newton version of things.
What about the second equation here?
If v over c is very small,
in other words,
let's now plug in some numbers.
Supposing v is a hundred miles an hour.
Let's even make it bigger.
Let's make it a hundred miles a second.
c is a hundred and eighty-six thousand miles a second,
and c squared is enormously big.
So v over c squared is a very,
very tiny number.
And so this term here,
if the velocity of the reference frames is relatively slow,
and if the velocity of
the reference frames is relatively slow,
this is negligible.
Also,
one minus v squared over c squared,
this is negligible.
Therefore,
the rule is t prime equals t.
For reference frames moving slowly relative to each other,
it's just the good old Newtonian-type formula.
This goes away,
this goes away,
v over c squared is negligible.
In other words,
wherever you see c in the denominator,
ignore that term because it's just too small to count.
So this is good.
As long as we're moving slowly
compared to the speed of light,
we get the old answer.
But when we get up near the speed of light,
there's huge corrections.
When we get up near the speed of light,
big things happen.
Okay.
Those are the Lorentz transformations,
which I assume you've seen before.
You may have even seen the derivation.
You may have seen the derivation before.
Incidentally,
what happens to y and z,
the other components of space?
Now,
we've been very specific in talking about
a frame of reference moving along the x-axis.
The motion,
the relative motion of the frames is along the x-axis.
But what happens to the
y direction when you do this?
Well,
physically,
what does it mean?
If your arm was the same length as my arm,
stick your arm out,
okay?
Stick your arm out.
And we went past each other,
the question is,
when we met at this point,
would our arms match?
Or would yours be longer than mine?
Well,
just by symmetry,
just by symmetry of the problem.
We could either refer to somebody
sort of moving halfway between us,
or it's clear that our arms are moving.
Our arms are going to match.
Because there's no reason for one
to be longer than the other.
Okay.
So therefore,
the rest of this Lorentz transformation
would involve y prime equals
y and z prime equals z.
In other words,
things only happen in the plane,
the x-t plane,
where the x,
where the motion is along the x-axis.
X and t get mixed up
with each other in this funny way.
Y and z are just passive.
They don't do anything.
They just stay the same.
Your y and my y are the same,
no matter how fast we're going,
but our x's and t's get mixed
up with each other in this way.
That's special relativity.
Let's talk very briefly about
time dilation and space contraction.
We might as well do it.
So we have all the ingredients we need.
I'll just do a couple of illustrations.
Again,
draw a picture.
Let's first talk about what we're doing.
I have a meter stick and I'm walking past you.
Or do I want you to be here?
Now you're the one who holds the meter stick.
You hold the meter stick.
You got the meter stick?
Hold it there.
Alright?
Right.
Now,
you know that that's a meter.
I walk past you,
and as I walk past,
I ask,
how long is your meter stick?
I measure it relative to my meter sticks.
But I have to be very
careful what I mean by that.
In particular,
since I'm moving,
if I'm not careful,
I will be measuring the end points
of your meter sticks at different times.
In fact,
I want to be measuring the end points of your
meter sticks at a common time which is synchronous to me.
Why do I want to do that?
Because that's what I mean by the length
of your meter stick in my reference frame.
I mean the length of your
meter stick relative to my meter sticks
where the two ends of your
meter stick are at the same time.
The end points of your meter sticks are
examined at the same time in my reference frame.
That's the definition of what I mean
by the length of your meter stick.
That I look at the end points of
your meter sticks at a common instant of time,
and I measure the distance
between them with my measuring rods.
So,
let's draw a picture to indicate what that means.
The meter stick is at rest in your reference frame.
It goes from x equals 0 to x equals 1.
1 meter.
Here's one end of the meter stick,
here's the other end of the meter stick.
Of course,
they exist at all times.
They're standing still,
and so the meter sticks are just vertical.
The ends of the meter
sticks are just vertical lines here.
Now I want to know,
in my moving reference frame,
so again,
we draw in the moving reference frame.
This is t prime equals 0.
This is x prime equals 0.
This is x equals 0.
And what do I want to know?
In my moving reference frame,
here's one end of the meter stick,
as I pass it right over here.
Here's the other end of the meter
stick at time t prime equals 0.
And I'm going to draw a picture of that.
Not at time t equals 0,
but in my moving reference frame,
I say that this is the two ends of
the meter stick at time t prime equals 0.
What do I want to know?
I want to know what
x prime is at this point.
x prime is at that point,
at the point t prime equals 0.
Well,
this is not hard to figure out.
First of all,
let's see,
t prime,
let's go back and set the
speed of light equal to 1.
I don't want to carry around the speed of light.
Here's the Lorentz transformations.
And let's look at this point right over here,
and see if we can
figure out what x prime is.
Let's figure out what its coordinates are.
It's x equals 1,
and it's t prime equals 0.
x equals 1,
t prime equals 0.
So,
t prime equals 0 means that t equals xv.
This surface is t equals xv,
all along here.
So that's the first thing I know.
I know that t is equal to xv,
and I also know that x is equal to 1.
So let's see if we can
find out what x prime is.
x prime is equal to x,
which is 1,
minus vt,
but t is equal to xv.
Everybody got the logic?
The logic is a little bit slippery here.
Let me go back through it.
We're trying to figure out what the moment is.
So,
we're moving observer ascribes to this point
at the other end of the meter stick,
at an instant of its time.
So,
we try to figure out what the coordinate x
prime is at the end of the meter stick.
What do we know?
We know that t prime
is equal to 0 over here,
and we know that x equals 1.
So,
we use the Lorentz transformations.
Shouldn't x prime equal 1?
No.
This is the meter stick at rest.
The meter stick is at rest.
Your frame.
This is being measured from the moving frame.
Yes,
we're trying to measure it from the moving frame,
which means we're trying to find
out what x prime is over here.
So,
we have two pieces of information.
One is that t prime is equal to 0,
the other is x equals 1.
First step,
use t prime equals 0.
t prime equals 0 tells us
that t is equal to vx.
So,
t is equal to vx.
We're trying to find x prime.
So,
its x prime is equal to x,
which is 1,
minus v times v times x,
v squared x,
divided by square root of 1 minus v squared.
Okay?
Okay.
So,
x,
that's just equal to 1.
In fact,
I don't even really need
to say it's equal to 1.
I could just say it's x.
But let's just say it's x equals 1.
And so,
what do we find?
We find that x prime is equal to 1 minus
v squared over square root of 1 minus v squared,
which is just equal to square
root of 1 minus v squared.
So,
the moving observer says that at an instant of time,
meaning to say along this surface of synchronous times here,
the two ends of the meter
stick are separated in his frame,
or in the moving frame,
by a coordinate distance or number
of meters in the moving frame,
which is given by square
root of 1 minus v squared.
In other words,
the meter stick looks in the moving
frame of reference to be a little short.
To look a little short.
Compared to what it was at rest.
Notice,
though,
that they're really talking about two different things.
The meter stick at rest,
we're talking about the distance
between this point and this point
as measured by stationary meter sticks.
In the moving frame,
we're talking about the distance
between this point and this point
measured by moving measuring rods.
They're not really the same
point of space and time here,
so there's no real contradiction that
one looks shorter than the other.
You can do the other calculation.
The other calculation,
I'll leave it to you.
Here's the way the other calculation,
the sort of opposite calculation.
Think of the moving meter stick now.
Here's the moving meter stick.
If it's one unit long,
what do we know about this line here?
Is it x equals one?
No.
It's a meter stick one unit
of length in the moving reference frame.
That means it's x prime equals one.
In the moving reference frame,
it is one meter ahead
of the other end of the meter stick,
of the tail end of the meter stick.
And so it's x prime equals one,
not x equals one.
And now the observer at rest sees
the moving meter stick being this long.
So he has to calculate what this point is,
what's x at that point.
You can do it,
and you'll find out that it's also shortened
by square root of one minus v squared.
The moving meter sticks look
short to the stationary reference frame.
The stationary meter sticks look
short to the moving reference frame.
Okay?
There's no contradiction.
They're just talking about different things.
The stationary observer is talking about lengths
measured at an instant of his time.
The moving reference frame is talking about
lengths at an instant of the other time.
So they're talking about different kinds of things.
Different notions of what they mean by length.
So you say the meter stick looks shorter.
Well,
forget look.
Let's be very precise about it.
I hold my meter stick,
and I move with it.
And at some instant of time,
remember,
you people have synchronized your clocks.
So at exactly 12 noon,
somebody is going to see the tail
end of my meter stick past them,
and somebody else is going to see the
front end of the meter stick move past them.
So they've got their watches synchronized,
and they've instructed each other at exactly 12 noon,
see who along here is contiguous or adjacent
to the two ends of the meter stick.
And then after you've done that,
compare notes and say how far apart were you.
That's exactly what you mean.
Forget saying that it looks shorter.
You mean something very specific with synchronized watches
and synchronized clocks.
Just ask exactly where the
ends of the meter stick were
in your reference frame at an instant of your time.
I can do exactly the same thing.
I have all my buddies lined up.
They also have clocks.
We've also done the synchronization.
My synchronization is not the same as your synchronization,
but we've done our synchronization.
You hold—who was holding the meter stick before?
No,
I was holding the meter stick a second ago.
Now one of you people is holding the meter stick,
and I march past,
and I instruct all my people at exactly our time,
12 noon,
look at the stationary meter stick and
see how far apart the ends are.
In both cases,
they will look a little bit short
from the frame of reference in which
the meter stick seems to be moving.
Because if it didn't look the same from each perspective,
it would imply an absolute reference.
It would indeed.
But since we—
we've established and made sure that
the relationships between x's and t's
and x'
and t'
are essentially the same relations,
except with v goes to minus v,
we know that that can't happen.
The mathematics of each half of it will
look exactly the same as the previous one.
So you can go through it.
Check this out.
The last thing to talk about before
we move on to the motion of particles—
Quick question.
Yeah.
This is the meter stick.
It's a light second stick,
because our units aren't meters.
What's that?
Say it again?
It's not a meter stick because our units aren't meters.
It's a light second stick.
You mean this is not a meter?
Yeah,
because we're assuming c equals 1.
Oh,
indeed.
Well,
of course—
well,
it depends on our choice of time.
You could use for time the time interval
that it takes light to go one meter.
Ah,
okay.
But then we—
Right.
Yes,
you're right.
You're right,
but I'm also right.
Good.
Okay.
Yeah,
you're right.
What about time dilation?
Time dilation,
we can pretty much work the same way.
Supposing we have a moving clock.
Yeah.
So,
I'm going to assume—
I'm going to assume that my clock is moving excitedly,
but instead,
I'm going to assume
that my clock is moving with uniform velocity.
In particular,
we have a clock that's moving with the moving observer.
My clock.
I'm moving,
and my clock is right sitting on top of me.
It's not one of my friend's clocks,
it's my clock,
and it is moving along a trajectory
like that.
Okay?
Well,
why don't we look at that!
Here's the question I want to ask.
At the instant when my clock reads to me,
to me personally,
when it reads t equals 1,
let's say,
maybe we could be a little more general.
No,
let's say t equals 1.
When it reads to me,
t equals 1,
the question is at that point,
what is the time in your reference frame?
So when I say t equals 1,
do I mean t equals
1 or do I mean t prime equals 1?
My coordinates are t prime.
So I have my clock.
It's my standard wristwatch.
It's been made in the Rolex company.
It's
a good watch.
It works well.
The guy sold it to me for 25 bucks.
And uh...
That's better than New York.
I got it in New York,
right?
I got it in New York from a guy.
Right?
But you know,
it works well.
So it's t prime equals 1.
One second,
though,
one unit.
t prime equals 1.
And I want to know what
the corresponding value of t is
all along the horizontal surface.
The horizontal surface is the
surface that you call synchronous,
that you call an instant of time.
All right,
now what else do we know?
We need two things in order to pin down this.
We also
know that x prime is equal to 0,
huh?
x prime is equal to 0 all along here,
and t prime
is equal to 1.
Let's see if we can find out what t is.
All right,
so we've got all the
Lorentz transformations.
x is equal to x minus vt
over square root of 1 minus v squared.
I don't think we got that.
All right,
so we're going to do that.
so we're going
to need that one.
And the other one is,
oh,
I'm sorry,
this is not the one we want.
We
want the other one,
which goes x is equal to x
prime plus vt prime over square root
of 1 minus v squared.
And t is equal to t prime plus
v x prime over square root of 1
minus v squared.
All right,
so we've got all the Lorentz transformations.
let's see if we can
get some of these things right.
Now,
one of the Lorentz transformations
be the Lorentz transformation of x minus v squared.
So it's going to be something like
this.
It's going to be the
Lorentz transformation of x and t.
So this is the Lorentz transformation
going the other way,
telling me that the x and t
coordinates in terms of x prime and
t prime.
OK,
so t prime is equal to 1.
x prime is equal to 0.
We've got the Lorentz transformation.
and what I want to find
out is T that's right over here.
Let's see what it is.
T prime is equal to 1.
X prime is equal to 0 divided
by square root of 1 minus v squared.
Right.
So the time over here,
is it bigger or smaller than 1?
Bigger.
The time interval over here is longer than
the time interval measured by the moving observer.
By a factor of square
root of 1 minus v squared.
This is a square root of 1 minus v squared.
This is the origin of the twin paradox.
The twin paradox involves reversing the
motion of the twin over here.
Two twins,
one at rest,
one moving.
Reverse them,
bring them back together again.
And ask how much time has
evolved in the two reference frames.
Well one of these reference
frames is not an inertial frame.
The one which bends and goes around.
But we've already calculated how much
time there was between here and here.
That's 1 over square root of 1 minus v squared.
In other words we found that there's a
little bit less time along here than along here.
Same thing is true for
the second leg of the journey.
The implication is that the time measured in the moving frame is
a little bit less than the time measured in the moving frame.
is a little bit less than
the time measured in the moving frame.
The time measured by this factor in the frame
of reference of the twin that stays at home.
And so the twin that stays at home is
a little bit older than the one who moves.
We're using here a basic idea that every clock
participates in this thing in exactly the same way.
And in particular the clock that has
to do with biological aging also slows down.
But this is just a
statement that the clock is moving.
Whatever we've said here applies to every kind of clock.
Not just Rolexes.
I had a hard time accepting...
I had a hard time accepting that I had
a hot noose shorter than one of the sides.
Say it again.
I can't hear you.
I had a hard time accepting that I had
a hot noose being shorter than one of the sides.
Yes,
isn't that interesting?
We're going to come to that.
Yes,
that's right.
That's exactly right.
No,
it's not right,
but I mean it's exactly something
that you might be puzzled by.
So now let's talk about exactly that.
Let's talk about exactly the issue of
the hypotenuse and whether it's shorter or longer
than the sides of the...
You were saying that the twin
that goes away and comes back,
less time has passed for him,
but from his point of view,
we flew away...
No,
no,
no.
Remember,
these two frames are not
symmetrical with respect to each other.
One of them underwent an acceleration.
They're really not symmetrical.
The twin who got sent
out and sent back knew that he
was the one who was going to fly.
The twin who went on the
curved trajectory because he experienced an acceleration.
That
twin was not in an inertial frame.
So is that the cause then?
Is it because of the acceleration?
You can think of it that way.
You can just calculate it or
you can think of it as the
cause of the acceleration,
if you like.
That's a legitimate way to think about it.
But you
know,
the mathematics is pretty similar.
Okay.
Pretty similar to the statement that if
you take two points in the plane,
ordinarily just two points in the plane,
and you connect them by a straight line or you
connect them by a curve,
don't be surprised that the
length along the straight line is
not the same as the length along the curve.
In fact,
the length along the curve is,
of
course,
longer than the length along the line.
And in the relativity case,
we actually found
that the time along the curve was a
little bit less than the time along here.
So there's
something going on that's different than ordinary lengths,
but it's a similar phenomenon
that the length along the curve is not
the same as the length along the straight line.
The straight line is the
shortest distance between two points.
Well,
in fact,
in relativity,
we've erased the diagram.
Did I erase it?
Yeah,
here it is.
As was mentioned,
the time along the hypotenuse is less than the time
along the vertical axis here.
So there's something funny going on,
and I want to talk about that
funny thing that's going on.
Let's just think about Euclidean geometry for a minute.
Think about the plane,
and let's think about different
coordinate systems on the plane.
Coordinate systems just related to each other by rotation.
Now,
there's an origin of coordinates.
Let's call this x and y.
This is now x prime and y prime.
This is not a moving reference
frame now.
This is just the rotation of coordinates,
and I'm using it to make a point.
But,
you
know,
let's take a point somewhere in the space over here.
It's the point .
The two reference,
well,
let me call them reference frames.
I really mean coordinate
systems.
The two coordinate systems do not ascribe the
same values of x and y to this
point.
Obviously,
the x and y of this point here are
not the same as the x prime and the
y prime.
They're related to each other.
If you know x and y,
and you know the angle
between coordinates,
you can figure out x prime and y prime.
But they're not the same.
But there is something that is the same,
no matter how you calculate it,
whether you calculate
it in the prime coordinates or the unprime coordinates.
And you know what it is.
It's
what?
The distance.
The distance from the origin.
Everybody will agree.
on the distance from the origin.
In fact,
I'll also agree about the square of the
distance from the origin.
So what is the square
of the distance from the origin
from the point of view of the unprimed coordinates?
Well,
it's just
Pythagoras's theorem.
It's just x squared plus y squared.
That's the square of the
distance.
What about from the point
of view of the primed frame?
In other words,
the quantity x squared plus y squared
for a point here is an invariant.
Invariant means that it doesn't depend on
which coordinate system you work it out in.
It's invariant under the invariant.
So it's invariant under changes of coordinates,
which in this case are just rotations of the coordinates.
So we say then that x squared
plus y squared is an invariant quantity,
and it's the same no matter
what frame you measure it in.
is there an analogous quantity associated with
the Lorentz transformations here which is invariant?
In particular,
here's something we might guess.
Let's try it out.
Let's try it out and
see if we can get it.
Let's try it out and see if
there's something similar going on in tx space.
Here's t,
here's x.
This point is characterized by a t and an x,
but it's also characterized by a
t prime and an x prime.
It has a t and an x
or a t prime and an x prime.
It has coordinates in the
unmoving frame and the moving frame.
What is the relationship between them?
It's the Lorentz transformations.
But we might guess,
we might ask,
is there something similar that's invariant?
Let's make a guess that it's t prime squared
plus x prime squared equals t squared plus x squared.
Let's try that out and see if it's true.
We know in terms of x and t,
we know x prime and t prime,
so we can work it out.
Let's see if it's true.
Okay,
so t prime,
let's start with t prime squared.
We just take this equation over here.
t prime squared has,
it has t squared,
it has plus v squared x squared,
and it has minus 2 v
tx divided by 1 minus v squared.
Did I do that right?
That's t prime squared.
What about x prime squared?
That has x squared plus v
squared t squared minus 2 v tx,
right?
Question.
Does this equal t squared plus x squared?
Hell no.
It does not.
And in particular,
one thing you can see immediately is that the
x term here adds to the x term here.
They do not cancel.
There's no x here.
They can't be the same in general.
And they're not the same.
They're simply not the same.
But now if you look carefully at it,
you might notice that if we subtract them,
the v x terms do cancel.
Okay,
let's see what else happens.
So let's try subtracting them.
This is t prime squared minus x prime squared.
And let's not prejudice by what's
on the right hand side here.
Let's find out what's on the right hand side.
t prime squared minus x prime squared is this difference.
Alright.
It contains the cross term here disappears.
They cancel now because of this minus sign.
And how about x squared?
Let's see what x squared has.
x squared has v squared minus 1,
right?
v squared minus 1.
And then there's plus t squared.
And t squared has 1 minus v squared.
1 minus v squared.
All divided by 1 minus v squared.
The 1 minus v squareds cancel and
you just get t squared minus x squared.
This is minus minus plus.
Okay,
so we've discovered something.
We've discovered that there's an
invariant quantity under any Lorentz transformation.
The combination t prime squared minus x prime squared.
Is the same as t squared minus x squared.
It's almost like Pythagorean theorem.
That there's a kind of notion
of distance from the origin here.
Which is composed out of the base of the triangle.
Namely x.
And the height of the triangle.
That stays the same if you do a Lorentz transformation.
In other words,
if you use other coordinates.
If you use other coordinates,
calculate x prime and t prime.
You find out that the combination t
squared minus x squared is the invariant.
You can also take it to
be x squared minus t squared incidentally.
x squared minus t squared
and t squared minus x squared.
Take your choice.
Okay.
This is an important thing to know.
It's very important to know what the invariant is.
What the coordinates are.
The components of a vector or the
components of a displacement are not invariant.
They depend on which coordinate system you're using.
The things which are invariant.
Things which all observers agree upon.
Are in this case the.
I'll give it a name in a moment.
Let's call it the space time distance.
The space time distance which is
defined with this funny minus sign.
Is invariant.
All observers.
So it must be an important quantity.
Okay.
Let's see if we can
figure out what it really means.
In particular,
let's suppose that between here and here.
That we happen to be talking about the motion.
In other words,
let's assume.
Let's take a special case.
Yeah.
Let's take the two points to be along the motion.
Okay.
All right.
Then for this moving observer.
What is T prime squared minus X prime squared?
Well,
X prime at this point is just plain zero.
This is the point X prime equals zero along here.
So it is just T prime squared.
In fact,
we can write immediately.
That T prime squared must
equal T squared minus X squared.
Why do I say that?
This point over here is the
point T prime and X prime.
But it's X prime equals zero.
So it's distance from the origin.
T prime squared minus X prime squared.
It's just plain T prime squared.
On the other hand.
Because this quantity is invariant.
It must also be T squared minus X squared.
Okay.
Let's take a look at this.
What is this quantity T prime?
It's the reading of a moving clock.
A clock moving along here.
Which starts at T prime equals zero over here.
Will read T prime over here.
That's what it is.
It's the reading of a clock.
That has moved on a straight line.
Between one point and another point.
It's how many units of time have occurred
in the frame that connects these two points.
It's called proper time.
It's called the proper time.
And everybody will agree on what
the proper time is along that trajectory.
They will calculate it the same way.
They will take the two points.
And calculate the square of the difference.
Of the time interval between the two points.
And the space interval between the two points.
In any frame whatever.
You pick your frame.
And you calculate T squared
minus X squared for this point.
And that tells you how much time evolved.
Between the clock reading over here.
And the clock reading over here.
It's called the proper time of that clock.
But you can also just think
of it as a measure of distance.
Along a line.
Connecting two points.
It's not a measure of ordinary distance.
It's a measure of space time distance.
Called the proper time.
It's this minus sign here.
Which gives the triangles the peculiar property.
That the hypotenuse is shorter than
the height of the triangle itself.
Why is that?
The minus sign makes it smaller.
Alright.
But in many other ways.
This functions as the notion
of a distance in space time.
Between two points.
Are there any questions about that?
Yeah.
So up there where we
actually drove the Lorentz transformations.
We used.
Drove?
Derived.
The.
But we didn't trust it.
We didn't trust it.
We used angles and slopes.
Yeah.
And matched coordinates.
But.
What this is saying is,
you can't.
You can't do geometry.
At least not.
No.
Right.
But we never used any notion of lengths in this.
We just used coordinates.
We.
We never really.
Yeah.
That's right.
Right,
you can't use ordinary notions
of Euclidean geometry on spacetime.
But still,
we were very careful and simply
defined coordinates in terms of how clocks
would read,
how...
and we derove the invariant.
We derove the invariant and that's it,
that's the invariant.
Right.
Right,
so relativistic spacetime is kind
of like ordinary Euclidean spacetime,
but with
a funny difference that you take the difference
between t squares and x squares and that's
the thing which everybody will agree on.
And you can think of
it as a kind of length.
Now there is one funny property of it.
What about the points,
let's take the point,
let's go back to this here,
let's take one
point at the end of the line,
and then we'll go back to the
point at the end of the line.
This is the origin.
And let's take some other point.
We can just use x and t,
let's just use x and t now.
x and t.
Another point at x and t.
Is it possible that the distance between these two points,
and these are different points,
this one's at the origin,
this one's not at the origin,
is it possible that this notion
of distance just gives zero distance between them?
Even though they're not the same point.
In ordinary Euclidean geometry,
if the distance between two points is zero,
the points are
at the same place.
Right?
Good.
What about in this crazy kind
of geometry with the minus sign?
Supposing the distance from this
point to the origin is zero,
what does that mean?
That means that x squared minus
t squared is equal to zero.
Alright,
x squared minus t squared can be
equal to zero without x and t.
Right?
With t being zero.
Incidentally,
x squared plus y squared equals zero
implies that both x and y are zero.
Right?
X squared is positive,
y squared is positive or zero.
Y squared is positive or zero.
If the sum of these is zero,
it means either one of them,
both of them have to be zero.
But if x squared minus
t squared is equal to zero,
it doesn't say any such thing.
What does it say?
It says either x is equal to
t or x is equal to minus t.
One or the other.
x is equal to minus t.
What does x equals t mean?
It means a light ray.
It means that a light ray could
go from this point to that point.
They're connected by a possible light trajectory.
Same for the other one.
x equals minus t would be over here.
Again,
light ray can go from one to the other.
So,
one of the facts here is that,
you know,
if you're going to be able to do this,
you're going to have to be able to do this.
So,
one of the facts here is that
if the distance between two points is zero,
it doesn't mean the two points are the same point.
It means that a light ray can connect them.
Still,
nevertheless,
it does mean that the proper time
between the two of them is zero.
In other words,
if a light beam could carry a clock with it,
there would be zero ticks of
the clock between here and here.
Clocks that move with the
speed of light simply don't tick.
They just stick.
They don't tick.
Right.
Question?
Yeah.
Could proper time just as well be called proper length?
Well,
okay.
Yeah,
that's a good question.
That depends on whether the two points...
All right,
here are two points which could not
be the path of a moving object,
of a clock.
Why?
Because the velocity,
in order to go from here to here,
would have to be greater than the speed of light.
Okay?
If we assume nothing can go
faster than the speed of light,
then this can't connect these two points.
That's the condition,
basically,
that x is bigger than t.
Here,
x is less than t.
If x is less than t,
a light ray can get from one point to another.
If x is bigger than t,
it can't.
If we're talking about two
points in this type of configuration,
they're called,
and there's a word for it,
they're called a relation between those two points.
It's called spacelike.
Spacelike means that the space component
is bigger than the time component,
or better yet,
that x squared minus t squared is greater than zero.
If the point is up here,
so that a trajectory can connect those two things,
then t squared minus x squared is greater than zero.
This is called spacelike,
this distance,
and this one is called timelike.
If the two points are spacelike connected,
then you would call this
quantity x squared minus t squared,
you would call the proper distance between them.
If they're timelike separated,
then you would call t squared
minus x squared the proper time.
So yeah,
you can think of it
also as defining a proper distance,
but only if the t component is larger than zero.
So that's the x component.
Alright,
we're close to the end,
there's only one for today.
I was going to talk about some relativity paradoxes,
but I don't think we have time today.
What was the other thing I wanted to mention?
I've forgotten.
I forgot.
Are there any questions?
Yeah.
If the velocity of light is not one,
do we have to put c's in the equation?
Oh yes,
absolutely.
So where would you put the c in this equation?
We could put it here,
c squared t squared.
Or we could put it in the denominator here.
A distance divided by a velocity is a time.
So this would be,
and this would normally be called proper time.
As units of time.
If we go up to x squared minus t squared,
and we put the c squared here,
we would call this proper distance.
But that's a pure convention.
It doesn't matter where you put the c squared,
whether you put it here or here.
Just make things consistent.
The definition of proper time is usually taken to
be t squared minus x squared over c squared.
The square root?
Where's square root?
The units for that would be time squared.
But for proper time,
would that be?
Oh,
sorry.
Proper time squared.
Yeah.
Thank you.
Right.
That would be proper time squared.
Yeah.
It's square.
It's like the Pythagorean theorem.
The notion of distance is to
take the square root of this thing.
Most of the times you don't take the square root.
But yes.
The proper time is the square
root of t squared minus x squared.
Thank you.
That's important.
Yeah.
Is it useful to think
of Lorentz transformation as a rotation?
Well,
yeah.
The trouble is it's a rotation by an imaginary angle.
Imaginary in the sense of imaginary.
Yeah.
It is literally a rotation by an imaginary angle.
So yes,
it is sometimes useful to think that way.
Right.
At the beginning you mentioned that Einstein added
the fact that c was a law of physics.
Was that to match the experimental data at the time?
Who knows?
Be careful.
Well,
you know,
I know the history a little bit.
Of course I don't know the history.
I know what the history is told by a participant.
I didn't know the participant,
of course.
All right.
And I think there's every reason to believe him.
I think Einstein was motivated by Maxwell's equations.
Yeah.
He took Maxwell's equations to be a law of physics.
Now,
he was only 16 years old at
the time when he started thinking about it,
according to himself.
He was 16 years old.
And what he knew about Maxwell's equations was
that they gave rise to these wave-like solutions
and that the solutions moved in a certain way.
And he was puzzled because he tried to figure out
what would happen if you moved along with a light ray.
Then you would see a static electric mass.
And he would see a magnetic field
that had a wave-like structure that didn't move.
And he knew somehow that that
was not a solution of Maxwell's equations.
So according to him,
that was the motivation that he was puzzled by
the idea of moving along with the speed of light,
the light ray.
But I think beyond that,
he knew Maxwell's equations,
or at least at some point he learned Maxwell's equations.
And it took Maxwell's equations to be laws of physics.
And Maxwell's equations say light
moves with the speed of light.
So I'm inclined to believe that that was the correct history
that he didn't know at the time of the Michelson-Morley experiment.
But who knows?
So he didn't know about it?
So don't you just say he didn't know about it?
According to his own historical testimony about it,
he did not know about it.
I think there's every reason to believe you.
He was surely smart enough.
I mean,
he was smart enough.
He was smart enough to know that.
So,
and the logic makes sense that Maxwell's equations,
you know,
in modern terms,
we would say it differently.
We would say here were these Maxwell equations,
and there's some symmetry of the Maxwell equations,
some set of coordinate transformations for which,
if you do them,
Maxwell's equations have the same
form in every reference frame.
If you take Maxwell's equations,
which contain x's and t's,
okay,
and you plug in,
you know,
the old Newton rule or the Galileo rule,
x prime is equal to x minus vt,
t prime is equal to t,
you'll find out that in
the new prime frame of reference,
Maxwell's equations change their form.
They don't have the same form that they had originally.
If you plug in the Lorentz transform,
you'll find that the Lorentz transform is the same.
You'll find out that the Maxwell equations in the new
coordinates are identical to what they were in the old coordinates.
So I think in modern language,
I think what Einstein did was to recognize that
the symmetry structure of Maxwell's equations was not these transformations,
but these transformations.
But it was all encapsulated in one principle.
He didn't have to really know Maxwell's equations.
All he had to know was
that Maxwell's equations were the same.
The Maxwell equations were a law of physics,
and the law of physics said
that light moves with a certain velocity.
And from there,
he could just work with the motion of light rays.
So,
yeah.
They're called Lorentz transformations.
Lorentz Fitzgerald transformations.
So he presumably had thought of
them earlier for some other purpose.
No,
he thought about them for the same purpose.
He did know about the Michelson-Morley experiment.
But he envisioned them differently.
Same equations,
but he envisioned them differently.
He envisioned them as effects on moving
objects caused by their motion through the ether.
So he envisioned that an
object moving through the so-called ether,
because of various kinds of ether pressures,
would be squeezed and therefore shortened.
Now,
was he wrong?
I suppose you can say in some
way or another that he wasn't wrong.
But he certainly didn't have the vision
that Einstein had of a symmetry structure.
Of what is the symmetry required of space and time
in order that it agree with the principle of relativity,
of the motion of the speed of light.
Nobody,
I think,
would say that...
that...
including Lorentz,
would have said that Lorentz did what Einstein did.
He...
And furthermore,
Lorentz didn't think it was exact.
He thought it was a first approximation.
That a thing moving through a
fluid of some kind would get shortened,
and that the first approximation
would be the Lorentz contraction,
and in some higher orders you
would see some other things happening.
So he fully expected...
that the Michelson-Morley experiment was not exact.
He thought that there would be higher
corrections to higher powers of velocity over C,
where you would see discrepancies.
Now Einstein said,
look,
this is really a law of physics.
This is a principle.
So he made a principle out of it.
And...
Not likely to go away.
Even in Italy.
Good.
All right,
next time we'll talk about the motion of particles
and how relativity...
helps you understand how particles
move and things of that nature.
For more,
please visit us at stanford.edu.