Stanford University.
All right,
we were,
last time we worked out basic Lorentz transformations
relating two frames of reference.
Whether or not I said it,
let me say it now,
we were mainly dealing with problems
in which all of the motion,
and in particular
the relative motion of different observers,
is along one particular axis.
We didn't try to think fully three-dimensionally,
and the picture you could have in your head
is that we have a long railroad track,
one-dimensional.
Some set of observers is sitting still at the station.
We could call those the stationary observers.
And other observers are in the train.
And they're moving around.
They're moving relative to each
other along the one-dimensional axis.
We didn't worry very much about the other axes.
I said one or two things about it.
And we talked about how you relate the
coordinates of one observer relative to the other.
And in particular,
we wrote down Lorentz transformations based
on the basic hypothesis of Einstein
that all reference frames see the
speed of light exactly the same.
In fact,
we said with the units that we used,
all observers see the speed of light being one.
That's of course a choice of units.
We work in years and light years,
or seconds and light seconds,
whatever choice of units.
If we choose them correctly,
we can make the speed of light one.
And that simplifies equations.
Of course,
if we really want to plug
in to the speed of light,
to the real observational physics,
we might want to use the fact
that the speed of light in common units,
in the common units that
an experimental physicist would ordinarily use,
is not one.
It's 3 times 10 to the 8th in some units.
And so we would put back the speed of light.
And there's always a unique way to do that.
The unique way to do it is to make sure,
simply stated,
that you modify the equations
by appropriate factors of the speed of light,
c,
so that the equations are dimensionally consistent.
I will go back and forth.
Mostly I will use the speed
of light set equal to 1,
but every now and then,
just to illustrate a point,
I will stick the speeds of light in,
and you can go through
the equations and do that yourselves.
Okay,
so,
two observers.
One moving down the axis with
a velocity v relative to the stationary,
moving down the tracks with a
velocity v relative to the stationary observer.
The stationary observer sees the moving observer
moving v units of space per unit time,
v being velocity.
And of course,
by symmetry,
just by the symmetry of the problem,
if we believe that all coordinate frames are equally valid,
the same relationships,
the same kind of Lorentz transformations,
will relate the stationary observer's coordinates
to the moving coordinates.
The two-way street,
the stationary observer ascribes stationary coordinates,
the moving observer ascribes moving coordinates,
his coordinates,
and they can each be related to each other reciprocally.
And the reciprocal relation is truly reciprocal,
exactly the same relations,
except that whereas if I were moving to the right,
your right,
if I were moving to your right,
you would say my velocity is positive,
you would be moving to the left,
as far as I was concerned,
I would say your velocity was negative,
and so in relating the two frames of reference,
the only thing we have to remember
is there's a sign change of
velocity when you go back and forth.
Okay,
so,
for example,
if x prime is the
coordinates as seen in the train,
here's the train over here,
let's draw a train,
that's the train,
okay,
there's an observer in the train,
and there's an observer in the tracks,
or an observer in the station,
here's the observer in the station,
here's the observer in the train,
and the observer in the
train is moving with velocity v,
v.
The observer in the train has meter sticks,
and the meter sticks can be
laid out on the floor here,
to form a grid,
the observer also has a timepiece,
a clock,
likewise,
the observer at rest,
well,
at rest with respect to whom?
Well,
at rest with respect to the station,
the observer at rest with respect to the station
also has his meter sticks laid out,
and also has his timepiece.
And they make various comparisons,
you know how all of this works,
an event which takes place,
an event means an event
happening at a point of space,
and a point of time,
in other words,
at some point of space-time,
I like to think of it
as a flash bulb exploding someplace,
going off someplace,
it doesn't matter whether it's in the train,
or outside the train,
let's say in the train for convenience,
a flash bulb goes off over here,
at a time that the stationary observer records,
and it seconds to be t,
time t,
at position x,
now position x means
coordinate x in the stationary reference frame,
x right over here,
at a time t,
according to the timepiece of the stationary observer,
so the stationary observer ascribes to it
coordinates x and t,
and the moving observer ascribes to the same event,
coordinates x prime and t prime.
And we worked out the last time,
the relationships that are necessary between
x,
t,
and x prime and t prime,
such that everybody will always agree
that the speed of light is one,
let me write them down quickly,
x prime,
these are the Lorentz transformations,
x prime is equal to x minus vt,
now Newton would recognize that,
but what he wouldn't have recognized
was the square root of one minus v squared downstairs,
and if you want to
put back the speed of light,
it goes right over here,
I'm going to put it
in and then take it out,
v squared over c squared,
and of course if the velocity is small
by comparison with the speed of light,
this is a terribly tiny correction.
Let's just call it one minus v squared,
and t prime,
is equal to t minus vx,
divided by that same square
root of one minus v squared.
If we wanted to add the other two directions,
in particular the directions out of the board and vertical,
in other words the directions perpendicular to the tracks,
we could add them in very simply,
perpendicular directions don't change
under a change of velocity along a given axis,
if the change of the velocities of the two frames,
relative velocities are along the x axis,
then the y and z coordinates are unchanged.
y prime,
sorry,
y prime equals y and z prime equals z.
Let's,
I won't write it,
if we need it,
we'll use it.
We can invert these relations,
this is simply a matter,
there's nothing sophisticated going on here,
this is simply a matter
of solving for x and t,
in terms of x prime and t prime,
let me remind you what the result would be,
it would be x equals x prime plus vt prime,
divided by that same square root,
and t equals t prime plus vx prime,
divided by square root of one minus v squared.
The only difference,
the only asymmetry,
is where you saw a velocity over here,
you change the sign of the velocity,
just to account for the fact that the relative velocities
are in opposite directions.
You can also read off,
if somebody gave you this form
for the relationship between the coordinates,
you could easily read off
what the relative velocity
between the two observers is.
You look at the x equation here,
and you say,
the moving observer's coordinate
is x prime equals zero,
right at the position of the origin of
coordinates inside the train,
x prime is equal to zero,
x prime equals zero corresponds to x equals vt.
You just look at this and you say,
the moving observer,
the prime observer,
let's not call them moving,
the prime observer is at rest,
or the position,
x prime is at rest,
or is equal to zero,
excuse me,
x prime is equal to zero,
the origin of the prime coordinates
corresponds to x equals vt.
You don't have to know about this denominator there,
you just look at x equals vt,
that specifies x prime equals zero,
and that tells you,
x equals vt tells you that the relative velocity
between the two observers is zero,
and the velocity between the two of them is v.
Alright,
now we want to do another exercise.
The other exercise is to assume
there's a third observer.
The third observer is moving relative
to the railroad car,
relative to the train,
he's got a little kiddie car inside the train,
and he's moving relative to the
passenger,
let's call him the passenger,
he's moving relative to the passenger
with velocity u.
The passenger sees the little kiddie car,
the little kid in the kiddie car,
pedaling down the aisle of the train
with velocity u relative to himself.
Question,
what does the stationary observer
ascribe to the car?
What velocity does the stationary observer see?
And the way to solve this is just to use,
I know of no way to guess the answer.
The answer is some velocity.
We can give it a name.
We can call that velocity w.
I don't,
you could use v1,
v2,
and v3,
but I hate subscripts,
and so I prefer to say
the velocity of the train is v
relative to the stationary observer,
the velocity of the car relative to the train,
is u,
and the velocity of the
car relative to the stationary observer
I will call w.
Alright,
so the stationary observer sees the car move
with velocity w.
And the question is,
what is w
in terms of u and v?
The answer is just to use a bit of logic.
The bit of logic is
that the relationship,
first of all we should give the,
there are also coordinates,
excuse me,
there are also coordinates in the car,
moving with the car.
This could be a set of meter sticks
laid out on the floor of the car,
and also a time piece
that the driver of the car has.
So there's three sets of coordinates.
In this case,
x and t are the coordinates
that the stationary observer uses.
x prime and t prime are the passenger's coordinates.
And a third set of coordinates,
which let's give them the name
x double prime and t double prime.
x double prime and t double prime
are the coordinates
that the kid in the kiddie car uses
to describe things relative to the position,
relative to his own frame of reference.
Alright,
so now it just takes a little bit of logic
to say we know what the relationship is
between the double prime and t double prime.
So we can write down the relationship
and the single prime coordinates.
Those are related by velocity u.
u is the velocity of the double prime
relative to the prime coordinates.
So we can write down those relationships
straightforwardly.
Let's,
we don't need this over here.
Let's write them down here.
x double prime is equal,
same exact kind of relationship.
Same exact kind of thing,
except we'll put in primes here.
And instead of v,
we will use the relative velocity u.
Alright,
so this is going to be
x prime minus u,
t prime divided by square root
of one minus u squared.
Alright,
so this is the Lorentz transformation
between the double prime frame,
and the single prime frame.
t prime minus u,
x prime over root of one minus u squared.
Alright,
so now how do we find the connection
between the double primed coordinates
in the car,
and the unprimed coordinates at rest
in the railroad station?
And that's simple.
All we do is,
let's take this equation over here.
Let's focus on this one.
The time equation also works out very nicely.
But let's focus on the space equation here.
We know what x prime is
in terms of x and t,
and we know what t prime
is in terms of x and t.
So all we have to do is to plug in.
And let's do so.
Oh,
good.
Nice,
good pin.
Alright,
so x prime is
x minus vt
divided by square root of one minus v squared.
Now that's just this x prime here.
So far that's just x prime.
Minus u
t prime,
and let's put in t prime.
t prime is t minus vx,
and the whole thing again divided by
another square root of one minus v squared.
Now so far,
I have only written this and this.
I have to put in the denominator.
To put in the denominator,
I just put in another
factor of one minus u squared,
one minus u squared.
Square root of one minus u squared.
So that is the relationship
between x double prime and x.
We can write this a little more simply.
Let's focus on what the,
let's,
there's some big denominator.
The denominator involves the product
of the two square roots.
Alright,
let's put it in.
Square root,
square root.
I'm not going to write
out what's inside the square root.
It's just the product of these two square roots.
But I'm interested in the numerator really.
The numerator has an x,
and it has a plus uvx.
x,
here,
and plus uvx.
Why is it plus uvx?
Because there's a minus sign
here and a minus sign here.
x times one plus uv.
One plus uvx.
And what about t?
t will multiply
minus
v
plus u
times t.
Minus v and minus u times t.
And this is the answer,
but it's not very transparent what it means.
But all we need to do
to figure out the relative velocity
of the double prime frame relative to the unprime frame
is just to do exactly what we did over here.
If we want to find out
what x prime equals zero means,
just set x minus vt equal to zero.
And that tells you that x is equal to vt.
It tells you how the fellow at rest here,
who is at x prime equals zero,
how he's moving relative to the unprime frame.
So we do exactly the same thing.
We say,
x double prime will be zero.
x double prime,
of course,
being zero,
means the position of the
kid inside the kitty car here.
x double prime equals zero
is the same thing as the numerator here being zero.
Denominator,
who cares about the denominator?
It's there.
But we can set the numerator equal to zero here,
and that will tell us under what circumstances
x double prime is equal to zero.
So what does it say?
It says x double prime is equal to zero
when one plus uv
x double prime is equal to zero.
So we can say that x
is equal to u plus vt.
I've set this equal to this
to make the numerator zero.
Or if I divide by one plus uv,
it tells me x is equal to u plus v
over one plus uv t.
So what is the relative velocity?
Sorry,
yes.
What is the relative velocity?
This tells us the x and t trajectory
of the kid in the kitty car here.
The trajectory of the child
or whoever it is in the kitty car
is x is equal to u
plus v over one plus uv
times t.
That corresponds to x double prime equals zero.
All right,
but another way to say it
is just that the stationary observer
sees the kitty car
moving along with velocity u
plus v over one plus uv.
So we now know what w is.
That's exactly what w is.
w,
we've worked it out.
We can now write it in the form,
well,
let's write it in the form
x double prime is equal to t,
minus wx divided by square
root of one minus w squared,
and t double prime is,
did I write that right?
No,
I didn't.
x minus wt.
And t minus wx over the same square root.
I don't have room for the square root there.
All right,
and what do we find w is?
w is just that.
It's just that.
That's how fast the kitty car is moving
as seen from the stationary frame.
So,
yes?
Why is that dimensionally incorrect?
Because we set c equal to one.
Right.
We're going to put him back.
We're going to put him back in a minute.
Yeah,
we're going to put him back in a minute.
you're a step ahead of me.
Okay,
all right,
so x is equal to,
so w,
the speed w is equal to w,
u plus v divided by one plus uv.
And now if I want to restore the units,
just to answer your question again,
if we set the speed of light equal to one,
of course,
we're working in units
in which velocities are dimensionless.
But if we want to restore the dimensions,
we simply look at this equation,
we say,
look,
w equals u plus v,
that's dimensionally fine.
It's adding one to uv,
which is peculiar,
but we restore the dimensions
by putting in c squared here.
One plus uv over c squared,
uv over c squared is dimensionless.
All right,
so this is the equation
with c being restored.
What is the Newtonian equation?
The corresponding pre-Einsteinian equation?
Well,
stationary,
stationary person sees passenger moving with velocity u,
passenger sees kitty car moving,
sorry,
stationary observer sees passenger moving with velocity v,
passenger sees kitty car moving velocity u,
the answer naively would just be u plus v.
But it's not u plus v,
it's u plus v divided by something
which as long as u and v
are significantly smaller than the speed of light,
uv over c squared will be very small.
We'll put in some numbers in a minute
just to test that out.
But as long as u and v are small
compared with the speed of light,
this will be negligible.
It's the product of two ordinary velocities,
100 meters per second or whatever
it is you want to put in,
divided by 3 times 10
to the 8th meters per second,
all squared.
This is a very,
very small number
and it's a very small correction.
On the other hand,
when u and v get
up near the speed of light,
it can get very significant.
So let's see what happens.
First let's do the case where u and v are
small velocities compared to the speed of light.
We can leave out,
well remember that u and v mean velocities measured
in units of the speed of light.
So if u and v are measured
in units of the speed of light,
and let's say for example,
supposing u is equal to 0.01,
1% of the speed of light,
and let's say v is also 0.01,
they're both 1% the speed of light,
then this turns out to be 0.02,
that's what Newton would recognize,
divided by 1 plus,
and now uv is 0.001?
Did I do that right?
And 0.0001 is a very small correction.
Now,
this is a very sizable velocity incidentally,
u being 1% of the
speed of light is damn fast.
It's not 3 times 10 to the 8th,
it's 3 times 10 to the 6th meters per second.
So this is pretty fast,
but the correction is small.
1 plus something.
Notice the answer is a little bit smaller
than what Newton would have estimated.
This number here is a little bit bigger than that,
and so in the denominator it's a little bit smaller.
Let's go to the other extreme.
Let's suppose u and v are
90% of the speed of light.
We could do 99%,
but I'm not so good at arithmetic.
u and v are 0.9.
v equals 0.9.
Newton would have said
the kiddie car is moving
faster than the speed of light
relative to the stationary observer.
In fact,
he probably would have said
1.8 times the speed of light.
He would have added these two numbers,
but Einstein would have put in the denominator here,
so let's see what we get.
We get 0.9 plus 0.9,
that's 1.8,
divided by 0.9 squared.
0.9 squared is 1.81.
Slightly bigger than 1.8.
The result is that the net
velocity is slightly less than 1.
In other words,
we have not succeeded in making the kiddie car
go faster than the speed of light,
even though blah,
blah,
you know the rest of the story.
So this is the answer to the question,
what happens if an observer is
moving faster than the speed of light?
Well,
you could ask that question,
but the answer is,
I think we are pretty well protected against
people moving faster than the speed of light
if the way they are made to move
is relative to some previous frame of reference,
moving slower than the speed of light.
In other words,
there's no way by
putting another observer inside the speed of the car here,
making him go 90% of the speed of light,
etc.,
we're never going to get
faster than the speed of light.
So it's consistent to,
it's a consistent thing to say,
all observers move slower than the speed of light,
even though they can move arbitrarily
close to the speed of light
relative to each other in any combination,
the net result will still be
slower than the speed of light.
If u and v are c,
then w ends up being 2 over c.
that means 1.
Okay.
Let's suppose u and v are 1.
c and 1 are the same thing.
Then u plus v is 2,
and 1 plus uv is 2,
so the net result is the speed of light again.
Okay.
So if you're moving very,
if each one is moving very,
very close to the speed of light,
the net result,
in other words,
if the kiddie car is moving relative to the passenger
very close to the speed of light,
and the passenger is moving relative to the station
the result will be that the kiddie car
is moving relative to the station,
and even closer to the speed of light,
but not in excess of it.
Okay.
That's the...
You see that through the,
the stationer sees it through
the eyes of the x prime.
What if the train had glass walls
and the stationer was looking at both of them?
If the train,
I assume the train did have glass walls.
I don't see how that makes any...
We're not talking,
we're not talking about
how appearances look.
We're talking about how measurements of phenomena
are,
by meter sticks and by well-designed clocks,
correlate with each other.
What somebody sees is much more complicated
for the simple reason that when an event happens,
light has to come from the event,
and it can be much more complicated
what you visually see.
We're not talking about what you visually see.
We're talking about correlating the locations
and times of events in frames of reference
which are defined by meter sticks
at rest relative to observers,
and time pieces which are
also at rest relative to them.
And it doesn't matter what
kind of walls the car has,
the transformation laws
are universal.
Okay.
Now,
the next thing we talked about last time
was the notion of proper time
or proper distance or proper interval.
Let me just remind you quickly about that,
very quickly.
If we have an event taking
place at point x and t,
we found out last time
that there's an invariant notion
of separation,
space-time difference,
or space-time distance between them,
proper time,
and the proper time or the proper...
Let's put this up higher,
over here.
Xt.
The proper interval between them
is called tau,
and it's defined by tau squared,
is equal to t squared minus x squared.
And the interesting thing about this,
the important thing about it,
is it's the same in every reference frame.
If the reference frame is moving,
then we would use prime coordinates,
but the same quantity here is t prime squared
minus x prime squared.
It's also equal to t double prime squared
minus x double prime squared.
It's an invariant.
All observers agree on the value
of this interval between here and here.
They don't agree about the coordinates themselves,
but they agree about this notion of proper time.
The proper time is also the time read
by a clock moving between these two points.
If the clock is set equal to,
let's say,
12 noon at this point,
and it moves along this trajectory,
then the time that it reads
at the end of the trajectory is the proper time.
And we worked out the time dilation last time,
but what I did want to say about this,
I want to now put back the other two coordinates,
y and z.
y and z,
and let's put them back
into the game for a moment.
I'll put them back in.
There is another kind of transformation that we can do,
not just a,
a transformation between two moving coordinates
moving along the x-axis,
but we can also consider rotations of coordinates.
Let's for the moment not
even think very much about relativity.
Let's just talk about two different coordinate systems
related by an ordinary rotation with respect to each other.
So the stationary observer might
have two different coordinate systems,
one oriented along the x-y axis,
and another one oriented along some x-y prime axis.
Not the same primes.
Some other set of axes rotated or
at an angle relative to the original ones.
Alright.
What happens,
now we can forget the prime coordinates for the moment.
What about this x squared here?
This x squared is really the distance,
from the place where the clock started
to the place where it
ended up in the unprimed coordinates.
Now supposing we take into account the other directions,
let's call this y for example,
then this becomes a plane here.
This point might not be located directly over the x-axis,
it might be a point in space-time,
which is not at the same
value of x as the origin here.
What then is the interval between here and here?
What is the invariant quantity?
Well this is actually fairly simple.
As long as the event is located on the x-axis,
it's t squared minus x squared.
If it's not located on the x-axis,
when we make a rotation,
then what was originally x squared,
becomes x squared plus y squared plus z squared,
becomes the spatial distance between the
origin and this point over here.
This really becomes minus x squared
minus y squared minus z squared.
Etc.
So,
if we're not working strictly along a one-dimensional axis,
the invariant proper time between a start of a clock
and the place where the clock gets to
is given by t squared minus
the square of the spatial distance,
which is x squared,
this is Pythagoras'
theorem,
it's just Pythagoras'
theorem applied to x,
y,
and z,
and that's the notion of proper interval.
And that's the one we'll work with.
If we make any combination of Lorentz transformations
and rotations of coordinates,
we will always find that any two inertial frames
which agree at this point over here,
we will find out that tau squared is invariant.
It's the same in all inertial reference frames.
And it's very,
very similar to the idea that
in ordinary Euclidean geometry,
different coordinate axes will ascribe different coordinates
to a point in space,
but they will always agree about the
distance of a point from the origin.
Here,
it's this funny kind of distance
with a relative different sign between the space components
and the time components.
And that is probably the most central fact about relativity,
is that this combination is invariant.
That's really what it's all about.
Okay.
So,
let's keep that idea in mind
and introduce a little bit of notation.
We get tired of writing x,
y,
and z,
and we try to condense the notation.
So let's condense the
notation to standard relativistic notation.
Yeah?
Just going back to the train there for a second,
if you assume that the speed v,
let's say it was 0.9,
like you said,
it's very close to the speed of light.
And speed u,
let's say that instead of a car,
that guy has a flashlight in his hand,
so he's actually sending a light beam,
and that's that.
And I'm kind of wondering,
how do these two people measure the speed of light,
and whether they get the same number?
Why don't you try it?
Take one...
Yep.
Here it is.
What if c is the speed of light?
That means it's 1.
V is 1.
Oh,
I don't know,
which one do you want to make 1?
Make u 1.
Make u 1,
okay.
Make u 1.
That's 1 plus v,
divided by,
u is 1,
1 plus v.
So the answer's 1.
The speed of light is the speed of light.
That light ray moves with the speed of light.
In both frames.
Last week I was confused about something,
and you pointed out that generally
it comes down to simultaneity.
Definitions of simultaneity.
The question I asked a minute ago,
I realized that with the glass walls,
to try and look at both of them,
is trying to reintroduce simultaneity into the...
Okay,
if you understand it,
good.
Let's talk about light rays,
how light rays move.
Light rays,
let's go back to the one dimension.
One dimensional case then.
One space and one time dimension.
Let's go back.
Light rays move,
for example,
along 45 degree axes like this.
That means they will move from the origin
to the point xt,
but only if x is equal to t.
That's just saying the light moves with velocity 1.
In a certain time t,
the distance it moves is equal to that time,
so it moves to the point,
tt,
or the same coordinate.
That means that t squared minus x squared,
sorry,
t squared minus x squared is equal to zero,
or that the space-time interval,
I'll call it space-time interval,
proper time,
any number of different
depth usages,
is zero.
That's different than ordinary Euclidean distance.
Euclidean distance of two points
is the distance between two points.
If two points have genuinely zero distance between them,
they're sitting on top of each other.
In space-time,
if two points have space-time distance,
or proper time equal to zero between them,
that simply means they are related
by the possibility of a light ray
going from one to the other.
Now,
if we introduce the additional coordinates,
y squared and z squared,
then what was originally x squared,
the distance that the light beam
is going to get from the axis,
the square of the distance,
will obviously become x squared
plus y squared plus z squared,
square of the distance,
and that will be equal
to zero for a light ray.
So,
the motion of a light ray
is t squared minus x squared
minus y squared minus z squared
equal to zero,
or again,
tau squared is equal to zero.
Tau squared is...
So,
that's one concept
of how a light ray moves.
It moves along trajectories
such that the proper time along the trajectory
is equal to zero.
Photons move that way.
We could draw a picture for this.
A light ray moving to the right
is a 45 degree axis to the right.
45 degree line to the right.
A light ray moving to the left
moves...
exactly the same way,
except in the backward direction.
What about a light ray moving outward?
Well,
that moves the same way,
except at a 45 degree angle
in the outward direction.
More generally,
we would draw a kind of cone.
Now,
I can't draw the full three dimensions plus time.
That's too many dimensions for
me to draw on the blackboard.
But if we had only two dimensions,
x squared plus y squared,
instead of,
let's forget the z squared here,
we would find that the motion of light rays
is such that in space-time,
they move along
the cone
created by 45 degree light rays
coming out of the origin there.
That's called a light cone.
A light cone is the set of points
that a light ray can arrive at
if it starts at the origin.
That's the notion of a light cone.
And this would be called the future light cone.
The future light cone is all of the places
that light can get to
starting at the origin.
There's also a thing called the past light cone.
The past light cone
is all of the places that can send
the light ray to the origin.
So the future light cone
is all of the places that the origin
can send the light ray to,
and the past light cone
is all of the places that can send
the light ray to the origin.
But they're just the cone turned over on its nose.
The past light cone and the future light cone.
And this is terminology.
Terminology is often very helpful.
But that's all it is,
is terminology.
Yeah?
You said the fundamental invariance
for these systems is
the calc square equals t
squared minus xy and z squared.
There must be something equivalent
for Newtonian mechanics,
some invariant.
What would that be?
Just t.
Everybody agrees
about the time interval between two events.
The time interval is just t.
Right?
That's a good point.
All right,
we're getting close to...
Let's talk about the concept of four vector.
The most primitive,
the most basic example of a vector
in ordinary three-dimensional space,
and I am not talking about the kind of vectors
we talked about last quarter.
We're not talking about state vectors
in quantum mechanics.
We're talking about vectors in space.
All right,
the most basic notion,
the example of a vector,
is the interval between two points in space.
Given two points,
there's a vector which connects them.
That vector could measure the...
could have to do with how far somebody walked,
or whatever.
That's a vector.
It has a direction.
It has a magnitude.
And if we wanted to,
we could think of it
as a vector beginning at the origin
and ending up someplace else.
It doesn't matter where it begins,
but the vector...
This is the vector.
We can move it around.
It's the same vector,
but we can think of it as being a...
an excursion starting at the origin
and ending at some point x.
And it has coordinates,
in this case,
x,
y,
and z,
the location of the final point.
Or we could call them xi,
i being one,
two,
or three,
representing x,
y,
and z.
Three coordinates.
xi would really stand for x,
y,
and z.
Or x1,
x2,
and x3.
Now we have another added component to worry about.
Not only do we want
to know where an event is,
but we want to know
at what time that event is.
Let's suppose that we're measuring space and time
relative to some origin.
That means we have to add in another coordinate,
t.
In other words,
the vector becomes a four-dimensional object
with a time component and space components.
The normal notation for it
is to represent it two different ways.
I'll tell you the two different ways.
We can represent x,
y,
and z.
We can represent x,
y,
and z by calling them x,
mu.
Mu goes over the four possibilities.
Usually,
it's normally one arranges them as t,
x,
y,
and z.
x,
mu.
And what does mu run over?
What are the values of mu?
Why did you say zero?
Because everybody says zero.
Yeah.
Did you hear me say it?
I didn't hear.
I didn't know I said it.
Okay.
Right.
For whatever reason,
historically,
t was not considered the first coordinate.
x was considered the first coordinate.
y was considered the second and z the third.
You might have thought that
time should be the fourth component.
For whatever historical reason,
time was thought of as the zeroth component.
So this stands for x is zero,
which is time.
x1,
which is x.
x2,
which is y.
And x3,
which is z.
What about the space-time distance between these points?
The proper time.
That's t squared minus x squared.
The square of it.
Tau squared is t squared minus x
squared minus y squared minus z squared.
But we can also write it
as x naught squared minus x squared.
x1 squared minus x2 squared and so forth.
x2 squared,
blah,
blah.
So that's just notation.
It's just a notation.
Whenever you see a mu,
that means the index runs over
the four possibilities of space and time.
Whenever you see an i,
that means the index runs over only space.
i stands for space
and mu stands for space and time.
Just as xi can be thought of
as a very primitive version of a vector,
not primitive,
a very basic version of a vector in space,
x mu with four components becomes
the notion of a four vector.
Just as vectors transform when you rotate coordinates,
four vectors transform when you Lorentz transform them.
When you go from a moving
coordinate system to another moving coordinate system,
then the x's transform exactly the way
the Lorentz transformation tells you they transform.
We could rewrite this as x1
is x1 minus v x naught.
x prime naught,
x naught prime,
is equal to
x naught minus v x1,
and so forth.
There's no content to this,
it's just a way of organizing
the components of a four vector
by calling them all by the same name
and giving them an index mu.
So we'll use that.
We'll use that just to make formulas nice and simple.
So they transform linearly?
Yes,
they transform linearly.
So they could be,
you could set them up
and operate them with a matrix?
Absolutely.
You can read off from here a matrix.
The matrix would be 1 minus v minus v 1.
Absolutely.
You can think of,
you can think of Lorentz
transformations having associated with them matrices,
and you could write that
x prime
is equal to this times x.
Matrix times column vector.
The components of the column vector
would be x's and t's.
x's and t's.
Yes,
you certainly can use matrices,
and I advise you to do so,
because it's a good thing to do.
Alright,
now,
let's talk about some other examples of four vectors.
In particular,
instead of talking about
the components relative to an origin,
let's just take a little interval.
Let's just take a little
interval.
It could be an interval along a trajectory.
We could have a trajectory.
And we might want to consider along that trajectory
a small interval.
Now,
when you hear small,
think calculus.
Eventually,
we're going to be talking about a little differential.
We're going to be talking about
a little differential displacement along here.
For the moment,
let's just call it delta instead of d.
So,
this differential element here
corresponds to,
or not quite differential yet,
some discrete distance,
corresponds to a dx mu,
or delta x mu.
Delta x mu means
the change in the coordinates,
the change in the four coordinates
in going from the tail of the
vector to the beginning of the vector,
and it's composed out of
delta t and delta x,
delta y and delta z.
Delta x mu.
What I want to do now
is to introduce a notion of
four velocity,
four dimensional velocity,
which is a little different
than the normal notion of velocity.
Velocity,
in this case,
this could be the trajectory of a particle.
Let's take this to be the trajectory
of a particle from here to here.
And I'm interested in a notion
of velocity at a particular instant over here.
What do I do?
If I were doing ordinary velocity,
I would take a little delta x
and divide it by a delta t,
and then take the limit,
and that would define for me ordinary velocity.
That velocity has three components.
The x component of velocity,
the y component of velocity,
and the z component of velocity.
There is no fourth component of that ordinary velocity.
I'm going to introduce now a notion of
four dimensional velocity,
and we're going to do that
by taking the delta x mu,
and instead of dividing it by delta t,
we're going to divide it by
the invariant distance between these two points.
Let's call it delta tau.
Delta tau is defined so that its square
is equal to delta t squared
minus delta xi delta xi,
minus,
you know,
the sums of the squares
of the delta x's.
Delta x squared,
delta y squared,
and delta z squared.
In other words,
it's the invariant space-time distance
between this point and that point.
We take the square root of this,
and it gives us delta tau,
and that is called the four velocity.
It's labeled by a u instead of a v,
and it has an index mu,
so it runs from zero to three.
Four components.
Now,
how does this thing relate
to the ordinary velocity?
We're getting,
we should probably go
if we want to get seats,
but...
We'll continue next time.
I'll tell you where we're going.
We're going toward a theory
of the motion of particles.
To have a theory of the motion of particles,
we have to have notions such as velocity,
position,
and velocity.
And the motion,
of course,
momentum,
energy,
kinetic energy,
whatever,
we're moving toward a,
first of all,
just the motion of particles,
and then toward a dynamics
of how particles move.
A generalization,
if you like,
of F equals ma,
we'll have a notion of acceleration,
all the things that Newton had,
except the relativistic generalizations of them.
And they will be in terms of four vectors.
Okay,
let's see if we can grab a,
let's see,
I have 10 to 8,
so who's right?
That clock's right,
we better,
get yourself a good seat.
For more,
please visit us at
stanford.edu.