Stanford University
Are there any other questions that
I can answer in five minutes?
You mentioned last week that a person traveling near
the speed of light would measure at a longer wavelength.
Well,
it depends on which way he's going.
If the light wave is going that way,
and you're moving with it,
then the wavelength looks longer
than if you were standing still.
If you're moving the other way,
it looks shorter.
That's the Doppler shift.
And,
alright,
let me tell you how you can work it out.
You can work it out just from geometry,
from the geometry of the Lorentz transformations.
So,
here's the geometry.
Here's what you do.
Alright,
first of all,
let's do the usual drawing of two coordinate frames.
One of them is at rest.
That's your frame.
And my frame is moving to the right.
And so my frame looks like this.
Alright.
Let's draw in one more thing.
Let's draw in the speed of light.
It's like that.
Alright,
now imagine that there was a wave.
And think about,
here's the wave.
And the wave is moving to the right.
As it moves to the right,
we can follow the peaks of the wave,
the high points of the wave.
And I'm going to draw them in in red.
They're also going to move with the speed of light.
So they're going to look like this.
Notice that as you move up,
meaning as time goes forward,
as time goes forward,
the wave moves to the right.
So that's a right moving wave.
And what's the wavelength?
The wavelength in your frame of
reference is this distance over here.
The distance between successive maxima.
What's the wavelength in my frame?
The wavelength in my frame is this distance,
but this distance as measured using
relativity and using the Lorentz transformations.
In other words,
this distance here is the distance between the two maxima,
at what you call an instant of time.
And the wavelength to me is the distance between the
two maxima at what I call an instant of time.
So,
if you work out the Lorentz transformations,
and you look along here and ask,
what's the distance between these
two points in my reference frame,
and compare it with the distance along here,
you'll find they're different.
That would give you the Doppler shift.
You have the tools to do that.
You can do that.
You know the Lorentz transformations.
You can figure out what the core...
Let's say the wave...
Well,
here's some wavelength,
some particular wavelength.
You can figure out what this point is.
And you can ask what's
the x prime distance between them.
x prime is my coordinate.
x is your coordinate.
The x distance between these,
is lambda.
And you can figure out
what the x prime distance is.
And that's the way to calculate the Doppler shift.
So I recommend it as an
exercise in working with Lorentz transformations.
Yeah?
Is the next course in the
sequence going to be next fall?
Yeah.
There's nothing this summer?
No.
No,
no,
no.
And what's the other part?
Do you know yet?
Take a vote.
I'm not sure.
I think...
Possibly general relativity.
Possibly more quantum mechanics.
Our coverage of quantum mechanics was reasonably deep
but not very broad.
Having not gotten to the harmonic oscillator,
that's a bad thing.
So I think before we study quantum field theory,
we do have to study more quantum mechanics.
But I'm not sure which way to go next quarter.
And I haven't decided yet.
Can I make a small request?
Yeah.
Whatever it is that you have,
could you cover infrared and ultraviolet connection?
Yeah.
We have to do general relativity first.
That's a gravitational issue.
We haven't studied gravity.
That's an issue of a
combination of quantum mechanics and gravity.
We may know enough about quantum mechanics at this point,
but not enough about gravity.
The scales are not the
same on X and X prime.
Is that correct?
What do you mean the scales are not the same?
You can't just look at the blackboard.
No,
no,
no.
You can't just look at the blackboard.
You have to do the Lorentz transformations.
Right.
Okay.
How do you do it?
Let's make this wavelength 1 just to simplify.
So this is 0,
this is 1,
this is 2,
and so forth.
All right.
Now I would like to locate what this point is.
It's clearly important for me
to locate where that point is.
This point is X prime equals 0.
That's the same as,
which is it?
T equals VX.
Do you remember that?
That the surface T prime equals 0
is the same as T equals VX.
Let me remind you why.
The Lorentz transformation involves T prime is equal to T
minus VX over square root of 1 minus V squared.
Right?
All right.
Now supposing I want to know
where T prime equals 0 is.
T prime equals 0,
that's what I call an instant.
It happens to be the instant T prime equals 0,
but that's okay.
And that's clearly T equals VX.
So this is T equals VX.
And what is this line over here?
Well,
first of all,
what is this line?
X equals T.
Moving with the speed of light.
C equals 1.
That's X equals T.
What is this one?
Oh,
come on.
It's easy.
All right.
X equals T plus 1,
right?
Okay.
So we're at the intersection of X
equals T plus 1 and T equals VX.
Let's work it out.
Let's see what that point is.
X equals T,
which is VX.
Plus 1.
Or X times 1 minus V equals 1.
Or X is equal to 1 over 1 minus V.
That's the X of this point.
And what about the T of this point?
Well,
if we know the X of this point,
let's say,
we can read off the T.
T is equal to V.
V over 1 minus V.
All right.
Now we would like to find out what the simplest thing to
do now is to figure out we know T and we know X.
What I'd really like to know,
what would I really like to
know about this point over here?
I'd like to know X prime.
I would like to know the
distance between successive minima in my frame,
the primed frame.
So we go to the primed frame.
X prime is equal to X minus VT
over square root of 1 minus V squared.
And now I just plug in for
X and T what I have here.
Do I really want to do that?
Yes,
I do.
X prime equals X 1 over
1 minus V minus V times T.
So that's V times T minus
V squared over 1 minus V.
All divided by square root of 1 minus V squared.
Right?
Did I do that right?
I think so.
Okay,
so let's see if we can simplify it now.
We have 1 minus V squared.
1 minus V squared divided by 1 minus V.
And also in the denominator,
I also have square root of 1 minus V squared.
Okay.
1 minus V.
Sorry.
1 minus V squared is the same
as 1 minus V times 1 plus V.
Right?
That's 1 minus V squared is
1 minus V times 1 plus V.
And so these cancel out.
What else can I do with it?
Well,
I can put this in the square root.
Just by squaring it and then
putting it in the square root.
And the whole thing becomes square root.
So let's put this in the square root.
Square root of 1 plus V times 1 plus V.
That's 1 plus V squared.
Divided by 1 minus V squared.
Which is 1 plus V times 1 minus V.
So the answer is square root of 1 plus V
over 1 minus V.
That's what x prime is over here.
Is it bigger than 1 or smaller than 1?
It's bigger than 1.
So my reckoning of this distance
gives me something bigger than 1.
You said the wavelength was 1.
I say the wavelength is square root
of 1 plus v over 1 minus v.
So that's the calculation.
Does that answer your question,
Warren?
Good.
So it's all there in these pictures.
Just draw the picture of the thing you're
trying to figure out and then convert it into
some simple equations.
Good.
Now,
let's put this up.
This of course is the relativistic Doppler shift formula,
square root of 1 plus v over
1 minus v.
And to really be correct about it,
this is v over c.
And this is v over c.
Not correct.
It was correct.
But to put units in,
which is the same as square root
of c plus v over c minus v.
What do you think happens if
you're going in the other direction?
If I was going in the other direction?
You would just change the sign of
the velocity from plus v to minus v.
That's just going in the other direction,
minus v.
And you would get square root of
c plus v over c minus v.
And now this is less than 1.
So if you're shooting against
the direction of the light ray,
you see a shorter wavelength.
If you're moving along the light ray,
you see a longer wavelength.
And what happens if your velocity
gets up near the speed of light?
Let's say this one over here.
If your velocity gets up near the speed of light,
then the wavelength is going to be
bigger and bigger and bigger.
And eventually,
if you're moving with a light ray,
if you could,
the wavelength would look infinite.
OK.
There's another way to...
Yeah,
that's fine.
Let's leave it that way.
OK.
Good.
All right.
If there are no further questions,
we will start tonight's lecture 10 minutes late.
Fields and particles.
Now in quantum mechanics,
fields and particles are just like a circle.
Fields and particles are the same thing.
But we're not doing quantum mechanics.
For us here,
fields are fields and particles are particles.
I won't say never that twain will meet,
because they will meet.
They will meet tonight.
But they are not the same thing.
In particular,
we want to ask the question if a
field affects a particle in a certain way.
For example,
by creating forces in the field.
So,
if there are forces on it that accelerate it,
or whatever they do,
must it not also be the
case that the particle affects the field?
Well,
why do I say that?
Why does it have to be the case?
Why,
if A affects B,
does B necessarily have to affect A?
And that's built into the idea of action.
That's built into the action principle,
or into the Lagrangian principle.
We can see it in a very...
In a simple context.
It's also called action and reaction.
It's a basic idea.
If A affects B,
then B will affect A.
So,
a simple example of it is
to suppose that you had two coordinates.
Now,
you could have any number of coordinates,
but let's just suppose for the
moment two coordinates and an action principle.
So,
let's call the coordinates x and y.
And the Lagrangian is going
to depend on the action principle.
So,
the Lagrangian is going to depend on x and y,
and x dot and y dot.
x and y do not have
to stand for the orthogonal coordinates,
Cartesian coordinates of anything.
They're just two coordinates.
And the Lagrangian depends on all of these.
Now,
one possibility is that the Lagrangian
is simply a sum of two terms.
The Lagrangian for x and x dot,
plus the Lagrangian for y and y dot.
A different Lagrangian.
I'll just continue to call it L.
Might be the same,
might be different.
If this is the case,
and you look at the equation of motion for x.
Let's write it down.
Then,
that equation of motion will involve d by dt of partial of L with
respect to x dot is equal to partial of L with respect to x.
And y won't get into it altogether.
Likewise,
if you write the equation of motion for y.
x doesn't get into it.
And so in this case,
x doesn't affect y.
y doesn't affect x.
What can you say if you
know that y does affect x?
That tells you that the Lagrangian must be more complicated,
and there must be things in it
which somehow affect both x and y.
For example,
here's a Lagrangian.
x dot squared over 2
plus y dot squared over 2.
So far,
they're completely independent.
You could have a potential energy for x,
or minus.
And maybe another potential energy,
v prime,
for y.
So far,
it's just a sum of two terms.
An x term and a y term.
x and y are not going to affect each other.
What do you need to do if
you want to see them affect each other?
Put something in addition to the Lagrangian which involves both
x and y in a way that you can't unravel it.
For example,
just x times y.
If you have x times y,
then the equation of motion for x will involve y.
And the equation of motion for y will involve x.
If you have them both in the Lagrangian in
a way which is coupled together in this way,
there's no way that it's possible
that one can affect the other.
Without the other affecting the one.
So that's as simple as that.
That is why if A affects B,
B affects A.
Okay.
Now let's come to the issue,
let's talk about particles and fields.
We talked a little bit last time about how
a field might affect the motion of a particle.
That was just a simple model,
but we'll go back to it.
Let's go back to it.
Talk about how a field might
affect the motion of a particle.
How the field affects the particle motion.
And then come back and ask how the particle,
the presence of the particle,
affects the field.
This is very much the analog of electric
and magnetic fields affecting the motion of charged particles.
And charged particles creating
and modifying the electromagnetic field.
For example,
just by having a charged particle creates a coolant.
A coolant field and so forth.
And those are not two independent things.
They come from the same Lagrangian.
So let's work out this example.
All right.
So let's begin with,
let's suppose first of all
that there is some field phi.
Phi depends on x and t.
For the moment we forget about how it
got to have the value that it has.
Somebody solved some equations for phi and found
out that phi of x and t has a,
or measured phi of x and t.
And it had some specific form.
Phi of x might be a wave
or it might not be a wave.
How does that affect the motion of a particle?
And for that,
we're not going to ask
about the dynamics of phi now.
We're going to ask for the Lagrangian for the particle.
This is the particle Lagrangian.
So let's remember what it is to begin with.
To begin with,
it contains minus m times the square
root of 1 minus x dot squared.
What was this?
This was the term in the
Lagrangian that corresponded to an action
which just added up all
the proper times along the line.
Along the little segments of a path.
Multiplied by minus m.
The integral of this Lagrangian,
let's write it out.
Let's write the integral dt,
that's the action.
That's the integral dt of this.
And this is the same as minus
m times the integral of the proper times
from one end of the trajectory to another.
Alright,
so that's the ordinary Lagrangian for a particle.
But that doesn't have anything in it
in which the field affects the particle.
So let's put in something for the field.
A simple thing.
The simplest thing we can think of.
The simplest thing I can think of.
Let me move this a little bit.
And let me put minus m plus phi.
Now phi is a function
of position and time in general.
So it's a function of x and t.
But we're imagining for the
moment that it's a known function
of the coordinates of the particle.
Times the same thing again.
One minus x dot squared.
That's the Lagrangian for a particle.
I could work out the Euler Lagrange equations
and find out how phi
affects the motion of the particle.
I'm going to do it,
but I'm going to do it in the simplified approximation
where the particle moves very slowly.
Just as an illustration.
I don't want to futz
around with all the relativistic things.
I want to get rid of the relativistic square
roots of 1 minus v squared and so forth.
This of course is v squared.
And we could be thinking
about a particle on a line.
We don't need y and z in this.
Just x is enough to illustrate the point.
Particle moving in one dimension.
Let me put back the speeds of light.
It's useful to put back the speeds of light
in order to see what the nonrelativistic limit is.
The nonrelativistic limit is basically the limit
in which the speed of light goes to infinity.
When the speed of light is bigger
than any other velocity in the problem,
that's the nonrelativistic limit.
The Newtonian limit.
Lagrangian has units of energy.
Mass does not have units of energy,
unless the speed of light is 1.
But if the speed of light is not 1,
we put in minus mc squared.
Now it has units of energy.
Phi I'm just going to leave that way.
The field is defined.
Oh,
let's put a constant in here.
Let's put a g in here.
This constant is a constant called a coupling constant.
It measures the strength by which the field
affects the motion of the particle.
So let's put a g in here.
g can be anything for the moment.
We don't know what it is.
It might have a c in it.
It might not have a c in it.
Not important.
At the moment it's just g times phi.
And phi depends on x and t.
Now,
let's exp...
Oh,
and of course,
this is square root of 1 minus x dot squared
over c squared.
That's the Lagrangian with all
the speeds of light in place.
And now let's go to the nonrelativistic limit.
The nonrelativistic limit,
when c gets very large,
we expand the square root.
We expand the square root.
Using the binomial expansion,
1 minus a small number to the minus...
to the one-half power,
that just becomes...
well,
this thing becomes
1 minus x dot squared
over twice c squared.
The twice comes...
the one-half comes
because this is something to the one-half power.
I'm using that 1 plus epsilon
or 1 minus epsilon
in this case
to the power one-half
is just 1 minus one-half epsilon
plus things which are really very much smaller
because they will involve higher powers
of the ratio of the
velocity to the velocity of light.
So,
this is what we get.
Plus tiny,
tiny things.
Let's erase this and write 1 minus x dot squared.
Over 2c squared.
Now we look at this
and we try to find the biggest pieces,
the pieces which are most important
when the speed of light gets large.
The obvious first piece is mc squared.
Just mc squared times 1.
But mc squared times 1 is just a number.
It doesn't do anything.
When you start different...
It's a Lagrangian we're talking about.
If you start differentiating it,
with respect to position or velocity,
it doesn't do anything.
It's just a number.
So that term is of no interest.
Adding a constant in a Lagrangian
doesn't have any effect on the equation of motion.
So the mc squared times 1 is of no interest.
The next term has the speed of light
canceling altogether.
So it's part of the limit
in which the speed of light goes to infinity.
And it survives.
It survives that limit.
So the next term is the product of mc squared
times x dot squared over 2c squared.
And that's familiar.
That's x dot squared m over 2.
The c squares have cancelled.
And that's just a good old 1 half mv squared,
the nonrelativistic kinetic energy.
And what about this term?
g phi times 1.
That has no speeds of light in it,
so it clearly survives.
So we add minus.
There's a minus sign here.
Minus g phi of x and t.
And that's all that there is
when the particle is moving slowly.
And we just compare that with,
you know,
the old-fashioned
nonrelativistic Lagrangian.
The old-fashioned nonrelativistic Lagrangian
was kinetic energy minus potential energy.
This is clearly kinetic energy.
And that identifies for us g times phi
as the potential energy of the particle.
The potential energy of the particle in a field.
g is just a constant.
But in,
for example,
electromagnetism,
the strength of the coupling
of a field and a particle
is just the electric charge.
The bigger the electric charge,
the bigger the force on a particle
in a given field.
So it's natural that there'd be some constant
multiplying something about the field.
We'll come back to this.
But if you like,
in this limit,
the nonrelativistic limit,
and the only reason I do the nonrelativistic limit
is so we don't have to muck around
with all these square roots of 1 minus v squared,
just to illustrate a point,
this is effect,
or this here represents the effect
of the field
on the particle.
Okay.
Now,
what about the effect of the particle
on the field?
The important thing to understand
is that there's only one action.
The total action altogether.
And the total action includes
an action for the field
and the action for the particle.
The physics problem we're trying to do
could be,
we should draw a picture
of what it is we're trying to do.
We have a region of space and time.
Time,
space,
and we have a field in it.
Let's just draw the field
as a bunch of red mush.
There's the field.
And first of all,
we're trying to find out how the field behaves.
That involves
knowing a Lagrangian for the field
and minimizing a Lagrangian for a field.
And in addition,
the mechanical system
or the system that we're studying
also happens to have a particle moving through it.
So what we're trying to do
is study a combined system
of a field and a particle moving through the field.
And we're trying to minimize the action
not just with respect to the motion of the particle,
but with respect to the motion of the particle
and the motion of the field,
or how the field behaves in there.
For that,
very simple.
We simply explore around
changing the field,
letting it wiggle in different ways,
change the particle trajectory
until we minimize the action.
And that will give us the trajectory and the field
that correspond to the principle of least action.
Okay,
so let's go and write
the whole action,
including the field and the particle.
Well,
first of all,
we need an action for the field.
We discussed this last time.
I'm just going to write down
what we wrote down last time.
A simple case of it.
The Lagrangian for the field
that we wrote...
L sub f stands for Lagrangian for the field
that we wrote down last time are...
well,
the action.
The action itself.
The full action is the integral
times d4x.
d4x means dt and dx.
It's an integral over the whole spacetime region
x,
y,
and z,
and t.
And the thing we wrote down last time
was the integral of
one half
partial of phi with respect to t squared
minus...
minus one half partial of
phi with respect to x squared.
I'm finished with the speeds of light for the moment.
I don't care about them anymore.
I just wanted to keep track of them
in this little exercise over here.
But if we wanted to keep
track of the speed of light,
I think there would be
a 1 over c squared here.
All right.
This is the Lagrangian for the field,
and it doesn't involve a particle at all.
But now we have to...
or the action.
This is the action for the...
for the field.
But now let's also add to that
the action for the particle.
Here it is right over here.
I'm going to take a very special,
simple case.
You can work out the more complicated case,
but I'm going to work out the case
where the particle
is at rest.
Let's put the particle at rest.
Let's assume for the moment
that there is a solution to the equations
where the particle is just at rest.
After all,
there are situations
where an electron might be at rest.
Right?
And ask what the additional term in the action is.
We can make the electron move.
It doesn't...
But for simplicity,
let's just take the electron to be at rest,
not moving.
That's the trajectory.
And what is the action in that case?
Here it is right over here.
X dot is zero.
This is just one.
MC squared by itself is of no interest.
And so the Lagrangian for the particle,
or the contribution to the Lagrangian
from this piece over here,
is just the integral of phi,
phi of x and t,
but an integral along where?
What kind of integral?
It's an integral dt,
right?
This is just a particle.
It's not a field.
It's an integral dt.
And it's an integral along
the world line of the particle.
But it involves phi.
It involves phi.
The reason the particle responded to the field
was because the Lagrangian for the particle involves phi.
The reason the field responded to the particle
is because that same Lagrangian
also has phi and the
positions of the particles in it.
So what do we add?
How can we add this term here?
I want to add it in a way that corresponds
to an integral over space and time.
How can I turn this into
an integral over space and time?
Oh,
sorry.
Let's go back a step.
So,
let's go back a step.
Let's go back a step.
Where should I put this particle?
For convenience and simplicity,
let me just put it at x equals 0.
It's a particle at position x equals 0.
Then what do we put in here?
Well,
we put in the position of the particle,
x,
which is 0.
phi of 0 and t.
Integral dt.
Now,
this term here is just
an integral over the world line.
This term here is an integral over all space-time.
In fact,
the way I wrote it,
space is only one-dimensional,
so this would really be only a two-dimensional integral.
But you know what I mean.
Okay,
how can I write this
so that it looks like an integral over all space-time?
Just to put it into one term.
And the answer is simple.
The answer is you use the Dirac delta function.
You use the Dirac delta function.
Here's the way you do it.
This is what I want to get.
Take phi at 0.
The time is not important here.
And let me write it in the following way.
It's an integral over all space
of phi of x
times the Dirac delta function.
The time dependence is not important here.
It just goes along for the ride.
Do you recognize this?
When you integrate the Dirac delta function,
the Dirac delta function is a
very high spike of a function.
It's a high spike of a function.
It's 0 everywhere except at x equals 0.
And so when you integrate
the field with the delta function,
you just get the field at the origin.
You get the field at the origin
or the field at the place where x,
where the delta function has its big spike.
Where does the dx cubed come from?
That's the integral over the volume.
If this was a one-dimensional axis,
we would just write dx.
Let's take the case of...
I guess I really need to tell you
what that delta function really means.
What I've written is just delta of x.
Let's be a little more precise.
Let's call this delta 3 of x,
d3x.
Delta 3 of x means
the product of three delta functions.
Delta of x,
delta of y,
delta of z.
Where is this function non-zero?
It's non-zero when all three
of these delta functions are non-zero.
There's only one place where
all three of them are non-zero.
It's at x equals 0,
y equals 0,
or z equals 0.
So what is it?
It's a function of three coordinates,
delta x,
y,
and z.
It's a function of the three coordinates of space,
but it only has a
value at one point of space.
And at that point of space,
it's enormously big.
When you integrate the field...
Let's write it out.
Let's write it out in bloody detail.
Integral phi of x,
y,
and z.
I won't bother writing the time dependence.
Delta of x,
delta of y,
delta of z.
dx,
dy,
dz.
That's what I've written here.
That's the meaning of this symbol here.
The triple delta function,
and then integrating over all space.
Alright,
how do you do this integral?
This is not a very hard integral to do.
Remember,
whenever you integrate a function with a delta function,
it gives you the value
of the function at the origin,
or at the place where the delta function is big,
where it has its spike.
We're just using the equation.
Integral f of x,
delta of x,
equals f of 0.
That's the defining property of the delta function.
It picks out for you the value of the function,
at the place where the delta function has its spike.
Alright,
so if I do the integral over x first,
this one tells me to set x equal to 0.
This integral tells me to set y equal to 0.
And this integral tells me
to set z equal to 0.
So the whole thing is just phi of 0.
That's what I've written here.
Notice,
I also,
in order to calculate the action,
I also have to integrate it over time.
The action was the integral of this phi over time.
So in the action,
we have the integral over all coordinates,
d4x,
that means the xdy dzdt,
phi of x and t,
delta cubed of x.
This delta cubed of x is doing
nothing but picking out the value of phi
at the spatial position of the particle.
That's all it's doing.
It's a trick just to write this thing here.
It's a trick for writing the value of
a field at a point as an integral.
Why do I want to do it?
Well,
I just want to do it,
because I would like to add here plus,
I missed something,
I missed a g.
Can we lose a minus sign?
Very likely.
Because of this?
Yeah.
Minus.
G,
delta cubed of x,
phi of x.
And now the whole thing is just one big integral
over all space and all time.
Here it is.
And this thing inside the big square bracket,
is the Lagrangian.
This is this thing inside the big square.
This is the action equals.
The action is now an integral over space and time,
like any good field Lagrangian.
It has the good old field action.
And this term over here represents the
effect of the particle back on the field.
It's just this term over here.
For the special situation where the
particle happens to be at rest.
We could jazz it up so that the particle moves.
This is phi of x and t.
We could do that by making
the delta function move around with time.
That's possible to do,
but it's not important right now.
Okay,
now let's go take this Lagrangian
and work out the equations of motion for it.
The thing inside the bracket is Lagrangian.
And let's work out the equations of motion.
First of all,
we have the derivative of the Lagrangian
with respect to partial of phi with respect to t,
d by dt.
What is that?
That's just equal,
what is dl by d phi dt?
It's just d phi dt,
right?
So this one is going to give us the
second derivative of phi with respect to t squared.
Sort of like an acceleration.
We have a kinetic energy,
phi dot squared.
When we work out the equation of motion,
we have something that looks like an acceleration of phi.
Now,
there are the other terms coming
from d phi by dx squared,
and they're exactly the same.
Same sort of thing.
I'm going to erase this,
and I'm just going to put in
minus d second phi by dx squared.
If that's all there was,
I would set that equal to zero,
and this would be a good old-fashioned wave equation,
one-dimensional in this case.
If we wanted to add more dimensions,
we would add minus d second phi by dy squared
minus d second phi by dx squared.
And we would set that equal to zero.
That would be the wave equation
describing waves of this thing phi.
But now we have more phi dependence here.
The Lagrangian depends on phi in another way.
What happens if we differentiate
the Lagrangian with respect to phi?
Remember,
what we're supposed to put here
on the right-hand side is not zero.
We're supposed to put the derivative of the Lagrangian.
That's the other side of Lagrange's equations,
or the other side of the Euler-Lagrange equations.
And we can see from here,
the derivative of L with respect
to phi at x and t
is just g times the delta function.
It's just g times delta cubed of x.
So,
our equation is just that this is equal to g,
times delta cubed of x.
Do you recognize this as an
equation you may have seen before?
Oh,
there's a minus sign,
I think.
Is there a minus sign?
Yes,
there's a minus sign.
Now,
this is an odd equation.
It's a wave equation,
except on the right-hand side at one point,
and only one point,
there's something different.
Something's going on at that one point,
which is different than the rest of space.
What's going on?
There's a particle there.
It's affecting the equation of motion,
but only at one point.
Let's,
just to try to make it a little bit familiar,
let's suppose that we're looking
for solutions of the equation.
After all,
the particle is standing still,
at least in this example.
If the particle is standing still,
there might be a chance that
there's a solution of the equation
where the field itself doesn't change with time.
Just the effect of the standing still particle
affecting the field
is likely to make a field
which also doesn't vary with time.
So,
we might look then for a solution to this equation
in which phi is time independent.
That means this is not there.
And,
we can see that,
we can change the sign of everything,
plus,
plus.
I don't know if you recognize this equation,
Poisson's equation.
This is the Poisson equation,
for example,
for the electrostatic potential energy,
the electrostatic potential.
It would sometimes be written as del squared phi
is equal to a source on the right hand side,
or charge density.
And,
in this case,
the charge density is just a delta function.
In other words,
a high,
sharp spike.
So,
you see,
now we're not really doing electrodynamics at the moment.
We're doing a sort of simplification
involving a scalar field instead of electromagnetic fields.
But,
you see how it works.
The same term in the Lagrangian,
which tells the particle
to move as if there was a potential energy,
g phi,
in other words,
which exerts forces on the particle.
Also,
that same term,
when used for the equation
of motion of the phi field,
tells us that the phi field has a source.
These are not independent things.
The fact that the field affects the particle
tells us that the particle
affects the field.
And with a specific,
simple example,
it even tells us exactly how.
Same parameter g.
The parameter g determines how strong
the effect of the particle on the field is,
and it also tells us how strong
the effect of the field on the particle is.
So,
we have a nice little story there.
Fields and particles affect each other.
Through a common term in the Lagrangian,
parts are qualche unapportwie
and that choreographyarmotas
A graph is
taken of the tree as the graph
for the egg in the antip waren Rudolf Dattel,
which is that
of our choice,
someplace else.
I didn't want to put it at the origin.
I wanted to put it at x
equals a.
What would I do here?
How would I change it?
x minus a?
Delta of x minus a.
Delta of x minus a has its
spike when x is equal to a.
Now supposing the particle
were moving,
that its position were a of t,
all you would do is write delta of x
minus a of t here.
And what this would tell you
is that there's a source of the
field,
but the source of the field is
moving and at any given time it's at
position a of t.
So you see we can't accommodate a moving particle.
We can't
accommodate a moving particle.
The only thing is if
we did have the particle moving,
we wouldn't expect the
field to be time independent.
If the particle is moving around,
obviously the
field will depend on time if the
source of the particle is moving around.
And so
we would have to put back the other term here,
minus d second phi by dt squared.
There's no way we could get a solution with
a time independent phi,
but where the right hand side does depend on time.
The only way
to make it consistent is to
put back the time dependence here.
So a moving particle,
an
accelerating particle or a vibrating
particle will affect the field,
give it a time dependence,
and you know what it'll do.
It'll radiate waves.
But the moment we're not going to solve
wave equations,
we're going to do something else.
We're going to spend a little bit of
time just talking about the notation of relativity.
The notation,
I mean the mathematical notation
that we use to make equations look simple
and pretty and not have to write every damn
time we write an equation,
second derivative with respect to x squared,
second derivative
with respect to y squared,
blah blah blah,
but have a neat notation.
The notation will
make sense.
The question becomes,
but what if we use a whoever idea,
and if I had a new
step veurein,
and if I'm okay with it,
and this became a first step,
what if,
for example,
I did aależline,
because a first step we already
had that goddess We're thinking about
.
.元stern V.
되 advocate
Is that actually not dependent?
Well,
if we really wanted to do real non-relativistic,
we would want to keep the v over c.
We would not want to go to the non-relativistic limit.
But even in a non-relativistic limit,
the right-hand side is time dependent,
and so it will create waves.
But I'm not sure exactly what you're asking.
I guess I would say where is
the relativity if I'm looking at that equation?
I guess it's in the form of v itself.
Is that right?
No.
It's in the form of
the left-hand side of the equation.
c squared.
No.
It's in the form...
From the unit analysis,
g times phi has to be equal to energy?
Yeah.
g times phi has to be equal to energy.
Well,
let's see.
Let's see if we can figure out the units.
I'll leave it to you.
You figure out the units.
The units of phi happen to be units of energy,
and that means the units of g are dimensionless numbers.
It depends on the dimension of space.
That's not always true.
For the moment,
this is not too important for us.
All right.
Now we want to spend a little time just reviewing.
For some of you,
it'll be reviewing.
it'll be learning.
Standard notation for relativistic vectors,
four vectors,
scalars.
We talked about this a little last time,
but I want to come back to it.
How you make scalars out of vectors,
how you make vectors out of scalars,
and how you condense notation so that things are neat.
I'm sure that most of you know this,
but we're going to do it anyway.
All right.
X mu,
of course,
stands for the four coordinates of space,
time,
space-time,
and it's t,
x,
y,
and z.
Usually this is called 1,
2,
and 3,
and this one is called 0,
but that's not important.
Mu runs over four values.
All right.
Notice now,
I'm going to pay attention now
to where I put this index.
I've put the index up on top,
above.
That's going to mean something to us shortly.
At the moment,
it doesn't mean anything.
But this quantity,
if thought of as a displacement from the origin,
is a four vector.
And I'm going to think about the way it transforms,
how it transforms under Lorentz transformation.
Anything that transforms the same way
under Lorentz transformation as x and t
is called a four vector.
I won't write it down for the moment.
It's a four vector,
has four components.
Saying that three of the components are equal to 0,
for example,
that might be true.
That would mean that it was a displacement
that only involved three of the
coordinates and not the fourth coordinate.
But it's not an invariant statement.
An observer,
one,
you may say
that there was a displacement of
an object which was purely time-like.
In other words,
it didn't move in space.
I will say it did move in space.
So the statement that a four
vector has three components equal to 0
may be true in some frame of reference,
but it's not an invariant
statement that everybody will agree upon.
But the statement that all four components are 0,
that everybody will agree on,
because all it says is that
that vector is the zero vector,
no displacement at all.
And we'll all agree that a
zero vector is a zero vector.
In fact,
zero transforms to itself under a Lorentz transformation.
If all four coordinates are zero before transformation,
there's zero after transformation.
So that's the notion of a four vector.
There are many four vectors.
Differences of four vectors are four vectors.
So differential displacements are four vectors,
and so forth.
Out of a four vector,
we can make a scalar.
A scalar meaning a thing which doesn't transform,
which is the same in every frame.
Now,
I know we've done this before,
and I'm going over old material,
but nevertheless,
let's do it.
Out of a displacement,
we can construct a proper time,
d tau squared,
and you know what that is.
That's dt squared minus dx squared
minus dy squared minus dz squared.
And that has the property that it
is the same in every reference frame.
It doesn't have components.
It only has one component,
one value,
and it's a scalar.
So let's call it a scalar.
This is a four vector.
Scalar.
Now,
if a scalar is equal to
zero in one frame of reference,
it's zero in every frame of reference.
Why?
Because a scalar is the same as a thing
which is the same in every frame of reference.
So if in some frame of reference,
a scalar,
whatever the...
It's practically the definition of a scalar,
the thing which is the
same in every frame of reference.
If it's zero in one frame,
it's zero in any frame.
So it's an invariant statement to say
that a scalar is equal to zero.
And here we have an example of how
you make a scalar out of a four vector.
That's very general.
If you have a four vector of any kind,
let's call it a mu,
to say that it's a four
vector means it transforms the same way
under Lorentz transformations.
Then the difference of the square of the time components
and the space components are a scalar.
I won't bother writing it.
The difference a time squared minus a space squared
are a scalar,
is a scalar,
and it's the same in every reference frame.
We want a nice way to write that.
I don't want to have to write
a time squared minus a x squared
minus a y squared minus a z squared.
Okay.
For that,
we invent a matrix.
The matrix has a name.
It's called the metric.
Okay.
In special relativity,
it's usually denoted eta.
Eta is the Greek letter eta.
E-T-A.
And it looks like that.
Eta is a matrix.
Eta is a Greek letter.
It stands for matrix.
And the matrix has two indices,
mu and nu.
But it's a very simple matrix.
It's practically the identity matrix.
But not quite.
It has three elements which are
equal to one on the diagonal,
just like the unit matrix.
But the fourth element is minus one.
The fourth element corresponds to time.
Minus one,
zero,
zero.
Zero plus one,
zero,
zero.
Zero,
zero,
one,
zero.
Zero,
zero,
one.
If I were to make this plus one,
it would just be the good old unit matrix.
But it's not.
Okay.
Now,
let's take this matrix.
We're going to represent four vectors by columns.
The column vector,
for example,
a mu,
will consist of four entries,
the time component,
and the three space components,
x,
y,
and z.
And let's take the matrix
and multiply it by the vector.
We can either do it by matrix multiplication,
or we can say,
let's call this a nu.
Let's use nu here.
Nu runs also from one to four.
Let's multiply the matrix.
We can represent that,
eta mu nu,
a nu,
summed over nu.
That's one way to write it.
That's just this one.
It's just matrix multiplication,
but it can be represented by summing
eta one one times a one,
eta one two,
a two,
and so forth.
And this represents a new object,
which we'll call a with a lower index here.
Let's see what it is.
Let's see if we can figure out what it is,
what this a with a lower index is.
It's not the original a.
If this really were the unit matrix,
and you multiply a vector,
you would get back exactly the same thing.
But not quite.
The minus one here means that
when you multiply eta by a,
what happens?
It changes the sign of the first term here.
It leaves everything else the same.
And so we can write down immediately,
without any further work,
that a mu,
mu or nu,
it doesn't matter,
represents the column,
the vector,
let's call it the vector,
minus at,
at,
y
a z
in other words
when i perform this operation
i simply change the sign of the time component
so that's one piece of
um...
it's notation this is purely a notational
device there's no real content in it
the second notational device which no
doubt you're also somewhat familiar with
is the einstein summation convention
the einstein summation convention says
whenever you see a downstairs index
and upstairs index
the same
in this case new
it's automatically the rule that you sum over it
you don't need to write summation every time
so whenever you see a repeated index
as long as one of them is
upstairs and one of them is downstairs
downstairs
don't bother writing the summation sign
it's implicit implicit in
the conventions in the notation
all right so this operation here
just has the effect of changing the sign
of the time component
now i should warn you
depending on who's writing the equations
it's not just the
this can sometimes be plus one
minus one minus one minus one
or minus one plus one plus
one plus one there are different conventions
i happen to like this one
almost everybody else i know likes the other one
unless they're
relativists relativists who study general
relativity like the convention i use
uh...
so
it's one of these conventions that never quite settled down
and you know it's it's it's it's
like Republicans and Democrats or Jews and
Muslims they hate each other like all
hell and there are those who use one
convention and those who use the other
convention and when I'm with one group
of people I use one when I'm with
the other group of people I use the other
and so far I haven't been killed about
over it okay we'll use this one now
question yeah you don't do you
need the summation of that normal matrix
multiplication just gives you a mu
lower mu matrix multiplication really means
multiply this by this plus this by this
plus this by this plus this by this now
in this case you multiply this by this
and you multiply this by this and you
this case it's just trivial but more
generally if Ada was not the unit matrix
if it was something else if it
was some other matrix okay some general matrix
it would be this times this plus
this times this plus this times this plus
this times that so yeah there would be
a summation but Einstein simply got fed up
writing summation symbols he just
realized every and every equation
he was ever writing down whenever there
was an index one upstairs and one
downstairs he was always summing over it
he cleverly said I will invent the
Einstein summation convention and that's it
all right good incidentally an index
like new here doesn't actually have a
value it's a dummy index it's a thing
you sum over this expression depends on mu
but it doesn't depend on new new is a
summation index a summation index is a value
of mu and mu is a summation of mu
and mu by mu what's amazing about
this theory is that it's only the shiningIV
in joking nanol ganz or something that when you
look at practice expression doesn't depend on
it's just sum over nu over me
upon is used toٌl or New over Now let's
go one step further the
quantity wim k storm big wim
k storm my damage they
soon we get some不多 but not enough altitude would be
limited to this pararimi Kotori of
the extra current can프라리아 that idea is
called a data limit write x shake
upper index is called a contravariant index
and the thing with the lower index
is called a covariant vector index.
Upper it's contravariant,
lower it's
covariant,
but I don't use that terminology because I always forget
which is which.
I just call them upper and lower.
Okay,
it's easier to remember.
Alright,
so A with an upper index and A
with a lower index and you go between
them with this matrix Eta.
You can also go back,
but I'll leave that to you
to figure out how to do that.
In fact,
you do it the same way.
Okay,
now let's take
a mu,
a mu.
This is summed over.
Why is it summed over?
Because by the Einstein
convention,
a repeated index one upper
and one lower is summed over.
So let's see
what this means.
This is equal to
a
t,
a t plus a x,
a x plus the same thing for y and z.
I'll write the y component,
but I won't bother writing the z component.
Now the space components of
the covariant and contravariant vectors are the same.
So this is just a x squared.
So this is a x squared.
This is just a x squared.
And it doesn't matter whether
you put it upstairs or downstairs.
Likewise,
this one is a y squared.
Does it have a minus sign?
Nope.
Not yet.
Why doesn't it have a minus sign?
Because when you plug in the
fact that the lower index
here gives you minus a t,
this becomes,
let's say,
a t.
So you
have a s
sworn up.
It will sangat a t squared.
In other words,
this notation here says some,
literally some.
No minus signs in here.
But the minus sign comes in for the simple reason
that when you lower the index it calls lowering the
The origin of lower indexing changes
the sin of the time component.
So a t upper times a
t lower depends a normal time.
If I make mon ergu,
you can put it opposite.
is minus a t squared
So you don't have to
In fact,
you mustn't put any extra minus signs in here
All you have to do is remember what
the meaning of a upper and a lower are
Well this is exactly the quantity
that we think is a scalar
It's the difference of the square of
the time component and the space components
In other words,
it's this quantity here except with an overall minus sign
It starts out with a minus
sign here and a plus sign here
But whatever it is,
it's clearly a scalar
It's clearly a scalar
And so we see an example
of building scalars out of vectors
And how do we do it?
We do it by soaking up all the indexes
It's called contracting the indices
Contracting the indices means
We're going to get a number of vectors
And craving index,
not an index
2 induction spectra That means when
you see 2 indices which
are the same An upper and
a lower You sum over
them This quantity With
an upper
andd a lower index sum Is a scalar
So why don't
we write as Debbie as a row matrix Take again
You're right,
I think if we wanted to be purists,
we might,
but I think we would.
But this is what it is.
This is what its components are.
Okay?
And this thing is a scalar.
What's that?
That's true.
Yeah,
yeah,
you're right.
Okay.
All right.
Okay,
I'm not going to...
We know what we did.
We know exactly what we did.
We could also write this in another way.
We could write this,
since a lower mu...
Well,
let's change the summation index here.
Let's call it a nu.
I haven't changed the expression.
I've just changed the dummy index there.
But now let's look...
Oh,
no,
I didn't want to change it.
I wanted to leave it.
Mu.
But now,
what I want,
what I want to do is use for a mu.
It is eta mu nu a nu.
A mu is equal to eta mu nu a nu.
So here's another way to write it.
You sum over mu and nu with the matrix eta.
It's the same thing.
All it stands for is a
times squared minus a space squared.
That's all it stands for.
But it's a neat way to write it
where we don't have to keep rewriting x squared,
y squared,
z squared,
and so forth.
So that's the first notational device.
So is it true that when you
use the Greek letters for subscript and superscript,
it always refers to the whole...
Yeah.
Whenever you use the Greek index,
mu and nu,
it refers to all four components.
If you want to refer just to the three components,
you usually use Latin indices.
Sometimes i and j,
sometimes m and n,
depending on who's writing.
Yeah.
Right.
Okay.
So this is a scalar.
Now,
what about...
Let's consider something else.
Let's take two four vectors.
Take two four vectors a and b.
A mu,
b mu.
That looks like it might be a scalar.
It's got no indices.
All the indices are in the same place.
The indices are summed over.
Question.
Is it a scalar?
Yes,
it is a scalar.
But let's prove it.
Oh,
well,
we need one thing to prove it.
To prove that it's a scalar,
all we really need is a statement that the sum of
two scalars and the difference of two scalars is also a scalar.
If you have two things,
you and I agree upon what
they are because we're in different frames,
but we agree.
We can add them and subtract them,
and we'll still agree about the values of the two.
The sum and difference.
So sums and differences of scalars are scalars.
Let's prove that this is a scalar.
That's easy.
All you do is you write a
plus b mu times a plus b mu.
Oh,
sorry,
mu.
Now,
this is a scalar.
A plus b is a four vector.
And if you take any four vector and consider it,
you get a four vector.
And if you subtract it with itself,
it's a scalar.
So this is a scalar.
Now subtract from this.
Take a look at what we have.
We have an a mu.
We have the a's.
The a a terms and the b
b terms are the same in both sides.
All that's different is the a b.
So we'll be left over when we
do this with an a mu b mu.
Oh,
incidentally,
here's something to prove.
This is the same thing as a mu b mu.
It doesn't matter.
You can put the ups,
downs,
and the downs up.
You get the same thing.
The difference is that you can put the ups,
downs,
and the downs up.
The difference between these two things is
just four times a mu b mu.
So here's a scalar.
Here's another scalar.
The difference between them is basically just a times b.
A mu b mu.
So if I take any two four
vectors and contract them in this way,
I get another scalar.
So it's a slight generalization of just
saying that a a is a scalar.
Take any four vectors.
With any other four vector,
it's also a scalar.
It's also a scalar.
Is there any analogy one can go
to like the dot product of vectors?
What's that?
The dot product of normal vectors and the cross product.
Yeah,
yeah.
The dot products.
The dot products,
except with a funny minus sign.
It's the Lorentz or the
Minkowski version of the dot product.
Right.
And the eta facilitates the change of sign.
That's all that's going on.
Okay,
now.
Let's take a scalar.
A scalar field.
Let's take a scalar field.
Phi of x.
X now stands for x and t.
If I write a thing like
this and I don't say otherwise,
it really means it's a function of all four coordinates.
And let's consider the difference
of phi at two neighboring points.
If you want to,
if phi is a scalar and we
consider its difference at two neighboring points,
and we agree on the values
of phi at each of those points,
we will agree on the difference between them.
And so,
oh,
I need a theorem.
It's a theorem which I won't prove.
I will tell you the statement.
It's something you can easily prove by yourself.
Here's the theorem.
Supposing you have.
Let's see how to say this.
Yeah.
Supposing you have a known four vector.
To say it's a four vector means
that it transforms in a certain way.
It's not just a statement that there are four components.
It means when you
transform it under Lorentz transformations,
it transforms in a certain way.
Supposing you have a four vector.
Number one.
And number two,
another quantity,
b mu.
Such that,
then when you multiply a mu
times b mu and sum over mu,
you get something which is a scalar.
In other words,
you get something which doesn't
depend on the frame of reference.
You know this is a four
vector and you don't know about this.
Then it's possible to prove that if you
know that this product is independent of reference frame,
that b is also a four vector.
That it also transforms as a four vector.
We'll use that in a moment.
It's sort of obvious.
If a is a four vector
and a times b is a scalar,
then b is a four vector.
Not too hard to prove.
Okay,
now let's take the difference
of phi at two neighboring points.
If we agree about the values of phi,
we will agree about the values of their difference.
And so we will say the difference
is something which we will agree about.
We'll call it for the moment a scalar.
Alright,
what is the difference between
phi at two neighboring points,
infinitesimally separated?
The answer is you differentiate phi
with respect to each of the coordinates,
multiply it.
This means derivative of phi with respect to t times dt plus derivative of phi with
respect to x times dx plus derivative of phi with respect to y and so forth.
This is the difference.
So what is the small change in
phi in going from one point to another?
Well,
phi is a scalar.
And so we will agree about
the value of the difference of phi.
dx itself is clearly a four vector.
It was the basic four vector that we started with.
Small differences,
small displacements.
This is a four vector and
the whole thing is a scalar.
What does it tell you about this?
It tells you it's a four vector.
The derivative of phi with respect to coordinate,
it's a complex of four quantities.
It stands for derivative of phi with respect to t,
derivative of phi with respect to x,
and so forth.
So the upper mu in the
denominator is like a lower mu.
Yeah.
Is that the notation?
Yes.
That's what I was going to say.
Right.
In order for this to make sense as a product,
as a product of this type,
this had better,
the d phi by dx had
better correspond to a covariant vector
if the derivative corresponds to a contravariant vector.
So what we find out is that
derivatives of phi with respect to x,
the complex of them,
the set of them,
form a four vector,
but they form the covariant components of a four vector.
The covariant components like a mu.
All right.
So now we know something else.
We know that derivatives of a
scalar with respect to x mu,
are a covariant vector,
and it's sometimes just written as d sub mu phi.
The index being a lower index here
to indicate that it's a covariant thing.
All right.
Good.
Well now we can use a
notational device to invent d mu phi.
What is d mu phi with the upper index here?
It's actually just exactly the same things here,
except the time component having the opposite sign.
Okay.
So let's write out the meaning of these symbols.
d mu phi stands for the complex of things.
d t phi,
or d phi by d t,
and d phi by d x,
y,
and z.
What about this new symbol,
d mu phi,
with the index upstairs?
It's the same set of things except minus.
Okay.
So it's minus d phi by d t,
and d phi by d x.
All right.
So it's a bunch of notation,
but all it's keeping track of is squares
of time components minus squares of space components.
So squares of space components
minus squares of time components.
That's all it's doing.
But it's neat.
Finally.
We can construct a new scalar.
Phi was a scalar.
The derivatives of phi form a four vector,
but now we can form a new scalar.
The new scalar is composed
out of these two four vectors,
or out of the four vector.
What is it?
We just take d mu phi,
d mu phi.
And sum over mu.
What does it stand for?
It stands for something we wrote down earlier.
d phi by d t squared minus
plus d phi by d x squared.
Sorry.
d phi by d x squared plus
the same thing for y and z.
In other words,
it's the thing we wrote down with a minus sign.
There's an extra minus sign here.
It's the thing that we wrote down
for the Lagrangian for the scalar field.
What is this telling us?
It's telling us that the
scalar field Lagrangian is a scalar.
The Lagrangian itself,
not the scalar field.
The scalar field is a scalar
because we said it was a scalar.
It means it didn't transform when you,
Lorenz,
transformed it.
But this little exercise here in
notation tells us that this quantity here
is also a scalar.
Why is that good?
Why is it good that the Lagrangian is a scalar?
And the reason...
Is that Lagrangian or Laplacian?
No,
no.
This is not the Laplacian.
This is the Lagrangian.
The Laplacian is composed out of second derivatives.
These are squares of first derivatives.
The Lagrangian,
okay,
in this language,
the Lagrangian for the scalar field
is equal to minus one half
d mu phi d mu phi.
And it is just time derivative squared,
one half,
time derivative squared,
minus space derivatives squared.
We could add things to this Lagrangian.
I won't do it now,
but we could add other things to this Lagrangian.
But the rule is the Lagrangian should be a scalar.
What's the value of saying the Lagrangian?
The Lagrangian is a scalar.
It says the action is
the same in every reference frame.
If you have a scalar,
a quantity which doesn't depend on frame of reference,
and you integrate it over all spacetime,
then the result doesn't depend on which frame of reference
it's been evaluated in.
So if your principle of physics
is the principle of least action,
and the action doesn't depend
on which frame it's written in,
then the same action principle
will give you equations of motion
in each frame which have the
same form in every reference frame.
In other words,
it will give you equations which are invariant
under Lorentz transformations.
So much of studying field theory
is really the construction of invariant Lagrangians,
construction of various kinds of fields,
scalars,
vectors,
other kinds of fields which we haven't discussed yet,
tensors,
spinners,
constructing out of these
objects Lagrangians which are scalars.
Why?
Because you want to build equations which
are the same in every reference frame.
You want your equations to be Lorentz invariant.
That's the...
And we'll use that.
We're going to use that over and
over and over again in what follows.
The tricks of index manipulation.
But then when we actually
come to write down real equations
that we have to solve,
we of course have to know what this means.
We have to know that it means
a times squared minus a space squared.
Okay,
that's notation for you.
Yeah?
When you were doing Lagrangians in Newtonian physics before,
would it require the Lagrangian to
be invariant under the first term?
Or would it require the Lagrangian
to be invariant under the second term?
Well,
we didn't talk much about it.
Right,
we didn't.
Now,
we didn't talk about relativity very much,
but there is a non-relativistic version of relativity.
Yes,
there is.
The special theory of relativity entails two things.
It entails the rule of law.
First,
the rule that the laws of physics
are the same in every reference frame.
And second,
that it's a law of physics
that light moves with a certain velocity.
Combine them together,
light moves with the same velocity in every frame.
If you leave out the statement about light,
then ordinary Newtonian or Galilean physics,
F equals m a type physics,
does have a relativity associated with it.
It's not the relativity of Lorentz transformations,
it's the relativity of the limit of Lorentz transformations
when the speed of light goes to infinity.
Let's talk about that for a minute.
We didn't talk about it.
Let's write down Lorentz transformations and take the limit.
X prime is equal to x minus vt
divided by square root of 1
minus v squared over c squared.
T prime is equal to 2.
T minus xv over square root of
1 minus v squared over c squared.
But I'm not quite right.
I think I have to divide this
by c squared to get the units right.
This is the,
and of course we have two others.
Y prime is equal to y
and z prime is equal to z.
We didn't speak much about this,
but we could take the limit of these transformation rules
as the speed of light gets very,
very big.
What happens to them?
Well,
the square root and the denominator here just becomes 1.
So it's just x prime
is equal to x minus vt.
Well,
that's familiar.
That's just the change of a coordinate.
Before anybody ever heard of
the special theory of relativity,
this is what they would have written down.
What about this one over here?
Again,
taking c to infinity,
this becomes 1.
But now we have x times v over c squared.
When c goes to infinity,
this goes to 0.
That's just t prime equals t.
So,
yes,
there is an invariance
of nonrelativistic Newtonian mechanics.
It's called Galilean invariance.
And it requires the equations
to be invariant under these replacements.
This replacement is trivial.
It just says that all observers,
all frames of reference share the same time.
Simultaneity is the same for everybody.
So that's easy.
And this is just the usual change of reference frame
from one inertial frame to another.
So when people say that the equations of physics
are the same in every inertial reference frame,
it's a statement of relativity.
It is a statement of relativity.
And in fact,
when we write down f equals ma,
typically those equations are invariant under this.
We didn't discuss it,
but they are.
Other questions?
The transformation properties for
a covariant and a contravariant,
the difference is just a change in d?
A sign of d?
No,
no,
not quite.
Let's do it.
Okay.
Almost.
Well,
let's work it out.
A prime t is equal to at minus vax squared,
1 minus v squared,
and so forth.
And a prime x is,
of course,
ax minus v at.
Usual thing.
Okay.
Now we just write that a prime
t is the same as minus at here.
At here is the same as minus at here.
A with an upper index t here is the
same as a with a lower index t here.
What about a superscript x?
That's the same as a lower superscript x,
only the time components change.
And so these just go downstairs.
Okay.
So let's see.
So I think you're right.
I think that it just
seems to just change the sign.
Okay.
Yeah.
I'm a little confused about when a,
a,
what I think of as a scalar value function
with some coordinate system,
when that would not be a scalar.
In other words,
define any function there,
it might have no physical meaning whatsoever,
and you just say,
well,
when you look at it in its other coordinate system,
that,
that
function at this point transformed,
transformed,
transformed.
So what would you say is the energy density?
Oh,
energy density.
Pardon?
Energy density.
Energy density of a,
um,
of a gas.
The energy of a gas,
density of a gas in a frame
of reference in which the gas is in
a box and the box is at rest,
there's a certain energy density.
If you're at rest and
you look at the energy density,
there's a certain energy density.
If you're moving fast,
relatively fast,
you're moving at a certain speed.
So in that relationship to that box,
the energy density in that box is a lot larger.
So energy density is something which we won't agree on.
So I guess what I would say then is that,
um,
what you mean is that a scalar function
is some physical quantity that in
every reference frame is described as something.
Well,
I don't get that.
And,
and that,
that transforms,
I wouldn't do,
okay.
Right.
When I say we agree about its value,
I mean if we measure it.
We agree about its value.
Right.
Yeah.
I don't just mean we agree
because we're nice to each other.
I mean we agree because we made
the measurement and we compared the measurements.
Right.
Um,
so energy density is a good example.
Uh,
there are lots of them.
the,
uh,
components of the four velocity of a,
of a system.
Time component of a four velocity is
not the same in different reference frames.
Other questions?
Okay.
If not,
we'll,
uh,
um,
move on.
This,
this,
this is all very easy stuff.
It's very easy.
It's just notation.
But,
uh,
until you learn it.
Okay.
It's a little bit unfamiliar.
Let's talk about waves.
Let's look at the wave equation.
Let's look at the wave equation and solve it.
Let's solve the wave equation.
Let's imagine we have some wave field.
And it satisfies,
oh,
let's,
let's even begin by writing down a Lagrangian.
Let's write down a Lagrangian.
We've already written down a Lagrangian.
But I want to write a slight extension of it.
Here it is.
The phi by dt squared minus the phi by the,
now I'm going to write it out in detail because,
uh,
also y and z.
I'm not going to write down the y.
Then they come in with the same sign as this.
We always put a one-half in.
So we have a one-half there
in front of the whole thing.
Okay.
And I'm going to add one more term.
The one more term is also a scalar.
It does not involve derivatives.
It's a function of phi.
And the simplest function of
phi that I can think of,
well,
we could just add phi.
That would be a simple function of phi.
But it's going to make a slightly more complicated one.
Phi squared.
Okay.
So including the one-half,
we're going to write with
minus a parameter which I'm going
to call mu squared phi squared over two.
Oh,
no,
it's already got a two in it.
Now this is the field
theory analog of the harmonic oscillator.
That's all this is.
It's the field theory analog of the harmonic oscillator.
If we were talking about a harmonic oscillator
and we called the coordinate of the harmonic,
the coordinate of the oscillator phi,
we call the coordinate of the oscillator phi,
we would write down phi dot squared over two for the
kinetic energy and then for the potential energy minus a spring constant,
which I'm calling mu squared minus
mu squared phi squared over two.
This would be the good old harmonic oscillator.
And the only difference is it now
has some space derivatives in the Lagrangian.
Let's take this Lagrangian,
work out the equations,
and then solve it,
find its solutions.
Well,
it's first of all derivative of
L with respect to time derivative.
That's just d phi by dt.
Then we differentiate it with respect to time.
We get second derivative of
phi with respect to t squared.
This,
of course,
is the analog of the acceleration term.
The acceleration in F equals ma.
But then we get minus d second phi by dx
squared minus same thing with y minus same thing with z.
And that has to be
equal to dl by d phi.
So that's equal to minus mu squared phi.
When you differentiate mu squared phi
squared with a factor of two,
you just get minus mu squared phi.
Or if we want to
put everything on the left side,
let's put everything on the left
side plus mu squared equals zero.
This is a nice simple equation.
It has a name.
Anybody know what the name of this equation is?
No?
The Klein-Gordon equation.
Yeah.
This is the Klein-Gordon equation.
Klein-Gordon,
Klein and Gordon,
I don't know if they were
connected with each other or not.
But I have a feeling Klein was
a German and Gordon was probably a Brit,
so they probably were not collaborating.
But in any case,
in some combination or another,
they wrote down this equation.
This was their attempt before Schrodinger to write
down the equation for a quantum mechanical particle.
They made the mistake of trying to be relativistic.
Had they not tried to be relativistic,
they would have written down
the Schrodinger equation and been very,
very famous.
They wrote down the relativistic version
of it and became much less famous.
Famous among physicists,
but not famous outside of the physics world.
Only one person here knew
that it was the Klein-Gordon equation.
The Schrodinger equation is somewhat similar,
but it only has a first derivative with respect
to time and it has some i's in it.
But this is called the Klein-Gordon equation.
And its connection with quantum
mechanics is not important right now.
What we want to do is solve it.
There are lots of solutions to it,
zillions of solutions,
but they're all built up out of plane waves.
The solution to this kind of
equations are sums of plane waves.
So let's write down a plane wave in exponential form.
It's useful when thinking about oscillating systems
to pretend that the coordinate is complex.
And at the end,
just take the real part of it.
We do that for the harmonic oscillator,
we do it for all sorts of oscillating systems.
Look for solutions which we allow to be
complex functions and later take the real parts.
I'll give you an example as we go along.
What kind of solutions are we going to look for?
We're going to look for
solutions which first of all oscillate.
I can't remember if I want plus or minus here.
Minus for positive energy solutions.
E to the minus i omega t.
That's an oscillation with time with frequency omega.
And now we're going to look
for solutions which oscillate in space,
which means they're e to
the i kx of some type.
E to the i,
and we can write here kx times x.
Plus ky times y.
Plus kz times z.
Well these are three numbers.
Kx and ky and kz are just three numbers.
They're called the wave numbers.
Or the wave vector.
Kx,
ky,
and kz.
And this is the form of
a solution that we'll look for.
We'll see.
Maybe there is no solution like this.
We'll check.
Alright.
First of all we can rewrite
this in a kind of neat way.
We could rewrite it as e
to the i k mu x mu.
Where does that come from?
Well if I think of k as
a four vector with components minus omega.
Do I want minus omega?
I think so.
And kx,
ky.
And kz.
If we think of the four components
of a complex of things involving omega,
kx,
ky,
and kz.
And I group them together in this form here.
Call them.
Think of them for the moment.
They may not really be.
They are actually a four vector.
But think of them as defining a four vector.
Then what's up in the exponent
here is just k mu x mu.
Time component omega times t.
X component of k times x.
So it's a nice little notation.
But we won't.
I'm not going to use it now.
I'm just going to use it in this form here.
Let's see what happens if
we try to solve this equation.
What is the second derivative of
phi with respect to t squared?
Well,
what happens when you differentiate an e to
the i omega t with respect to time twice?
That will multiply what you
have here by minus omega squared.
So let's call this the.
This is our guess at phi.
What happens if we differentiate
it twice with respect to t?
We get minus omega squared times phi.
What happens if we differentiate with respect to x?
We get kx squared with respect to y twice.
Ky squared.
So altogether we'll get minus omega squared plus
kx squared plus ky squared plus kz squared.
But we're not finished.
We still have plus m squared here.
So there's plus m squared.
And we're going to have
minus omega squared phi equals zero.
Well,
it's very easy now to find the solution.
You simply say omega must equal the square root of
kx squared plus ky squared plus kz squared plus m squared.
In other words,
you just have to find the solution.
You just set what's in
the bracket here equal to zero.
And you have a solution.
This is just telling you what the
frequency is in terms of the wave number.
Frequency,
square root of kx squared plus ky
squared plus kz squared plus m squared.
That's the solution of the Klein-Gordon equation.
There are two possible solutions.
A square root like this can be plus or minus.
It'll solve the equation whether you
put plus omega or minus omega here.
And of course,
for every kx,
ky,
and kz,
there are two solutions with plus omega and minus omega.
Or the plus or minus roots of the square root.
Those are the solutions of the Klein-Gordon equation.
And we're going to come back to it many,
many times.
This is the quantum mechani- or this
is the classical field version of an equation
which describes a quantum mechanical particle with mass m,
energy omega,
and momentum k.
This is e equals square root
of p squared plus m squared.
There's some Planck's constants in there
that I didn't tell you about,
but they're there.
All right.
So these equations aren't hard.
They're simple.
They're linear equations.
You add solutions.
And at the end of the day,
after you've constructed your solution in this way,
you can take the real part of it.
And the real part of it,
if the field is supposed to be real,
then if it's supposed to be a real number,
you just take the real part of it.
Okay,
any questions?
We're getting,
you know,
we're moving along now,
and we're talking about real stuff.
Yeah?
Where did the Klein-Gordon equation come from?
I mean,
did you use something to the Lagrangian to take it?
Here's Lagrangian.
I made up this Lagrangian.
If you look for,
okay,
good.
Okay.
This is pretty much the unique
Lagrangian which would lead to linear equations.
A linear equation.
We'll come back to why we're looking for linear equations,
but for the moment,
this is just an example.
At the moment,
it's an example.
The next step going from
that Lagrangian to the Klein-Gordon equation.
It took the next derivative of
each term with respect to the variable.
Yeah.
Derivative of Lagrangian with respect to d phi dt.
That's just d phi dt.
And then you differentiate that with respect to time.
Right,
right.
Yeah.
Same thing.
And you add the second partial with
respect to x and with respect to y.
Yeah.
Remember,
remember what the rules are.
Okay,
let's write down the Euler-Lagrange equation for a field.
d by dx mu.
All right,
we'll now write them in a neat form.
d by dx mu of partial of L
with respect to d phi by dx mu.
And that means sum over mu.
And then,
let's double-dropping that feature.
Here's the next part if you have any questions.
So atひ above L minus D
plus X defy by dx mu,
observe,
if you have a fraction of L
in terms of pi and pull-through is notihad.
d by dx mod facto is a divine number.
But at check of time,
you can see that dib is zero.
This means that by taking out
zero at 10 to the nthdır,
index,
but this is of the form of
a lower index times an upper index.
And you can see that this
equation has some nice relativistic structure.
Upper indices and lower indices contracted,
and everything is a scalar.
What in nature obeys the Klein-Gordon equation?
Scalar particles,
the Higgs boson.
The Higgs boson.
Let's go back to something else.
Let's go back to the action for a particle.
I made this up,
of course.
but I was using some rules.
The rules are that it should
be relativistically invariant and fairly simple.
So we generalize.
This thing times the square
root of 1 minus v squared.
We generalize and put in minus m plus phi.
That's a guess.
I mean,
that's something you can write down.
Can you think of anything else?
Yeah,
you can think of lots of other things.
But this is one thing you could write down.
Now notice that this has an interesting property.
If for some reason or another,
phi was not equal to 0,
for some reason or another
you had a region of space
in which phi was not equal to 0,
but was equal to some fixed value,
for whatever reason,
then effectively this particle will move
with a mass m plus phi.
For all practical purposes,
if phi is a constant,
it just shifts the mass of the particle.
Well,
it's even possible that you might have a massless particle
with no term at all,
and the entire mass is due to some field
not being equal to 0 in some region of space.
If for some reason there's an environment
in which phi is not equal to 0,
it can not only shift the mass,
it can create a mass for a particle
that didn't even have one to begin with.
That's the nature of the Higgs boson.
It creates mass.
In this sense,
in roughly this sense.
And,
because it creates masses for particles,
such as quarks and other particles,
because it creates masses,
the presence of those particles will,
where are we,
will react back on the field
and create field.
Particles create field.
Field affects particles.
Higgs boson is a particular case.
When you said you take
the real part of the solution,
does that mean the imaginary part adds up to 0?
Does it mean you just throw away the real part?
It just means you write it as the
sum of a real part and imaginary part.
Let's write it.
Let's take a solution.
So where was our solution?
I lost it.
Well,
it was of the form
e to the i omega t
minus k dot,
k mu,
k dot x,
let's call it,
minus k dot x.
The i multiplies everything.
So,
okay,
so,
this is equal to cosine
of omega t minus kx
plus i sine omega t
minus kx.
Both the real and imaginary parts,
if something is equal to 0,
you know,
we went through an exercise,
set all of this equal to 0,
if all of this is equal to 0,
it means both its real and
imaginary part are equal to 0.
So both the real and imaginary part
are solutions of the equations.
A construction like this gives you two solutions,
two real solutions,
cosine,
omega t,
and sine.
Cosine and sine.
You can add them together.
You can add them together with real coefficients too,
and they're still solutions.
But,
you know,
exponentials are a neat trick for facilitating
taking derivatives.
That's the reason we used exponentials,
not because the field is imaginary or complex,
but because it just helps us do the algebra
of taking derivatives.
But once we have a solution like this,
the real and imaginary parts
are both separately solutions.
They're both plane waves.
They're waves in,
in what are they?
They're 90 degrees out of phase.
If this is a wave that
moves down the axis like this,
such that at time t equals 0,
the,
uh,
the wave is,
peak is located here,
that's the cosine,
then the sine is just another wave
that's displaced
like that.
You can add them together,
you can subtract them,
and they're still solutions.
Okay.
Any other questions?
Yes.
Can you explain the superconductor case?
What?
哈哈
Where did that come from?
From the giving particles mass,
particles acquire mass
when a field appears
Can I explain?
Yeah,
I can explain superconductor,
but not yet
We haven't done any electricity,
any magnetism
The superconducting case is a situation
where the electromagnetic field gets a mass
And it gets a mass
from a similar thing like this
But not at this point,
no,
I don't think you want me to,
no
Yeah,
it's certainly a connected phenomenon
But we haven't gotten into,
it's,
the answer is that
It is an effect
It is an effect where a scalar field,
where the presence of a scalar,
sorry
Where the presence of a scalar field
affects the photon and gives it a mass
But not yet,
yeah
So what you said about the Higgs boson,
these have been mathematical conclusions
Is there any way that it's possible
to visualize how a Higgs boson creates mass?
Yes
Here it is,
here it is,
here it is
I mean,
a physical way,
do we think of a particle flying through space somewhere
And spitting out masses as it goes along,
or what?
No,
no,
it's just,
this is what phi does to it,
it shifts its mass
That's it,
there's no other,
there is nothing else,
that's it
So different masses,
different couplet bosons?
Yeah,
that's right,
I didn't put the G here,
did I?
So
Right,
so different coupling constants
could lead to different masses,
right
And in fact they do
The strength,
the strength,
the strength with which a
particle couples to the Higgs field
Will determine its mass
When you compute its momentum
Okay
Yeah
Phi is the mass term
Yeah,
that's right
But in every respect it functions as a mass term
And if the Higgs field were zero,
all particles would be massless?
Not all particles,
no,
no
Quarks would be,
Z bosons,
W bosons would be massless
The Higgs boson wouldn't be
And protons and neutrons wouldn't be massless
Protons and neutrons do not get
their mass from the Higgs phenomenon
And
Electrons,
neutrinos would be massless
Electrons and neutrinos would be massless
Protons and neutrons,
not
Quarks,
in some sense,
yes
But protons and neutrons not
If the Higgs field went away one day
Electrons would become massless
That would be a disaster for atoms
Because the size of an atom is governed
by the inverse of the mass of the electron
And if the mass of the
electron were to go to zero
The atom would become infinitely big
And that would not be good for you
But if the mass of the
electron were to go to zero
With protons and neutrons would be virtually unaffected
Very,
very weakly affected,
not very much
Um,
right
Yeah
Well,
I mean,
it is true that a world without a Higgs boson
Would be a bad world for your survival
Many,
many things would go wrong
And,
um,
as I said,
not the least of all
Would be the electron would become massless
And when it did so,
uh,
atoms would just,
uh
Have no,
uh,
no cohe- no,
um
The electron would become completely unlocalized
Okay
For more,
please visit us at stanford.edu