Stanford University.
Alright,
what I wanted to talk
about before going into Maxwell's equations,
we've talked about the motion of
a charged particle in an electromagnetic field.
We have not talked about the
dynamics of the electric and magnetic field,
in other words,
the field equations,
or for that matter,
the related effect of charges on the electromagnetic field.
We're going to do a bit of that tonight.
This time,
not starting with the action principle.
I'll tell you why.
We'll come back to the action principle.
But first I thought,
we sort of jumped to
some very formal and mathematical technology.
I had occasion last week,
actually while I was in Belgium,
visiting Mrs.
Salford.
She was the Solveig of the Solveig family,
who were the people who first brought
together probably the very first physics conferences
that took place,
ever,
in the early 1900s.
I had occasion to look at Einstein's first paper.
I had to struggle through some of it in German,
just because some historical discussion came up about it.
And I looked at it.
And I read the first paper.
It's a basic paragraph.
The title of the paper in English
is on the electrodynamics of moving objects.
And Einstein expresses,
I had read this long ago,
in fact more than once,
and I had more or less forgotten about it,
expresses extremely clearly what his
logic and what his motivation is.
And I'd like to come back to
it and just discuss it for a moment,
because it is deeply
connected with the transformation properties
of the electromagnetic field tensor.
I want to go through it.
If you have access to Einstein's first paper,
it's worth,
first of all,
it's worth reading.
You can now,
I'm sure you can understand it now.
But if nothing else,
just reading that first paragraph is,
it's marvelous.
I wish I had it here.
I would read you the first paragraph,
but I don't.
But he expresses,
the puzzle,
which by that time no longer puzzled him,
but the puzzle of the
invariance of certain electromagnetic phenomena,
that in fact you describe in
different ways in different reference frames.
In one reference frame you blame
a certain effect on a magnetic field.
In another reference frame you
blame it on an electric field.
And he says,
look,
there's no real difference between the phenomena
viewed in the two frames,
but we describe them in a completely different way.
There's something there that we should understand,
that we should understand the
transformation from one frame to another,
and why two different descriptions give
rise to exactly the same phenomena.
In other words,
he's talking about relativity.
And the two phenomena he's talking about,
or the single phenomena he's talking about,
is of course the effect of
electromagnetic fields on moving and stationary charges.
He,
more explicitly,
he talks about charges moving in wires,
in other words,
currents.
It doesn't matter very much whether
the charges are moving in wires,
or whether they're just moving in free space.
He might have talked about
charged particles moving in space,
just ordinary charged particles,
the reason he didn't was probably because at
that time it was not easy to see
the motion of a charged particle,
it was much easier to
push a particle through a wire,
a charged particle through a wire.
But in any case,
here was the situation he was talking about.
Here's your three dimensions of space.
Let's suppose that they're,
what can we call them,
we can call them x,
let's see,
x,
y,
and z,
I guess this would be y,
and this would be z,
and supposing,
oh I think I have in my
notes here that I call this y,
which is probably inconsistent with the right hand rule,
but never mind,
x,
y,
z,
and let there be a magnetic
field pointing out of the blackboard,
in other words,
b,
y.
A magnetic field,
and that's the only component of the electromagnetic field,
what would create such a magnetic field?
Well,
it could be the poles of a magnet.
The two poles of a
magnet are a pole over here,
and another pole over here,
with a magnetic field into the blackboard,
let's see,
north pole,
south pole,
magnetic field coming,
I know that doesn't look like
it's coming out of the blackboard,
but think of it as out of the blackboard,
in other words,
along the direction y,
and let there also be a charged particle,
and the charged particle is moving along the x-axis.
It's moving along the x-axis in this direction.
In our frame of reference,
all there is is the magnetic field,
and the particle is moving.
Alright,
now in Einstein's imagination,
he really was thinking about a wire in this direction,
the wire contains,
of course we know what the wire contains,
the wire contains atoms,
and the atoms are nailed in place in the wire,
they can't move,
and electrons,
and electrons in a conducting
wire can move up and down,
so really it was only the electrons that mattered,
Einstein didn't talk about electrons and
protons and neutrons and so forth,
he just talked about a current and a wire,
but he might have been
just talking about a charged particle,
and now the wire is made,
the wire or the charged particle
is made to move along the x-axis.
What happens?
What happens is a force
is exerted on the charged particle.
We call it,
and in fact Lorentz,
I don't know what Lorentz called it,
but Lorentz knew about it,
it was the Lorentz force,
v cross b,
electric charge times v cross the magnetic field,
so if the magnetic field is out of the blackboard,
the particle is being forced to move along the x-axis,
there will be a force which
is both perpendicular to the velocity
and the magnetic field,
the magnetic field is out,
velocity is this way,
so there's a force on the charged particle,
either up or down,
you're a better man than I
am if you can figure out instantly
which way it is,
whether it's up or down,
and I don't care for the moment,
yeah,
you,
right,
is it down?
Well,
that depends on whether the charge is plus or minus.
Okay.
Right.
But there's a charge along,
along,
sorry,
there's a force along the y-axis,
which for example would cause a
current to flow along the wire.
That's a description from one frame of reference
in which the effect on the charges,
the effect,
the current is produced
by the motion of a charge in a magnetic field.
Well,
Einstein then says,
wait a second,
we also know another fact,
this time keep the wire fixed,
don't move the wire,
but move the magnet.
Move the magnet,
and what happens when you move a magnet
and you have a wire like that?
Well,
according to,
according to Einstein and everybody else at the time,
a moving magnetic field like that,
will create what they called an EMF,
an electromagnetic force,
which effectively means an electric field.
It creates an electric field,
taking a magnetic field which points
either into or out of the blackboard,
and moving the magnet,
creates an electric field vertically,
which has the same effect,
causes charges to flow,
or exerts a force on a stationary particle.
Imagine now,
in other words,
if there was a stationary particle,
but a moving magnet,
it would have the same effect.
So what Einstein said is,
look,
we have these,
the phenomena is the same,
of vertical force.
We have two totally different descriptions.
In one description,
the magnetic field exerts a force on a moving charge,
and the other,
the moving magnet,
creates an electric field,
and the electric field exerts
the force on the charged particle.
His attitude was,
these are the same effect.
These must be the same effect.
And the only explanation is
what looks like a magnetic field,
a pure magnetic field,
in one frame of reference,
in another frame of reference,
namely in this case,
the frame of reference that happens
to be moving with a particle,
looks like a bit,
at least a bit,
of electric field.
So,
what he said is,
electric and magnetic fields are particles,
part of the same complex of objects,
which transform into each other,
under a,
I don't,
he didn't call them Lorentz transformations,
he probably would have preferred
that they were called Einstein transformations,
I don't know,
but,
motion.
Okay,
so can we see in detail,
mathematically,
this transformation,
when,
if we have a magnetic field,
let's forget the charged particle now,
we have a magnetic field,
in your frame of reference,
there's a magnetic field pointing at it,
and that's all,
just a magnetic field,
and I move along with the charged particle,
can we see that I perceive an electric field?
Can we see it from the
transformation properties of the electromagnetic field tensor?
Okay,
so,
for that,
we need to,
explore,
a little bit,
the transformation properties of
the electromagnetic field tensor,
if,
we did some of this,
I want to come back to it,
and talk about this particular effect.
Alright,
let's remember what the electromagnetic field tensor is,
first of all.
It's a thing with two indices,
F mu nu.
It happens,
just to,
just to put all the,
put everything out on the table,
F mu nu happens to be,
expressed in terms of the vector potential,
let's write it,
although I don't think I'll use it for the moment,
d mu A nu,
minus d nu A mu,
this means,
the derivative with respect to X mu,
of the,
nu-th component of the vector potential,
minus,
the derivative with respect to X nu,
of the mu-th component.
d sub mu,
means,
d by dx mu.
Alright,
that's the,
that's the field tensor,
it's anti-symmetric,
just to,
to recall a couple of facts about it,
mu and nu,
go from one to four,
they run from time,
X,
Y,
and Z,
time is zero,
X,
Y,
and Z are one,
two,
and three,
and F naught,
N,
that's the time,
that's the mixed space-time components,
oh incidentally,
this is anti-symmetric,
and so the diagonal elements of this are zero,
but the mixed space-time components,
are electric fields,
little m and N,
now are ordinary spatial components,
mu and nu,
are space-time,
m and N are space.
Alright,
so that's,
that's the connection between the field tensor,
anti-symmetric field tensor,
and the electric field,
it happens from this equation here,
that it's the time derivative of a m,
minus the,
no sorry,
this is N,
N,
if the left-hand side has an N,
the right-hand side has to have an N,
and times the time derivative of,
no sorry,
times the N derivative of a naught,
a naught.
Alright,
that's just rewriting this for the naught,
alright,
I'm not going to use this particularly,
the expression in terms of the vector potential,
but just to remind you,
that's the electric field,
and the magnetic field,
is related to the space-space components,
and N,
and the connection is,
that the magnetic field,
is equal to the curl,
of the vector potential,
when restricted to the space components,
this expression here is connected,
is simply the components of the curl of a vector,
and so the corresponding,
the F M N,
the magnetic field is the curl,
of the space components of the vector potential,
for example,
this would say,
an example of it would be that,
B sub X,
is equal to the derivative with respect to Y,
of the Z component of the vector potential,
minus the derivative with respect to Z,
of the Y component of the vector potential,
this is just shorthand,
for these equations,
three of them,
for BX,
BY,
and BZ,
okay,
now we can summarize,
the connection,
between the electric magnetic field,
and the field tensor,
by,
writing down,
a big matrix,
a four by four matrix,
and filling in the components,
with electric and magnetic fields,
so just to,
to write that out once,
I know we've done it before,
but let's do it anyway,
F mu nu,
is a big matrix,
and in order to keep track of the elements,
we will let nu,
run horizontally,
and mu,
run vertically,
that's a standard rule,
the right,
the second element here,
runs horizontally,
the first element runs vertically,
and,
the first,
we can,
just to,
organize the matrix,
let's put some guidelines in,
it's a four by four matrix,
alright,
the diagonal elements are zero,
and the upper right hand corner here,
oh,
just to remind you,
the first row here,
is the time component,
the next one is x,
y,
and z,
and likewise,
for the rows,
time component,
x,
y,
and z,
the time,
the mixed space time components,
are electric fields,
so that means along,
here,
we have electric fields,
e x,
e y,
and e z,
minus e x,
it's anti-symmetric,
minus e y,
and minus e z,
and then the other components,
the space space components,
are components of the magnetic field,
and those get filled in,
as the y component,
no,
that's the z component,
whoops,
and then the y component,
sorry,
z component,
why is it the z component?
Because,
it is the x,
y component of f,
x,
y component means the z component of b,
you'll just have to remember that,
minus b sub y,
and b sub x,
and down here,
minus b z,
that's the anti-symmetry,
what's in the lower,
half of the matrix,
is simply,
the reflection,
except with a minus sign,
plus b sub y,
and minus b sub x,
and that's the electromagnetic field tensor,
incidentally,
just,
to,
let's see,
if I put,
here's a little exercise,
fill in the blanks,
for f mu nu,
with upper indices,
the rule is,
whenever you go from a lower index,
to an upper index,
if you have raised a time component,
you get a minus sign,
if you've raised a space component,
no minus sign,
alright,
so in fact,
it's easy to work out,
what,
f mu nu with upper components is,
it's in fact exactly the same,
except one,
slight,
difference,
let's see here,
we need some lines in here,
the only difference is,
that this is minus e x,
minus e y,
minus e z,
e x,
e y,
and e z,
why did that happen?
That happened,
because the electric component,
has one time index,
and one space index,
so when you raise the indices,
you're raising one time component,
and one space component,
and that gives you a minus sign,
the magnetic terms are the same,
are unchanged,
b z,
minus b y,
and b x,
and you can fill in the lower corner here,
it's just anti-symmetric,
alright,
so it doesn't matter which one of these you use,
you fill in the blanks,
and that's the field tensor.
I'm reading this correctly,
the magnetic components don't have any time components,
yeah,
the magnetic components are space-space components,
pure space,
so that means,
okay,
where are the space,
let's take advantage of some colored pens,
and block out here,
the space-space components,
this is time x,
y,
z,
alright,
so this green 3x3 matrix,
is the space-space components,
and they consist only of magnetic fields,
and zeros,
the mixed space-time components,
are the ones along the edges here,
okay,
now,
what do we want to do,
we want to figure out how this object,
transforms when we move from
one frame of reference to another,
in other words,
given an electromagnetic field tensor
in one frame of reference,
in which the electric and magnetic fields are,
what are written down here,
if I now move relative to it,
and let's say move along the x-axis for simplicity,
if I move along the x-axis,
what are the new components of the
electromagnetic field tensor in the new frame?
Alright,
so to work those out,
we simply have to remember,
the rules for,
transformation of tensors,
of things with indices,
tensors are just things with indices,
alright,
so let me go back first,
to the simplest of all,
well the simplest of all tensors are of course scalars,
and scalars don't transform,
they're too simple,
but,
four vectors,
in particular the four vector x mu,
x mu,
prime,
it's x,
y,
z,
and t,
or t,
x,
y,
and t,
we know how they transform,
in fact,
they transform by Lorentz transformation,
t prime is equal to t,
minus v x,
over square root of one minus v squared,
x prime is equal to x minus v t,
y prime equals y,
z prime equals z,
but we can organize this into a matrix expression,
or we can write it in two ways,
we can write it,
using the Einstein summation convention,
we introduce a matrix called L,
L for Lorentz,
mu,
nu,
x nu,
now remember we sum over nu,
this is shorthand,
for this set of four equations here,
summing over nu,
and if we do that,
we can read off the component,
or we could,
another way to think about it,
same equation,
is to line up x prime,
this is x one,
x two,
x three,
x four,
no,
sorry,
x zero,
x one,
x two,
x three,
and prime the whole thing,
I don't want to put the primes in here,
there's too many,
that'll,
make it look like it's x eleven,
or x twenty one,
or x twenty three,
I don't want to do that,
just prime on the outside,
and that's given by some matrix L,
a four by four matrix,
whose components are called mu,
nu,
times the column vector,
x naught,
x one,
x two,
x three,
same equation,
and the matrix L,
can we read off the matrix L,
sure we can read off the matrix L,
we can read off the matrix L,
from this equation here,
I'll write it down for you,
the matrix L,
that's associated with the Lorentz transformation,
is again a four by four matrix,
I put lines in so that,
just to guide my eye,
I'm not very good at keeping rows and columns neat,
so I put the lines in,
alright,
so x naught prime is a,
one over square root of,
one minus v squared here,
there's a one over square root of,
there's a v over square root,
of one minus v squared,
also here,
v over square root of,
one minus v squared,
zero,
one,
one.
ah,
sorry,
I didn't hear what you said but I
suspect you said there was a minus sign here,
is that what you said?
Thank you.
And it's correct,
of course.
The minus sign is this one over here.
And now we have it.
If this matrix is multiplied by x0,
x1,
x2,
x3,
also a.k.a.
t,
x,
y,
and z,
a.k.a.
stands for also known as,
t,
x,
y,
and z,
it simply reproduces these four equations over here.
So this is the matrix
which represents the Lorentz transformation
by velocity v along the x-axis.
All right,
now what do we do with
a tensor like F mu nu?
How do we transform it?
I will take the tensor with the upper,
the upper version of it.
Why?
Just because I already have
rules for things with upper indices.
I've written them down there.
How do you transform a thing with two upper indices?
Here we know how to transform
a thing with one upper index.
Here's the transformation for a thing with one upper index.
In fact,
you know what I'm going to do?
I'm going to change this index here.
I'm going to call it sigma.
Sigma.
It's a summation index,
and so it doesn't matter what I call it.
I'll call it sigma.
All right,
so let me write down for you,
and it's more or less obvious what to do.
You write down that F mu nu prime,
the field tensor in the new coordinates,
in other words,
in the moving reference frame,
is L mu sigma,
exactly that same object that's up
on the top of the blackboard.
That's how the mu index works.
That's associated with the transformation of the mu index.
The transformation of the new
index is you put another L
and introduce another summation index.
What do you multiply it by?
You multiply it by F sigma tau.
In other words,
the way the mu index transforms
is exactly the way it would
be if you put another L.
You would if there was only the mu index.
L mu sigma,
F sigma.
The way the new index transforms
is exactly the way a new index would transform.
L nu tau,
F tau.
When both indices are present,
that's it.
Very simple rule.
If you had an object with more indices,
you could have any number of indices,
the rule would be the same for every index
you transform the same way.
All right,
so that's the rule for transformation.
So that's the whole idea of the transformation of tensors.
And now let's try it out.
Let's see if we can figure
out what the primed tensor is.
Let's see if we can discover whether or not
there is an electric field along the x-axis.
Is that what we want?
An electric field?
Yes.
Okay.
Let's see.
Let's see if we can figure
out what the primed tensor is.
We were...
We had a particle moving along this axis here.
We had a B field coming out along the y-axis.
And we're now going to move,
so we should see a
Z component of an electric field.
The question is will we see
a Z component of electric field?
Okay.
So,
let's try it.
Let's try to compute the
Z component of the electric field
in the primed reference frame.
We can call this E prime or EZ prime.
Let's see if we can calculate that.
Now,
what is it?
What is it?
EZ is really F naught Z.
F naught Z is EZ.
I'm not going to worry about signs.
Signs are too complicated for me to keep track of.
It's either plus or minus this,
and it's not terribly important right now.
F naught Z is the Z component of...
or F time,
the mixed space-time component,
is the electric field,
the primed version of this.
That's what I would like to compute.
So,
let's say I want to compute the electric field.
Now,
let's go up to this equation and compute it.
What do we know,
incidentally?
We know something about the unprimed tensor.
What do we know about the unprimed tensor?
That it's a pure magnetic field along the Y axis.
Right?
It's a pure magnetic field along the Y axis,
the unprimed.
So,
we know that on the right-hand side,
the F sigma tau has only one component.
And what is it?
It's FxZ.
FxZ is what corresponds to By.
FxZ is By.
So,
on the right-hand side,
there will be an FxZ.
There will be two Ls.
And let's now match...
Let's now match indices.
Notice,
this mu index here matches the mu index up here.
So,
we're looking for F0Z.
There had better be a 0 index up here.
What about nu?
Nu is associated with the second index here,
and that's Z.
So,
there has to be a Z up here.
What about the lower indices,
sigma and tau?
Well,
those have to match the indices over here.
So,
that means that this one is
X and this one is Z.
What happened to the summation
that you were supposed to do
that's implicit in these formulas here?
Well,
the summation collapses to a single term
for the simple reason that we're assuming
that there's only one component of F here.
Namely,
the component FxZ.
And we're only looking for
one component on the left-hand side.
We're trying to compute a
particular component on the left-hand side.
And there only is an FxZ on the right-hand side.
We've assumed only a B
component sticking out of the blackboard.
Alright,
so now let's see.
What is...
Here is our matrix.
Let's put these things in.
What is L,
Z,
Z?
That's just one.
Okay?
So,
L,
Z,
Z is just one.
I don't think I will erase it.
I'll just put one over here.
But what about the mixed component L,
0,
X?
That's this one over here.
0,
X.
So,
this one over here
has a minus V over square
root of 1 minus V squared.
So,
this product is nothing but our
old friend V plus or minus,
not important,
V over square root of 1 minus V squared.
And the Z goes along for the ride.
Now,
what about FxZ?
What is that?
That's just the magnetic field that we started with,
right?
So,
this is just B,
B sub Y.
The original B sub Y.
And what's the left-hand side?
The left-hand side is the
electric field along the Z axis.
That's along this axis.
The electric field along the Z axis
in the moving frame of reference.
So,
in particular,
we see that it's not 0.
We started with an electric field which was 0
and a magnetic field only along the Y axis.
We subjected ourselves to a motion along the X axis.
And what do we discover?
That there is,
in fact,
a Z component of the electric field
in the new frame of reference.
But in the new frame of reference,
the electron,
or whatever it is,
is not moving.
Well,
I assumed that.
I assumed that I moved fast
enough to keep up with the electron.
And therefore,
there's no magnetic force on it.
It's at rest in my frame.
My frame,
moving with the electron.
The electron is at rest.
But nevertheless,
there is a force on it,
and the force on it is electric.
It's an electric force,
which is,
in fact,
proportional to the velocity.
This 1 minus V squared over C squared.
This is something very,
very close to 1,
as long as the velocity is not very large.
And so we discover,
in the moving frame of reference,
the same effect,
the effect which in the stationary frame of reference
was due to the magnetic field and the moving charge,
becomes an electric field
acting on a static,
stationary charge.
That was the content,
if you like,
of the first paragraph of Einstein's paper.
Of course,
no.
The content was the question.
The rest of the paper was the answer,
and this was the answer.
Okay,
so that,
wow.
That took over 40 minutes.
Holy smoke.
Well,
it took Einstein 10 years.
All right,
let's come to Maxwell's equations now.
Let's come to Maxwell's equations.
I am not going to derive
them today from an action principle.
If we went back to the first part
to our standard methodology,
usually we know what the answer
for the equations of motion is,
and then we look for
an action principle to describe it.
We could go the other way,
and next week I will go the other way
and start with the basic action principle
and derive the equations of motion
of the electromagnetic field.
Uh...
What's that?
Isn't that what you already did?
No.
Oh,
you're talking about...
We're talking about the field equations,
not the equations for the charged particle.
Okay.
There are two kinds of Maxwell's.
How many Maxwell's equations are there altogether?
I will tell you the answer.
Don't try to figure out that.
Eight.
But they come in combinations.
Vector notation converts them into four.
Eight?
One,
two,
three,
four,
five,
six,
seven,
eight.
Yes.
Eight equations.
Half of them,
four of them,
come for free.
They come for free.
They are consequences of the definitions
of the electric and magnetic fields
in terms of the vector potential.
In other words,
half of the equations are simply identities
that follow...
...from these equations
together with some identities,
some vector identities.
Identities are what an identity is.
An identity is a mathematical fact
which just follows basically from a definition.
But sometimes,
even though they just follow from a definition,
sometimes they're a little bit non-obvious.
Okay,
so let me start with two basic identities.
The first identity involves the divergence of a curl.
A now does not have to be the vector potential.
A stands for any three vector.
I'm only the three components for the moment.
A stands for a three vector.
And del cross A is the
curl of a certain three vector
which has been called A.
As I said,
A could be any three vector field.
It has to be a field
because we're going to differentiate it,
but it could be any three vector field,
whatever.
It doesn't have to be the vector potential.
Does anybody here not know the definition of the curl?
I'm going to assume everybody
knows the definition of curl divergence.
It's the divergence and gradient.
Alright,
so the first identity is...
What is the nature of this object?
What's the nature of a curl?
The nature of a curl is it's another vector.
It's another vector field.
Alright,
a curl is a vector field.
And as such,
it has a divergence.
Del dot.
Maybe I should put over here the definition
of curl and divergence,
just since we use them.
The curl of a vector
can be specified by its components.
For example,
the x component of the curl of A
is by definition dyAz minus dzAy.
And...
You cycle through going from one to the next.
You let x go to
y and y go to z.
You can work out the other two components.
Well,
I'm not going to spell them out.
You just cycle.
Let x go to y.
Let y go to z.
Let z go to x.
And cycle through them.
And you can write out the
other two components of the curl.
Definition of the curl.
Divergence of a vector,
any vector now,
del dot A for any vector,
is a scalar quantity.
And it's given by derivative with
respect to x of the x component
plus derivative with respect to y of the y component
plus derivative with respect to z of the z component.
And the last concept
is the gradient of a scalar,
which you know very well.
I'm just writing them out so that we'll have them.
The gradient of a scalar
is a vector.
And it's a vector whose components,
for example,
whose x component
is just derivative of s with respect to x.
And likewise for y and z.
Alright,
so here's the identities.
The first identity is the divergence
of a curl is always zero.
Now how do you prove that?
You prove it just by
writing out the whole damn thing.
Does anybody want to see it?
No,
nobody wants to see it,
right?
No,
no.
You just literally write out
the components of del cross A
and then differentiate them according to the rule
for a divergence.
And you will find out
that there's a whole bunch of cancellations.
Typically the terms will involve something like
derivative with respect to x times
the derivative with respect to y
which is d by dx,
d by dy
of some A something
minus the derivatives,
the same derivatives in the opposite order
and you'll say that that's zero.
So just a simple identity.
Divergence of any curl is equal to zero.
And the other identity
is that the curl of any gradient is zero.
Given that any gradient,
the curl of del s
this is a vector,
del s is a vector.
Let's put some signs here to
indicate that there are three vectors.
s is not a three vector,
it's just a scalar.
The curl of a gradient is also always zero.
In particular I emphasize
this is not a statement about any particular vector field
like the vector potential.
It's an identity that's true for any vector field.
As long as it's differentiable
and nicely,
smoothly behaved
so that you can do the derivatives.
Okay.
These two identities are enough to prove
two or half of Maxwell's equations
without doing anything else.
In other words,
they follow as definitions
or they follow from definitions.
Let's begin with the magnetic field
which is the curl of A.
And let's take the divergence of the magnetic field.
Let's take the divergence of the magnetic field,
del dot B.
That's the source of the magnetic field
in the sense that divergence,
the outgoingness of the field,
the tendency of the field
to spread out from a point.
Del dot B is equal to,
del dot,
curl of A.
From the simple fact,
or from the simple definition
of the magnetic field is
the curl of the vector potential.
Alright.
But the divergence of any curl is automatically zero.
So without any further work,
no dynamics,
no just pure definition or pure kinematics if you like,
the divergence of the magnetic field is zero.
What is,
just to get ahead of,
to get ahead of ourselves for a moment,
what is the divergence of the electric field?
Charge density.
Charge density,
electric charge density.
In particular,
a point charge has a divergence,
a spread of the electric field coming out.
Among other things,
this would say,
if it could be trusted,
that there cannot be magnetic charges.
Magnetic field has no divergence,
and so if we saw a configuration
with a magnetic field coming out of a point,
like out of a magnetic monopole,
if there was such a thing,
then we would say something's wrong with this equation.
If there's something wrong with this equation,
there must be something wrong with this definition.
So,
from a simplistic
and a straightforward point of view,
this equation says there are no magnetic charges.
Now,
we're going to have to come back at some point
and understand
there are ways around this,
but simplistically,
or simply,
this is a statement that there are no
sources of magnetic field.
Now there's another equation,
one of them,
this is one of Maxwell's equations,
there's another one,
which also follows for free.
Let's go back to the definition
that the electric field,
let's write it over here,
let me just write this as
electric field
is equal to time derivative of the vector potential,
indicate it that way,
well,
maybe I'll just write it as d-1,
d by dt,
d by dt of A,
minus,
now,
derivative of A-naught with respect to x-n,
that is just equal to the gradient of A-naught.
From the three-dimensional point of view,
just space,
the time component of A-naught,
can be thought of as a scalar.
It's not a scalar from
the point of four-dimensional vector spaces,
but it is a scalar from
the point of view of three dimensions.
The vector whose components are derivative of A-naught
can just be thought of as the gradient of A-naught.
So we have the electric field,
two terms in it,
one is the time derivative
of the space component of the,
let's,
of the vector potential,
and the other is the gradient of the time component.
Okay,
now,
let's,
let's consider the curl of the electric field.
The curl of the electric field is first of all,
the curl of the time derivative of the vector potential,
that's the first term.
That also happens to be the time derivative,
of the curl of A.
Why is that?
Because you can interchange derivatives.
When I take a derivative to
make a curl out of this,
I can interchange the space
derivative with the time derivative,
and pull the time derivative on the outside.
So the curl of the time derivative of A
is the time derivative of the curl of A.
Number one.
Over here,
then we have minus,
the curl of the gradient of A naught.
The curl of any gradient is equal to zero.
So we get nothing from here.
If I compute the curl of E,
I get nothing from here,
and just the time derivative of the curl of A.
But what's the curl of A?
The curl of A is just the magnetic field.
So,
zero.
Here's another Maxwell equation.
Curl of the electric field,
let's write it as minus the time derivative
of the magnetic field is equal to zero.
Those are the two Maxwell equations that,
as I said,
follow from the fact that the electric and magnetic fields,
are defined in terms of the vector potential.
There are two more Maxwell equations.
Well,
how many equations is each?
Really,
how many equations are here?
Well,
this is a vector equation.
It has three components.
So,
you know,
this is really three independent equations,
and this is a fourth one.
So this stands for four independent equations.
But of course,
if we think of them in vector notation,
this is one equation,
which is a scalar equation,
and one more which is a vector equation.
These are...
I'm not sure if they have names or not.
This is one half of the Maxwell equations.
The other half of the Maxwell equations,
I'll write down over here.
And this half
is the half that you derive from the action principle.
It's the half that is dynamical.
It's the half that is not defined
in terms of...
is not purely definition.
It could be different.
If I chose a different action,
then I could make the second half
of the Maxwell equations be different.
But the Maxwell equations as Maxwell knew them
was entirely analogous to these two,
basically with the electric and the magnetic field
interchanged,
but not quite.
So let's write down the other two
equations.
One of them involves
the divergence of the electric field.
Alright?
So we know what the
divergence of the electric field is.
It's called the charge density.
We're going to spend some time in a few minutes
talking about what charge density and current are.
But for the moment,
I'm just writing down
the equations formally.
The right-hand side
is the charge density,
which means the amount of charge per unit volume,
or the charge in a small volume of space
divided by the small volume of space.
That's what's on the right-hand side here.
And the other equation looks a lot like this one
with E and B interchanged,
but not quite.
It's del cross B
plus
dE by dt,
and what is it equal to?
The current density.
I will tell you in a moment.
So far,
we're just going to give it a name.
We're going to give it a name,
and that's all.
We're going to call it
J.
Now what kind of quantity is J?
Well,
the left-hand side is a three vector.
Electric field is a three vector.
Its time derivative is a three vector.
The curl of a three
vector is also a three vector.
So J is a three vector,
and rho
is a three dimensional scalar.
Now,
they're not four vector,
in four vector language,
more complicated.
In four vector language,
we will discover
that the three components of J
and
the rho,
together form a four vector.
There are four components,
three components of J,
and one component of rho.
J is called the current density.
The electric current density.
And rho is called the
charge density.
Charge density and current density.
So let's talk about them,
and let me explain
what they are.
the J's and rho's.
Oh!
Cool!
This is rho,
the thing in here.
But,
let's see.
So,
this is rho.
And rho is the current density.
So,
somebody's teaching quantum mechanics.
Next quarter,
I have a crazy teaching
assignment.
Steve Schenker and I are
volunteered
to do something which I know is going to be
incredibly frustrating.
To teach quantum mechanics in the mathematics
department.
Frustrating for whom?
Well,
possibly for the
poor sucker physics
department students who have to have a
mathematician come and teach statistical mechanics.
No,
I think it will be fun,
actually.
Someday I'll tell you why we decided to do this.
This is not an undergraduate course.
It's mainly the faculty who wanted to
learn quantum mechanics.
They heard that they cannot understand
Ed Witten told them they have to
understand quantum field theory
if they want to understand basic
modern mathematics.
And they were told that
they could not understand it.
And they believed him.
So they tried to understand
quantum field theory and found out
they couldn't understand it.
So they said,
well,
the reason we can't understand it
is because we don't know anything about quantum mechanics.
So please help us teach us quantum mechanics.
Why am I getting into this?
Forget it.
But,
yeah,
okay.
Charge density and current density.
What are they?
So,
let me explain exactly
what they are.
First of all,
charge density
is exactly what it sounds like.
You take
a region of space.
I'm going to draw some pictures.
Here is time.
And the other two directions are space.
Now the problem here is,
of course,
there are three directions of space.
And it's going to be
a little hard for us to
I'm not going to try to draw
four-dimensional space-time
on the blackboard.
So we'll have to imagine
that these two directions
are standing for three dimensions of space
and one direction of time.
Alright,
we take a little
cell in space.
I'll draw it as a little square here.
But of course it's a cube.
It's not a square,
it's a cube.
It's a cube because it has three dimensions.
And therefore it's a little volume element.
A small volume element.
We imagine
charged particles.
Charged particles have world lines.
So let's draw some world lines.
And let's imagine
that the space
and time
are filled with a
kind of a bundle of
charged particles
moving
sort of flowing,
a fluid of them.
Those are the world lines.
And think of the world lines
that pass through
Yes?
There they are.
They're passing through
this little cube.
Now what does it mean?
That means
that at an instant,
here's an instant,
at an instant,
the particles which pass through that cube
are simply the particles that are in the cube
at that period,
at that instant of time.
All the particles,
the charged particles,
they could be electrons for example,
we take all the electrons
that are in there,
we count up all their charges,
and we think of it
as the total charge
passing through
that little
volume of space.
Passing through in the sense
they were in the past,
then they were in the future,
but at the instant that
we drew that little volume element,
they were in the volume element.
And so you can think of them
as passing through the volume element.
The total charge in that little volume element
divided by the volume element
is the charge per unit volume
and it's rho.
Rho is equal
let's call it
the charge
within the volume delta v.
Delta q over delta v
in the limit that
the volume element goes to zero,
I don't have to spell that out,
infinitesimal volume element
infinitesimal charge in there,
that ratio,
charge per unit volume
is called
the charge density.
And it is literally the amount of charge
per unit volume.
Now what about the current density?
The current density is
simply this thing turned on its side.
Now here is where we get
into a little bit of problem.
The vertical axis
here is time
and
the horizontal axis
or the two horizontal,
sorry,
the two horizontal,
let's get this right.
There's a time axis
and yeah,
right,
that's it.
Alright.
Now
this is the x axis.
This is the x axis.
I guess this here stands
for the y and z axes.
Since I can't draw them
I'll just call them the y and z axis.
Alright,
so
think of
a little cell here in space and time
which is perpendicular
to the x axis.
That means it's a little cube
in space and time.
In space and time
it's a cube.
It has an edge
along the time axis
and it has two edges along the
y and z axis.
Let me take it out
and put it over here
and draw a pure space diagram.
x
y and z
this edge over here
really stands
for a two dimensional square
the y and z square
and so it's a little square
in the,
yeah,
that's okay.
It's a little square
in the y z plane.
We can ask
how much charge,
think of it as a window,
think of it as a window.
There's a little window over there
if I,
I'll get into big trouble
I'm gonna wall here.
Okay,
I won't.
Alright,
here's the window,
this thing over here.
That's a window and that window
is
along the y z axis.
It's right,
hmm?
What's that?
Yeah.
I guess the window here is on the ceiling.
Sorry,
the window here is on the ceiling.
Yeah,
the problem is
there's just not enough axes
in the world to draw.
In any case there's a window.
The window in this case is perpendicular
to the x axis.
So if the x axis is that way,
yeah,
if the x axis is that way
the window is in the y z plane.
It's like that.
And now I ask the question,
how much charge
passes through that window
per unit time?
The amount of charge
that passes through
a small window
per unit time.
In other words,
it's the charge passing through
a little cell
per unit space
per unit time.
Per unit area per unit time.
The amount of charge passing through
a unit area
in a unit time.
Or per unit area per unit time.
That's
the precise analog
of turning this on its side.
This cell
was perpendicular to time.
is purely spatial
but
it's perpendicular to the x axis.
Sorry,
it has a time component
and a y and a z component.
No x component.
So it's like turning it on its side.
That's called J.
J sub x,
to define J sub x,
you take a window perpendicular
to the x axis.
Perpendicular to the x axis,
you ask
how much charge is flowing through it
from
the negative x side to the positive
x side.
How much charge
flows through it per unit time.
So J sub x
is the charge
per unit area
per unit time.
Volume,
area,
times time.
And this area here is an area
perpendicular
to the x axis.
In other words,
it's a y z area.
But perpendicular to the x axis.
That's J x.
What about
J y and J z?
J y and J z are the same thing.
The amount of charge
per unit area per unit time
passing through a window
perpendicular either to the y
direction or the z direction.
So there's J sub z,
J sub y,
and
J sub z.
The formula is the same.
Delta q over delta x
over delta a
over delta t,
except
delta a is a little window
perpendicular to either the y
or the z axis.
That's the definition of J.
And in fact,
J x,
J y,
J z,
and rho
form a complex of things
which in fact are a four vector.
We'll see why I say they're a four vector
soon enough.
But they are a four vector.
And
they enter into
Maxwell's equations.
Where were
Maxwell's equations?
Did we erase
Oh,
here they are.
Here they are.
Yeah.
And that's what's here.
The J is a kind of
flow of charge.
They represent the
flow of charge from one place to another
across these windows,
or through the windows.
Alright?
So the x component
of del cross b
plus the time derivative of the x component
of de
is equal to the flow
of charge through the x window.
There's one more thing
about the charge,
about the density
and current vector which is important.
It actually can be
derived from Maxwell's equations.
Let's see.
Yeah,
we can derive them
from Maxwell's equations.
I won't,
but I'll let you do it.
You can derive it from Maxwell's equations.
But it's really just charge conservation.
So let's talk about charge conservation.
Yes.
In fact,
let's take a break for five minutes.
Ask me the question,
but let's take a break for five minutes,
during which I'm going to take my jacket off.
So basically these four numbers
are just the complements in the...
One is flow in the time direction,
and the other one is flow in the x,
y,
and z directions.
Right.
Is that what you're saying?
That's the way to think about it.
Okay.
Yep.
Right.
So you can think of a spatial volume
as a kind of window perpendicular to the t-axis.
And if you think about it that way,
then uniformity.
Four definitions.
Does the eta function come into play eventually?
Is it a scenario?
The eta?
Yes.
You mean the...
Yeah,
I think you're asking a sensible question,
but I would rephrase it.
I would ask whether the rho and
j are a covariant or a contravariant vector,
four vector.
And we'll come to that.
We'll see that as defined,
they form the components of a...
A vector.
Contravariant vector.
Upper index.
In other words...
And we'll see why this is soon enough.
We'll see that the complex rho,
jx,
jy,
and jz
can be thought of as the
components of a four vector called jmu
with an upper index.
But we'll come to why that's true
as soon as we study it.
And we'll come to why that's true as soon
as we study the relativistic formulation of the Maxwell equations.
Okay,
let's take a two minute break.
I'm happy to answer questions,
but I want to take a
break from lecturing for a few minutes,
for a couple of minutes.
I have a question.
My son was watching you on TV,
and he asked me a
question about something that you said,
and I didn't know the answer.
So maybe you can tell me,
and I'll tell him.
Yeah.
He was watching that show where you were talking about...
black holes and the different point
of view of somebody falling in
versus the person watching.
Right.
And from what you described,
the person that's outside the black hole
sees the person falling in and slowing down
and eventually stopping.
So what he asked me is like,
if it eventually stops,
wouldn't you see around the black hole
basically everything that's ever fallen onto it,
and you wouldn't see a black hole at all,
but just a bunch of litter?
Classically,
the answer is yes.
That's what you would see.
All the stuff that falls onto the black hole
forms kind of sedimentary layers,
which just asymptotically,
slowly,
slowly gravitate to the horizon.
Quantum mechanically...
Well,
it also slows down.
It also slows down,
which means that the rest...
Radiation coming...
You know,
if I were this in-falling person
and I was sending out messages,
let's suppose I was sending out messages at some frequency.
So,
as I would approach the horizon,
I would send out the messages
in a way that sounds to me normal.
Okay?
But to you far away,
it would be redshifted.
Redshifted means that...
You know,
the frequency would get lower and lower and lower.
And if the frequency of
the sound that I was making
was a finite frequency,
there basically would be a last wave
that I would send out
before,
you know,
before the end of the message.
Now,
I could send out more waves
if I would increase the frequency.
I'll make it higher and higher.
But for any given frequency,
there would basically be a last bit of the message
that I could send out.
So,
for any finite thing falling in
with a finite frequency,
with a finite amount of energy available
to send out photons and so forth,
it will slow down,
get redder and redder and redder.
My flashlight that I send out
with optical radiation,
will look to you as I fall in
as,
you know,
infrared.
I fall in a little further,
it starts to look like microwaves coming out.
Not look like,
it's microwaves coming out.
Not to me.
I'm sending out perfectly good flashlight light.
You're seeing infrared,
microwave,
radio wave,
longer and longer wavelength radio waves.
The photons coming out carry less and less energy.
And so,
in effect,
it turns black.
It does turn black.
Is this asymptotically approaching the event horizon?
Mechanically,
it's a little more complicated
because the event horizon has a temperature.
And so,
this reddened,
reddened radiation
gets mixed up with the Hawking radiation
that comes out and becomes indistinguishable from it.
So,
um...
What happens when the wavelength,
gets shifted to the point where it's
exceeding the radius of the observable universe
to just disappear?
Clearly,
it's lost,
but it's lost long before that.
That's a good question.
I mean,
it's a good question.
Basically,
the black hole sends out
one photon,
per transit time across the black hole.
Transit time across the black hole.
The horizon of the black hole has a certain radius
called the Schwarzschild radius.
There's a time associated with the transit time across that.
You know,
just a...
What do you do?
You take R and divide it by C?
Yeah,
you take R and divide it by C.
That gives you a time.
And every such time unit,
it sends out one photon.
Now,
that's not a lot of photons.
One photon per transit time
is a very,
very weak radiation.
But on top of that,
the radiation gets longer and longer wavelength.
So that means the black hole,
as it radiates...
I'm talking about the Hawking radiation now.
It sends out longer and longer wavelengths.
And one per horizon crossing time.
And that really just gets to be negligible
from the point of view of anything
that we could reasonably measure.
It's...
So,
yeah,
in that sense,
it gets quite black.
Yeah.
Is that rate,
one per transit time,
the same during the life of the black hole?
No,
the black hole evaporates.
The thing shrinks.
And so,
it speeds up in that sense.
But that relationship still holds for...
Yeah.
Okay.
All right.
We've defined J.
So we know what's on
the right-hand side of this equation.
Now,
it's an interesting exercise.
Try to work it out.
I think it's almost obvious,
but I'm going to let you work it out.
From this equation,
we could compute...
Oh.
Wait.
No.
I didn't give you the punchline yet.
Go back.
Back,
back,
back.
Rewind.
Conservation of charge.
Conservation of charge is what it says it is.
The total charge in the universe doesn't change with time.
But,
really,
the conservation of charge is a more detailed law
than just saying the charge in the universe doesn't change.
Okay.
It says it doesn't change,
and it doesn't change in a special way.
The special way is the following.
If I take a region of space...
Well,
first of all,
what does the conservation say?
Start with a region of space that I'm interested in,
and look at the total charge in there.
Let's call it Q.
Q is the standard terminology for electric charge.
Call it Q.
Let's suppose after a small amount of time,
the charge within this region,
this region has changed.
Maybe it's decreased a little bit.
That means the charge someplace else must have increased.
That's conservation of charge.
But the conservation of charge
wouldn't be very helpful to us
if there were no rules about where the charge increased.
For example,
it would be perfectly consistent
with the conservation of charge
that every time the charge
changed in a box over here,
it reappeared instantly at Alpha Centauri.
But then from the point
of view of our laboratory experiment,
it would be tantamount to
saying that the conservation of charge
would be meaningless unless we could do an experiment
that involved out to Alpha Centauri.
And if you can do
an experiment out to Alpha Centauri,
go out to the Coma Cluster or wherever you want,
conservation wouldn't have much bite
if the rule was simply that the quantity,
total quantity doesn't change.
The real rule is that the total quantity of charge,
that the charge within a region,
can only change if it passes
through the walls of that region.
In other words,
somebody standing and monitoring the boundaries of this box
will,
if the charge on the inside changes,
it will be due to the fact that they
discover charge passing through the walls of the box.
Now the walls of the box are these little windows.
So what it says,
is that changes of charge
in the interior of a box
must be accompanied by something or
other having to do with the current
on the boundaries of the box.
In other words,
a change in charge,
let's take this to be a small box,
a small box,
then the charge inside that small box
is basically the volume of the small box,
I'll take the volume to be one
so that I don't have to
write it over and over again,
let's take the volume to be one,
but think of the volume as small,
but in some units where a
small volume is just a unit volume,
then what is the time derivative
of the charge in that box?
Well the charge in that
box is just the charge density,
if I take the volume
of the box to be one.
If the volume of the box is one,
charge per unit volume,
then rho is just the charge in that box.
The time derivative of the charge is just rho dot.
The time derivative of rho.
What the conservation,
or we can call it the local conservation of charge,
the idea that charge can't change within a volume
unless it's discovered to be passing through the walls,
that's called local conservation.
Local conservation says that rho
dot must somehow be connected with,
which means equal to,
something or other about the boundary.
So that's the boundaries of the box.
Okay,
so,
supposing rho,
let's take the case where it increases,
supposing the charge increases,
that must mean there's some
net flow of charge coming in.
The net flow of charge coming in
must be the sum of the
charges coming in through this window,
plus this window,
plus the charge coming in from this window,
plus that window,
plus the ones in the front and the back.
Okay.
So let's consider the charge coming in
through this window over here.
What is that?
That's the value,
let's take this to be the x-axis.
We'll take that to be the x-axis.
The vertical one will be the y-axis.
The other one is the x,
y,
z,
z-axis.
The charge coming through this window over here
is proportional
to jx.
Now,
in fact,
jx is defined in such a way
that it corresponds to the flow from
lower values of x to larger values of x.
So in particular,
the charge coming into here per unit time
through this window
is actually minus jx,
and it's minus jx at that point,
or in the neighborhood of that point.
So there's some charge flowing in from here,
and we can add them all up.
Minus jx over here.
What about over here?
What's the charge flowing in from this side?
It's plus jx,
but not at the same point.
jx at a somewhat displaced point,
displaced along the x-axis.
So if I take this contribution
and that contribution,
it corresponds to a certain derivative of jx,
the difference between jx over here and over here,
and it is basically
the derivative of jx with respect to x.
In fact,
it's minus
the derivative of jx with respect to x.
That's the contribution from the two faces
which are perpendicular to x.
The two faces which are perpendicular to x,
the charge per unit time
flowing per unit time
is proportional
to minus the derivative of jx with respect to x.
What about the charge flowing into the box
through the y faces,
through the faces perpendicular to the y-axis?
Same thing.
Minus the derivative of jy with respect to y.
In other words,
some charge flowing in here,
because of the opposite sense of direction,
it's a difference.
Minus jy with respect to y,
and finally,
minus the derivative of jz
with respect to z.
This is the net charge per unit time
flowing into the box
by flowing through these three kinds of windows.
This must be equal to the time rate of change
of the charge in the box.
So we now have an equation
that rho dot is equal to minus
and what is this?
This is the divergence of j,
del dot j.
Or,
rho dot plus del dot j
is equal to zero.
That equation is a local point,
neighborhood by neighborhood expression
of the conservation of charge.
If it's true,
then the charge within any small region
will only change
due to the flow of charge out of that region,
the flow of charge through the walls of the region.
Okay?
All right,
so that's the idea of...
This equation is known as the continuity equation.
Continuity.
I don't like thinking of it as a continuity equation
because continuity sounds like something
that's necessarily continuous,
which it's not.
I like to call it local conservation.
In other words,
conservation,
but a strong form of conservation
which does not allow a
charge to disappear at one place
and reappear at another place
unless in between there's a flow of charge,
a current.
Okay,
so this is the continuity equation,
and it's another one of...
It's another equation that has to be added to these,
but in fact it really doesn't
have to be added to these.
It's a consequence of these equations.
So I suggest to you the following exercise.
Here we have an expression for rho.
Here we have an expression for j.
You can take the time derivative of the left-hand side,
and it will give you rho dot.
You can take the divergence of the right-hand side,
and it will give you divergence of j.
See if you can prove that as an identity
that rho dot plus del
dot j is equal to zero.
In other words,
that Maxwell's equations
require the charge to be conserved.
It's such an important thing
that I'm sort of tempted to see
if I can get it right.
I can do it on the blackboard.
It is really central.
It's really central.
Charge conservation is not an option
that it follows from the Maxwell equations.
I'm going to let you do it.
It's fun.
It's a little bit of an exercise.
It uses a couple of identities.
And,
you know,
it's truly central to the whole game.
Okay,
so now we have Maxwell's equations.
And the real question that I want to address
is can we express all of these equations
in a relativistic notation
which makes it clear
that the collection of equations
is invariant on the Lorentz transformations?
In other words,
can we express them as tensor equations?
Equations with indices upstairs,
downstairs,
with the rules of indexology.
Yes,
sir?
We didn't really show those last two equations
how they came to be.
Which ones?
The second set of the hard ones.
No,
we haven't come to these yet.
We have not.
No,
exactly.
that's right.
Well,
this is the target.
This is the target.
This is Maxwell's...
Let's see.
This and this were known to Faraday.
Faraday also knew that del cross B equals J,
but he didn't have it worked out
in the case where there was time dependence.
This term here was invented by Maxwell.
Without this term,
you would not discover...
In fact,
you would discover that
charge conservation is false.
This term is essential to prove that
rho dot plus del dot J is equal to zero.
So,
in fact,
what Maxwell did is
he knew about charge conservation.
So did Faraday.
They knew about charge conservation.
They knew about the continuity equation.
And Maxwell realized that he
has to put this term in
in order for charge to be conserved.
That it wouldn't work unless
you were able to do it.
So he added this term over here.
So that's a nice exercise to work out.
Okay.
Let's see what we can do about making these equations
relativistically invariant.
In other words,
some...
just relativistic notation.
Well,
this one over here is pretty clear.
It's pretty obvious.
Let's rewrite it in a
form that is easy to see.
Rho dot is d by 2.
d by dt of,
let's call it rho.
It is rho.
What about this?
This one is plus d by dx of Jx
plus d by dy of Jy
plus d by dz of Jz.
Now,
so far,
I've not been thinking about
four vector notation and so forth.
We've been thinking three-dimensionally.
So from the three-dimensional point of view,
there is no difference between an upstairs index
and a downstairs index.
But when we look at this equation,
it becomes natural to think of it
in a notation which is sort of manifestly Lorentz.
Lorentz invariant.
First of all,
differentiating with respect to an xm,
that's a downstairs index.
If we put...
If we write the index upstairs,
then this is part of a scalar.
Let's say it more completely.
Let's define rho
to be the time component
of J.
In other words,
take Jx,
Jy,
and Jz.
Put them together with rho.
Rho,
Jx,
Jy,
and Jz.
I'm putting the index here upstairs,
but it doesn't matter because
three-dimensional indices doesn't matter
whether you put them upstairs or downstairs.
Put them together and call the whole complex
of four objects,
Jmu,
with an upstairs index.
Then this equation has the form of a
four-dimensional relativistically invariant equation,
Djmu by Dxmu,
summed over mu,
Einstein's summation in the convention,
equals zero.
So it's natural,
therefore,
to think of rho together with J
as the components of a four vector.
In fact,
it's not hard to prove
that they really do transform
as the components of a four vector.
Let's not try to do that at the moment.
Let's just make use of our notation
to take it as a very strong suggestion.
That the components of rho and J
form a single complex.
Of course they do.
They were defined pretty much in the same way.
You took windows in various directions in space and time
and asked about the charge passing through those windows.
So it's a rather symmetric thing
with respect to space and time.
And in fact,
that symmetry
is just the statement
that the complex rho,
J,
form a four vector.
Question.
Yeah.
Is there some
trick that I missed
when the
code derivative of rho
with respect to T became a partial derivative?
Oh,
no,
it is partial derivative.
It was always partial derivative.
Why?
What does it mean?
It means you stand at a point in space,
a little box,
and you ask how much the
charge inside that region changes.
Now,
we're not moving the box from place to place.
We're keeping the box fixed.
That means we're differentiating
with respect to time,
keeping x,
y,
and z fixed.
We're looking at a particular box.
We're not moving it.
And we're saying,
what's the rate of change of charge in that box?
That's a partial derivative
because it's asking how the charge density changes
if you vary time,
not varying x,
y,
or z.
So rho dot could signify partial derivative?
Yeah,
rho dot meant partial derivative.
Right.
We're not following some trajectory.
We're just looking at a fixed box.
So that's right.
Rho dot just meant literally
partial derivative with respect to time.
That's a good point.
Okay,
and then the rest of them
are also partial derivatives.
So now we have the elements necessary to...
We know that E and B form a...
anti-symmetric tensor with two indices.
J and rho form a four vector,
in other words,
a tensor with one index.
And here's a set of...
Here are a set of four equations,
and the question is,
can we express them in a way
which is invariant under Lorentz transformations?
Yeah.
Thank you.
Let's begin with the left side,
not the left side,
sorry.
Let's begin with the two equations in this box,
the equations that were for free.
The equations that were just a consequence of the
definitions of B and E in terms of vector potential.
What are they?
They're some kind of derivative.
Each one of these equations has a
derivative acting on a component of F.
And the result is equal to zero.
How many such equations are there?
There are four such equations.
Here's one,
and there are three more here.
There are three because it's a...
Right.
So...
So there are four such equations,
and I will just show you how
to write them out in tensor notation,
and then we can check.
We can check them one by one and
see that they're the same set of equations.
Here it is.
There are some tricks to doing it,
but the answer is more interesting than the tricks.
Or the answer,
the fact that it's covariant.
So let me write it out for you.
Here it is.
It's d sigma.
Now sigma can be any one of four.
T,
x,
y,
or z,
or 0,
1,
2,
or 3.
F nu tau.
Plus d nu.
I'll tell you how you get this in a moment.
Nu tau sigma.
Plus d tau.
F.
Now.
Let's see.
It's tau,
so it's got to be nu and sigma,
and it must be sigma nu.
Nu.
Equals 0.
You take...
Any three of these components,
sigma,
nu,
and tau,
for any combination of sigma,
nu,
and tau,
1,
2,
3,
1,
whatever,
this is equal to 0.
That's equivalent to these equations.
Let's check.
Let's just check.
The way to do this is
just to go through them and check.
In particular,
let's take the case...
Let's see.
Yeah.
Let's take the case first where all three indices,
sigma,
nu,
and tau,
are space components.
Okay?
Let's see what this says.
If sigma,
nu,
and tau are space components.
So this is d...
Well,
I won't rewrite it.
I'm getting a little tired,
but let's go through it.
Yeah.
Notice...
Let's see.
Let's take sigma equals x,
nu equals y,
and tau equals z.
Let's try that combination and see what we get.
Then,
this is derivative with respect to x.
Now,
this is f,
nu,
tau.
So that's f,
y,
z.
f,
y,
z is what?
It's a component of the magnetic field.
Which component?
Good.
Bx.
Okay.
How about this one over here?
Now,
nu is equal to y.
So this is plus derivative with respect to y.
Tau and sigma.
What are?
Z and x.
So what kind of B is that?
By.
You have to check the sign.
The only thing that could go wrong is the sign.
And the last one,
tau is equal to z.
And sigma and nu are x and y.
So this is Bz.
And that's equal to zero.
That's simply del dot B is equal to zero.
Okay.
So if we take all three of
these to be different components and pure space-like,
sigma,
nu,
and tau,
we just get del dot B equals zero.
We get exactly the same thing,
incidentally,
if we took nu to be x,
sorry,
nu to be x,
and sigma to be y.
It wouldn't change.
You get the same thing.
Okay.
Let's try another one.
Let's take one of the
components to be a time component.
Which one?
Do you have a preference for which one is time?
Tau.
Oh,
good.
Tau is time.
Yeah.
And let's take sigma and nu
to be y and x again.
So let's see what this says.
Okay.
D sigma,
that's derivative with respect to y,
of nu tau.
Now,
what's f nu tau?
One leg in time and one leg in space.
That's an electric field.
The electric field are the mixed space-time components of f.
All right.
So let's not try to keep track of the signs.
It's a little too tricky
to keep track of the signs.
Let's just be a little loose with the signs now.
So f nu tau.
That's f nu tau.
And then f nu tau is e sub x.
So this is derivative with respect to y of e
sub x with a plus or minus sign that is
a little too hard to keep track
of in real time on the blackboard.
What about this one?
This is plus or minus derivative with
respect to x of f sigma tau.
That's e sub y.
And no doubt there is a minus sign between them.
So what is this a component of?
What is this thing here?
That's a piece of the curl.
It's a component of the curl of e.
Which one haven't I kept track of yet?
This one?
Okay.
So this one is plus derivative with respect to t.
So this one is plus derivative of f sigma nu.
That's the magnetic field in the z direction.
f x y is the z
component of the magnetic field equals 0.
And again,
there's some sign there that I haven't kept track of.
But that's just at the curl of e minus
the time derivative of b is equal to 0.
Okay.
Here's the problem.
all of these equations,
you can just see there are some repetitions.
In general,
it doesn't
matter which way you set sigma nu and tau,
x,
y,
t,
or t,
y,
x,
you'll get the same equation.
You'll just find that these equations,
all of them,
for all possible sigma nu and tau,
either just give you zero.
There are times when you just get zero.
In particular,
if
any two of the components are the same,
you'll get zero every single time.
And if they're
not the same,
you'll get either this equation or this equation.
So the first equation here
can be represented in a
completely relativistically invariant tensor notation.
This is a tensor
with three components,
or three indices,
sigma,
tau,
and nu.
And this is true.
You can check
this another way.
You can remember that f is the derivative of
a nu with respect to x tau minus the derivative
of a tau with respect to x nu.
That's this one.
And then you have another one over here
and another one over here.
And you can simply work them all out,
and you will discover term
by term,
they cancel.
They just cancel.
They cancel among themselves,
and you get zero.
So these equations here,
the ones which
come for free,
the ones which just are determined by the
fact that f is defined in terms of
the vector potential,
they are equivalent to this tensor equation.
Completely Lorentz
invariant.
You can check that.
You can see how it transforms.
And this equation,
or this
complex of equations,
has a name.
The name is called the Bianchi identity,
or it's a
special case of an identity called the Bianchi identity.
Giorgio,
is there an h in that?
Yes.
The Bianchi identity.
It has a similar identity in general relativity.
It has a certain
geometric meaning.
Geometric meaning is interesting,
but it's
not for us tonight.
What does it express?
Again,
one of the things it
expresses is the fact that the
magnetic field has no divergence,
so there's no charge
densities,
sorry,
no magnetic charge densities,
but if there are no
magnetic charge densities,
there are no magnetic currents,
you might have thought
that by analogy with this equation,
you could put a magnetic charge density here,
the analog
of an electric charge density,
and a magnetic current over here.
What we're finding is that the Bianchi identity
is the statement that there are no magnetic charge
densities or magnetic currents.
Next time,
we will come to these equations.
These are the equations which
are derived from an action principle.
These,
as I said,
are just identities,
you get them for free.
These are the ones
that are derived from the action principle,
and we'll do that next time.
Okay,
I think we're finished for tonight.
Any questions?
Yeah?
So,
the capital F matrix
essentially has six independent entities.
Yeah.
Three electric and three magnetic fields.
And that's 64 different entities.
Yeah,
there's not that many there.
Yeah.
So,
you end up getting four
pieces of anything in the middle.
Is there any reason?
Yeah,
there is,
but I'm going to let you do it.
Okay.
You'll just discover that the 1,
2,
3,
that if any two of them are repeated,
you get zero.
In other words,
the x,
y,
y component is zero.
And you'll discover that the 1,
2,
3 component piece of the equation
is the same as the 2,
3,
1,
is the same as the,
so there's only a handful of independent ones.
And that you can check.
So,
as you said,
it looks like there's,
what,
64 equations here?
Four times four times four?
But there aren't.
Pardon?
There are not.
There are 24.
Really only four.
How many of them?
There are only four.
Pardon?
There are only four,
really.
Namely,
these.
Right,
I understand,
but there are literally 64.
Yeah,
yeah,
literally 64.
Most of them go away.
Right.
Well,
it's not that they,
a good number of them go away.
And a good number of them
are just repetitions of other ones.
Right,
that's true.
Yeah.
So,
that's,
yeah.
If your charge and current are zero,
then you have the duality.
If what?
If charge and current are gone,
the duality between E and B.
So I'm confused.
When you have your space,
your E's are your time space
and your B's are your space,
what's the meaning of that?
In light of duality.
Yeah.
What's special about E?
That it's time and space and.
In the end,
as far as we think we understand things,
there is no difference.
I mean,
that is to say,
if there was such a thing as magnetic charge density,
we would
put it in on the right,
let's call this electric charge,
electric current,
magnetic charge,
electric current.
So,
if you have a charge,
magnetic current.
I can't remember,
yeah,
I think,
I'm not sure about the sign of this one,
maybe a minus
sign,
I can't remember.
They're completely parallel or invariant with,
not with respect to changing E to B
and B to E.
That doesn't quite work.
Why not?
Because of this minus sign
here and a plus sign here.
Yeah.
You think about it a little bit differently.
You make a,
you make a plane whose axes are E and B.
Okay.
Now interchanging E and B would be
reflecting E into B and B into E.
That's not what you do.
What you do is you
rotate the diagram by 90 degrees.
E goes to B.
B goes to minus E.
That's the duality.
E goes to B.
B goes to minus E.
And either electric charge goes to magnetic charge or
electric charge goes to minus magnetic charge.
So,
there are many,
many ways of expressing this duality.
But if you go back and you say that
E and B really came from a vector potential,
then,
at least at a naive level.
It would be a negative potential.
It would say that the
magnetic charge and current are zero.
There you go.
So.
It seems so clean and elegant and everything the
way that E and B interchange and all fits
with relativity.
It almost seems meaningless to
talk about a magnetic monopole given,
given that.
What,
I mean,
you have to change what you
mean by magnetic field almost or something.
You know what I mean?
Yeah.
Of course I know what you mean.
We will come back to magnetic monopoles.
I will try to cover magnetic monopoles this
quarter and discuss how they fit into this
picture.
Of course,
it's an interesting fact that
nobody's ever discovered a magnetic monopole.
But we'll come back to that.
Let's not push it tonight.
I'm tired.
Okay,
good.
For more information,
visit www.FEMA.gov.
Or please visit us at stanford.edu.