Stanford University.
All right, as I said, the basic
tool of the trade is quantum field theory.
And that is what we're going to
spend a little bit of time learning.
I'm going to teach you a very
elementary version of what a quantum field is,
I think, tonight.
But I do want to get up
on the blackboard some basic mathematical facts,
just to review and to remind you.
This is too elementary to be a
serious part of this class at this point,
but I do want to get it up there.
The first mathematical set of facts
does have to do with waves.
Waves are, of course, an example of fields.
Field configurations.
Fields are things which vary throughout space.
Waves are particular kind of configurations in which
the fields are moving in a wave-like motion.
And waves and particles are closely
connected through the link of quantum mechanics.
I am not going to teach
a quantum mechanics course this quarter.
So if your quantum mechanics
is fuzzy, uncertain, ha ha ha,
go back to the lectures
on quantum mechanics.
The two sets, there was a class called quantum entanglement,
which we'll get up there hopefully soon,
and another class just called quantum mechanics.
And that is the basic starting
point for what particle physics is.
Also special relativity.
But let's just review very,
very quickly one mathematical fact,
which comes up over and
over and over and over again.
Just what the relation
between sines, cosines, and exponentials.
Everybody, probably most of the people here know this,
but I just want to
get it up on the blackboard.
Um, for future reference.
Okay.
Let's remember what an exponential is.
An exponential is an exponential function.
It has the form e, e is
a certain number, to the alpha x.
X, alpha is a number.
It could be any number, real or complex.
Or pure or nothing.
Okay.
Or imaginary.
And e to the alpha
x is a function of x.
An exponential is a function which grows,
in this case with respect to x,
by an amount, each separate little interval of x,
it grows by an amount proportional to itself.
For example, a population of a petri dish.
The increase in the population
is proportional to the population itself.
And so the hallmark of an exponential,
let's call this f of x,
is that the derivative of f
of x, with respect to x,
is proportional, in this case
with the proportionality factor alpha,
times f itself.
The rate of change is proportional to f itself.
And such a function is called an exponential,
and it's denoted e to the alpha x.
Or something, it can be a
number times e to the alpha x.
Okay.
That's the hallmark of an exponential.
Now, let me remind you of
some facts about sines and cosines,
and then put them together very quickly.
Sines and cosines, you know what they are.
They're functions which oscillate like this.
That's sine of x, and cosine
of x is exactly the same function,
except shifted over by 90
degrees, and it looks like that.
And I'm sure you all know this.
I won't bother going into detail.
But the important thing about sine of, let's say, kx.
Let's call it sine of kx.
Sine of k, where k is a number,
any number, real number in this case, times x.
Could be positive, could be negative.
And the other function of interest is cosine of kx.
All right.
Sine of kx and cosine of
kx can be differentiated, both of them.
And I'll just remind you what the derivative is.
No, you'll remind me.
What's the derivative of sine
of kx with respect to x?
The sine of kx with respect to
x is equal to k times cosine kx.
And the derivative of cosine with
respect to x is minus k sine.
So you get the derivative of sine of kx.
So neither one of these is an exponential.
Neither one has the property that when you differentiate it,
you get something back proportional to itself.
They have the odd property that when you differentiate one,
you get something proportional to the other,
in one case with a minus sign.
In each case, there's a cosine of kx.
Cosine kx, thank you.
Cosine kx.
So you differentiate this one, you get the other one.
You differentiate the other one.
You get minus the first one.
All right.
So out of these two,
you can now build an exponential.
But it's an exponential of an imaginary thing.
So let's just do it
once and be done with it.
If you take the combination, cosine kx plus i
sine kx, i being the square root of minus 1,
and you differentiate it.
If you differentiate it with respect
to x, what do you get?
You get from cosine, you
get minus sine kx plus i.
I'm sorry.
Minus k sine kx plus ik.
Cosine kx.
Did I do it correctly now?
I think I did.
Which is, just spend a couple of minutes doing the
algebra, i times k times the original thing back again.
Cosine kx plus i sine of kx.
In other words, to make a long
story short, cosine kx plus i sine kx.
Cosine kx.
Is the function e to the ikx.
When you differentiate it with respect to
x, you get ik times the same thing.
All right.
So that's an important mathematical fact
that comes up over and over again.
Sines and cosines are of course
the functions which describe wave-like oscillations, either
oscillations with respect to space.
If x is a space, then it's a space.
If x is a space coordinate,
there's an oscillation that oscillates with space.
If x happens to be time, it
corresponds to an oscillation with respect to time.
All right.
We'll come.
Now let's consider in a little more detail,
well, not so much detail, but just quick review.
All right.
We have a wave.
The wave is moving past us.
It has a certain frequency,
and it has a certain wavelength.
Let me just remind you of
the connections, because we'll use them.
We can call f the frequency.
It's the number of cycles that pass you every second.
Frequency.
And it's measured in cycles per second.
C stands for cycles per second.
A cycle is one full oscillation of the wave.
Another definition.
Now this is definition.
Omega is another form of the frequency.
It's the angular frequency measured in radians per second,
and it's just equal to 2 pi times f.
So f and omega are the same
thing except for a factor of 2 pi.
And I may go back and forth between them, try to
keep equations as simple as possible with as few factors of pi.
So sometimes I may use omega.
Sometimes I may use f.
All right.
Okay.
Lambda is, of course, the wavelength.
And now for a light wave, a
light wave moves at the speed of light.
Because it's moving past you with the speed
of light, the wavelength and the frequency are related.
And they're related by the formula.
The wavelength is the distance traveled in one full cycle.
And if you move it, it's
the distance traveled in one full cycle.
And if you multiply that by the
frequency, that gives you the speed of light.
That's the velocity.
The frequency is how long, well, the inverse of
the time that it takes to go one full cycle.
So this is a distance divided by the
time that it takes to go one full cycle.
And for a light ray, this is c.
If it's a sound wave, then
you put the speed of sound there.
If it's a water wave, you put the speed
of water waves there, or whatever it happens to be.
But we'll be, of course,
particularly interested in light waves.
Now, that's one set of equations.
The other set of equations that we discussed last
time, just a quick, brief review of last time,
is the equations of quantum mechanics,
which relate wave-like motions to particles.
And we're not going to go
in heavy depth into the explanation.
We're going to go in deep
depth into the explanation of these equations.
For that, you go back and
open up the lectures on quantum mechanics.
But nevertheless, I'll try to be as complete
as possible, or at least as self-contained as possible.
The important thing when going to quantum
mechanics is a new number, Planck's constant.
It comes in two varieties,
not varieties, two separate notations.
There's the old Planck's constant.
Which was Planck's original notation.
And then there's the new Planck's
constant, which is the same as
Which is the same as the old Planck's
constant, except for a factor of 2 pi.
And that 2 pi is put there, so...
To save 2 pi's in somebody else's...
To save 2 pi's in somebody else's equation.
But they always come up, and
there's just no escape from 2 pi's.
You're always going to have them.
But the other definition is h-bar, and that's
the old Planck, that's the new Planck's constant.
That's the old Planck's constant divided by 2 pi.
I will simply save 2 pi's by
sometimes using h and sometimes using h-bar.
Try to keep the number of 2 pi's...
To a minimum.
Now, lambda times...
Let's see.
Okay.
Yeah.
That was...
That's not an equation, that's just a definition.
And what is h?
h is a number, which
is a tiny, tiny, tiny number.
Anybody remember what it is?
6 times 10 to the minus something.
34 or something?
In some units.
In some units or another.
Oh, that was an interesting question.
In my email, it showed up somebody questioning
whether the origin of the unit meter, pointing out...
Let's see, what is the meter?
The meter is 1 40 millionth of
the way of the circumference of the Earth.
And said, no, I was wrong.
It didn't have anything to do with this.
It's 1 40 millionth of the...
Do you think that somebody just came along and said, let's define
a unit which is 1 40 millionth of the circumference of the Earth?
No, of course not.
That unit had been in use...
I don't know whether it
was called a meter or not.
In England, it was called the yard.
But why 1 40 millionth?
Why not 1 40 trillionth or 1 40...
Well, because you wanted some unit that was
easy to deal with for a human being.
Good to measure rope with,
good to measure cloth with, whatever.
And I do believe that the origin of a unit
which is about the length of a human being's arm...
predated knowledge about what the
circumference of the Earth is.
Anyway, which in fact was
known for a long time, but...
Yeah.
In any case, in standard units, meters, seconds,
and kilograms, h bar is a very small number.
Do I have it right, something
like 10 to the minus 34?
Yeah.
1 point...
That's little less than 1.
That's a little less than 1.
Yeah.
That's little h bar. That's h bar.
H is 6 times 10
to the minus 34, or whatever.
And c, of course, is 3 times
10 to the 8th meters per second.
3 times 10 to the 8th meters per second.
Okay, so this is just a definition of some number,
or the definition between a relation between two numbers.
But the fact is that
the energy of a single photon,
a photon associated with a wave of a given wavelength,
and therefore a given frequency...
Notice this equation here tells you
the relationship between frequency and wavelength.
Frequency and wavelength are inversely related.
The bigger one is, the smaller the other is.
The energy of a single quantum...
Single quantum, yeah, energy...
Now, this is not the energy of an electromagnetic wave.
This is the energy of
one quantum of the electromagnetic wave.
That's equal either to h bar omega,
where omega is the frequency of the wave,
the angular frequency of the wave.
Incidentally, the frequency of an electromagnetic optical...
an optical wave, one that
you can see with your eye,
is very, very rapid, something like about
10 to the 15th cycles per second.
Did I have that right? About
10 to the 15th cycles per second?
So, typically, omega is very, very large,
10 to the 15th, blah, blah, blah, blah, per second.
But h bar is more than small enough to
make the energy of a single quantum very, very small.
If you multiply these two in
the units that we've been using,
you get the energy in joules,
and you find out that the
energy in joules is very small,
10 to the minus 19th, or something like that.
So it would take a huge number of optical photons
to add up to
any appreciable macroscopic conventional energy.
All right, so the energy...
And this, of course, is also
equal to the other Planck's constant
times the other frequency.
So they're the same thing, just two different notations.
All right, now let's talk about momentum.
Let's remind ourselves about momentum.
Energy, incidentally, and
momentum are especially interesting
because they're conserved quantities.
They're conserved.
Total amount of energy is conserved.
Total amount of momentum is conserved.
And therefore, they're good bookkeeping devices,
good for writing balance equations,
and useful, among other things, besides being deep.
Momentum is a vector.
It points in a direction,
points typically in the direction or motion of an object.
It's defined by being conserved.
But having said that it's defined by being conserved,
by the fact that it's conserved,
we count it and so forth,
we can ask, what is the momentum
of various kinds of objects in nature?
And the first thing we can write down
is the momentum of a non-relativistic object.
Non-relativistic object just means one moving
slower than the speed of light.
Oh, a lot slower.
A lot slower than the speed of light.
A lot slower.
The momentum of such an
object is proportional to its mass,
times its velocity, and its velocity is also a vector.
All right.
If I give you any pulse of radiation,
electromagnetic radiation,
and it's all collimated along a given direction,
not a dispersed wave which is going
out in a variety of different directions,
but in which everything is lined
up and collimated along an axis,
then this is non-relativistic.
The opposite extreme is super-relativistic,
in other words, moving with the speed of light,
and it's not a very good formula.
Now, this formula is not right
for moving with the speed of light.
You could plug in for v, the speed of light,
but what do you plug in for m?
Remember, I told you, m is
always, by definition, the rest mass,
what we used to call a rest mass.
And a photon doesn't have a rest mass.
Okay? Its rest mass is zero.
Try to bring it to rest, it has nothing.
But this is not the right formula.
This formula has a look
which looks a bit like this.
If we were to have
used, inappropriately, e equals mc squared.
Now, mainly I'm using this for
units, in order to get units right.
Energy is mass times velocity squared.
Then, of course, mass would be an
energy divided by the speed of light squared.
All right, now if I, as I said, inappropriately,
ascribed to a photon a mass equal
to its energy divided by c squared,
the energy of the photon divided by c squared,
and then said that the
velocity of the photon was c,
in fact, more or less somewhat accidentally,
I would get the right answer
that the magnitude of the momentum,
this should be read as the magnitude of the momentum,
Or you could just write, like, r hat.
Yeah.
Right. But the magnitude of the
momentum is the energy of the photon,
or the energy of the electromagnetic wave,
for any electromagnetic wave all
moving in a constant direction,
the direction of the momentum is, of
course, the direction of motion of the wave.
That's easy.
But the magnitude of the momentum is the energy
of the wave divided by the speed of light.
From that, we can say, supposing the
wave consisted only of a single photon.
Now, are we using it legitimately?
Yeah, you get the right answer.
What is the momentum of a single photon?
And to get the momentum of a single photon,
you just plug the energy from
here into the formula for the momentum.
So let's do that.
The momentum for a single photon.
Now, let's do it over here.
Momentum of a single photon.
Let's write photon over here.
Can that be read?
Everybody read that?
The momentum of a photon.
And I'm concentrating now on its magnitude.
Incidentally, the double bar here means the magnitude of it.
The direction is along the
direction of the beam of light,
or along the direction of the photon.
Let's plug it in.
The energy.
Let's see, let's use this formula over here.
H times frequency.
Energy is H frequency divided by C.
Right?
What's the frequency divided by C?
Right.
Wavelength or one over the wavelength?
Frequency divided by C.
I've divided by C.
Is equal to one over lambda, right?
Did I get that right?
Yes.
Frequency divided by C is one over lambda.
So, this is just the equation that the photon momentum.
Photon momentum in magnitude is equal to Planck's constant.
That makes it small.
Times the frequency divided by C,
which is divided by the wavelength.
So, the smaller the wavelength, the
larger the momentum of the photon.
That's a pattern, and it's in
some sense the most important fact
coming from quantum mechanics about particle physics.
That if you want short wavelength,
for the purposes of studying very small objects,
the price that you pay is you have
to put a lot of momentum in it.
Thank you.
Question.
Yeah.
The formula E equals H bar omega.
Is that fundamental or is that derived from some symmetry
that we're going to learn later on?
It derives from the quantum
mechanics of a harmonic oscillator.
So, the place to look it up is on lectures,
previous lectures about the harmonic oscillator.
I will make use of those lectures,
but that's where it comes from,
from a deeper point of view.
We'll come to the right statements,
although not the demonstration of them.
Yeah.
Just to touch on that.
Since we have waves,
in a group of photons or electromagnetic wave,
it has an amplitude,
and all waves have amplitudes.
But a photon in itself,
we haven't talked about its amplitude.
Let me answer the question.
Let me answer the question now.
I knew it was there,
and I was waiting to get to the right point,
but why don't I just say it now.
Right.
An electromagnetic wave or any other wave
has several features,
one of which I have not written down here.
It's the amplitude of the wave.
Now, the amplitude of the wave,
well, okay,
here are two waves with the same frequency,
and they're the same,
in every respect the same,
except that there's a,
and here's another one.
One of them is just some small number
times sine kx, for example.
Maybe the small one is just sine kx.
The other one is a great big numerical multiple,
which I'll call A times sine kx.
They're exactly the same,
except one is much stronger than the other.
It's got a larger amplitude.
A is the amplitude of the wave.
And now the question is,
in photon language,
what is the meaning of the amplitude?
Or, another question you could ask is,
what is the amplitude associated with one photon?
Now, the question is a little bit ambiguous,
because quantum mechanics always has uncertainties.
Technically, it has uncertainties,
and you can't measure everything simultaneously.
For example, you can't measure both the amplitude
and the phase of the wave.
The phase of the wave is where it's located,
but never mind that.
Or, there's a sensible order of magnitude question.
Order of magnitude, what is the amplitude
that's associated with a single photon, for example?
Okay, the answer is the following.
The energy of a wave,
now this is a completely classical statement,
the energy of a wave is proportional
to k times the square of the amplitude.
For example, if this was the electromagnetic field,
let's say the electric field or the magnetic field
associated with an electromagnetic wave,
what's the energy of an electromagnetic field?
It's proportional to the
square of the electromagnetic field.
So, the energy of a
wave is proportional to the square
of the electromagnetic field.
So, typically, the energy of a wave
is proportional to the square of the amplitude.
If you take...
Ah, good.
Now, the energy of the wave
is also proportional to the number of photons
in that wave.
So, here I've described for you
some features of a single photon,
but a wave of light consists of a single photon.
So, if the energy of
a light consists of many photons,
let's suppose the number of photons
in some wave of light is n.
Then, the energy is proportional to n.
In fact, the energy will be n,
the number of photons,
times h-bar omega.
So, that means that there's a proportionality
between the square of the amplitude
on the one hand,
and the number of photons in that wave.
Let's just call it little n.
The precise, exact, detailed connection
I'll work out for you another time.
But the square of the amplitude of the wave
is proportional to the number of photons.
Now, there's a factor of h-bar in there
because the square of the amplitude is the energy,
and we should have an h-bar...
h-bar omega
in the energy.
So, the square of the amplitude
is proportional to h-bar in n.
Now, of course, the point is that
h-bar is an extremely small number.
This is the energy of the wave.
Another form, another way of writing the energy
of a wave with many photons.
Not a single photon, but many photons.
And now you say, well, look,
this is a terribly tiny number.
How can you get any appreciable amount of energy
in an electromagnetic wave?
Well, the answer is by having a lot of photons.
So, a typical electromagnetic wave
that carries an appreciable energy
has an enormous number of photons
to overwhelm this factor of h-bar.
But the amplitude, if you like,
a, is proportional to the square root
of the number of photons.
So that's the missing wave category.
This is a characteristic that I didn't write down here.
And as I said, it is proportional to the...
Yeah.
I think that there's a common confusion
about the oscillation
when you see a diagram of
the e and the b fields
that are perpendicular sine waves.
And there's a temptation to think of that
as a spatial...
You know, the height of the sine wave
as being the distance that the photon
is within the space or something.
No, no, right, okay.
Okay, so here's a wave.
It's moving down the x-axis.
What's plotted vertically here
is not the y-axis or the z-axis.
What's plotted vertically?
The electric field.
Right, so this is not a plot.
Only one of the directions here corresponds to space.
The other direction, of course,
corresponds to the electric or the magnetic field.
I think that's what you were asking me to clarify,
and properly so.
Now, of course, the wave
could be oriented in any direction.
That way, that way, that way.
And the momentum carried by the wave
is along the axis that the wave is moving.
I have a question.
Yeah.
You say the number of photons in the wave
being within one period of the wave?
Both.
You mean the number of photons within one period?
Let's say within one period, yeah.
Because A squared is like the power density
rather than energy, right?
That's right.
So that's why it's necessary to say within one wavelength.
Well, the proportionality,
I purposefully wrote proportional to here.
We were talking about two wavelengths,
three wavelengths, four wavelengths.
Of course, the answer would be...
Well, yes, you got the right idea.
So does that mean that the
amplitude of a single photon is meaningless?
Well, order of magnitude,
it's given by this formula with n equals 1.
But yes, in some sense it is meaningless.
It's as meaningless...
For an electromagnetic wave,
an electromagnetic wave has both a magnetic field
and an electric field.
Now, the magnetic field and the electric field
are related to each other by a relation
which is similar mathematically
to the relationship between the position of a particle
and the velocity of a particle.
And those are things
which cannot be measured simultaneously.
They are...
The uncertainty principle prevents you
from knowing both of them.
And in the same way,
there's an uncertainty principle between
electric field and magnetic field
that prevents you from knowing both of them.
So yes, there are limitations on
how well you can know the amplitude.
But as an order of magnitude statement, this is correct.
We'll try to do better as we go along.
We're sort of getting into
the subject of quantum field theory,
which is a difficult and abstract subject.
Okay.
I wrote down some equations
here which are true for photons.
Some of them are true for any particle.
Others are not.
All right. The definition of frequency,
that's a general definition.
Omega being 2 pi f, that's perfectly good.
Lambda equals a wavelength, that's a definition.
This is true for waves which
will move with the speed of light.
So it would not be true for a general wave...
Let's put something around those equations
which are not expected to be of great generality.
By great generality, I mean they would be
true for almost any kind of wave or particle,
whether or not it moves with the speed of light.
This is not so general.
Anything that has a c in
it will not be very general.
When I say not general, it'll be general
for anything which moves with the speed of light.
Okay. This is general.
Now, energy equals h bar omega.
That is also a very general fact.
This clearly...
Neither of these...
This is specific to things which
move with the speed of light.
This is specific to objects which move
with much less than the speed of light.
There's an interpolation in between
which I won't get into now,
which is true for things which move
with some fraction of the speed of light.
Let's see if I can...
Where were we? Yeah, we were...
We were trying to figure out which
equations are of great generality which are not.
This one, hf over c, that contains c in it.
That is not terribly general.
Oops, where's my blue?
Momentum equals h divided by lambda is general.
Okay.
Now, where this comes from, I'm not going
to try to prove these things to you now.
I'm just telling you as facts.
Go back to your quantum mechanics.
Momentum is h over lambda.
That's general.
Okay. Let's use these facts now.
Here's the relationship for a photon between...
What is it?
Between frequency and wavelength.
And as I said, it's not very general.
What about a slowly moving
electron or a slowly moving nucleus,
or for that matter, a slowly moving bowling ball?
What's the relationship between frequency and wavelength?
Can we figure it out?
Is there something on the blackboard or something...
Do we have to add something else?
Question.
For an electron...
I did tell you last time
that electrons are also described by waves.
Did I not?
I told you that you
can do interference experiments with electrons.
So there is an electron wave.
Let's call it psi.
And the question now is what
is the relationship between frequency and wavelength?
Can we figure it out?
Yes, we can, but we need
to know one fact about non-relativistic systems.
It's the analog of knowing...
It is not the analog.
It's knowing the relation between momentum and energy.
Okay.
But for an electron moving slowly,
the momentum is not the energy
divided by the speed of light.
What is it?
C squared.
Okay.
Energy is equal to...
Now we can start at the beginning and write...
I mean kinetic energy.
One half mv squared.
And the momentum?
mv.
p equals mv.
So we can solve for the velocity.
p over m.
Everything is a vector, but that's alright.
And then the energy becomes
one half m times v squared.
And v squared is p squared over m squared.
If you don't know this equation, it's an important equation.
It occurs over and over.
The energy in terms of the momentum...
is one half p squared divided by m.
People get confused.
The m is upstairs when
you multiply by the velocity squared.
It's downstairs when you multiply by the momentum squared.
Okay.
Now we have what we need to
find the relationship between frequency and wavelength.
Energy...
is...
Where is it?
Is h bar omega...
or h times frequency?
Let's use h times frequency.
Of a single electron now.
We're talking about a single electron.
h times the frequency of
the wave describing that electron...
h times frequency.
That's energy.
On the right hand side...
we have one half...
Let's put the m downstairs.
And what about the momentum?
The momentum is h times the frequency of the wave.
The momentum is h divided by lambda.
So that's h squared...
over lambda squared.
And we can divide this equation by h.
And we find that the frequency...
is one over two m...
times Planck's constant...
divided by the square this time...
of the...
wavelength.
Notice how different it is.
Over here...
the frequency...
was proportional to one over the wavelength.
Here it's one over the wavelength squared.
Now you don't have to remember this.
You don't have to memorize this.
You can always re-derive it.
The basic ingredients are the equation for the energy...
and the relationship between...
momentum, wavelength, frequency, and all that kind of stuff.
Alright.
This is just to...
illustrate...
the connections.
So that's a non-relativistic particle...
when moving slowly.
For example, an electron in an atom...
the frequency of its...
Schrödinger wave...
would be one over two m...
times Planck's constant...
divided by the wavelength squared.
Let me slow down now...
and take some questions.
That would be for...
any particle, not just an electron.
That is true for any particle...
as long as it's moving slowly...
compared to the speed of light.
Maybe we should...
Well, we'll come back...
and we'll interpolate between the slow and the fast...
another time.
There is an interpolation.
Wouldn't it work for...
the speed of light?
Neutrino is...
Well, it depends on how fast the neutrino is moving.
Most neutrinos in nature...
are moving very fast...
with close to the speed of light.
Very close to the speed of light.
So for neutrinos...
the speed of light is a good approximation...
for...
But, in principle...
neutrinos can be slowed down...
and if they're moving with very
much less than the speed of light...
it's the other formula.
The non-relativistic formula.
Yeah, question.
In the discussion about...
the abiotic proportion of the prosper...
and so that's where...
the electrons all have the same wavelength?
Yeah.
If they're different wavelengths...
then you can take the 70...
and you don't...
We'll come back to the relation between amplitudes and...
and quanta...
soon enough.
And that's...
that's what the whole story is about.
But we haven't gotten...
to the point where we can...
An electron accelerator...
let's say with 20 keV...
We have an accelerator with 20 keV...
very low energy accelerator.
As an example...
is it slow or fast?
Is it what?
Is to consider slow or fast?
Very...
For an electron...
slow.
Slow.
All right, well you...
All right, good.
All right.
Um...
If you want to know...
Okay.
First of all...
Let's work in units in which...
c is equal to 1.
In such units...
momentum and energy have the same...
exactly the same units.
All right, where do we have it?
Momentum...
and energy have exactly the same units...
of c is equal to 1.
If you want to know if something is relativistic...
or non-relativistic...
you want to compare its momentum to its mass.
If its momentum is large compared to its mass...
its rest mass.
It's not...
It's not mass, it's rest mass.
A photon has no rest mass...
and so its momentum is always much larger than its...
than its mass.
And so it's highly relativistic.
As relativistic as it can be.
The figure of merit...
the thing that you compare...
is the momentum to the rest mass.
So now you have to tell me...
what's the rest mass of an electron...
you gave me in kev.
Okay?
Kev kiloelectron volts...
is a unit of energy.
Alright?
And remember...
energy and momentum have the same units.
Alright?
So what's the mass of an electron?
Half a million electron volts.
So 20 kev is a lot less than 20...
than half a million.
And so that's a slow...
that's a slow electron.
Alright.
Any other...
cookies...
Any other questions?
Frequency and wavelength...
for a real wave...
are related.
Yeah.
So by the speed...
by the velocity of light.
So is that equation...
the last one you had...
can you rewrite it...
based on the speed...
and get the right equation...
all the way up to...
Yeah but electrons...
electron waves...
do not move...
with the speed of light.
So there's no C.
So the question is...
can you derive a velocity...
from this?
Yes.
The answer is yes you can...
but it won't be the velocity...
of the electron.
Oh.
Okay.
It would be the velocity...
of the probability wave...
or whatever.
Well...
Okay.
You can't...
you can't...
Oh.
There are two...
Yeah.
There are two velocities...
that go with waves.
One of them is called...
a group velocity...
one of them is called...
a phase velocity.
All right.
I'll...
I'll be specific.
Since you asked me...
If you take...
a general wave...
the wave...
let's assume...
it's a wave packet.
Now a wave packet...
means that it looks like a wave...
except that it...
it's not...
uh...
it's, um...
confined...
to some...
packet-like...
structure...
like that.
So it locally looks like a wave...
meaning to say a plain wave...
a sine or a cosine.
But...
it has an envelope...
that, uh...
that sort of...
confines it...
to some region.
Now in general...
In general...
depending on the specific nature...
of the wave...
you'll see that...
as that wave moves...
there are two different...
waves in the center...
of the center...
and...
the centerINE...
in the center...
is...
There are two separate velocities
associated with it and they're different
One of them is the
overall velocity of the wave packet
The other is the velocity of the
crests and troughs or whatever you call them
And what you would see, if you looked
at this wave, let's say, from some other perspective
where you see waves and troughs moving along
is you would see the packet moving with one velocity
but the waves moving through
the packet with a different velocity
In fact, typically the wave,
one is called the phase velocity
That's the velocity of the troughs and peaks and valleys
And the other is called the group velocity
The group velocity is the velocity of the whole packet
Guess which one you identify with
the non-relativistic velocity of the particle
The group velocity
And the group velocity
The group velocity is usually slower than the phase velocity
The phase velocity has not got to
do with the actual velocity of the particle
Now, there is one special case
The special case is when all waves
of all frequencies move with the same velocity
That would not be true
for a non-relativistic wave like this
Let's see
The velocity is the frequency times the wavelength, right?
So let's look at this
The frequency time the wavelength
The frequency times wavelength is 1
over 2m h bar over lambda
So different lambdas move with different velocities
And when different wavelengths
move with different velocities
you have this situation where group
and phase velocities are not the same
For the special case where all wavelengths move
with different velocities you are in the pressure sunshine
wavelengths move with the same velocity, then
group and phase velocities are the same.
So for a light wave,
all waves move with the same velocity,
the group and the packet velocity, the
the group and the phase velocity are
the same. That's a special and simple case.
All right, but we didn't, I just
wanted to illustrate some of the equations here.
And
incidentally,
this equation over here
is equivalent to another equation of
physics. Anybody know what it is?
The Schrodinger equation.
The Schrodinger equation is an equation
for a wave, and
this tells you the time
dependence of the wave, the frequency.
This tells you the space dependence of the wave. The Schrodinger
equation is exactly an equation for the relationship between the time
dependence of a wave and
the space dependence of the wave.
We will come back to it.
But this is just the Schrodinger equation in a
slightly disguised form.
Or better yet, if you knew the Schrodinger equation,
and you said, supposing I had a wave
of a given frequency that had a given wavelength,
what would the equation tell me about the relation
between wavelength and frequency? And it would be exactly this.
Okay, so that's the Schrodinger equation in a nutshell.
Can the phase velocity go faster than light?
Yes.
But the phase velocity as a
rule carries no information with it.
You can't send information faster than the group velocity.
Phase velocity doesn't really carry any
information with it.
So,
we'll come back to that. It's a technical issue that
we don't need to deal with right at this moment.
Okay.
Let's see.
Let's go on a little bit more with waves.
There are one or two
other concepts about waves that are
necessary.
And, you know, there's a lot of technical detail that I'm getting
into, but every single piece of it is really very central or important.
Okay.
We will be interested in waves moving in infinite space.
But I use the word infinite space,
infinite, infinity.
Computers don't like infinity.
And if
physics is the art of writing
equations that computers can solve in principle,
it is necessary to always remove the infinities and write
the equations for finite systems first, and then take a limit.
All right. So in studying quantum mechanics, waves,
quantum field theory, particle physics, and so forth,
it's necessary in the back of your mind,
to get rid first round of everything that's infinite,
and state the problems as if everything were finite.
And in particular, what I have in
mind now is the extent of space itself.
So one way of...
What I want you to think about
now is a wave moving in one dimension.
Three dimensions is really no different than
one dimension, except there are three of them.
So let's concentrate on one-dimensional wave motion.
It could be a violin string, it could
be a rope being wiggled back and forth,
or it could just be a wave
in a mathematical universe of one dimension.
One way of getting rid of the infinity
of space would be to make the wave
only propagate on a region of
length L.
For example, by holding down the wave at this end, holding
down your string at this end, just like a violin string,
the string is held down, holding it down at
this end, you can have all sorts of waves.
And the waves move, and they bounce off. When
they get to the end, they bounce off and reflect,
and they go back and forth, and back and forth.
That's a perfectly good way to describe things.
The problem with this kind of, let's call
it boundary condition, this is called the boundary condition,
namely, that waves, when they get to the
end, reflect. It's called a reflecting boundary condition.
The problem with it is it violates one of the
important conservation laws of physics. What would that conservation law be?
Momentum. After all, if the momentum of a wave is,
it's a vector quantity, it points in a direction.
If a wave is moving along this, here's a little wave,
it's moving along this axis, its momentum is pointing to the left.
It's pointing to the right. When it gets
to the end, it bounces off and reflects.
So, the momentum has changed sign.
Okay, the momentum has changed sign, the momentum is not conserved.
That's okay. There's nothing wrong with it. You can study it.
But if you want to keep track of things like momentum
conservation, there's a smarter thing you can do. It goes as follows.
Imagine this line is such that we identify
the beginning and the end. Now, we can
do that by replacing the line by a circle.
It doesn't have to be a legitimate geometric circle.
Just
mathematically, we connect the beginning back to
the end. So we go on a cycle.
And so as we move from here to here to
here, we can imagine we start here, move along here, and
in this magic line, when you get to
the other end, you come back to the beginning.
That's a closed,
I don't want to call it a circle because I
don't mean to imply it's a circle in two dimensions.
I just want to imply that it's periodic.
Periodic is the term for this.
Periodic space. Now you can imagine a wave
which is moving along,
moving along here,
and when it comes to the end over
here, what does it do? It just keeps going.
Right? It just keeps going. It doesn't care
about that point. That point is not a square.
It's not a special point anymore.
And so the wave just keeps cycling around,
cycling around, cycling around, and the momentum is conserved.
It doesn't suddenly reflect into the
other direction. In terms of this picture,
you can just imagine when the wave gets
to this end, it reappears at this end.
And it just keeps going to the
right if it were going to the right.
It goes to the left if it were
going to the left, and just keeps going forever.
With this trick, with this mathematical trick
of replacing space by a periodic space,
we can first of all get rid
of the infinity in the size of space,
feed it into a computer,
and we can get rid of
the problem of momentum, of non-momentum conservation.
Momentum is now conserved.
But there is a cost.
I don't know that it's a cost, but it's
a fact. The fact is that in such a world,
momentum is quantized.
Now I don't mean in the sense that,
well, it is that momentum only
comes in discrete multiples of a unit.
And it's useful to work
in understanding quantum fields, their
relation to particles, and so forth.
It's useful to remember that the momentum comes in
discrete multiples of something. So let's see how that works.
Well, first of all, it's obvious that the wavelength,
an integer number of waves, must fit.
Let's give this distance around here a
name. Let's call it L. L for length.
If it were a circle, it would be the circumference.
But let's just call it L. The total distance
around from beginning back to beginning again. Call it L.
All right.
If we're going to put a wave in there, and let's
say now that it's a wave, a sine or a cosine,
wave or whatever,
an integer number of wavelengths
has to fit onto the circle.
That means that the wavelength has to be
equal to the length around divided by an integer.
Okay, divided by an integer. So the wavelength must be
the total distance around
divided by some integer. I don't want
to call the integer n. Let's see.
Um-
I'll call it capital N.
Capital N.
Little n will be reserved for something else.
So the wavelength is necessarily the
total distance around divided by n.
Now that means the
wavelength comes in discrete possibilities.
It can be L. It can be L over 2. It
can be L over 3. It can be L over 4.
But it can't be L
times the square root of 1.
It can't be L times the square root of
2 or L divided by the square root of 2.
An integer number of waves just won't fit in here.
In other words, if you tried to put a wavelength of
the wrong wavelength in here, by the time you got back,
the wave wouldn't match with what it
was supposed to be at the beginning.
Okay, so that tells you that wavelengths come in discrete
possibilities with the integer appearing in the denominator.
Now we had an equation here somewhere
for momentum.
Momentum in terms of wavelength.
What was it?
Momentum was equal h bar.
h over lambda?
Yes, h over lambda.
P is equal to h over lambda.
So now this is also telling us that momenta come
in discrete possibilities.
The momentum of any quantum must satisfy the
constraint that it's h divided by an allowable wavelength.
So the allowable momenta of
quanta, the allowable momenta of electrons,
the allowable momenta of photons, the allowable
momentum of anything in this one-dimensional world
has to be h divided by, okay, let's
work it out, that's h divided by lambda.
That means n divided by l.
I turned lambda upside down, n over l.
And what does it say?
It says the momenta come in
discrete multiples of a basic unit,
and the basic unit is Planck's
constant divided by the total distance around.
Okay.
There's a neat fact.
If you put a particle on a wire, and the wire
is a circular wire, a bead, a bead on a wire,
that bead can only have momenta which
are discrete multiples of 1 over l.
Not n over l, n is the multiple.
1 over l.
1 over the length of the wire.
Now, of course, h is a very small number,
and the l, if l is a
big macroscopic length of wire or something,
1 over l is a very small number.
And so the quanta, the separation between different values,
different allowed values of the momenta is very small.
You can get, ohm,
if l is large and h is
small, you can get almost any number.
Not almost any number, but you can
get a very dense collection of possible numbers.
All right?
But, okay.
That's the quantization of momentum in
a world in which everything is periodic.
Question.
Yeah.
Are we talking about the total momentum
of the wave or a period of time?
Total momentum, no.
Total momentum of the object.
Total momentum of any quantum.
Now, if every quantum has to have an
integer multiple of this basic unit of momentum,
then any number of quanta also have
to have an integer multiple of it.
All right?
You might have, each quantum is identified
in terms of its value of n.
In terms of its momentum.
But there are allowed momentum and disallowed momentum.
The allowed momentum are discrete multiples of a basic unit.
And any number of photons, electrons, and
so forth necessarily come in these discrete multiples.
This is...
When do we get to have stationary models
when you come back to the same point?
That's the assumption that the
space is really genuinely periodic.
That there's nothing special about any point.
And it is a fair question.
It is a good question.
But it's also the assumption that,
for example, the electromagnetic wave, electric field,
is an observable quantity and it
doesn't have sudden jumps in it.
In fact, a sudden jump, you would have...
If it didn't come back to itself, it would
have to make a sudden jump at this point.
A sudden jump is very
costly in energy and in momentum.
So, sudden jumps in fields...
Fields are continuous things.
They're not allowed to jump like that.
What if you have a packetized wave?
If you have what?
What if you have a packetized wave covering land?
What kind of wave?
Packetized.
Oh, that's all right.
Any packetized...
That's a good word.
Any packetized wave...
That's a packetized wave...
Is a sum of individual plane waves.
Sines and cosines.
That's the Fourier analysis.
The statement, the real statement is, any
allowable wave is a sum of waves,
each of which has this discrete,
this discretized possible values of momentum.
So it's a statement about Fourier transforms,
that the Fourier analysis of any allowable
wave only has these discrete multiples of...
of basic unit of...
P.
Okay.
Is there a problem when
L gets very, very, very small?
Yeah.
As small as momentum gets very, very, very big.
How small is very small?
You don't want to get smaller than that.
You want to get smaller than that.
Yeah.
You want to get smaller than the Planck length.
That's a bad thing to do.
Up till that, no, there's no problem.
We could...
Yeah.
Let's pursue this a moment.
Something that's not in my notes, but let's pursue it.
It's important.
Let's really imagine now that we genuinely have
a particle moving on a genuine circular wire.
For fun, let's really now take a bead,
moving on a really circular wire,
and see if we can understand what
this quantization of momentum means in another language.
Let's take the circular wire to have a radius r.
Okay.
Let it have a radius r.
Oh, I erased the important equation.
What was the important equation?
The important equation was the allowable momentum
is equal to an integer times h over lambda?
Sorry, over l?
Over l, right?
Okay.
Now, the radius of the orbit is r,
and that means that p is
n h over 2 pi r, right?
You can see by now that h bar
would have been a better choice in this equation.
Right?
Let's leave it.
Later on, we'll put back h bar.
Okay, that's the momentum, and the momentum is quantized.
Every single electron, photon, or anything else
has to have an integer multiple of this.
Now, what about the angular momentum?
What's the relationship between
momentum, radius, and angular momentum?
For a circular orbit, for the simplest possible orbit,
it's 2 pi r.
Omega.
2 pi r.
Yes, it is mvr.
Well, for a non-relativistic particle, it's mvr.
mvr.
L stands for angular momentum.
But what is mv?
p.
So it's p times r.
Now, mvr is not completely general.
For a relativistic particle, the
momentum is not m times v.
But angular momentum is equal to
momentum times distance is very general.
That is, for a particle, that is the definition
of the momentum, at least for a circular orbit.
For other orbits, it's the cross product, r
cross p, but it's always r times p.
And so now look at this.
What this says is that
r times p multiplied by r,
angular momentum is an integer multiple
of h divided by 2 pi,
or an integer multiple of Planck's other constant.
All right, so angular momentum
is a quantity which is quantized,
but always in the same unit, unlike the momentum.
Here the momentum is quantized in a
unit which depends on the angular momentum.
So, on L, whoops, did
I use L for two things?
Excuse me.
What shall I call angular momentum?
Angular momentum.
Am.
We'll eventually change that.
I don't like that.
But for the moment, angular
momentum is n times h bar.
Momentum is quantized in this particular unit.
It's a periodic world, but the unit of
momentum depends on the length around the circuit.
Okay?
The angular momentum is quantized, but
always in units of h bar.
All angular momenta come in units
of h bar, except when they don't.
When they don't is when you
have fermions, but we'll come to that.
That's later, not tonight.
There are exceptions to this rule.
Okay.
Now we want, in the next hour,
to invent the idea of a quantum field.
And what is a quantum field?
In the simplest possible
case, the simplest possible situation,
what exactly is a quantum field?
How is the quantum field related
to particles and to its quanta?
What is the connection between particles and fields
with some precision?
And that's what we'll do next,
but let's take a five-minute break.
All right, now we have to enter into
the real world of quantum mechanics a little bit.
And for that, if you're not knowledgeable about it,
you have various alternatives.
One is to go to sleep.
Another is to listen and try
to get, you know, sort of a,
what's the right word for a very impressionistic,
hmm, a what?
Yeah, you know, get the, oh, there
must be some word for a very impressionistic,
sort of soft, fuzzy feel for things.
And the third is to go back, what, what?
Fox News.
I hope to do better than that, please.
And the third is to go back
and learn a little bit about quantum mechanics.
There will be nothing here that
I haven't discussed in previous lectures
on quantum mechanics.
In particular, the most important thing for our purposes now
is one of the simplest of all quantum systems,
the harmonic oscillator.
Why does the harmonic oscillator come up?
The harmonic oscillator is important
for a great many reasons,
but in our particular context,
it's because waves are oscillations.
If you just see a wave going
past you, obviously the amp, the field,
electric, magnetic, whatever it is, oscillates.
In fact, the fact that it oscillates is
equivalent to the statement that it has a frequency.
A wave may be made up out
of a superposition of many different wavelengths.
For example, light, you can
mix together different colors of light
and create light of mixed different wavelengths.
But you can also separate it,
as did Newton, into its component wavelengths.
And so every light wave can be
thought of as being made up of individual,
components, each with its own frequency,
its own amplitude, and so forth.
Therefore, it can be thought of as being
made up out of a collection of quanta,
and the quanta are not all
of the same energy and momentum,
but still it can be separated
into quanta of different energy and momentum.
And each energy and momentum
is associated with a wavelength.
Each wavelength is associated with a frequency.
And a frequency is by definition an oscillation.
So one can think of a
wave as a collection of harmonic oscillators.
Harmonic oscillators being the simplest
kind of oscillation, sines and cosines.
In order to proceed with what a quantum field is,
we have to go back
to what the harmonic oscillator is.
So let's begin with the harmonic oscillator.
Quantum mechanics is a strange theory.
It has things, numbers in it, which
don't satisfy the usual rules of arithmetic.
Technically, they are operators representing the
observable things that you can measure.
And they have some rules.
You can add them, you can multiply them,
but they don't necessarily commute.
What does that mean?
That means if you have two variables describing
two different attributes or properties of a system,
each of which by itself might be measurable,
might be something you can measure,
let's call them A and B,
just to give them names.
A could stand, for example, for electric field.
B could stand for magnetic field.
Or A could stand for the position of an electron.
B could stand for the electric field.
But any two pair of things,
then ordinarily, in ordinary mathematics, of course,
the product of them,
doesn't matter which order you multiply them,
A times B is equal to B times A.
That's just a property of numbers.
In quantum mechanics, of course, that is not generally true.
It may or may not
be true of two observable quantities.
And when it's not true,
we just write that the difference between these two,
these two A's,
is not equal to zero.
Now what nonsense.
I mean, if I measure the
electric field and it's some number,
and I measure the magnetic
field and it's some other number,
and I multiply them,
how can it possibly be
that it doesn't make sense to
multiply them in the opposite order
and get the same answer?
Generally speaking,
when the answer depends on the order of multiplication,
what it really means,
in other words, when this is not zero,
what it really means is that you
can't measure both of these things simultaneously,
that they interfere with each other.
The experiment that measures one of them
necessarily screws up the measurement of the other one.
And in that sense,
there's no contradiction when this is not zero,
simply means you can't measure both of them together.
When you can measure two things simultaneously,
and you measure them,
you get numbers for them.
When you multiply the numbers,
the numbers have to commute.
It doesn't matter which order you multiply them in.
And so the test for whether you
can measure two things at the same time
is whether this quantity,
which is also called the commutator,
AB minus BA is called
the commutator of A and B.
Commutator, you know, like going back and forth,
going to work and back.
You interchange the order of them.
It's labeled,
by a bracket with a comma,
and A and B,
the order matters.
So typically, this is not equal to zero.
Incidentally,
the commutator of B with A,
that's just exactly the same thing,
except in the opposite order.
And that's just a sign difference.
These two are the same,
except for a sign.
Okay, that's quantum mechanics in a nutshell.
We just did quantum mechanics.
Examples.
Now, I'm not proving this.
I'm just telling you this now.
But nevertheless, it's a fact.
Partly empirical fact,
partly mathematical fact.
A particle has different components of position.
X, Y,
and Z, for example.
You can measure the position of a particle.
So the components of position of a particle
are candidates
for things which are observables.
These things commute with each other.
You can measure
the X and the Y of a particle
at the same time.
You can measure the X, the
Y, and the Z of a particle
all three simultaneously.
What else can you measure
about a particle?
You can measure its velocity,
mass times velocity,
and those things are called,
the components of them are called
PX, PY, and PZ.
They're the components of the
vector momentum.
And they also
commute with each other.
You can measure the three components,
or better yet, the magnitude
and the direction of
the momentum.
But you can measure all three components
simultaneously. There's no obstruction.
They commute with each other.
So, X commutes with Y,
commutes with Z.
PX commutes with PY, commutes with PZ.
But the components
of position do not commute
with the components of momentum.
So, for example,
you cannot measure
the position,
the X component of the position
of a particle,
and the X component of the momentum
every time
you try to measure the X component
of position, you will give
the particle a whack and change
its momentum, and the result
is you can't measure both of them.
This is not equal to zero.
It's equal to I times
Planck's constant.
It's small.
Simply reflecting the fact
that, um,
well, the uncertainties in position
and momenta are small and
of order H bar.
Likewise, for the Y component,
the Y position
and the Y momentum
don't commute with each other.
Same for the Z components.
How about X with the Y component
of momentum?
Can you measure X and the Y
component of momentum simultaneously?
Yes, as a matter of fact, you can.
Uh,
that may not be obvious,
but it is true.
Okay, um,
so that's
another aspect
of quantum mechanics.
And now let's consider the harmonic
oscillator. Now I'm telling you facts
for the most part, but I'll try to put
the mathematical facts into some kind of
context. These are the facts
that we went through previous
quarters, so I'm not going to
derive them.
Just one quick question.
Yeah.
When we go from X to Y,
is it conventional to go
I to J?
No.
What is the square root of minus one?
This is not I, J, and K
which are unit vectors along the three axes.
No.
And they're also not quaternions,
which also have an I, J,
and a K associated with X, Y, and Z.
But, uh,
no, just I. Just the square root of minus one.
Where does the square root of minus one
get into a formula like this?
Don't ask. We're not going to need it.
The fact is we won't
really need it. We just need to know
that algebraic
manipulations in
quantum mechanics are a little bit
funny, and the funniness
is that you can't, as a rule,
interchange the orders of
operations.
Sir?
Yeah.
A,
AB minus BA.
That means first measure A, then...
It doesn't mean measure.
Forget measuring.
Uh,
these are simply mathematical
manipulations
which
are...
Yeah. It doesn't mean first measure A
and then measure B.
It's simply a...
Not simply.
It is a mathematical
manipulation that, uh,
uh,
It's matrix multiplication.
Operator multiplication, yes.
But, uh, we're not going to...
We're not going through the principles of quantum
mechanics here. I'm just restating
things that we've learned in the past.
And if, uh,
you, uh,
need
to understand them better, the only way to do it
is to go back to earlier
lectures. Okay.
Question? Yes, sir.
Does that apply to a photon?
Not quite.
But close.
There is a... It doesn't really apply to
a photon. It applies, strictly speaking, to
non-relativistic particles.
Um,
the problem is that the position of a
photon is not so well defined.
The position of a photon is harder to define
than the position of a non-relativistic
particle. Uh,
So,
um,
But let's... We can come back to that.
That's a subtlety which is not terribly
important to us now.
Okay, the harmonic oscillator.
The harmonic oscillator
is a system, a classical
system, which has a quantum
mechanical analog.
And it simply means a system which
oscillates a weight
on the end of a spring which
oscillates up and down.
Uh, a sound wave that
oscillates, a light wave
that oscillates, anything that oscillates
like a spring going back and forth.
We can think of thousands of examples,
and the mathematics of them
is always the same.
Every oscillation, or every oscillator,
has a frequency.
It can either be taken
and we can call it an
omega.
The frequency, again, is 2 pi
times the number of cycles
per second.
Alright? Cycle per second for a spring
with a weight on it is
just how long it takes to go
through one full swing and
come back to the same place.
Not just the same place, but the same velocity.
So if you have a weight
on the end of a spring
and it oscillates,
the frequency
is not
how long it takes to come back to the same
place, but how long it takes
to come back to the same
place moving in the same direction.
So one full oscillation
uh
is the period
the number of
cycles, or number of oscillations
per second is the frequency f
and as usual
omega is 2 pi f.
Nothing
unusual. The usual
omega.
Now,
what is unusual about the
quantum mechanical harmonic oscillator
is that energy
is quantized.
Not momentum, not the
uh, but energy
is quantized.
This is something which you
either look up
or accept.
So let's plot vertically
the energy levels of such a
harmonic oscillator.
Classically,
of course, there is a lowest energy
which is zero.
Just the oscillator at rest.
And then you give it a little poke
and it starts to swing back and forth.
You can give it any positive value of energy.
Of course, if you hit it too hard
and try to give it
too much energy, you might melt
the spring or
break the spring.
But in a mathematically idealized
version of the harmonic oscillator,
you can give it any positive
value of energy.
Not so the quantum mechanical oscillator.
The quantum mechanical oscillator
has discrete
integer
units of
energy.
If we call the lowest energy
zero,
sometimes
it's appropriate
to call the lowest energy
not quite zero, but we can define.
We can define the lowest energy
to be zero, then what's the
next energy level?
H bar omega.
The same formula
as the energy of a photon
of frequency omega.
What's the next one?
Two H bar omega.
That could either be
the energy of a single
photon associated
with a frequency twice as big
as the first one,
or it could correspond
to two photons
both associated
with a wave of frequency omega.
It's the second
idea
that I want to dwell on.
That this has the same energy
as two photons.
Now, so far there are no photons.
There's only springs and balls
and oscillations back and forth.
But nevertheless, this does have
the energy of
one photon
associated with a frequency omega.
This has the energy of two photons
of frequency omega
and so forth. Three H
bar omega and so forth.
Those are the
possible energies of the harmonic
oscillator.
Nothing in between.
We can label them
with an integer.
And we can write that the energy
is an integer
times H bar omega.
Where
n is just an integer
which labels which one of these states
the oscillator
is oscillating in.
It's
just a matter of notation.
For us here, it's just a matter
of notation.
Mathematics of it, we don't
need to get into.
We label the various states of the oscillator
by an integer
n.
And it's
conventional to just label
the states of the oscillator by a little
pointy thing like that.
It's called a ket.
It's called a ket because it's the right hand side
of a braket.
But we don't need the bra end of it.
We only need the ket end of it.
And it's
as I said, go back and study quantum mechanics
but all this is, all this
labels, this is a symbol
representing
if you put n equals zero here
it represents the state of the oscillator
where it's in its ground state.
Ground state means the lowest energy state.
If you put a one here
it represents the oscillator
oscillating with one quantum
of energy, one unit of energy.
You put a two here, it represents
the oscillator with two units of energy.
And so forth.
So it's just a notation.
It's just a convenient notation
for labeling the various possible
configurations of the quantum
harmonic oscillator.
Now
let's invent
an operation.
It's actually not only an operation,
it's an operator. There's a difference.
An operator.
And this operator
acts
on a state
to change the state
to a new state.
So a mathematical operation
which
takes you from any state
to the neighboring one
one unit above it.
Acts on this state
to give you this one.
Acts on this state to give you this one.
So
we can write down what it does.
Let's call it A+.
And the plus indicates
that it raises the energy of a state.
And it acts
on the nth state
to give what?
n plus one
but with a coefficient in front of it.
Square root of
n plus one.
Now this is
mumbly jumbly unless you know the
bit about the
mathematics of linear operators
and so forth.
So as I said, either you know it
then you can follow it or you don't know it
then you can just get a
hazy impression of what it means.
But this is the mathematical
property
of this operation here.
It multiplies
any state vector
by a square root of n plus one
and raises you to the next level.
But basically, it's a shift.
A thing which shifts you
from one level to the next.
Just an operation which shifts you from one level
to the next.
And we gotta keep track of a numerical coefficient
in front of it.
What about A-? What does it do?
Takes you down
and minus one
What's the coefficient?
Square root of n.
What happens if this one
acts on the bottom state?
Where does it take you?
It doesn't take you anywhere.
It just gives you zero.
That's because if it acts on the bottom state
and is zero, then it just gives you zero.
Nothing. No state there.
Just the non-state.
There's nothing to get to, so it just gives you
zero.
This is the mathematics of creation
and annihilation operators
or raising and lowering operators.
Now we're just gonna
do some little mumbo jumbo
with it.
I'm gonna show you some properties
of these operations.
They're interesting,
they're entertaining, and you can do some
you can have some
fun with them.
Just knowing some
very simple set of rules.
And this is the rules.
Let's
see what
happens if we take
the state n
and multiply
it first
by
a minus and then by a plus.
In other words, let's
hit it with a minus
and then a plus.
What do we get?
All we do is follow the rules.
Alright, so first of all
Oh, one important thing.
Some things
are just numbers.
Not everything is one of these
peculiar things that
where the order of multiplication matters.
Some things are really just numbers.
Things like
n are just numbers.
That means that the order that
you multiply them doesn't matter.
Some things, the order of
multiplication is perfectly
ordinary, and n
is always something
rather ordinary.
Okay, so what happens,
what is this equal to?
Well, let's take it in pieces.
Let's first multiply a minus by n.
What does it give?
a plus and then a minus times n is what?
Square root of n
times n minus one.
So let's take that on the
outside and
n minus one.
Now what happens
if we hit it with a plus?
If we hit any vector
or any, sorry, any state
with a plus,
it raises us back, it raises us
to the next level up, but
multiplies
by
square root of n plus one.
But what does square root
of n plus one here mean?
It just means square root of n.
Since I'm now starting at n minus one,
hitting it with a plus,
will give me square root of n,
another square root of n,
and n.
Square root of n
times square root of n is n.
It just gives me the number n
times n.
That's just a little game
that we're playing. We're playing
a little game with a set
of logical rules here.
And what we find out
is if we multiply by a plus
and a minus with this set of logical
rules, it's equivalent
to multiplying by the numerical
number n.
Whatever state we put here, if we put here
the first, the zero state,
or if we put here the lowest state,
we get zero. If we put here the first state,
we get one. If we
put it in the second state,
we get two, and so forth. So whenever
we do this combined set of operations,
it picks out for us,
it picks out for us
the numerical
level,
and tells us which level we're at.
If we want to find out which level we're
talking about, I may not know
what it is. I may just call it by some
other name.
Blupas. We just put blupas here.
We want to find out what n
blupas corresponds to.
Well, we multiply it by a plus times a minus
and we find out what the numerical coefficient
is. That numerical
coefficient tells us
what
level of the oscillator
we were
playing with.
So we can write this in another way.
We can simply write that multiplication
by a plus times a minus
is the same as
multiplication by n.
But what is n?
n is simply
the energy level. Well, not
quite. The energy level, we need something
else. We need h bar omega.
We need to multiply by
h bar omega.
So we can write n h bar omega
is
h bar omega
times a plus a minus.
And what does that tell us?
That tells us that the energy of the oscillator,
if we didn't know what the energy
of the oscillator was,
we could find out mathematically,
not as a matter of
empirical experiment,
but as a matter of playing
this logical game,
we could determine what level we were
talking about by taking
the state, unknown state, and
multiplying it by a plus a minus
times h bar omega. Now, this is
a little game, as I said,
and doesn't correspond to any actual
experiment, but in fact,
this is the actual
energy of the oscillator.
Okay, so that's a mathematical
bunch of tricks, bunch of trickery.
Let's
multiply them in the opposite order.
Alright, so what did
we find out? We found out that
a plus times a minus is equal to
n,
meaning to say
that if you do this operation on
any state, it just multiplies
by n. What about the opposite
order? Let's try it in the opposite
order, using the same
little logical rules.
A minus times a plus
on n.
What does that give? Did I do that right?
A minus times a plus.
The opposite order. So what
does a plus give?
This gives square
root of n plus one
times n plus one, right?
And now let's multiply
that by a minus.
A minus will bring
you back down to n,
but
it will give you another factor of
square root of n plus one.
Alright, whenever a minus
acts,
it gives you the numerical coefficient,
which is the same as the thing
inside here.
So that gives you
square root of n plus one
times square root of n plus one
again, times n.
Brings you back down,
but gives you the overall
factor of n plus one.
So what did we find? We found
that multiplying in the opposite
order gives us different answers.
Almost the same answer, but not
quite. In one
order,
a plus a minus is n, and the
other order, a minus times a plus
is n plus one.
So with this
little bit of
logical gamesmanship here, or
mathematical
symbology,
we find that the order
of these two operations isn't the same.
Well, what does that mean?
Does that mean that a plus and a minus,
that if we were to measure them
and then take the
values that we measure for them,
the numerical values
whatever they are, whatever they correspond
to, we measure them,
that when we multiply their values
by each other, they don't commute?
Well, that doesn't make sense. Numbers always
commute when we multiply them. What this means
is that whatever a plus and a minus
correspond to,
you can't measure both
of them simultaneously.
Now what they correspond to
is a combination of the
amplitude of this harmonic
oscillator, how big the oscillation
is, and its phase.
Its phase,
does everybody know what the phase of an
oscillation is?
It's basically the time at which the oscillator
passes through the origin.
The oscillator
can oscillate back and forth,
or you can delay it a
little bit so that it goes
through the origin at a later or earlier
time. You can't,
you can't, whatever a
is, you can't measure it,
a plus and a minus simultaneously.
That's what this tells you. That's all
it tells you.
That they don't commute,
and therefore they're not simultaneously
measurable, but they're still
interesting mathematical little
objects. What do
they do? What do they do?
They are mathematical operations
which raise
you up and down this
tower.
What do they do? They add and
subtract quanta of
energy of the oscillator.
Okay. Now if
the oscillator happens to correspond
to an electromagnetic
oscillation, an
oscillation of the electromagnetic
field, then
what these operators
do is they add and
subtract photons.
They add
and subtract photons. They are
what are called creation and annihilation
operators.
Alright, so let's, uh...
Does that correspond to any
physical experiment that we would do?
Or talk about like a...
Well, you can measure the number of
photons, but you
can't measure the a plus and the a minus
separately.
It's an interesting question of whether
you can measure a plus or a minus
individually, and the answer for technical
reasons is no, but, uh...
But, uh...
But this doesn't tell you that.
Okay.
Alright, so we
have the idea now of
operations or mathematical
quantum mechanical operations,
which would make no sense classically at all.
We wouldn't, we wouldn't, uh, multiply
states by operators like this,
but quantum mechanically,
we have the idea
of creation and annihilation operators,
mathematical operations which
add and subtract quanta of
energy for a fixed frequency.
Alright.
Now, when we have a system
which has many oscillators,
you can imagine a
system where we have many springs
with many balls hanging off them
of different frequencies,
or you can imagine
electromagnetic waves in a cavity,
each different wavelength
has a different frequency.
We can excite them independently.
We can excite one wave,
we can excite another wave,
excite them independently.
Then we have a system which contains
many different oscillations
with many
different frequencies.
That means
to describe
this may be a good place
to slow down a little bit,
um, this is,
this of course is a little bit indigestible
unless you've seen it before.
How many people have seen it before?
When?
No, no, of course
I gave a lecture on it in another course.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, right.
I gave many lectures on it probably.
I don't know if you've seen it.
Oh, in this course you gave another lecture.
In this course I have not talked about this yet.
By this course I mean this sequence.
Oh, the sequence of course, yes.
We've talked about it many times, I think.
But, uh,
it certainly is in the lectures
on quantum mechanics.
It may not have been recorded
because we had to move to a different room.
It wasn't recorded?
It may not have been
because we were in a different room
and I don't know if
anybody set it up for that.
We were in the same room.
Now, it's okay. Just move on.
Yeah, okay.
The harmonic oscillator
is the most basic quantum mechanical system.
Please learn it if you want to follow these lectures.
And it is, you know,
you can see where it's going.
We describe particles
as oscillations
and we create
and annihilate particles,
put them into the system,
take them out of the system
by mathematical operations
and annihilation operators.
So they're absolutely central
to the understanding of
quantum field theory
and particle physics.
Just completely.
Okay, let's come back
very quickly now
and I think we'll have to discuss this again.
But let's come back
to this little model
of a world on a circle.
Where we made the world finite
by making space to be a circle
instead of an infinite line.
And now it's a very simple world
of only one dimension
but we have this line.
Distance around it is L.
Let's imagine
photons or electromagnetic radiation
or whatever kind of particles
moving on this line.
There are some allowable values
of the wavelength.
So the allowable values
of the wavelength
are L divided by N
where N is any integer.
That means
there are allowable values
of momentum.
There are allowable values
of frequency
and allowable values
of momentum.
Those allowable values
of frequency
we can call
omega N.
N goes from
minus infinity to infinity
whatever it goes over
well N goes
sorry
from zero to infinity
all the possible values
of frequencies.
The waves moving
on this system here
are a collection of harmonic oscillators.
One harmonic oscillator
for each value of N.
For each frequency
of oscillation
you can
add energy
independently
to each frequency.
You can take any given frequency
and add energy to oscillations
in that frequency.
You can then add energy on top of that
with some other frequency.
So a system of waves
moving on a circle like this
or moving in anything for that matter
is really just a collection
of harmonic oscillators
with a certain set of allowable frequencies.
The question is
how do you describe this system
mathematically
in quantum mechanics?
And the answer is
let's begin with the idea of a state.
We're not going to do this in detail now.
We're not actually going to get to our first example
of a quantum field.
We'll get there next time.
But let's
work around it a little bit.
How would we
label
the states of a system
where there are many possible
oscillators around?
You can either think about this as all the oscillations
of a wave on a circle
or you can just think of it
as a bunch of balls and springs
with different frequencies.
How would you label it?
Well, each harmonic oscillator
has a quantized
energy.
The quantized energy for each one of these
oscillators is some integer
times
omega n times h bar.
So what we have
to state then is
the integer
excitations
of each oscillator.
The number of
quanta
with the
lowest frequency
the lowest frequency whatever it is
or n1
the number of quanta
with frequency nb.
The number of quanta
with frequency nb2
or the number of quanta
with the third frequency
and so forth.
And on and on
for infinity forever.
This would correspond
to a state in which
the lowest
wavelength
or the longest wavelength
oscillator
has n1 quanta in it.
The next longest wavelength
oscillation would have n2, n3.
I'm getting a little bit tired and I suspect
you are also, but what
I want you to think about
is the guitar string or the violin
string and how you
how you create harmonics.
What we're talking about is harmonics.
So there's an overall
mode of
oscillation of the string
where it behaves
up and down like that.
If we forgot
everything else and just thought of this
as a simple harmonic oscillator
oscillating back and forth
we could say that the energy level
of the system is just
one, possibly no
excitations, one unit
of excitation, two units of
excitation, three units of excitation
and how much would each unit of excitation cost?
It would cost an energy unit
which was the frequency of
that particular note,
omega, times h-bar
times
the number of oscillations
with that frequency.
Then we could add
additional energy
in the form of the first harmonic.
So if this oscillation
corresponded to middle C
this oscillation would be what?
C one octave above
middle C or whatever.
Add some energy in that.
That has twice the frequency.
Twice the frequency
so we would be then adding
a number of quanta
with the second
frequency.
And then we could add
oscillations on top
of that. I always have trouble
drawing this next one.
I can't draw it, you know what I mean.
Three
with two nodes, yeah,
two nodes, but it would have
three times the frequency, right?
Three waves fit in that has
an oscillation like that has
three times the frequency
and how many oscillators,
how many quanta would we put in?
Well, we could put any
number in, but that would be
n three. And the entire
configuration of this
oscillating string,
quantum mechanically oscillating string
would be characterized by a
collection of integers which tells
us how much quantized energy
there is in each mode of
oscillation.
So basically what we have to do
mathematically is repeat
the mathematics of the harmonic
oscillator infinitely many
times, one for each
mode of oscillation.
The result is a
quantum field. That's what a quantum
field is, is it's a collection
of harmonic oscillators, a
collection of creation and annihilation
operators which add
and subtract energy
in each
mode of oscillation.
And it's the mathematics of that
collection of oscillators which is called
quantum field theory.
So if we want
to carry on with this subject,
we have to get used
to this language.
Okay.
Let's quit here.
Well, let me just say one more thing.
If we're interested in
particle physics experiments,
what happens in particle physics experiments?
Particles with given
energy momentum come in.
They
rearrange particles with
other energy and momentum go
out. So in
other words, we remove particles
with annihilation, we remove
particles from the initial state
and replace them by
particles in the final state.
The mathematical description of
that is to remove
particles with annihilation
operators and replace
them with particles of other
momentum and energy involving
other creation and annihilation
operators. So that's what these operators do.
They remove particles
and put particles in, and the
mathematical description of the creation
and annihilation of particles
is through these kind of
mathematical symbols.
That's why they're so important.
Yeah.
The n
is used to indicate
the energy level, but then it's
also used to indicate the
count of
number of quanta. Is that right?
There are two integers going on here.
One integer
has to do with the number of nodes here,
and the other has to do with the number
of quanta. I'll spell this out again.
There are two distinct
integers.
In this
example,
the number of nodes
would tell you the frequency, and then
the number of quanta
with each frequency.
So there are two integers
floating around.
Yeah.
Right, one of them is associated with the...
This is hard stuff.
This is not easy. It's abstract.
It's too abstract.
For more, please visit us at
stanford.edu.