Stanford University.
Group velocity and phase velocity?
Okay, good.
Let's talk about it a little bit.
Generally, the phase velocity of a wave
doesn't have anything to do with measurable properties
of the wave or of
the measurable things in quantum mechanics.
It's the group velocity which is really the velocity
at which signals move, the velocity
at which particles move, and so forth.
So let me just show you
what's at stake and what's going on.
The first thing is, if you have a plane wave,
a sine or a cosine,
or an e to the i kx,
and that's all, just e to the i kx,
let's write e to the i kx
minus omega t,
or just sine, the sine of
kx minus omega t will also do,
in fact, let's just write that,
sine of kx minus omega t.
Looks like that.
And how does that wave move?
How does the top of each crest move?
The top of each crest
moves in such a way that
this thing inside the sine is constant.
In other words, for example, right over here,
at time t equals zero, and at x equals zero,
the sine wave, or the sine wave
of the sine wave of the sine wave,
is constant.
So, that's the wave.
The sine wave is not a maximum at that point.
At x equals zero and t equals zero,
the sine wave happens to be over here.
Okay.
But where is the sine wave
after a certain amount of time t?
It's at the place, or that point here,
has moved, it's moved to the place where
kx minus omega t is equal to zero.
Where is that?
That's at the position x
is equal to omega over kx.
So, omega over k times t.
Just dividing by k.
Now, that's not too surprising.
If you think about it for a minute,
omega is a frequency.
So, it's inverse to the period of oscillation,
to the time of oscillation.
It's one over the time of oscillation.
There's a two pi in there, but
the two pi's appear in both things.
So, omega is like one
over the period of the wave,
one over t, the amount of time
that it takes for the wave to oscillate.
And k is like one over lambda.
Actually, there are two pi's in these equations,
two pi's in the numerator.
Let's put them in.
And so, omega over k, what's omega over k?
Omega over k is lambda over t.
It's the wavelength divided by the period.
The wavelength is the distance it moves in one oscillation.
The period is the time that it takes.
The ratio is the velocity.
So, this is the velocity
of the peak of each wave,
for a plane wave.
So, that's called the phase velocity.
Now, let's think about Schrodinger waves for a minute.
Schrodinger waves have a connection between omega and k.
The connection is, to remember it,
all you have to remember is
that omega is really secretly energy,
and k is really secretly momentum,
if we set h-bar equal to one.
And so, using the formula that energy
is equal to momentum squared divided by mass,
that just becomes omega squared is
equal to k squared divided by 2m.
Did I say momentum squared divided
by mass over twice the mass?
This is, as usual, with h-bar equal to 2m.
With h-bar equals c equals one.
In fact, there's no c's in
this formula, but there are some h-bars.
Okay, so that would tell you, for example,
let's compute the phase velocity,
the phase velocity of a Schrodinger wave.
For a Schrodinger wave, omega, sorry, omega
is equal to k squared over 2m,
not omega squared.
Omega is k squared over 2m.
So, what is the group velocity?
It's omega divided by k.
Omega divided by k.
Omega divided by k is equal to k over 2m.
That's the phase velocity, k divided by 2m.
What's the velocity of a particle in
terms of its momentum and its mass?
Momentum divided by m.
There's an extra factor of two here.
What's that doing there?
Peculiar thing.
The velocity is not the velocity
of the motion of a classical particle.
Okay, let's just keep that in mind.
That's true.
But let's do something else now.
Supposing I add a constant
to the frequency of every wave.
I simply take the frequency of every
wave, all of them, for all k,
and I add the same constant.
What should I call that constant?
I've got a name for it.
It's mc squared.
But let's not belabor it.
It's not important.
Let's just add a constant, an overall
constant, to the frequency of all waves.
What does that do to the phase velocity?
Well, it changes it.
Omega divided by k will now
have an extra term in it.
It'll have an extra term in it,
and it won't be the same.
Whatever it does, it'll be c over k.
It'll have an extra term in it.
The phase velocity will have changed.
But I tell you right now, there is no physics
in just adding a constant to
the frequency of every Schrodinger wave.
What does it correspond to?
It corresponds to adding a constant
to the energy of a particle,
and adding a numerical constant to the energy
of a particle.
And the energy doesn't ever change anything.
Only energy differences are ever important.
All right.
Can we see what's going on
in terms of the Schrodinger wave?
Well, a Schrodinger field, psi, is
some kind of sum or integral,
either a sum or an integral,
of creation operators,
or rather, annihilation operators in this case,
e to the ikx,
e to the minus i omega t,
where omega is the omega which is related to k.
So let's write omega of k.
Now supposing I add to omega just this constant c.
What does it do?
It adds in or multiplies in
to each one of these waves,
e to the ict.
Sorry, e to the minus ict.
All of the waves in here
that make up the Schrodinger field
all get multiplied by the same time-dependent phase here.
So what it does is if you
had a solution of the Schrodinger equation,
and you added a constant to the phase,
it would just change the solution,
let's say psi of x and t,
it would just multiply it
by e to the minus ict.
That's all it would do.
It would multiply the wave, sorry, by,
times psi of x and t.
It would change the wave by multiplying it
by a time-dependent phase.
All of the quantities of physical interest
that are made out of the Schrodinger field
involve psi times its complex conjugate.
The probability density,
for example,
is psi times psi star.
All possible expectation values,
quantum mechanical expectation values,
always involve psi times its complex conjugate.
So what happens to psi times its complex conjugate
when you perform this operation?
It cancels out.
It cancels out because psi star
gets multiplied by e to the plus ict.
And when you multiply them,
they cancel out.
As a consequence,
there is no physical measurability
to adding a constant to all of the phases,
and nevertheless,
it changes the velocity
of the Schrodinger waves.
So there must be something about
this change of velocity,
or this change of frequency,
which is not so much,
let's say for the phase velocity,
the phase velocity is not something
which is ever measured
when or ever appears
when you multiply psi times psi star.
So it's an artifact of a particular
mathematical
set of conventions.
On the other hand,
the group velocity
really does mean something.
It is the motion of the wave.
The motion of a,
let's say,
a wave packet
which is centered in some place.
In other words,
if you have a bunch of waves
which add up,
a bunch of waves,
a bunch of plane waves,
which add up to something
that looks like that,
maybe it has some oscillations in it,
but which look like a lump,
the whole lump moves with a velocity
that's called a group velocity.
But let's see if we can see,
just a little roughly why.
If you take a whole bunch of plane waves,
every plane wave looks like this,
goes on and on forever.
How is it possible to add them up
so that you get a concentrated lump someplace?
The answer is destructive interference.
Right?
Destructive interference
so that the waves are in phase
and add up over here
and they're out of phase
and cancel over here.
So the question then comes up.
If we're interested in the motion of waves,
and how waves of slightly different frequency
reinforce each other
and make high points and low points,
let's try to follow how that works.
Let's take two waves,
not a single wave,
but let's take two waves
of very neighboring close momentum
and try to follow
where the reinforcing
constructive interference takes place.
That'll be good enough.
Let's just follow where the constructive interference
takes place between the two waves.
So in particular,
take e to the i kx.
We could just take sine.
Sine is good enough.
Sine kx minus omega of kt.
And let's add to it,
this is just a wave moving
along with momentum k,
energy omega.
And let's add to it another wave,
which is,
let's put parentheses around this,
sine k prime,
where k prime and k
are very close to each other,
x minus omega of k prime.
So that's k prime times t.
Where are they in phase
and where are they out of phase?
In phase means they reinforce each other.
Out of phase,
in particular,
it'll mean that the two terms here
have the same sine,
and there are other places
where they'll have opposite sine.
Well, one easy way to find out
where they reinforce each other
is to ask when is the argument,
argument meaning the thing in the bracket here,
when is the argument of this wave
the same as the argument of this wave?
Those are the places,
in that case,
in that particular place,
where the argument of this wave
and the argument of this wave are the same,
it's clear the waves will reinforce each other.
They'll reinforce each other
and they will be in constructive interference.
Where is that?
That's at the place where
kx,
minus omega of kt,
is equal to k prime x
minus omega,
let's just call it omega prime,
omega prime means omega of k prime t.
But let's write this in the following way,
k minus k prime x
is equal to omega minus omega prime x.
omega of k prime x.
So,
k minus k prime x
is equal to omega prime x.
So,
k minus k prime x
is equal to omega prime x.
So,
k minus k prime x
is equal to omega prime x.
So,
we have this equation.
We have to find out
where x and t are related by this equation.
Okay,
so,
k and k prime are very close to each other.
Just for simplicity,
let's imagine
that they only differ by a very small amount,
a small fractional amount,
then,
what is omega minus omega
prime over k minus k prime?
It's the derivative of omega with respect to k.
That's all it is,
is the derivative of omega with respect to k,
if omega and omega prime are near each other.
And so, what it says,
is the place where the,
is the place where they reinforce each other
will travel along an orbit
which is x is equal to the derivative of omega
with respect to k.
That's right.
d omega by dk times t.
This is also a velocity.
It's the velocity of
the place where the waves
reinforce each other.
Okay.
And it's called the group velocity.
It's the group velocity.
Let's calculate it.
If omega is k squared over 2m
plus an arbitrary constant,
this is,
all right,
this is the phase velocity,
v phase.
What about the group velocity?
That's the derivative of omega with respect to k.
Derivative of omega
with respect to k.
That's equal to 2k divided by 2m,
otherwise known as k over m.
And what do we get from here?
Nothing.
Zilch.
Okay.
This, of course,
this is the group velocity,
v group.
And notice two things.
The group velocity does not depend
on this extra additive thing
that I put into each frequency.
Number one.
And number two,
it's exactly the velocity
of a non-relativistic particle,
momentum divided by mass.
Okay.
So...
The two goes away.
The two went away.
Yeah, that's right.
Exactly.
When I differentiated k,
I got 2k divided by 2m
and two went away.
So the group velocity
is,
is the thing which is most closely
associated with the classical motion
of a particle.
It's also the only thing
that's associated with
propagation of signals and so forth,
not the phase velocity.
We could go ahead a little more with this.
Let's see.
Do we want to?
When they say,
if you don't like the c,
is that the phasor group velocity?
Okay.
Both.
So let's go through that.
Let's go through that
and see why that's true.
This c here is not the speed of light,
incidentally.
Right.
This c is not the speed of light.
But let's go through that.
Let's take a relativistic wave
and calculate both the group
and phase velocity.
All right.
For that, we need to know a factor, too.
We need to know the relationship between,
we need to start with the relationship
between energy and momentum.
Does any of this have anything to do
with the speed of light?
Sometimes they talk about light going faster
than the speed of light.
No.
No, it doesn't.
It doesn't.
It's a good,
it is a good question,
but it doesn't have to do with that.
It's a separate issue.
Yeah.
Could he be thinking of,
you know,
the classic,
look at a wave guy,
where the phase velocity is always greater
than the speed of light
and the group velocity is almost less,
and the product is the speed of light?
Yeah.
Let's,
so let me give you an example
of that happening.
So,
let me give you an example
of that happening right now.
Not for a wave guide with a,
yeah,
it is a wave,
not a wave guide,
just a wave equation
for a particle with a mass.
We begin,
we begin in order to figure out
the relation,
the wave equation is nothing but
the relation between omega and k.
The hell with the wave equation.
Just the relation between omega and k
for a relativistic,
a relativistic particle,
a particle moving close to,
but not at the speed of light.
It's got a mass.
If it didn't have a mass,
it would move with the speed of light.
Okay.
What's the connection?
Omega is energy.
Let's write it first in a form
that we might remember best.
What's the relation between energy
and momentum for a particle
which is relativistic?
Anybody remember?
Z over C,
because momentum,
what's that?
Meta,
mega,
z over C?
The relation between,
the relationship between
the energy and the momentum
for a particle
which is relativistic.
You better remember?
Z over C,
because momentum,
what's the relation with momentum?
P.
Square root,
okay.
Square root of P squared
plus M squared,
but do we want to put the speeds
of light into here?
I think there's a C to the fourth
and a C squared,
but let's set C equal to one.
Yeah,
we've already set C equal to one.
Later on,
we can put back the C's
if we want to.
It's not necessary.
Here's the energy,
and if we now set H bar equal to one,
this is the energy
that we're going to get.
So,
we're going to get
the energy
that we're going to get
in the form of a particle.
So,
we're going to get
the energy
which is exactly the same
as writing omega
is equal to square root
of K squared
plus M squared.
So,
for a relativistic wave,
a relativistic particle,
the frequency
is the square root
of K squared
plus M squared.
Now,
if M happens to be equal to zero,
then it's omega equals
the magnitude of K.
Apart from a speed of light,
which I've set equal to one,
that's the relationship
for a wave moving
with the speed of light,
and then,
if we write omega
is equal to K,
what's the group velocity?
First of all,
what's the phase velocity?
The phase velocity
is omega over K, right?
V phase is omega over K,
and that's one.
What does that mean,
one?
Speed of light.
Right.
What about the group velocity?
V group.
That's the derivative
of omega
with respect to K.
What is that?
One.
So,
what's the derivative
of omega
with respect to K?
What is that?
One.
Because we had a wave
of mass.
Omega over K
would be
the velocity
of a wave
of mass
winning.
So,
the group velocity
and the phase velocity
are the same
for a wave
with mass
over k. That's the phase velocity. That's the
square root of k squared plus m squared over
k, but let's put it all inside the square
root. Let's put it all inside the square root. Then
it becomes k squared plus m squared over k
squared. This is bigger than or smaller than 1.
Bigger than 1. k squared plus m squared over
k squared is bigger than 1. So the phase velocity
omega over k is bigger than 1, bigger than the
speed of light. Okay, uh-oh, you get still a bit
scared, waves moving faster than the speed
of light, but what about the phase velocity?
Let's work that out. Ah, group velocity, thank
you. The group velocity is the derivative of omega
with respect to k.
All right, what's the derivative
of omega with respect to k?
Whoops, not t, the omega dk.
All right, we have to take the
derivative of a square root. That gives us
1 over twice the square root of k squared
plus m squared, and then we have to differentiate
the argument here with respect to k, so that just
gives us k. It gives us k over this. This
is the derivative.
So we have to take the derivative
of omega over k squared plus m squared.
Which is also equal to square root of
k squared over k squared plus m squared.
Isn't that nice? The group velocity is squared
of k squared over k squared plus m squared.
The phase velocity is square root of
k squared plus m squared over k squared.
They're inverse to each other. This one is greater
than 1. This one is always less than 1.
Okay? This one is less than 1. In fact, this
is the velocity of a relativistic particle with momentum k.
k squared, thank you.
Yeah. They're just inverse to each other. And
as it happens, as was pointed out by somebody,
the product of the group velocity and the phase velocity
are equal to 1. So they're just inverses of each other.
Now that's somewhat accidental. That's
a little bit of a coincidence.
That's not a very general fact.
Yeah.
Very in there somewhere is that the
wave speed must be a function of frequency.
What?
The wave speed must be a function of frequency. If
the wave speed is constant of frequency, you get no dispersion.
That's right. That's this case here where
omega is equal or proportional to k.
That's the case where all waves have the same
velocity. Right. So it's only in the case where
all the waves of different frequencies are equal to k. So it's only
in the case where all the waves of different frequencies are equal to k.
have the same velocity that the
group and phase velocity are the same.
That's a good approximation not only for light, it also
happens to be a good approximation for sound and other things.
To at least low frequency sound waves
all move with pretty much the same velocity.
And so they...
But if it's not true, then
the shape of the wave is historic.
That's right. That's right. So it's good. That's right. That's right. So
the difference of these two kinds of velocities is connected with wave dispersion.
With the changes, with the...
Yeah.
With the fact that waves change shape. Absolutely.
Change shape.
Absolutely. Okay. So that's the story about
waves, about group velocity and phase velocity.
And as I said, in quantum
mechanics, because the effect, for example, here,
the effect of an additive shift
in omega is no physical effect whatever,
it's an example of the fact that most times the
phase velocity is irrelevant to real physical propagation of any signal.
Or any energy flow or anything like that. Probability flow.
Question. A moment ago, last, you said that you can't
measure the phase velocity because these complex conjugates of those...
At least for the Schrodinger wave, yeah.
Okay. Can you measure it for a photon?
Well, for a photon, they're the same.
They're the same, yes.
They're the same. Now, it gets a little more
complicated when you have various kinds of dispersal waves.
There's a lot of different kinds of
dispersive materials that the photon can move through.
But, you know, that's for these squalid state physicists.
Is all this for waves
that don't spread out over time?
Yeah. What's true for waves that don't
spread out over time are the ones
for which all waves have the same velocity.
If different components of the wave have different velocities,
then it's going to spread out, all right? All
right. So that's the case where omega is a nonlinear
function of k, basically. If omega is a
linear function of k, then they don't spread out.
And that's the case of
all waves having one universal velocity.
Okay. At some point, maybe if somebody comes
back and asks me this question about light cones,
and things, we can come back to it. It was
a good question, but it's not quite related to this.
All right. Let's see. Was there anything else
I wanted to fill in before getting to fermions?
Yeah. Before getting to fermions, let's discuss
the issue of momentum conservation. We discussed
the issue of energy conservation. And I showed
you an example. It was really just an example
of how the time-traveling of the light cone and the energy conservation of the light cone, the time-traveling of the light cone, and
the action of light, you know, and the way that it's going over the spectrum of light and the wave, that's the case.
the time translation invariance of the
amplitudes that go into a scattering
process in quantum field theory conserve
energy. I'll just remind you very quickly
and then show you how
the momentum conservation works, very very
similar. We will come back to these things,
but then I want to get on to
fermions. That's what I want to get
to tonight. Okay let's let's get back, where
were we? I was going to
talk about momentum conservation just really
quickly. Remember how energy conservation
worked. Energy conservation we had for
example some process, it doesn't matter what
it is, a bunch of psi creation
operators, no a bunch of psi
annihilation operators, a bunch of psi creation
operators,
act on a state with a bunch of
particles in it with momenta and then we calculate
the overlap or the inner product or
the probability amplitude for a final state
with a bunch of other particles k
prime blah blah blah blah blah. Okay these
fields act on the initial states, these
fields act on the final states, and I'll
just remind you a little bit more about that.
So let's go back to the first example,
and I'll show you a little bit how it
worked. We said supposing all the
processes take place at the same point
of space and time, at the same point or
the example that I gave was one in which
one particle came in, one particle went out,
and they came in and scattered off a
point in space, but we integrated
over all possible times. The particle was
there, not this particle, but the target was
there, and so the particle could have
scattered at any time whenever it gets
there and that's represented by
integrating this over time. If you
remember each one of these psi's or each one
of these psi's is made up out of a
bunch of things involving a's, e to the i
kx's, and e to the minus i omega t's.
Omega t's.
Omega's being the energies, k's being the momenta.
Now if we said all of this took
place at the origin of
spatial coordinates, space coordinates, then this
is just equal to one. When
the operators act and we're finished calculating
everything, the only time dependence in this
amplitude comes from these e to the
i omega t's.
Let me remind you what it looked like. It
looked like e to the minus i omega of each
momentum k1 t e to the minus i omega of
k2 t dot dot dot dot. That's for the initial
states and then for the final states there
was something similar, e to the plus i omega
k prime one blah blah blah blah.
Times t.
Blah blah blah means the sum of all
of the outgoing momentum and here it's minus the
sum of all the incoming
momenta. Omega k incoming times t.
The last step was to say if we
integrate this over all times, representing the fact that
the scattering could happen at any time.
The integral of this gives what? Integral over time.
A delta function. A delta function of the
sum of the final momentum minus the initial
momentum. Sorry, final energies minus the
initial energies. When we integrate this over
time, what we get is a Dirac
delta function of, let's call it, omega t.
Okay.
Omega final. That means the sum of
all the incoming energy, outgoing energies minus the
sum of all the incoming energies. In other
words, the answer is zero unless the incoming
energies are equal to the outgoing energies and
this was just as a consequence of saying
that the process could happen
with equal probability at any time.
Okay.
Now, what about momentum conservation? Momentum conservation
is exactly the same sort of thing.
Except it has to do with space translation. If
a process can happen at any point of space
with equal probability, then it's momentum that's
conserved. Let me give you just one
example, one very simple example. This is a
process in which a particle comes in and
splits into two particles. Okay.
Can this really happen in nature?
Yes, it can really happen in nature.
Particles decay. Okay. Particles decay and an incoming
particle of one momentum can decay into particles
of other momenta. But as you know, momentum
is conserved, but let's see if we can see
why that is. So the incoming particle is described,
well, of course, it's described by a
particle coming in, the outgoing particles, this is
k, outgoing particles.
Okay.
So k prime one and k prime two.
The operator which eats the initial particle, let's call
that psi of x. This represents the particle
being absorbed at point x and then two particles
created also at point x.
That's a simple example. One particle is eaten
at point x and then it spits out two
particles also at the same point for simplicity. But
it can happen at any place. It can happen
at any place and that means we have to
integrate this over all space. Let's see what we get.
Again, these psi's have creation and annihilation operators.
There's some annihilation operator in here which
can annihilate or just work on this
particle, eat that particle. That's some A minus of k
and it has an E to the ikx in it.
Let's forget the omegas. We don't
need the time dependence in here.
All right. So that's the operator which
eats this particle over here. And then there's
these two part operators which put back the particles over
here and they give us some A plus over here.
Okay.
A plus of k1 prime, A plus of k2 prime, and then
there's an E to the minus ik1 plus k2 prime, x, same x.
All right. These operators act. They annihilate
the particles. We calculate the matrix element.
That's all trivial. The only thing of interest
that's left over is this function of position.
This is the amplitude that
the process happened at point x.
But then since x is not a special place,
it could happen anywhere as we integrate it over x.
What do we get when we integrate it
over x? A delta function of momentum conservation.
All right. So if a process can happen with
translation and variance in space, then it will conserve momentum.
And in fact, it didn't matter
how many particles were coming in.
It didn't matter how many particles were coming
in and going out in this little demonstration here.
It would have worked the same way.
Translation and variance or the idea that
the process could happen anywhere with equal amplitude,
that's momentum conservation.
The idea that it can happen with
equal probability at any time, that's energy conservation.
There was another symmetry we talked about a little bit.
The other symmetry that we talked about a little bit
was a possible symmetry if we multiply psi by
e to the i times, let's call it lambda.
In other words, just change the phase of psi.
What will that do to probability amplitudes?
Well, the answer is it will do nothing to them as
long as there's the same number of sies inside each of them.
So that's the same thing as saying that the number of particles
coming in is the same as the number of particles going out.
And so symmetry with respect to changing
the phase of the wave function like that,
just multiplying it by an overall phase and
multiplying its complex conjugate by the opposite phase,
that's associated with certain conservation laws
such as conservation of a wave.
Such as conservation of electric charge.
Conservation of electric charge tells us that
is contained in symmetries of this type here.
If these were charge-carrying fields, charge-carrying
fields mean fields for electrons, for example.
If they were fields for electrons,
then this symmetry would be correct
only if there were as
many electrons in the initial state
as in the final state.
This is of course a law
of nature that charge is conserved.
So the law of nature that charge
is conserved is the same as the symmetry
under changing the phase of the wave function.
These are some examples of symmetries.
That was a quick review.
Now I want to move on
to the notion of a fermion.
When you're doing the integration over
space, that's overall three spatial dimensions?
Yeah, say.
That would mean conservation of all
three components of the momentum, exactly.
Then if you have two positive k's and
a negative k, the k's may have a distribution.
In other words, you could have one is
larger, one is smaller, the other one is larger.
Yes, yes, yes.
Is there anything here that could point to...
Some relative probability for different
ways that the momentum is shared?
Yeah.
Not for this case here.
For this case here, it's basically neutral with
respect to the ways the momentum is shared.
Can't say anything.
Here it's just nothing.
We'll come back to these things.
The kinds of...
We'll come back to it.
I simply wanted to give some very,
very simple illustrations of the connection between symmetries
and conservation laws and how
quantum fields are used to describe,
and how quantum fields are used to describe,
physical processes of creation
and annihilation of particles.
Yeah.
A technical question.
I have in my notes where we have the...
We were doing a sum over k of annihilation
operator times e to the plus ikx times some state.
And I wrote that it reduces to one term...
The state has a particle in it.
That's right.
There's one particle.
And it's annihilating by summing over k.
Right.
And I wrote that it reduces to one term.
And I wanted to ask whether that means that if
the terms which are annihilating places where there are no particles...
They just don't...
Zero.
Gives you zero.
Yeah, zero vector.
Right.
Zero vector is zero.
It's nothing at all.
All right.
So, let's...
Depart from the theory of bosons.
The characteristic of bosons is, first of all, you
can have any number of them in any quantum state.
And as we described a couple of lectures ago, they
have a tendency to want to accumulate in the same state.
An example of that is...
If a particle decays and produces a photon, for example, an atom decays and produces a
photon, it may produce a photon in any direction with any momentum with some probability distribution.
But if at the same time as it decays, there happens to be a large number of photons all
in the same state, in other words, all moving the same way with the same energy and the same frequency,
it will preferentially decay so that the photon that comes out
has the same momentum as the extra photons which are already there.
That's the square roots of n
that occur in the boson operators.
Fermions are very different.
Fermions don't like each other.
They don't like to congregate into the same state.
In fact, they simply can't be in the same state.
This, of course, is a very interesting phenomenon.
This, of course, was a discovery that
was first made by Pauli, I guess.
Was it Pauli?
Yeah, sure, Pauli exclusion principle.
In the context of atoms, that two electrons
never occupy the same quantum state within an atom.
And that was generalized by
Pauli himself, Pauli, Fermi, others,
to a powerful principle that fermions are particles that simply can never
be in the same quantum state in atoms, out of atoms, anywheres.
Very different than bosons.
Okay, let's work out some of
the mathematics or some of the bookkeeping.
The mathematics of creation and annihilation operators
is really a form of bookkeeping, useful bookkeeping.
But let's try to work
out a theory of quantum behavior.
Let's work out a theory of quantum fields of
fermions, particles that can never be in the same state.
Well, we start with the same kind
of construction as we did for bosons.
Imagine a quantum field, psi of x, which
is again exactly the same formula as for bosons.
Summation over all of the allowed momenta,
I guess I call it k usually,
all of the allowed k, if the
allowed k are continuous, it becomes an integral.
Annihilation operator for a particle of momentum
k, e to the i k x.
The states of the system are again labeled by
how many particles there are in each quantum state,
but the rule is never more than one.
So the state of the system is always the same.
The state of the system is
a bunch of zeros and ones.
Never more than one particle in the same state.
That's the character of a fermion.
Now, are there other kinds of things that can
have three particles in the same state but not more,
or that must have more than seven particles
in the same state, or other odd varieties?
The answer is no.
But to prove that there are other kinds of
things that can have three particles in the same state,
we have to prove that the mathematics
of quantum mechanics together with special relativity
dictate that the only possibilities of fermions and
bosons would take us far beyond this class.
So we're not going to do that, but
we are going to describe what a fermion is.
All right, so this is exactly the same.
This formula is exactly the same as for bosons.
Psi dagger of x, same thing.
Incidentally, this is all non-relativistic particles.
We'll get back to relativistic particles.
Eventually we will.
But what do the creation,
same thing with creation operators.
A plus of k, e to the i kx.
But now the rule is a little different than before.
Yeah, there is a minus sign.
All right, so now let's focus just
on one possible momentum of the electron,
or this could be an electron.
Now let's focus on one possible state.
Not worry about all of the states,
but let's just say some particular quantum state,
it's either filled with an electron or it's empty.
Those are the only two possibilities.
Let's represent that.
I guess we can represent that by zero.
That represents no electron in that state.
Or one.
That represents one electron in that state.
This isn't multiplying this.
This is just two possible states.
Put a comma here.
What is the algebra or the abstract
mathematics of the creation and annihilation operators?
Let's see if we can make some guesses.
You'll make the guess.
A creation operator on the state with no particle.
You want to guess?
One particle.
What else could it be?
What about a creation operator
on the state with one particle?
Zero.
Now zero does not mean the state with no particles.
It just means the zero vector.
I don't write that as just zero.
It doesn't mean anything.
It's not a vector at all.
It's a non-state.
What's that?
Louder.
Is the operator still linear?
Yeah, they're all linear operators.
In quantum mechanics, all operators are linear operators.
When one speaks about an operator, especially
in quantum mechanics, it's always a linear operator.
I think mathematical terminology is that operator
usually means, maybe always means linear operator.
Otherwise it's operation, but I'm not sure.
But yes, in quantum mechanics,
operators are always linear operators.
Okay, let's see if we can make some more guesses.
What about A minus on O?
Well, you can't take away that which is not there.
But what about A minus
on the state with one particle?
No particles.
No.
All right, so these are operators
which, well, they do what they do.
They do what they do.
Just to clarify, the zero there, that means
that doesn't happen and you can't do that?
No.
Let me give an example.
If we described harmonic oscillators by
wave functions, ordinary wave functions, then
there would be a wave function for the ground state.
And the wave function for the ground
state, let's just discuss this for a minute.
The wave function for the ground state would
be some Gaussian wave function like E to the
minus X squared.
All right?
So this is the wave function.
This would be identified as the ground
state and therefore the state with no excitations.
All right?
On the other hand, the wave function, psi
of X, which is literally equal to zero, that's
the state zero.
No wave function at all.
All right?
Probability is just zero.
It's not a state.
It's just a nothing.
Okay.
That's the...
This is the starting point for the
algebra of fermionic creation and annihilation operators.
There's nothing in the notation that helps
us distinguish between the fermions and the
bosons, then?
Well, yes, I suppose we should.
Yeah, it's a good point.
We should probably use a different letter.
Let's not call fermionic operators A.
Okay.
We could call them alpha.
Sometimes C is used.
Why don't I use C?
Okay.
Well, the problem is that there are
many different, not inconsistent, but many different notations
in the literature.
And I guess for us, we probably are
wise to use a notation where bosonic and fermionic
operators have different letters associated with them.
So let's call this C.
This is a common notation also
that fermionic operators are labeled C.
But they are the analog for
fermions of the As for bosons.
Okay.
Whoops.
All right.
Okay.
Let's see if we can figure out what C
dagger C, or C plus times C minus, does.
What does that operator do when it acts on anything?
All right.
So let's figure out what it does.
What happens when it acts on O?
Well, C minus, when it
acts on O, just gives zero.
And C plus isn't going to do, is not
going to be helpful in getting it back to being
non-zero.
Zero is zero.
So this is zero.
You simply can't take away what's not there.
Okay.
Even if you try to put it back
afterwards, you can't take it away to begin with.
What about C minus times C plus on O?
What does that give?
C plus, when it gives O, gives what?
Zero.
One.
And then C minus?
Zero.
O.
Let's call it O.
Let's call this O, as opposed to zero.
So this gives back this state.
In other words, it gives back exactly the same state.
It gives back exactly the same state.
What about C plus, C minus plus C minus plus?
C plus.
C minus C plus. If it acts on O, let's
see, what does it give when it acts on O?
We're just adding those two equations, right?
It just gives O. The ground state, right.
Sometimes known as the vacuum. Let's now
do the same thing acting on one.
What is C minus C plus acting on one?
Well, C minus when it acts on one takes the
particle away and leaves O, the vacuum, and
then C plus puts it back, right? So
this gives one back again. What
does it give when it acts on
one? One. One. Acting on one.
Minus, yeah. That's correct, isn't it? Yeah.
Okay. Now what happens when we do this?
It's zero because we can't add another
particle to one that's already present if
it's a fermion, so this is zero.
What happens if we add these two
equations?
We find again C plus C minus plus
C minus C plus on one gives one.
So four equal to I. Yeah. Both
of these operators, well this operator, this particular
combination when it acts on any
state gives back exactly the same state.
So that's written in operator notation by saying C
plus C minus plus C minus C plus is
equal to the unit operator. It just gives
back the same state, whatever it acts on.
This combination, an operator times
another plus the interchange, what would
you call it if there was a
minus here? You would call it the combination.
Minus.
Minus really is the best.
Minus itself is what?
Because it could be defined as, well if
you have a plus and you've got five
units at food point A, I count them
all as an thenness, a consideration of the
products in that Bailey of learning.
There's a one.
If.
If you get it.
Well, if you gave it a negative.
What?
You can get it that way, just by noodle ordering.
Okay.
So the number here of
goodasses is called the binary ef.
By A, root 1 K.
So we have a process with him a first mono.
As a matter of fact, A, l, m, f.
Like root zero onto A.
Think about A and b again even by this expression.
After I showed you the first
one he had the threeennes in it.
B plus BA.
So the first thing we
learn is the creation and annihilation
operators anticommute to give 1 on the right-hand side.
This is incidentally the analog.
Yeah, it doesn't matter which order you write them in,
since they're the same.
Well, no, sorry, they're not the same.
But it doesn't matter which order you write them in.
C minus, C minus, C plus, same thing.
This is the analog for bosons
of the commutator of A minus
with A plus is equal to 1.
It's the analog.
It's not the same thing, but it's the analog.
In this case, it's commutator.
For bosons, in this case, it's anticommutator.
Now, what about the anticommutator
of C plus with C plus?
The anticommutator of C plus with
C plus is just C plus,
C plus, plus C plus, C plus.
It's just twice C plus squared.
Twice this.
What does this give when it acts on anything?
Well, if it acts on the
vacuum, it can create a particle.
But then the next one is going to try
to create a particle on top of a particle which
is already in the vacuum.
So it's going to try to create
a particle on top of a particle,
which is already in the vacuum.
So if it acts on
a particle, which is already there,
it can't do that.
If it acts on a particle which is already there,
So whatever it acts on, C
plus, C plus always gives 0.
All right?
So C plus, C plus gives 0.
What about C minus, C minus?
Anticommutator C minus, C minus.
That's just twice C minus squared.
So the first operator acts with a particle.
The first operator removes a particle.
And the second one looks for a particle,
can't find one, and says 0.
If it acts on a state
without a particle, it also gives 0.
This is the analog for harmonic oscillators of commutators.
Is that 0 or 0?
No, I mean, C minus, C minus.
Can't you get the vector?
No.
This is an operator.
It's not a vector.
Right, it's the operator 0.
Yeah, it's the operator 0.
The operator 0 is such that
when it acts on any vector,
on any state, it gives 0.
It really is literally 0.
Whenever it acts, it just doesn't give anything.
It gives 0.
There's an operator which is 0.
And there's a vector which is 0.
Not a vector, but a state vector, a state vector
which is 0.
Two different uses of 0, but they're both 0.
And in fact, when the
0 operator acts on any vector,
state vector, it gives the
state equal to 0, 0 vector.
OK, so fermions and bosons have a parallel mathematics
to each other, where wherever you see commutator,
for bosons, you replace it by anti-commutator for fermions.
And it is a consequence of
this that you can't put two particles
in the same state.
If you try, that's trying to
put C plus, C plus on O.
And C plus times C plus is 0.
That's what this equation says.
C plus C plus plus C
plus C plus is equal to 0.
So this algebra.
OK.
Incorporates and encompasses the idea
that you cannot put two particles into the same state
described by these creation and annihilation operators.
I want to prove a little observation about this.
These C's here create and annihilate particles
with given momentum.
What we've proved, what we've assumed,
it's some combination of prove and assume,
proved from the, from the, oh, incidentally, yeah,
we should write this more completely.
Supposing we're now talking
about creation and annihilation operators
for different momenta, K and K prime.
Then I will just tell you
this is delta K K prime.
In other words, it's 1 over delta K K prime.
OK.
1 if K equals K prime.
0 otherwise.
And these, and these things are always just 0.
C minus C minus are just equal
to 0 for all K and K prime.
That's the algebra of
creation and annihilation operators, which,
if you like, by definition.
This defines the algebra of
creation and annihilation operators for fermions.
The fact that it really does
describe fermions in nature, of course,
is a marvelous correspondence between mathematics,
simple mathematics, and some physics.
But here's an interesting question.
As defined up till now, what this says is
that you cannot put two particles into the same momentum.
You cannot put two particles into the same momentum.
You cannot put two particles into a momentum state.
You cannot make two particles carrying the same momentum.
Two fermions.
Two fermions of the same kind, incidentally.
Two fermions of the same species.
You cannot put them into the same state, momentum state.
Can you put them into the same position state?
What this tells us is that if we find
a particle with momentum K, a fermion, an electron,
an electron, we cannot find another one
with exactly the same quantum state, same momentum.
What about the same position? Can we find two
particles at the same place in, not in momentum,
but in position? So let's try to find out.
How do we create a particle at point x?
We create a particle at point x using psi of x.
Psi of x on the vacuum represents a particle at point x.
Oh sorry, I think we should
have psi dagger, huh? Yeah, creation operators.
So the question is what happens if you
try to create two at the same point?
What happens?
Well, let's see what we have. That means we're going to have a sum over
a k and a k prime of c plus of k, c plus of k prime,
and then let's do it at the origin.
Let's just do it at position zero.
Then these e to the i
k x's aren't there on zero.
Well, what is this?
Can anybody tell what this is?
All the terms are zero when
k does not equal k prime.
No, no, the zero in any case.
You can rewrite this.
You can rewrite this in the form c plus of k, c plus of k prime, one
half c plus of k plus one half c plus of k prime, c plus of k.
Because it's under the summation here.
But this is just the anti-commutator of two c pluses.
Anti-commutator of c pluses are all equal to zero.
So this is zero.
Of y?
Because the anti-commutator of c pluses is zero.
Then y is zero?
You should have asked me that before.
Because I wrote it on the blackboard.
Well, yeah, yeah, no, right, right.
All of this is very clear
if we're talking about only one k.
It gets some real impact, non-trivial impact, when we generalize
it in this fashion here to all k and k prime.
All right, so there's basically
some physics that's going in here.
And what is that physics?
It's the physics that not only can't you put two particles into the same
momentum state, but you can't put them into the same position state, for example.
What I'm showing you is that with this algebra,
if this algebra is correct,
then it's not just that you can't
put two particles into the same momentum state,
you can't put them into the same position state.
In fact, you can't put
them into the same state altogether.
But this was just an example.
With this algebra, it says that you cannot put particles either into the same
momentum state or the same position state or any other state, for that matter.
So these are fermions.
This is the pattern for fermions.
Yeah?
I've always maybe misunderstood that you could have two electrons
in the same momentum if they were far enough apart.
Yes, yeah.
The correct statement is you can't
have two electrons in the same state.
Now, what constitutes a state?
It constitutes a state may not just be its momentum.
It may be its momentum and its
spin, which we haven't come to yet.
This is one of the things we're going to come
to shortly, is the concept of spin, a very important concept.
We haven't come to it yet.
So at this stage, we're imagining that
a particle is characterized by a momentum.
And if it's a fermion, you
can't have two in the same momentum.
Now, the correct statement is, of course,
you can't have them in the same state.
And if a state requires other ingredients besides its momentum, for example, its spin,
then you can't have two particles with the same momentum with the same spin.
But spin is only really parallel and anti-parallel.
Yeah.
But what about two electrons and two hydrogen
atoms that are separated in some distance away?
Could they possibly have the same momentum?
Momentum or?
Momentum.
I just want to stay with momentum.
You want the atoms or the?
Well, just an electron.
Maybe you used a bad example.
Well, electrons and a hydrogen
atom are not in momentum states.
They're in atomic energy levels.
Now, the atomic energy levels over here and over here
for two different atoms are two quite different wave functions.
So if you have an atom over here, an electron
might occupy a wave function that looks something like this.
Another atom over here might have
an electron which looks like this.
This wave function and that
wave function are not the same.
Right.
They're quite distinguishable by the fact that one of
them is over here, one of them is over here.
So yes, you can have two electrons in two different atoms,
both, for example, in the ground state, in some particular state.
Yes.
But you can't have two electrons in
the same atom with the same quantum numbers.
To be more generic.
What's that?
To be more generic, instead of specifically talking
about atoms, could you just use the term systems?
Is that used in the language?
States is the right statement.
The right nomenclature is you can't have
two electrons in the same quantum state.
In the same quantum state, yeah.
A system means a collection of atoms.
A system means a collection of degrees of freedom.
But it doesn't imply a particular state.
So an electron is a system.
An electron can be in a particular state.
So the nomenclature is an electron is a system.
The state of the electron is perhaps some particular
orbital state, orbital and spin state in a particular atom.
Can I just carry that one further?
Yeah.
I mean, you have a
picture tube, a cathode ray tube.
Yeah.
You have a stream of electrons.
So that means that no two of those in
that little glass jar would have the same state.
Yeah.
They really look like this.
A packet over here, another packet over here, another packet over
here, another packet over here, and they're not in the same state.
But not in the same momentum.
That's right.
They're not in the same momentum.
They're not in the same position.
Right.
In big contrast to the idea of photons,
photons march down the axis all for zero.
For example, in the same plane wave.
Right.
That's why you can't build up a coherent beam of electrons
in the same sense that you can have a coherent beam of...
You just can't put more than
one of them in the same state.
So a fermion is in many
respects a bigger abstraction than a boson.
Can you have two electrons in
the same place with different momentum?
No.
No, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no.
No, no, no, no, no, no, no, no.
You can't describe a thing by a
position or a momentum, and not both.
Position and momentum are intertwined.
Mutually incompatible.
Right.
So it's only like spin and position that...
Yeah.
That's because spin commutes with momentum and position.
All right?
But position and momentum don't commute, so you can't
speak about an electron at a position with a momentum.
But you can speak about an electron
at a position with a particular spin.
Is there some sense in that?
Is there some sense in which this bound electron over here and that
bound electron are therefore, in that sense, in a position representation or something?
This is...
No.
They're not at position eigenstates because the wave
function isn't that concentrated, but they approximately are.
They're approximately located at the position of the atom.
You can't put two of them into
the same atom in the same way,
but you can have two different atoms, which is like
having an electron over here and an electron over here.
That's fine.
Yeah.
Yes?
So what is the definition of a state?
Yeah.
What is the definition of a state?
Hmm.
I think I would have to refer you either
to my own lectures or a book on quantum mechanics,
but it just means...
It's the quantum mechanical analog
of the configuration of a system.
The configuration of a system...
A system is a collection of degrees of freedom.
It's a collection of coordinates
and momenta and things like that.
A state is a particular value in
classical mechanics of the positions and momenta.
In quantum mechanics, the state of an electron is the...
Everything you have to specify about the electron to state
all the things that can be measured about the electron.
It's a wave function, actually.
Can an electron here, an electron, let's say, in the
Andromeda Galaxy, three electrons, can they be in the same state?
No.
Obviously not.
One of them's here and one
of them's in the Andromeda Galaxy.
That's pretty different.
It's like saying to me, well, suppose you
have one in Nevada and one in Connecticut.
Can they be in the same state?
Yeah.
you don't really know
their momentum with infinite precision.
So if you know anything about where they are,
it means that you don't completely know the momentum.
But yes, to within the
extent that an electron in Nevada
can have a pretty well-defined momentum, but still not
so well-defined that it might be in Connecticut, right?
Well-defined, but not so well-defined
that it might be in Connecticut.
Then yes, you can have an electron in Nevada
and an electron in Connecticut, which have pretty much
the same momentum.
But if you really tried
to make that momentum infinitely sharp,
that electron in Nevada would be equally
likely to be in Connecticut.
And the one in Connecticut
would be equally likely to be
in Nevada.
And you simply can't put
them both into the same state.
You just multiply the uncertainty by together,
and you get Planck's constant of the greater.
Right.
OK, so we now know what
a fermion is, more or less.
We use the algebra of these operators
in a very similar way.
We write down expressions involving electron operators,
which annihilate electrons, or which take electrons out
of the initial state.
Creation operators, which put electrons
into the final state.
We can even multiply them by operators for photons, photons
incidentally being bosons.
And we can write mathematical expressions
for the process of some number of electrons coming in,
some number of electrons going
out, plus a bunch of photons.
And we can write similar
kinds of bookkeeping, as we used
to describe just the simple processes involving bosons.
And we're not going to go into that now.
I mean, it is the story of particle physics,
how you describe those reactions.
But before we get to that, I want
to talk a little more about the differences between fermions
and bosons.
Question?
Yeah.
Just on the two-state example,
is the Pauli exclusion principle
a locally communicated principle, or is it ?
Is it globally enforced instantly, like entanglement?
In other words, if you had two
different processes going on in Nevada and Connecticut,
they were both about to create a particle.
But if one is known to be in Nevada
and the other is known to be in Connecticut,
then they're not in the same state, period.
Yeah, but let's say it's not known.
Let's just say there's a slight probability difference.
So there's a certain amount of fuzziness.
All right.
Oh, now, hayah.
You heard me clearly.
Yeah, that's better.
Now there are two differentanche.
You said you have to have
ML, my paper points in this.
Oh, no, I'm sorry.
So here's my second, here's my last magnitude variation,
but I can't tell you
all the values in this .
All right, so here is the situation.
Let's imagine that Nevada is a point and Connecticut
let's call it capital N incidentally. N
is not an integer, it's just Nevada.
An electron in Connecticut I will call
C. Now there's a quantum state of an
electron which is a superposition of
being in Nevada and Connecticut. It has
some probability of being in Nevada
and some probability of being Connecticut.
Nevada plus Connecticut. This is
one electron with equal probability, you
should put a 1 over square root of
2 here to make the probability come out to
be 1. This is a state of an
electron which has equal probability of being in
Nevada or Connecticut. It's a quantum state
and if you look for that electron
you'll either find it at the center
of Nevada or at the center of Connecticut
with an equal probability. Incidentally there
is another state like this which
is orthogonal to it.
Which has a minus sign here. Okay what
you can't have is two electrons both in
this quantum state. You can have
one electron in Nevada, one electron in
Connecticut, but you can't have two
electrons which are in this state of
both being equally shared between
Nevada and Connecticut. Now that has
implications. It's probably not at all
obvious to you what those implications
are.
But so you can't have two
electrons in the same quantum state.
Supposing we tried to make two electrons in
this state, you can't do it. You can't
have two electrons which are equally shared
in this way between Nevada and Connecticut.
Can one have a plus sign
and the other one a minus sign?
Yes. One can have a plus sign and the
other have a minus sign. Yes, yes, yes, yes, yes.
One electron can be in the state with a plus
sign, the other one in the state with a minus
sign.
And we're talking about at the same time
here. We're talking about at the same time.
Absolutely.
We're talking about at the same time.
So the ambiguity then is
Nevada and Connecticut are spatially separated.
And so there's a question of what
do you mean by at the same time,
simultaneity. But when you think about it in
a momentum space, you don't have the spatial separation.
Remember we're doing non-relativistic physics, so there's no limitations of
the speed of light and making experiments and so forth.
At the same time, it's not a matter of time.
I mean the same time.
Somebody can jump from here to there
in no time at all and check.
So what happens when you
throw in relativistic physics into it?
Not much.
There is an additional fuzziness because
of relativity about how particles are located.
But for the moment, I wanted
to deal with the non-relativistic ideas.
Let's cut to the point.
Let's come to the ground state of a system of bosons and the
ground state of a system of electrons to see how different they are.
Let's imagine the three-dimensional world.
And since I can never draw
three dimensions, I will only draw two.
But I'm...
And...
I want to plot all of the possible allowable momenta.
Two-dimensional momentum.
This is the x component of momentum.
This is the y component.
I really want three dimensions, but
as I said, I can't draw it.
Of electrons.
Electrons confined to be in a certain finite volume.
The finite volume is very much like when we studied
one dimension, we studied electrons on an interval of length L.
With periodic boundary conditions, but
that's not so important here.
If electrons are confined, or particles are confined to
be within a given volume, then the momenta are discrete.
Remember when the electron was moving
on the periodic interval, it had momenta.
Which had to be, what was it?
N...
N over L, and there's a 2 pi in there.
2 pi N over L.
Is equal to k.
Right.
So, what did we say?
We said if we drew the momentum
axis, the possible values of momenta were discrete.
And that was a consequence of the space being finite.
Space available to us.
Space available to the particle being finite.
The bigger L is, the closer these levels get.
Alright, let's continue to think about
things confined in a finite volume.
In that case, both the x and y and
z components of the momentum would again be discrete.
So the allowable values of the
momentum vector would form a lattice.
This is not space.
This is momentum space.
The values of the possible momentum vectors.
Let's put 0 right over here at the center.
And then, they go on and on forever.
It's not bounded.
It just goes on and on forever.
Just like this axis goes on and on forever.
This N can be anything.
So these are the possible values.
So these are the possible allowable values of the
momentum of a particle in a periodic three-dimensional box.
Let's start with bosons.
Let's take a collection of N
bosons, all identical to each other.
They're all the same kind of particle.
And let's put them into our box.
And let's look for the ground
state, the state of lowest energy.
Well, let's put the first boson in.
Where will it go?
Where will it go if it's supposed
to go into the state of lowest energy?
0 what?
0 momentum.
In other words, we'll put the boson in.
That's 0.
This is kx, ky, kz is
equal to 0 right at that point.
That's the single particle state of lowest energy.
Remember, the energy is k squared over 2m.
The lowest possible energy.
The lowest possible energy for that
boson is to carry 0 momentum.
If we want to find the ground state,
we just put in the particle with 0 momentum.
Now, supposing we want to add another particle
to it, another boson of the same kind.
Where do we put it to
keep the energy as low as possible?
Same place.
Hmm?
Right.
Just the same place.
We put all particles in at the same place.
In fact, we put all in
particles in at the same place.
That'll be the state of lowest energy.
Okay?
So, that is called a boson condensate.
It's roughly a, the idea of a boson condensate is
a large number of particles all in the same state.
But in this case, all
in the lowest energy state available.
Incidentally, the lowest energy state available, since
it has the lowest momentum, fills up.
It's a wave function which fills up the box.
And so the wave function of each
one of these particles fills up the box.
And we simply put a lot of particles in.
All of them, very uncertain about
where they are in the box.
Put a lot of them in.
That's, first of all, called a boson condensate.
And it's also the ground
state of a system of bosons.
The large number of particles builds
up a kind of classical field strength.
So that the Schrodinger wave function is pretty classical.
Okay, that's very, very different than what
would happen if we had n fermions.
Let's forget spin.
We're not going to be interested in spin now.
Where, if we, where should we put the first one?
We're going to put them in one at a time.
We want to keep the energy as low as possible.
Okay.
Obviously the first one to go in, we
want to put in to the lowest state.
What about the next one?
Whatever the next energy level is.
Over here, the next one would maybe go over here.
There happen to be four states of the same energy.
So we could put it here, here, here, or here.
This is in two dimensions.
In three dimensions there would
be, what, six states altogether.
So by the time we put in five electrons,
they will fill up these states here.
Now let's put in some more electrons.
We can't put them in the same state.
Forbidden.
So the next one will go
in in the next lowest energy level,
which will be over here.
Incidentally, the energy being proportional to k squared
is proportional to the distance squared from the origin.
So what we want to do to
keep the energy as low as possible
is crowd the electrons in in momentum space,
into as small a sphere as we can.
In other words, when we have a lot of electrons,
when we put them in, they
will fill up in momentum space.
They'll fill up a sphere.
There might be a little confusion about the jaggedness.
of the spherical edge here, but that's not important.
This, of course, will have a lot more energy
than the corresponding boson system.
The corresponding boson system had all
of its particles in the lowest energy.
If you look for a particle,
all you will find is a particle of zero momentum.
In the ground state of the mini-fermion system,
you will find the more fermions you put in,
the higher the maximum momentum will be.
There will be lots and lots
and lots of particles of large momentum.
And of course, only a handful at low momentum,
because there aren't that many states at low momentum.
There are clearly more states within
a given shell at large momentum.
So, first of all, the energy
of the system will be much higher.
Putting fermions into a box,
costs more energy, number one.
Number two, there's this pattern
that they fill up a sphere
out to some boundary, where the boundary is determined
by how many electrons you have.
Depending on the number of
electrons, it will fill a sphere,
and that sphere is called the Fermi sphere.
It's called the Fermi sphere.
The history of this is a little bit confused.
It was Dirac who figured out fermions,
and that's why they're called fermions.
It was Einstein who figured out bosons,
and that's why they're called bosons.
No, they all contributed very heavily to the subject.
Anyway, this is the ground
state of a collection of fermions.
Fills the Fermi sphere.
Let's draw over here the
corresponding thing in momentum space.
This is all in momentum space.
I don't need to draw these lines.
Just all the particles condensed at
the center of the momentum space
for bosons, bosons, fermions.
Let's put a little bit of this lattice in
so we can see where the next states are.
Okay.
What's the first excited state we have in bosons?
They're all at the center.
What's the first energy level above the ground state?
Well, that's easy.
We take one boson and move
it to the next energy level.
We take out one boson in the ground state
and put it into the first excited state.
Which one, which boson do we do?
It doesn't matter.
They're all the same.
So we have n minus
1 bosons in the ground state
and 1 boson in the first excited state.
There are four first excited states.
That's not so important.
The second excited state, it might correspond,
depending on the details,
it might correspond to putting one
electron in the second excited state
or two electrons in the first excited state.
But one excited, not electrons, bosons.
A variety of different things.
But you can see the way
the pattern to excite the system,
to give it more energy,
is to take electrons from the ground state
and put them into higher energy states.
OK.
Let's come to the fermion system.
Well, it's also very similar.
But let's try to figure out
exactly what would correspond to the lowest...
Yeah, question?
OK.
What would correspond,
maybe not to the exact lowest energy state,
but to the very, very low energy states
above the ground state?
We want to give it
just a little bit of energy.
What's the cheapest way to give it energy?
Should we take an electron from the center here
and move it outside the energy state?
We can't move an electron
to someplace inside the Fermi sphere
because there's already an electron there.
I think as you were about to say,
it wouldn't be too smart to
take one deep inside the Fermi sphere
and bring it to the outside
because that would take a lot of energy.
It takes how much energy?
You're going to take one out of low energy
and put it back at relatively high energy.
That's pretty costly.
What's the cheapest thing?
Right.
Take one from very near the surface of the sphere,
inside the sphere,
and move it to the outside.
How much energy does that cost?
Not much because you've taken a pretty high energy electron
and just displaced it a little bit in energy.
So that creates an electron out here
with a little bit of energy
above the edge of the Fermi sphere,
but it also leaves something.
It leaves a hole in the Fermi sphere behind it.
That hole is a thing.
Let's suppose these are really electrons.
Let's consider a real world situation.
We have a box,
and that box is full of positive charge.
The positive charge is protons, of course, or nuclei.
But for simplicity, let's just imagine
the positive charge is smeared over the box,
and then we put electrons in on top of it.
And we put enough electrons in
to fill up a Fermi sphere like this.
It's electrically neutral because
there are as many electrons
as there are protons in the box.
So it's electrically neutral.
In the ground state,
the fermions fill up this Fermi sphere here.
Now we take an electron out
from just below the Fermi sphere
and put it in just above the Fermi sphere.
We have not changed the charge.
It's still electrically neutral.
But we have created one extra particle
with a little bit of
extra energy above the Fermi surface
and left a hole in the Fermi surface.
Left a hole with a missing particle.
A missing particle,
just think of it literally as a hole.
It's an absence of a bit of negative charge.
A bit of negative charge
with a certain momentum over here.
It can be thought of as the presence
of a positive charge hole.
A hole can be thought
of as a kind of particle.
In this context,
a hole behaves as a particle.
Is it a particle with negative energy
because it's below the Fermi sphere?
No.
Let's see how much energy it takes.
How much energy does it take
to move a particle from here
to here?
Well...
It's got a square in it.
Well, let's just say
we took out a particle of energy,
let's call the particle that we took out,
let's call it energy epsilon.
And we put in another particle
of energy epsilon prime.
When we took out the particle
of momentum of energy,
how much energy does that cost?
Difference.
The difference.
キ Eso s Just start
カ
と。
と・カ
に
すごい
Some of the difference.
I think the difference.
You think the difference. I think the sum.
Okay.
Well, no, no, no.
I'm sorry, I'm sorry.
Let me be more precise.
It is the difference, but
I'm getting tired.
I'm reaching the point of...
The point is it costs some energy.
It costs some energy. I'll
tell you how much energy later.
But you have to push energy
into the system in order to
pop an electron out
to the next energy level.
Yeah.
Well, the point is, how much energy
do you have to put
in? You have to put in
the amount of energy that it would take
to remove this particle
and bring it exactly to the Fermi surface,
and then an additional amount
of energy to bring it from the Fermi surface
off the Fermi surface.
So here's the picture.
Here's the Fermi sphere.
The Fermi surface is the edge of the
Fermi sphere.
Let's take a particle just below
the Fermi surface,
bring it from here to here,
how much energy does it take?
Well, it takes two bits of positive energy.
We can count it this way.
The first bit of positive energy is the energy
that it would take to remove
this particle and bring it right
to the Fermi surface.
That's a little bit of positive
energy to bring it to here,
and then a little more positive energy
to bring it to here.
So it's actually the sum of two positive
terms. The two positive
terms being
the absolute value of the
difference of the energies from the Fermi surface.
You have to add two little bits
of energy. One of them
can be thought of as the
energy of the electron over here,
measured relative to the Fermi surface,
and the other one can be thought
of as the energy of the hole.
And they're both positive.
This one has a bit of
positive charge because it's an electron.
This one has a bit of negative charge
because it's a missing... no, sorry.
This one has a bit of negative
charge because it's a positron.
No!
I did that on purpose.
I didn't.
This one has a bit of negative charge
because it's an electron,
and this one has a bit of positive charge
because it's a hole.
Thank you.
Right. Now,
this electron could be moving
around,
and then suddenly
pop into that hole.
The hole is available now. The hole is
available for the electron
to drop down into. Just as an electron
can drop from an
excited level of an atom
down to an unoccupied
quantum state, if there's an
unoccupied quantum state,
this electron can drop down into
this hole. What will happen
when an electron drops
its energy and drops
down into the hole?
Well, energy
has to be conserved, so the energy
of the electron has decreased,
and the electron has to be
discharged.
So, what happens when an electron
drops into the hole?
A photon is emitted.
Alright. You can say it another way.
You can say an electron comes together
with a hole and annihilates
the electron, annihilates the hole,
and a photon, or a photon
or more than one photon,
some number of photons goes out.
So you can speak about this in the language
of quantum mechanics.
But it's a kind of fake particle
that has the opposite charge
of the true electron.
It can be counted as having
some positive energy,
and when the electron
drops down into the hole,
you can think of it as the electron
and hole coming together,
annihilating and producing some
heat, radiation, whatever.
The process of annihilation.
Question?
Yeah?
When you say you're moving these electrons,
you're moving from one lattice point
to another lattice point?
Lattice in momentum space.
Yeah.
No, no.
You're moving them from one energy level to another.
So it's the
analog of
having an atom.
Alright, let's speak about the analog of what this means
in atomic physics.
In atomic physics, the box could be,
not the momentum space box,
but the box that confines the electron
could just be the atom.
The proton at the center
is some positive charge,
and we fill it up with some negative charged
electrons.
Of course, in this case,
the proton charge is not smeared
over the atom,
so it's concentrated
at the center.
It's a little bit different.
But we take an atom which has
the same number of electrons
as protons,
and we start with all of the electrons
in the lowest available states.
The lowest available states,
that's the ground state of the atom,
that's the analog of filling up
the Fermi sphere here.
Now a photon comes along
and hits an electron
and kicks it up into an excited state.
Alright?
Photon comes along, hits an electron
just below the Fermi surface
and kicks it up just above the Fermi surface.
It's a low energy electron.
A low energy photon.
So it doesn't have much energy.
It can't take an electron
from the center here and bring it to the outside.
That would take a lot of energy.
It's a very low energy photon.
And so it comes in
and all it can do is hit an electron
or be absorbed by an electron
near the Fermi surface
and kick it just above the Fermi surface.
Another language
is the photon has
annihilated
and been replaced by a particle.
Or an electron and a hole.
So it's particle
hole creation
by
taking the energy from a photon.
The same way that a photon
hitting an atom
excites the atom.
Of course when it excites the atom
it leaves a vacancy.
The vacancy in this language is called a hole.
Holes have
So across the whole sphere
if a photon hits anything
in that sphere will it kick off
something near the edge?
Well if it's a low energy photon
let's say
a radio wave photon
very low energy
and it tries to get absorbed
by an electron near the center
it just can't give that electron
enough energy to get out of the Fermi sphere.
It can't
jump to any place inside the Fermi sphere
because it's already occupied.
So the answer is a low energy photon
can't be absorbed by an electron
in the interior.
So the cross section doesn't get
bigger as the sphere gets bigger.
It's related to the surface
not the volume.
It all comes off the surface.
A high energy photon
of course that can kick an electron
from deep inside
the language is
that things inside the Fermi sphere
are in the Fermi sea.
S-E-A
This is deep in the Fermi sea
This is near the surface of the Fermi sea
Only a high energy photon
or a collection of high energy photons
coming together
can kick an electron
from deep inside the Fermi sea
to the outside.
A low energy photon
can take a shallow electron
or one just beneath the surface
and put it just above.
Yeah?
Is there anything that keeps electrons
from interacting with electrons directly
without using photons?
Nothing except we're ignoring it.
No.
Interactions between electrons
make the story somewhat more complicated
but interactions between electrons
are pretty weak.
They're pretty weak.
They're not very strong
and for the most part
they can be ignored inside a metal
for example.
If a photon has excess energy
it has enough to kick multiple electrons
Say it again.
If a photon has a lot of energy
enough to excite multiple electrons
then what happens?
Does one electron get extra excited
and then fall back?
Anything can happen
as long as it's consistent
with the conservation laws.
But typically it's a much lower probability process
to create two electrons
and two holes.
If it kicked out two electrons
it would make two holes
and if it kicked out two electrons
and that would be a process
in which four particles
were created altogether.
That's much less likely.
Super excite one.
That's right.
It's more likely to super-excite one.
Another question.
A philosophical question here
Is it ever the case
that a two photon simultaneously
can be absorbed by an electron
that one of them wouldn't do it
but both of them would?
or do you need both of them to conserve energy?
it's just a probability
the situation is not prohibition
if you have a low energy photon
that's not
that doesn't have enough energy
to excite any of the electrons
well it doesn't take
it just takes a tiny tiny bit of
energy to kick it from here to here
so yeah there is some energy which is
so low that it can't do anything, it's true
yeah it pretty much just passes through the system
that they provided
نعم،
هذا
هو
الموانئ
will find other ways to interact.
It will stop a whole collection of electrons sloshing.
That's more complicated.
But does it?
You mean that they're actually moving on the grid back
and forth?
They actually will be moving
on the grid back and forth.
Space.
Well.
But that's more complicated.
Why do you say that
electrons interact weakly with each other?
Say that again?
You said that electrons do not
interact with each other very strongly.
But don't they all have the same negative charges?
Yeah, but they're also in
a background sea of positive charges.
So the whole thing is a little bit more complicated.
Yeah.
So the electron charge is electrically neutral.
The electrons are interacting with each other,
but the electron interactions are pretty weak.
Partly they're weak because the electron
charge is screened by the proton charges.
But I really didn't want
to get into the electron interaction.
That's a separate issue that we .
Will we talk about that screening?
Yeah, we can talk about it.
But not.
We'll talk about it later.
Yeah.
I don't want to talk about that now.
Right.
Yeah.
Screening is an important phenomenon in particle physics.
And it has its analog here.
But let's come back to it another time.
What I really wanted to
get to was the Dirac equation.
And I have 15 minutes to give you
the very, very simplest version of the Dirac equation,
which we will come back to repeatedly.
But the very, very simplest version of the Dirac equation.
And I'm going to go through it one by one.
Just to sort of complete a story here.
It's obvious.
You know what story I'm starting to tell you.
I'm telling you the story about antiparticles.
OK?
Holes are antiparticles.
But what does this have to do
with not a metal in a box,
but with relativistic quantum field theory
and the vacuum and particles and antiparticles?
So.
I'm going to spend just a couple of minutes
giving you the very, very simplest version of Dirac's logic.
And to keep it really simple,
let's stay with one dimension of space.
OK?
One dimension of space and only one dimension.
X.
We'll come back to more dimensions next time.
And.
Let's write a wave equation.
This wave equation is going to be for
a field that I'm going to call psi.
OK?
Ah.
Right.
This electron, this is not an electron, it's a neutrino.
Ah, I don't know what it is.
It's a particle.
It's a fermion.
It's a fermion, but it happens
to move with the speed of light.
OK?
It moves with the speed of light.
And that means omega equals k.
Right?
Omega equals k is the relationship between frequency
and wave number or between energy and momentum.
This is c equal one.
Omega equals k.
There's another possibility.
Omega is equal to k.
And what's the other possibility?
Omega equals minus k.
OK?
But let's take omega equals k.
What kind of wave equation does that correspond to?
Well, that corresponds to the wave equation d psi by
dt is equal, I think it's minus, d psi by dx.
This is partial derivative.
This is even simpler than the Schrodinger equation.
Why do I say that this is omega equals k?
Let's imagine that psi is equal to
e to the ikx minus omega t.
d psi by dt brings
down a factor minus i omega.
d psi by dx brings down a factor ik.
If the relation between omega and k is
just omega equals k corresponding to c equals one,
then that just says d psi by dt
is equal to minus d psi by dx.
All right?
So this is a very, very simple wave equation.
And it describes waves which only move in one direction.
They cannot move in both directions.
They move only, is it to
the right or to the left?
Can you tell if this, uh...
Yeah.
These waves move to the right.
Okay?
What would it take to make
waves that move to the left?
You'd want d psi by dt
equals plus d psi by dx.
All right.
With either of those two equations, you
have particles which move in one direction,
let's say in this case to the right.
And let's suppose these are fermions and
let's even imagine they carry electric charge.
So they're electrically charged.
They're not just fermions.
Okay.
Now there's something a little bit crazy about this.
Omega equals k.
Energy equals momentum.
Can k be negative?
Sure.
Why not?
I can write e to the ikx.
And I can also write e to the minus ikx.
All right.
I can write both possibilities, things which are...
But there's something a little ugly, not ugly,
a little bit dangerous about negative values of k.
They carry negative values of omega.
And negative values of omega mean what?
Negative energy.
All right.
So this equation describes...
Electrons are electrons of positive and negative energy.
Let's just draw a picture.
Omega equals k.
Here's omega equals k.
Omega versus k.
It's just a straight line.
For k positive, the energy is positive.
For k negative, the energy is negative.
Okay.
This equation simply describes electrons which
can have either positive or negative energy.
That sounds like trouble.
Why is there trouble?
Why is electrons with negative energy trouble?
Well, if electrons can have arbitrarily low momentum...
Remember what happens in an atom
to an electron which is excited.
It radiates and drops down to a lower state.
If there were unboundedly
low energies, arbitrarily negative,
then electrons, let's say positive energy electrons,
could emit photons and drop down in energy.
But they wouldn't necessarily have to stop at zero energy.
They could keep dropping down
and dropping down and dropping down
and make arbitrarily negatively energy electrons
while at the same time pumping
up the energy of the electromagnetic field.
This sounds very dangerous, and it is dangerous.
Something wrong with this.
Okay.
You can't have arbitrarily low energies.
Well, what is the lowest
energy state of the multi-electron system?
How do you...
The thermosphere?
What's that?
What is a thermosphere in this case?
The thermosphere in this case is...
Let's suppose we have a zillion
electrons, as many as we like,
and we put the first electron into the system.
Where does it go?
To the hole.
It goes down into the lowest energy state.
But the lowest energy state is
way the hell down there somewhere.
Off at minus infinity somewhere.
The next one, off at minus infinity.
This is very dangerous.
This is a bad idea.
What Dirac said...
This is the simplest version of Dirac equation.
This is a Dirac equation in one dimension.
What Dirac said is,
let's pretend that all of
the negative energy states were filled.
Just like filling the thermosphere,
fill all the negative energy states
all the ways up to zero energy.
So all of these states are filled.
There's an electron in every negative energy state.
You can't make a state
of lower energy than that, incidentally.
That's the lowest possible energy you have.
You've filled up all the negative energy states.
Every time you put a negative
energy thing in, that lowers the energy.
You've put as many things in as you can.
You've put as many negative
energy states in as you can.
Now if I start putting in positive
energy electrons, that will increase the energy.
So the very lowest energy state,
the thing that you could call a ground state,
is to fill it with as many negative
energy electrons as there are negative energy states.
And that's your starting point.
Instead of a starting point with no electrons,
your starting point is fill
up completely the negative energy C.
That's the vacuum.
That's empty space according to Dirac's theory,
Dirac's simple version.
Start with that.
Since it's the state of lowest
energy, let's call it the vacuum.
And now what can you do?
You can take, the only thing you can do
is to take an electron out of the C,
the negative energy C, and give it positive energy.
So you can take an electron from
over here and put it someplace else.
Okay.
So you can take properties of
a state with one electron over here,
with positive energy and positive momentum,
and one missing electron over here.
Okay.
It's a missing electron.
Well, how much momentum does it have, incidentally?
It, uh...
Well, we remove the negative momentum electrons.
Yeah, so it's zero.
No, no, no, no, no, no.
The whole.
How much, how much, uh,
how much does the whole have?
Positive.
Is it positive or negative?
Why is it positive?
Because it's a missing deficit of negative momentum.
All right.
So what we've done is create
a positive energy, a positive energy electron,
and a positive, and positive momentum.
We've created two positive momentum
objects, both moving to the right.
Uh, one with plus charge, sorry, one with minus charge,
the electron with minus charge,
and the missing electron having positive charge,
negative charge and positive charge.
That, uh, that in summary, and
we're gonna do this more completely,
but that was Dirac's theory
of the electron and the positron,
that the positron was simply a
hole in the infinite negative energy C.
He wrote down this equation, or the generalization of it,
looked at it and said, I love that equation,
but it's got this terrible
disease of having negative energy states.
No problem.
These are fermions.
You can't put more than one electron in there.
You can't put more than one
electron in a negative energy state.
So just fill it up
completely and call that empty space.
Having called that empty space,
what can you do to it?
You can remove one of the negative energy electrons
and put it back as a positive energy electron.
Sorry, put it back, yes, put
it back as a positive energy electron.
That leaves a hole.
And Dirac said that hole is
a particle of positive, uh, charge.
All right.
Now, at first he was very excited
because he thought it was the proton.
It's easy to prove that
the mass of the particle here
has to be the same as the mass of the...
These are particle and antiparticle.
This was the discovery of particles and antiparticles.
But this was the basic logic,
and it was equations like this which led to it.
Notice what a disaster you'd be in
if you tried to describe a boson by this equation.
That would be a madhouse.
You would just keep putting
particles into the negative energy state,
negative energy, lowest, as many as you like,
and there would be no ground state.
There would be no ground state.
You could just keep putting in more
and more and more negative energy bosons.
So this wave, this wave
equation only makes sense for fermions,
would not make sense for bosons.
And that was Dirac's great discovery,
that fermions can be described by Dirac equations like this
that would not make sense for bosons.
Why?
Just the reasons I explained.
And the idea of antiparticles.
We'll come to antiparticles for bosons next time,
and we'll discuss the Dirac equation in more completeness,
the real Dirac equation.
This is an elementary version of it.
But we'll come to it next time.
There's a number of things wrong with this electron.
For one thing, it only moves to the right.
That's the problem.
That's crazy.
For another thing, it moves at the speed of light.
So there's a number of things
that are wrong with this electron.
It's a neutrino.
No, it's a neutrino.
A neutrino is a boson.
Yeah, this is a neutrino.
But it's not quite a neutrino,
because a neutrino also has mass.
For more, please visit us at stanford.edu.