Stanford University
Okay, the question arose about the paradox of
if two particles, both fermions, make up a boson,
can we have a boson, two bosons,
which are, let's say, in the same state?
Perhaps a more general question.
The wave function of bosons is supposed to be symmetric
on the interchange of the two bosons.
That means, for example, if you had two bosons
and the wave function describing them was
a function of, let's say, x and y,
this doesn't mean the two bosons are the same.
This means that if you're using two coordinates,
x and y, in the x and y direction,
x and y are simply now standing
for particle number 1 and particle number 2.
If they're bosons, then the rule is that
that must equal psi of y and x.
That's another way of saying you
can't distinguish between the two particles.
There's no difference between saying
you have a two boson system
in the state psi of x and y,
and saying you can distinguish between the two bosons.
You have two bosons in the
state psi of y and x.
It's interchange symmetric between them.
And in that case, you can certainly
have two particles in the same state.
For example, a special case of this
would be that psi is a product function.
Psi of x and y is a product of,
I don't want to use the label psi again,
because I've used psi to label two particle wave functions,
but let's invent another thing
to describe one particle wave function.
Let's just call it phi.
And psi of x and y could
be phi of x times phi of y.
This would correspond to a boson
with two bosons with wave function phi,
with the same wave function.
In other words, in the same quantum state.
That's what this would mean, a two particle state,
and each particle is in the state phi.
So, the cross is obviously symmetric.
It is the same as phi of y and
x, sorry, phi of y times phi of x.
Wave functions are not operators.
They commute.
Wave functions are just ordinary numbers.
They're not matrices.
They're just functions of x,
and they satisfy all of the
algebraic properties of perfectly ordinary functions.
And so, what did I write?
Yeah, I wrote the right thing.
Yes, two bosons can be in the same state,
and the wave function be symmetric.
What about two fermions?
The rule for two fermions, if we
put them, if we have two fermions,
is that the wave function has to change sign.
Now, that's a very odd thing, but nevertheless,
that is the mathematical rule,
the abstract mathematical rule for fermions.
When you interchange them, the
sign of the wave function changes.
Now, okay, so that's the difference between them.
Then, can you have two fermions in the same state?
No, because phi of x and y is
not equal to minus phi of y and y.
You see what I mean.
Phi of x times phi of y is not equal to
phi of y and phi of x with a minus sign.
All right, now, supposing I have a wave function
for two particles.
Can I make, and it's
not symmetric and it's not anti-symmetric,
can I make something out of it which is symmetric
or something which is anti-symmetric?
So let me show you how you do that.
Supposing I had some wave function
which was neither symmetric nor anti-symmetric.
Let's just call it phi of x and y.
When you interchange x and y, it neither changes sign,
nor does it stay the same.
So it's neither symmetric nor anti-symmetric.
All right, if you want to make something symmetric,
which is an appropriate wave function for two bosons,
you just add
phi of y and x.
Now this is obviously symmetric.
If you interchange x and y,
this one becomes this one, this one becomes this one,
and nothing happens to that.
Now this is a symmetric wave function.
This is a possible wave function for
bosons for any psi of x and y.
And if we're talking about fermions,
we can do the same thing,
except that we put a minus sign there.
Now what happens if we interchange x and y?
This one goes to this one,
this one goes to this one,
but the whole thing will change sign.
The whole thing will change sign
if we interchange x and y.
Okay.
So this is a wave function for fermions.
Symmetrized is called symmetrizing and anti-symmetrizing,
a wave function for two particles.
Okay, now let's suppose we have four particles altogether.
Four fermions.
Four fermions, what are the rules for four fermions?
And for simplicity, let's suppose there
are two different kinds of fermions.
Let's say there is electrons and protons,
but we're talking about hydrogen atoms.
Now, the rule, okay, so
let's see what is the rule.
We have a four-body wave function.
Let's now let electrons be called
x and protons be called y.
So the wave function is a function of two x's,
let's call them x1 and x2, y1 and y2.
So a function of four variables.
What are the rules?
The rules are, first of all, that
the wave function has to change sign
if you interchange x1 and x2.
That's the fact that the electrons are fermions.
It must also change sign
when you interchange y1 and y2.
Incidentally, let's see.
Let's do this right.
It must also change sign
when you interchange y1 and y2.
Yeah, that's the rule.
Those are the only rules.
Sign change when you interchange x1 and x2,
that's because electrons are fermions,
and a sign change when you interchange y1 and y2
because protons are fermions.
So let's see what kind
of wave functions we can build.
Let's start with a hydrogen atom.
A hydrogen atom located at the origin.
A hydrogen atom located at
the origin has a wave function,
which is a function of its electron and its proton.
So one now picks out
one of the two hydrogen atoms.
One now stands for one of the two hydrogen atoms.
And this might be some wave
function governing one of the hydrogen atoms,
over here.
But supposing I want to shift its location.
How would I shift its location?
Well, it's easy to shift its location.
You just shift the origin of both x1 and x2.
I guess I don't really have to do it.
Okay.
I don't need to shift its origin.
And then we have another pair.
And the other pair is describing
a hydrogen atom at some other location.
All right.
Since it's a hydrogen atom at another location,
it has a different wave function.
The wave function may be the
same except that it's been translated,
but it's not.
It's been translated, but it is different.
Phi of x2 and y2.
Now, in general, this is neither
symmetric with respect to the x's
or anti-symmetric with respect to the x's
or, for that matter, with respect to the y's.
So it's not a good wave function for fermions.
Supposing I want to make it
anti-symmetric on the interchange of the electrons.
That's very easy.
We just subtract off here
psi of...
I just interchange x1 and x2,
leaving y1 and y2 alone.
All right.
So let's do that first.
Minus psi of x2y1
phi of x1y2.
It is now anti-symmetric with respect to the x's.
If I interchange the two
x's, the whole thing changes sign.
But it's not anti-symmetric with respect to the y's.
Okay.
How do I make it
anti-symmetric with respect to the y's?
The answer is take the
whole thing that I have here,
interchange the two y's, and put a minus sign in.
All right.
So we put in minus
psi of x1 and y2.
phi of x2y2.
That's exactly this with...
Sorry, y1.
This and this are the same, except
that y2 and y1 have been interchanged.
And I put a minus sign in.
And then I want to anti-symmetrize this one
with respect to the exchange of the y's.
So that becomes plus...
I have to change the sign.
psi of x2y2.
phi of x1y1.
Okay.
So this is now anti-symmetric with respect
to both the x's and the y's.
If you interchange in this expression, x1 and x2,
it'll go to this one and change sign.
If you interchange x1 and x2 here,
this one, and so forth.
The whole thing is fully anti-symmetric.
Fully anti-symmetric, yeah.
My problem is if you take those two hydrogen's atoms
and put them closer and closer,
there's nothing preventing you from doing
that because there are bosons, right?
There may be forces between them.
There may be...
The Pauli principle does create a
kind of force between the atoms.
It will make it very, very...
It'll make it essentially impossible
to put two atoms right on top of each other.
But you'll simply attribute that to a force.
But will you be able to put
two atoms into the same momentum state?
Momentum states are spread out all over the place.
They are spread out in space.
So when you put two
atoms into the same momentum state,
you're not ramming them in on top of each other,
and it doesn't cost a lot of energy.
So, yeah, the question of whether you can
stick two things on top of each other
is a different question than
whether they're fermions and bosons.
It can even happen that, you know,
billiard balls can be bosons.
You can't stick them on top of each other.
They have hard cores.
Nevertheless, they can be bosons.
You can put them...
You can't put them at the same point.
It just costs too much energy,
but you can put them into the same momentum.
But if your wave functions are eigenvalue...
Eigenfunctions of momentum,
then couldn't you...
Couldn't you have the two hydrogen atoms
in this same eigenstate of momentum,
and then you would have
two fermions in the same state?
No. No, no, no, no, no.
Just take any wave function like this.
Is this...
It's anti-symmetric with exchanges to x.
It's anti-symmetric with respect to exchanges of y.
What about if I interchange one and two?
One and two is interchanging the two atoms.
Right?
What happens then?
It's symmetric.
Yeah.
So it's symmetric with respect to
the interchange of the two atoms.
And why?
Because when you interchange the x's,
you get a minus sign.
When you interchange the y's,
Minus times minus is plus.
So let's say...
Yeah.
If I interchange one and two,
x one,
y one,
will become x two, y two,
with the same sign.
x two, y two,
will become x one, y one,
again with the same sign.
So this one will...
These two will transform into each other
by simultaneous changes
of everything with a one or everything with a two.
And that's exchanging the two atoms.
Likewise,
let's see, we have psi of x two, y one,
but here we have psi of x one, y two.
Both of them have minus signs,
so these will go into each other.
So the whole thing is symmetric
with respect to the interchange
of atom one and atom two.
That doesn't mean that it doesn't...
This is quite...
This whole story here is independent
of the question of energies.
It may be impossible for other reasons
to put two things on top of each other,
in space.
The reasons being that it may be
very strong repulsive forces.
But a good example...
Can I ask what we do physically?
Physically?
We just wrote down a wave,
an appropriate wave function for two atoms,
for two bosonic atoms.
In momentum space?
No, these may or may not be in momentum space.
They may be anything.
Well, I mean, what is...
Are we saying that...
If we have two bosonic atoms,
that that's what their state will be?
Yes.
Okay.
If we have a bosonic...
If we have an atom with a wave function
psi of x1 and y1,
and another atom...
If we didn't know anything about this atom over here,
we might write down a wave function
for the electron and proton in the other atom.
And now we want to write down a wave function
which is appropriate for the two-atom system.
Okay.
All right?
The wave function for the two-atom system
has to be antisymmetric when you interchange any x's,
antisymmetric when you change any y.
And so I just basically use this rule,
except I use it twice.
Once to exchange the x's,
and that gives me the top,
and then take the whole thing
and interchange the y's and change the sign.
The result is, quite clearly,
if you look at it carefully,
interchange symmetric,
under the exchange of the two atoms,
one and two,
atom one and atom two.
So...
And that, at the end of the day,
at the end of the day,
that is the rule
that a bosonic atom and another bosonic atom,
when you interchange them,
the wave function has to have the same sign.
Okay, now what kind of states can you put two...
Yeah, momentum states,
you can put two atoms into...
in the same wave function.
That doesn't cost a great deal of energy
because they're hardly ever on top of each other.
But it is true that if
you try to stick two atoms
on top of each other,
it's very hard to do
because it costs very, very costly in energy.
Let's see.
What would happen...
In fact, what would happen...
Okay, let's see what would happen
if we made both atoms with the same wave function.
Not one atom with wave function phi
and one atom with wave function psi,
but two with the same...
What happens then?
Let's see.
Okay, so let's...
Okay, so there are two
atoms with the same wave function.
We have to subtract...
All right, so this is this.
Psi of x1, y2,
psi,
psi.
Is that zero or not?
I don't think so.
It's not zero, is it?
Oh, I don't know.
It's a diagonal, isn't it?
Sure it is.
Is it zero?
Yeah.
x1, y1.
Where else do you see it?
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
No, no, no.
It's not zero.
No.
This one and this one are the same.
Okay?
So it's just twice this.
Two doesn't...
Two is irrelevant.
We don't care about a factor of two.
And twice this.
This is it.
And this is not zero.
Okay?
This is two atoms in the same state.
It's not zero.
Okay?
Some magic is going on here.
You can't put two electrons in the same state, meaning
to say the electron wave function has to be anti-symmetric.
The proton wave function has to be anti-symmetric.
Both are true here.
But yet the two atoms are in the same state.
So ponder that a little bit.
Write down that wave function and look at it and...
And...
Of course, the point is, among other things, that in
the atom, the electron is not in a well-defined position.
It has a probability of
being many places in the atom.
You put two atoms in the same place, it's quite
true the two electrons can't be in the same place.
That's true.
Two electrons cannot be in the same place.
Let's see.
What would happen?
All right.
Here's our wave function for the two atoms.
Anti-symmetric and so forth.
Now supposing we try to stick
the two electrons into the same place.
That would mean setting x1 equal to x2.
Then it would be zero.
All right.
So although the two atoms are in the same state, it's still true that
in that state, if you try to find the two electrons in the same place...
Let's just see.
What would that be?
The two electrons in the same place
would be psi of x1, y1, and...
And...
Y1 psi of x1, y2.
I've just set the two x's equal to each other.
Minus psi of x1, y1, psi of x1, y2.
So I forced the two electrons to
be in the same place, and guess what?
I think they cancel.
Yes, they do.
Okay?
So...
So as I said, ponder it a
little bit, and you'll get familiar with it.
And you'll see how it can possibly
be that two fermions can be a boson.
Does that finally mean that whereas you can exchange
two atoms, two hydrogen atoms in different states, you can't...
So this...
Before I said x1 equal to x2 here,
these two atoms were in the same state.
The atoms were in the same state, but the
electrons and the protons were never in the same state.
Okay.
The atoms are with the protons,
the electrons are with the protons.
Whereas if they're both electrons and
protons, you can't have a second case.
When you did this operation of anti-symmetrizing, you basically projected out the pieces of the wave function
where the electrons were at the same point and where the protons were at the same point.
Yeah.
So nothing was left of
that piece of the wave function.
It's still zero if you go back to feet.
If we go back to what?
To, I think, feet.
Feet.
In other words, the atoms are in different states,
but you put the electrons in the same space.
Yeah.
Just any time you try to put electrons in the same
place or in the same momentum, it's going to be zero.
Right.
Okay.
Let's come back to spin a little bit.
Spin is more fun than we've dealt with so far.
The reason I'm spending time with spin is because the mathematics of spin is what you really have to know to know
such things as the mathematics of isospin and the mathematics of color and the mathematics of all of the symmetries of particle physics.
The mathematics is the same.
The physics, as was pointed out here.
The analogies between these different kinds
of conserved quantities are formal mathematical analogies.
But nevertheless, let's study the
mathematics of spin a little more.
A little bit more about
the Dirac equation, just a bit.
And then I want to introduce the concept of isotopic spin or
isospin, which is a concept which I think dates back to the 30s.
Okay.
So let's start with half spin.
The half spin, the electron is a half spin particle.
So I'll call a particle an electron.
I could call it a proton.
I could call it a muon.
Any one of the half spin particles,
but let's just call it an electron.
It has two possible states.
If two possible values for the
angular momentum along the angular momentum.
Along the z-axis.
Along the z-axis, we've called L sub z.
We've called that M.
Not quite.
There's an h-bar in there, right?
But from now on, we'll set
the h-bar equal to you know what.
Okay.
So for the electron, this is not
the full angular momentum, incidentally, of the electron.
In fact, I'm using a really weird notation.
Usually L is used for orbital angular
momentum and S is used for spin.
So let's revert to that.
S for spin.
S for spin, but the mathematics of it is
exactly the same as the mathematics of the Ls.
In fact, we could write it down over here.
Let's write it down over here.
The mathematics of angular momentum, but not of the Ls.
And now I'm calling it
S for spin instead of L.
I don't know what L stands for.
It stands for angular momentum.
All right.
So what was the commutation relations we wrote down
last time where Lx with Ly equals I h-bar Lz.
Now it becomes Sx with Sy is equal to
I h-bar, but I'll set h-bar equal to 1.
Isz.
And cycle down.
You know what to do next.
Sy is z equals Isx and so forth.
All right.
Cyclic permutations.
Oh, one other thing.
We have S plus and minus.
Just to remind you, S plus and
minus is just Sx plus minus Isy.
All right.
So what is the form of linear momentum?
The form of linear momentum is that the operators raise the value of the
z component or lower it depending on whether there's a plus sign or minus sign.
And so they're raising and
lowering operators for spin angular momentum.
All I've done is change notation from L to S.
Intrinsic spin.
It doesn't.
It could be any spin.
I mean, it could be a spin, which is
due to, due to, you know, the rotating basketball.
But.
Let's say intrinsic spin.
Intrinsic spin, yeah.
Okay, let's focus on half spin.
Half spin is the case where Sz or M can
take on the value minus a half and plus a half,
and that's all.
That's a two-state system.
Incidentally, I'm also forgetting completely
everything else about the electron.
We're forgetting, for example, about where the
electron is, what its momentum is, and
all that sort of stuff.
Just forget it for the moment,
and we're just concentrating on the spin.
All right, so concentrating on the spin,
the quantum mechanics is the quantum mechanics
of a system with two orthogonal
states and only two orthogonal states.
It doesn't matter where it came from.
In quantum mechanics, the space of
states is just the space of states.
It's just the space of states of a
two-component or a two-state system, and you can always
write it as a column vector.
Let's call it alpha and beta, where alpha
is the amplitude that the spin along the z-axis
is up, and beta is the amplitude that it's down.
So you can always write the
state of the system, the ket vector.
Let's call it the psi, which is
alpha up plus beta down along the z-axis.
You can just symbolically represent it by
constructing a little column vector and putting
an alpha there and a beta there.
Alpha star alpha is the
probability that the electron is up.
Beta star beta is the probability
that it's down, and that's it.
In the same notation, operators become matrices.
Okay?
So operators become matrices.
Let's see what we can learn about the matrices.
These components of the spin have to be two-by-two matrices.
Why two-by-two?
Because the space of states is two-dimensional.
So they have to be two-by-two matrices,
and they have to satisfy this algebra.
That's it.
If you can find two-by-two
matrices which satisfy this algebra...
Oh, one other thing.
We might want Sz to be diagonal.
Okay?
So, yeah?
Did you just say the
dimensions of space are two-dimensional?
No, no, no, not the dimensions of space.
The dimen...
No, no, no, no, no.
The dimensions of spin space.
Spin space.
Yeah.
Not the dimensions of space.
No, what I said to
do is to forget about space.
Forget for the moment the position of the electron.
Forget its momentum.
We're thinking now of an electron that somebody has
nailed down to the wall so that it can't
move around.
And all you can do is measure its spin.
It has two distinct states if you
measure the Sz component of its spin.
That's it.
Only two states.
And so let's label them up and down.
Any quantum state of the spin is
a linear superposition of them with complex coefficients.
And the probabilities are...
The probability for up is alpha star alpha.
The probability for down is beta star beta.
It's just a change of notation, a
common change of notation, to replace this clumsy
thing here by just writing a little
column with an alpha and a beta.
And remembering that the lower component stands
for down, the upper component stands for up.
In the same way, operators become 2x2 matrices.
And 2x2 matrices just act on these 2x2 matrices.
Yeah.
two component vectors.
What did you say? Did you
say you wanted SZ to be diagonal?
No, I said I would choose SZ to be
diagonal. SZ. It doesn't matter. You just search around
and see if you can find matrices,
two by two matrices, which satisfy this rule.
Is SZ a matrix?
Yes, it's an operator. It's
the angular momentum. It's an observable.
It is an observable, it's an
operator, and it becomes a matrix.
All operators become matrices that act
on vectors to give other vectors.
Okay? Same thing we've done over in the past.
Okay? Alright, so let's see if we can find, well,
of course we can, otherwise we wouldn't be doing this.
Alright.
Thank you.
Three matrices which satisfy these commutation relations.
XYZ.
Alright, so two by two matrices, two by two matrices.
Alright, they are not unique.
They are not unique.
They are not the same.
And the choice, the choice of them really
corresponds to a choice of orientation of axes.
But there is a choice of
them which is particularly useful for us.
They're all equivalent, incidentally, as I say.
They're related just by rotation of
the spatial axes, spatial, real space axes.
And it is not important what choice you use.
I'm not going to give you the
answers, but I will choose the following choice.
And you can check that these matrices satisfy
SX is equal to 0, 1, 1, 0.
SY is equal to minus I, I, 0, 0.
SZ is equal to 1, 0, 0, minus 1.
You'll never find three matrices which have these
rules, which, no, sorry, one half of this.
One half of that.
Okay?
Check it.
Just go through it.
I will not do it on the blackboard.
It takes two minutes to do.
Well, maybe three.
Three minutes to do.
And you'll find that these matrices
do satisfy these commutation relations here.
Okay?
They are the Pauli-Skyz.
And the Pauli-Skyz are the spin matrices.
The Pauli matrices are these things without
the one half in front of them.
Okay?
But the real angular momentum matrices which
satisfy these rules here are half of them.
Without the half, they're called Pauli matrices.
With the half, they're just called spin matrices.
I think they're properly called spin matrices with the half.
Okay?
So this is a...
representation.
I would say this is a representation of the angular
momentum matrices, a particular two-component representation of the angular momentum...
of the half-spin angular momentum matrices.
Okay.
Let's now see if we can find the states.
That means the states means the column vectors,
which correspond to sigma-z being up and sigma-z being down.
All right?
Or s-z being up and s-z being down.
Those are the two possible
orthogonal states, eigenstates of s-z.
All right?
This is very easy.
We just say...
What does it mean to say a
state whose s-z is plus or minus?
It means an eigenvector of s-z
with eigenvalue plus one or minus one.
We expect, incidentally, that the components of
spin have value plus and minus a half.
All right?
Plus and minus a half.
But that means that the s's should
have value plus one and minus one.
Of course, that's true.
These diagonal elements here are the eigenvalues of s.
So let's just be very pedantic.
Being very pedantic.
We're looking for vectors, let's call them alpha-beta,
which have the property minus one.
That this is either equal to plus
or minus, let's say plus first, alpha-beta.
This would be an eigenvalue
in which sigma-z equals plus one.
What about sigma-z equals minus one?
That would be one-zero-zero minus one.
That would be one-zero-zero minus
one alpha-beta equals minus alpha-beta.
That's the meaning of an eigenvalue and an eigenvector.
If we find solutions of these, the solutions will correspond to the
states in which the spin is up and the spin is down.
Let's just check.
Let's check that out.
Okay, so it's completely obvious.
Well, let's just work it out.
The top entry here by matrix multiplication
is one times alpha plus zero times beta.
So just multiplying out the matrices, this is going to
be one times alpha plus zero times beta in the top,
and zero times alpha and minus beta in the bottom.
Well, obviously this is not equal to this unless what?
Unless beta is zero.
If beta is zero,
then we've found a solution to
the eigenvalue or the eigenvector problem,
which corresponds to an eigenvalue plus one,
and surprise, surprise, it corresponds to a vector
which only has an entry in the upper place.
The upper place stood for spin up.
What shall I choose alpha to be?
I can choose it to be one.
Why one?
Because I want the sums
of the probabilities to be one.
So alpha star alpha plus
beta star beta should be one,
and a convenient choice is just
to choose alpha equal to one.
Now what if I, let's put back what I erased.
What I erased is that this thing
times alpha beta was alpha minus beta.
Supposing I want to get a
minus sign, then what do I do?
Choose alpha equal to zero.
If alpha is equal to zero,
this is true.
And that corresponds to the vector zero one.
Again, no big surprise, it corresponds to the
state in which the electron is definitely down
and has no probability of being up.
Okay, let's go a little bit farther.
What about, we've done this many
times in these series of classes,
but just to spend a
minute or two doing it again.
What about wave functions, state vectors,
whatever we want to call them,
ket vectors, corresponding to the possibility
that the x component of spin,
we're now going to do a different experiment.
We're going to measure instead of
the z component of the spin,
we're going to measure the x component of the spin.
Again, the two possibilities are plus
a half and minus a half.
What are the eigenvectors which correspond to
the two possible measurements for that case?
We're measuring sigma x and not
the, or sx and not the, alright.
In that case, we want to ask zero
one one zero alpha beta equals alpha beta.
That's the eigenvector with eigenvalue plus one,
and the eigenvector with eigenvalue minus
one will have to satisfy one one,
if such things exist, alpha beta equal minus alpha beta.
These are the eigenvalue equations for plus and minus.
Here I've put in sigma x
instead of sigma z, alright, sigma x.
Okay, so what is the top equation?
Let's do the top one first.
What does the top equation say?
Alpha equals beta.
Alpha equals beta, right.
Let's be pedantic again.
Zero times alpha, one times beta.
So, working out the matrix product
here, or the matrix times vector,
it gives us beta alpha.
This matrix just interchanges top and bottom.
One times alpha, sorry, zero times alpha, one times beta.
Same thing on the bottom row.
And so, is there a solution of this equation?
Well, yes.
All it says is beta equals alpha.
In fact, the bottom equation says alpha equals beta,
which is the same as beta equals alpha.
So, we solve the equation
by setting alpha equal to beta.
A convenient choice,
a convenient choice,
they're all equivalent to each other,
but a convenient choice is that
we choose one over square root of two,
one over square root of two,
and why one over square root of two?
So again, so that the
total probability adds up to one.
If we had the one-halves over here,
would we be looking for eigenvalue one-half?
Yes, yes, yes, yes.
Yes, if we had included the one-half,
we would be looking for eigenvalue one-half.
So, to look for eigenvalues of Sx, we
just look for twice the eigenvalue for sigma.
Good point.
Okay.
All right, let's see what the other possibility is.
The other possibility is alpha beta,
which happens to be beta alpha.
That's by multiplication here.
That should now equal minus alpha beta.
That's the other eigenvalue.
Take this away for a minute,
the thing in the middle here.
This just becomes the eigenvalue
equation or the eigenvector equation
for an eigenvector with eigenvalue minus one.
All right.
And what does that require?
That says beta equals minus alpha, and
it also says alpha equals minus beta.
If beta equals minus alpha, then alpha equals minus beta.
And so all we have to
do is put into the entries here,
sorry, not this, but,
alpha beta here is equal to
one over square root of two
minus one over square root of two.
All right, so what does this say?
It says that if we
take a linear superposition of states
where the electron is up along
the z-axis and down along the z-axis,
we superpose those states
in the quantum linear superposition,
we make an electron,
which is, let's use the right word,
which is polarized along the positive x-axis.
If we make the same kind
of linear combination with a minus sign,
then we get one which
is polarized along the minus x-axis.
All right, so we've now accounted for electrons
which are up along the z-axis, down along the z-axis,
up along the x-axis, down along the x-axis,
and finally,
there's the issue of the y,
electrons polarized along the y-axis.
I'm not going to work it out.
We can just, just minus i, sorry,
minus i, i, alpha beta,
you have to solve this one,
and this one,
equals minus.
And the two solutions are easy, very easy to do.
The two solutions are alpha beta equals one i,
that's for the plus sign,
I think that's for the plus sign, let's see,
I think that's for the plus sign,
and the other one is one minus i,
one minus i.
Yeah, sorry, excuse me,
one over square root of two again.
Notice that there's more information
in these complex coefficients
than just the fact that the probability
of the z components of
spin is a half a half.
Both,
this has probability of half a half,
so did the previous case where the electron
was along the x-axis.
The fact that there's an i here is something new.
It tells us that the electron is along the y-axis.
All right, so this way.
So now we've accounted for electrons
which are polarized along all six directions.
What about a general direction?
An electron which is, whose spin is pointing along
a definite, along another axis.
Well, for that, you have,
I'm not going to go through it now.
You take linear combinations of these,
we won't do it now, we'll do it another time.
It's not something I intended to do this evening.
All right, so that's quantum mechanics of a...
I'm guessing that the minus sign
goes on the other eigenvalue.
I may have the sign wrong. Do I?
Well, I'm thinking that the minus
i over square root of 2
goes with the first one because
of the minus i in the...
You may be right.
I think you're probably right.
So let's see.
So this one should be minus then,
and this one should be plus.
I think that may be right.
Do I have it in my notes?
Well, I don't have it in my notes.
All right, that's spin 1⁄2.
That's the whole theory of spin 1⁄2.
All wave functions are all state vectors
corresponding to all possible directions of spin
are linear combinations of the two states
in which the spin is up along the z-axis
or down along the z-axis.
I take it back.
Do you take it back?
Yeah, b equals i a.
Okay.
That's plus, huh?
Minus.
I never remember.
What about spin 1?
We've done this before.
I mean, we've done this a lot of times before,
and so I've made fast work of it.
But now let's do spin 1.
Spin 1 is also interesting.
Again, there are many, many choices of the matrices,
and they're all equivalent, physically equivalent,
representing the angular momentum.
But I'm going to show you one.
All right, spin 1,
the z component of angular momentum has three states.
Spin 1 is the integer angular momentum.
It corresponds to bosons,
and it's the case where
the angular momentum can be 0.
The z component can be 0, 1, or minus 1.
So there's three possibilities.
Evidently, the space of states is three-dimensional now,
not two-dimensional, three-dimensional.
Again, we want to find spin matrices,
which satisfy, 3 by 3 matrices,
which satisfy exactly the same algebra.
The algebra means the set of commutation relations,
Sx with Sy,
and then the set of commutation relations,
Y equals Isz, and so forth.
Do there exist, I've left out the H bar
because I've set H bar equal to 1.
Do there exist 3 by 3 matrices which satisfy this?
They're better because we sort of worked out,
we worked out the existence of a three-state system
by assuming these commutation relations.
Yes?
I will just show you a representation,
and you can work it out and
see if you can prove the commutation relations.
They're 3 by 3 matrices.
Let's see, I think it's S,
sorry, Sz, not Z, but Sz.
Or S.
Spin along the Z direction is
equal to I times 0, 1, 0,
minus 1, 0, 0, 0, 0, 0.
It sort of looks sort of familiar but not familiar.
It's 3 by 3, but it
kind of looks like Sy over there,
but it doesn't have the factor of 2.
It's different.
S, let's see what's next.
Sy is equal to I, 0, 0,
1, 0, 0, 0, minus 1, 0, 0.
Notice that this one has zeros in
the third row and the third column.
This one has zeros in the
second row and the second column.
And Sx has zeros in the
first row and the first column,
and it's 0, 0, 0, let's see,
Sx, 0, 0, 1, 0, minus 1, 0.
There's a real symmetry between them.
Each one has a 1 and a minus 1.
They're all anti-symmetric.
Each one has a 1 and a minus 1,
and it has zeros all along the
row and diagonal that match the letter here.
If Z stands for 3, then the
third row and third column are 0.
If Y stands for 2, the second row
and second column are 0 and so forth.
So they're easy to remember.
The only trouble I ever have is remembering the signs.
And again, you check those
by checking the commutation relations.
And they're not completely unique,
but they're all very similar.
Let's see if we can find the eigenstates of Sz.
This time Sz is not diagonal.
I have not chosen Sz to be diagonal.
But nevertheless, we can certainly
work out what the eigenstates are.
They're not too hard to guess.
So we want to solve Sz on...
Well, we want to take this matrix
and now multiply it not by alpha and beta,
but by alpha, beta, and gamma.
How many... what should the eigenvalues be?
1, 0, and minus 1.
Those are the three states of Z component.
Let's try for 1 first.
I hope I have them written down.
Yeah, good news, I do.
No.
Um, yeah.
Yup, it's just...
Incidentally, this corner of it over here
is very similar to Sy over here.
So it's going to be similar.
I think it's 1, minus i, and 0.
So here's an eigenvector.
I think this is a true relationship.
You can check it later.
Here is an eigenvector with eigenvalue plus 1.
It corresponds to the state where Sz...
where M is equal to plus 1.
I didn't give it to you,
Sz, in the simplest possible form.
I gave it to you in a very symmetric form
where X and Y and Z
look very similar to each other.
But nevertheless, the right way to find the state
which corresponds to M equals plus 1
is just to find the eigenvector with eigenvalue plus 1.
What about the eigenvalue minus 1?
That turns out to be this one.
Minus.
And what about the eigenvalue 0?
Oh, incidentally, you should put a
1 over square root of 2
if you want them to add up to...
Okay, what about the eigenvalue 0?
Anybody see what the eigenvector with eigenvalue 0 is?
This one is obvious.
Take the top row, multiply it this, you get 0
because there's nothing to match this 1.
Likewise here.
This is just plain 0.
Big fat 0.
Okay, what do these things mean?
These mean that the three states,
M equals to plus 1,
M equals to minus 1,
and M equals to 0,
correspond to the vectors
1, minus i, 0,
1, i, 0,
These you might want to put a
square root of 2 if you like
to make the probability add up to 1.
All right, so again, we really do find,
and you'll find there were no other eigenvectors,
no other eigenvalues, that's it.
And these are the mathematical representations
of the very abstract things we did last time.
One of the marvelous things is
that these square roots of 2
really do turn up in experimental predictions,
and we're going to do a couple of them,
but not with ordinary spin, but with isotopic spin.
I'm going to show you
how those square roots of 2
turn up in various experiments,
in various experimental quantities,
but not now.
Can you read the second column?
Those are both 1 over the square root of 2?
No, i over the square root of 2.
That's i over the square root of 2,
and the first one is 1 and
i over the square root of 2.
And minus i over the square root of 2.
1 over the square root of 2,
minus i over the square root of 2 and 0,
1 over root 2,
i over root 2 and 0.
This is, I think, M equals 1,
this is M equals minus 1,
and this is M equals 0.
Now as I said, there are other representations,
there are other triplets of matrices
which satisfy the same algebra,
but they are in fact physically completely equivalent.
And I'm not going to go
into the reasons for that now.
These are a good set of matrices to work with.
They're...
fairly elegant and...
we'll use them.
We'll use them more than once.
Okay, um...
Another question...
Yeah.
Supposing we now return
to the real electron which can move around in space.
It can move around in space
so it has a position,
or a momentum,
and a spin.
Incidentally, spin and position
are things which can simultaneously be measured.
Spin and momentum are things
which can simultaneously be measured.
What are the things which can't simultaneously be measured?
Well, position and momentum,
but also the different components of the spin.
They don't commute with each other.
But spin and momentum do commute with each other.
All right, how do we represent
the wave function or the state vector
of an electron
given the fact that it also has a position?
It has a position and a spin.
And the answer is,
we turn these two-component...
They're called spinners.
This is what a spinner is.
The right-hand side,
a two-component object like this,
which just represents up-spin and down-spin,
is called a spinner.
All right?
We just turn the spinner components
into functions of position.
All right?
So, let's imagine that now.
The electron is free to move around.
The full state of the electron
is described not just by a simple function of x,
but by two functions of x.
Let's call it psi up and psi down of x.
And if we like,
we can just make a symbolic notation
where we put them in a column.
What's the meaning of this?
The meaning of this is the following,
that you don't just ask,
what's the probability that the electron is up
or the electron is down?
You ask a more refined question.
The more refined question is,
if the electron is found at position x,
what is the probability that it's up?
That may depend on x.
So the probability that the electron is up
might depend on where you look.
All right?
Another way of saying it is classically,
just corresponds to the classical statement,
that the spin of the electron
could vary from place to place.
Quantum mechanically,
what varies is the probability to find it up,
the probability to find it down.
And so at every point in space,
each point in space,
you have a spinner.
And the spinner tells you,
at that point in space,
what's the probability the electron is up?
Well, it's psi star psi,
up,
psi up of x.
That's the probability that if you look at point x
and discover an electron there,
and then measure the z compo-
and then measure the spin,
the z component of the spin,
this is the probability it will be up.
And psi star,
psi star down of x,
psi down of x,
is the probability that it's down.
But at each point x,
you have all of this apparatus here
in exactly this form.
And that's the whole story of what an electron is.
An electron is a particle
described by a wave function
which has two components.
The two components being
the amplitude that the electron is at,
and the amplitude that the electron is up or down.
Okay?
What about a spin one particle?
Exactly the same.
A spin one-
well, not exactly the same,
almost exactly the same.
But the spin one particle,
and I'm not going to call it psi,
let's just give it another name, phi.
Phi is a more common name for bosons.
And spin one particles are always bosons.
So,
it becomes
phi one of x,
phi two of x,
phi three of x.
Where at each point of space,
at each point of space,
this phi one, phi two, and phi three
replace alpha, beta, and gamma from before.
Psi three of x,
yeah, okay, you understand.
Um,
so it's just reproducing exactly the same structure
over and over in space.
And, um,
that's,
that's what spinners are.
Yeah?
I'm not sure,
is psi one the probability that it's spin one?
No, no, no.
Okay, so let's go back.
Let's go back.
Good, that's a good question.
All right, let's find out,
let's ask, what is the probability,
here's our wave function,
what is the probability that the electron,
that the electron has,
uh, spin plus along the z-axis
and spin minus along the z-axis
and spin zero?
Okay, let's work it out.
Here's what we have to do.
Remember those eigenvectors,
the eigenvectors of spin.
For the spin one,
not for the spin, uh, zero.
Where are they?
Hmm?
Okay, for m equals one,
that's spin up along the z-axis,
the eigenvector was one over square root of two
minus i over square root of two
and zero.
This is the eigenvector for m equals one.
Now, I'll remind you what the rule is
for calculating the probability
for this condition,
given this wave function.
The rule is take the inner product
of this
with the complex conjugate of this,
we take the inner product of this
with the bra vector corresponding to this ket vector,
which is its complex conjugate,
and then square it,
take it, it times its complex conjugate.
So what we do, here's the rule,
standard quantum mechanics,
standard quantum mechanical rule,
we take the inner product,
we'll call this state here phi,
and let's call this m equals one.
We take that inner product
and then square it.
We'll take its absolute value squared.
It times its complex conjugate.
All right?
How about this bra vector
that I've called m equals one?
Bra vectors are always complex conjugates
of ket vectors.
Okay?
So that means the bra vector
can be thought of as a row vector,
that's just a convention,
one over square root of two
plus i over the square root of two and zero,
plus i because it's the complex conjugate
in the second place here,
i over square root of two.
We take the inner product of that
with
phi one, phi two, phi three,
what is that?
i over the square root of two phi one,
no, one over square root of two phi one, right?
Phi one over square root of two
plus i phi two over square root of two,
and that's it.
One over square root of two phi one,
phi two over square root of two times i.
And then we multiply this by its complex conjugate.
All right?
So what do we get?
What's the complex conjugate,
what does this times its complex conjugate give?
I think it's just phi one squared
plus phi two squared over two.
All right.
This times its complex conjugate
will give phi one squared
plus phi two squared over two.
So the probability that the electron
is up along the z-axis
appears to be phi one squared
plus phi two squared over two.
What about the probability that it's down along the z-axis?
I think it's the same.
phi one squared minus phi two squared over two?
I don't think so.
Is it, um, hmm?
No, I don't think so.
It can't be negative.
All right, I think it's the same.
For this, uh,
for this state it's the same.
Uh, what about, um,
what about the probability that
the z-component of spin is zero?
That's phi three squared.
In that case,
the m equals zero state
is one one zero.
And the inner product
is just phi three.
Ah, sorry, zero zero one.
My mistake.
Zero zero one.
And the inner product is just phi three.
So the probability that the electron
is, uh, in the zero angular momentum state
is, um, phi three squared.
Okay?
So here are the probabilities.
Looks like it's phi one squared
over two plus phi two,
phi one squared plus phi two squared.
Over two.
Same thing.
Phi one squared
plus phi two squared
over two.
And phi three squared.
Comma, comma.
Those are the three probabilities.
They add up to one.
Phi one squared plus phi two squared
plus phi three squared.
Okay.
Uh, sorry, this, this should really be...
No, no, no, no, no, no.
Phi one squared means phi one times phi one star.
No, yes, it does.
It does.
I think I, uh, I'll leave this here
for you to work out in detail.
I don't, um,
I hate doing things on the blackboard
when I don't have them in my notes.
I tend to make mistakes,
and I probably have made a mistake.
But you get the principle.
The principle is take the inner product
of these things with...
Oh, I know what I did.
Yeah.
The reason I got these two to be equal
is because I assumed that
phi one, phi two were real.
They don't have to be real.
If they're not real,
you'll get different answers for these two.
Check it out.
Try it out and see what you get.
Okay.
But the principle is always the same.
Take the eigenvector,
take its inner product,
uh, with the actual wave function,
and take its square,
its comp...
times its complex conjugate.
And then you get the final result.
So you get a lot of probability.
And notice, most important in this case
is that it's a function of position.
These phi's are functions of position.
Can vary from place to place.
So that's the basic idea of spin.
It's an exercise to work it out for spin two
or for spin three halves.
And, uh,
it's significantly more complicated,
but not in principle.
Not in principle.
Uh,
it's not hard to find the, uh,
the matrices,
but a little harder.
All right.
Um, I very, very quickly want to come back
to the Dirac equation.
Let's see how we...
Yeah.
For three halves,
then what...
what does the matrix...
Uh, three halves should be, uh, four.
Yeah.
Let's see.
Three halves...
Three halves is the case
plus a half,
minus a half,
three halves,
minus three halves.
So the four states.
Spin, uh,
spin two is five states.
Another question?
Yeah.
None of this discussion seems to be symmetrical
with respect to time.
It's x, y, and z, but no t.
Oh, that's true.
Yeah.
So is all this non-melting this thing?
Um...
Spin is something like mass,
best defined in the rest frame.
So,
uh,
it's a constant.
It's a constant.
Uh,
So,
in that sense,
uh,
what you do
is you study it in the rest frame
and then you find
the right way to Lorentz transform it
to some other frame,
but we won't do that now,
but
uh...
it really doesn't change very much
when you go to relativity.
And that's because
the definition of spin
is
pretty much
what you would get
if you did all this
in the rest frame
particle. But yeah, we can simplify the story,
just say so far this is pretty non-relativistic.
It won't change much in relativity, with
one exception, which we won't do now.
Let me come back to the Dirac equation and
see what the Dirac equation has to do with
spin. Again, spin is best defined
in the rest frame, but let's...
Okay, here's the Dirac equation. It had
matrices, 4x4 matrices, and it looked like this.
I dpsi by dt. Now, the psi's
were four component objects, psi1, psi2, psi3, psi4.
Where did that come from? All right, I'll tell
you in a moment where it came from, but
let's write the equation. The equation is that
this is equal to minus i alpha sub m,
m runs from 1 to 3, the three directions
of space, x, y, and z, times the derivative of
psi with respect to psi.
So, we have, in respect to x, m, sum over
m, so this is alpha1 dpsi by dx, plus alpha2
dpsi by dy, plus alpha3 dpsi by dz, plus
beta times the mass of the particle times psi.
That was the Dirac equation that we wrote
down a couple of lectures ago. And let me
remind you what the conditions on
the left side of the graph are.
And I'll show you what the conditions
on the right side of the graph are.
So, what the conditions on the matrices alpha
and beta were in order, what was the condition?
The condition was that the frequency, let me
write this in a different way, this is
frequency is equal to momentum alpha dot k, we
can write it this way, or just alpha m,
km. This is the same as alpha1 k1, or alpha
x kx, plus alpha 2 kx, plus alpha 3 kx, plus
alpha 2 k2, plus alpha 3 k3, which is the same
as alpha x kx, alpha y ky, alpha z kz, plus
beta m. This is shorthand. This is shorthand.
Do I have a, am I missing an i?
Are those m's different?
Yeah, these m's are an index, this is the
mass of the particle. Okay, let's not use m here.
I, I.
Good, thank you.
Yeah, sorry. And this means sum over i.
Usual summation convention.
Okay, when an index is repeated twice,
it always means you sum over it.
And we're required that omega
squared is equal to k squared,
plus m squared. Remember what we did.
We took omega squared by squaring this out,
and require that we got k squared plus
m squared. What were the conditions for that?
The conditions were conditions on the matrices alpha
and beta. I'll just remind you what they were.
They required every alpha, uh,
squared to be 2, I believe.
Is it 2? I think
it's 2. Uh, no. No, 1.
1. Every alpha squared i, for each i, alpha
x squared equals alpha y squared equals alpha z squared.
Is beta different for each of
the, uh, psi 1, 2, 3, 4?
No, no, beta is one matrix.
Oh, beta is a matrix.
Beta is a matrix. It requires
beta squared to be equal to 1.
These things are just there so that
you get the k squared plus m squared.
Okay. But then, in order
that you don't get cross terms,
in order that you don't get things like
k times m when you square it out,
or k 1 times k 2 and so
forth, we require things like alpha x, alpha y,
plus alpha y squared.
alpha x equals zero. That would be, for
example, the cross term between kx and ky.
All right, so same thing for alpha x
alpha z. We can write this in a
needle notation. Anti-commutator of alpha x
alpha y equals zero, anti-commutator of
alpha x alpha z equals zero, an
anti-commutator of alpha z with alpha y
equals zero. What about
anti-commutator of alpha x with alpha x?
Oh, sorry, and one more. Any alpha with
beta should be also equal to zero.
What's the anti-commutator of beta with
itself? Two. Because it's beta times beta
equals zero.
It's beta times beta.
plus beta times beta. Okay? Right.
So we can summarize these commutation relations
just by saying that everybody's
anti-commutator with himself is 2,
everybody's anti-commutator with somebody
else is 0. Okay? Simple
anti-commutator. Alright, it's a theorem. It's not
hard to prove, but I'm not going
to prove it. That the smallest
dimension, the smallest number of components, the
smallest matrices which can solve this are
4x4. If you didn't have the betas here,
then you can find 2x2 matrices
which satisfy it. In fact, the sigma
matrices, the Pauli matrices, satisfy
it. The Pauli matrices anti-commute with
each other. That's something you can check.
And their square is equal to 1. So
if you didn't have the extra beta matrices,
if you didn't have the extra beta
matrices, then you can't solve these equations.
Now, if you had the 2x2 matrix
here, the Pauli matrices would solve these
equations. But in 2x2 matrices there
are only three matrices which anti-commute
among themselves that way. And if you look
for a fourth one, there just won't be
one. You have to go to larger
dimensional matrices. You try 3x3 matrices, there
aren't.
of this anti-commutation algebra here
I think I wrote down a representation,
I'm going to write down another one tonight
which is a little different,
but it's basically, again, it's equivalent
So I'll give you an example of
four matrices which satisfy exactly this algebra
Now, 4x4 matrices, these are 4x4 matrices
But you can write them in block form
Writing them in block form means that
you divide this up into 2x2 blocks
You have 2x2 blocks
Each one of which is a 2x2 matrix
That's just a simple way to write them down
And then for the alphas, for each
alpha, alpha 1 to alpha 2, alpha 3
Put in this 2x2 box over
here, the corresponding Pauli matrix, sigma i
It's a 2x2 matrix, so
it fills up four entries here
Down here, put the same Pauli
matrix except with a minus sign
And zero is here
That's pretty easy
Isn't it the other way around?
I know, I told you, I
used a different representation last time
They are equivalent
I think I put last time,
I put the sigmas off there
I put the sigmas off diagonal, did I?
Yeah
Yeah, they are equivalent
They're mathematically equivalent and
there are similarity relations
Similarity transforms which relate them
But I like this one better,
I decided I like this one better
And what about beta?
Beta is just in the
same notation, same 2x2 block notation
It's just 1, now what's 1?
1 is the 2x2 matrix 1 0 0 1
It really is 1, the unit
matrix and the unit matrix down here
And that's it, those matrices have the desired property
Incidentally, when you multiply 4x4 matrices in this form
You can do it by tricks where
really you multiply in the blocks 2x2 matrices
So it's an easy way to do this
and it's no harder than working with 2x2 matrices
But I'll leave that to your devices to check
These are the Dirac matrices, the alphas and the betas
Or one particular realization of the alphas and the betas
Excuse me, I think last time we had
beta with the bottom of the minus sign
Minus sign here?
No, that was last time
What's that? This is a different representation
The last time I had these off diagonal and
I don't remember what I had for this one
I can't remember
I thought I had beta diagonal last time
I thought I had beta diagonal, I can't remember
Yeah, yeah
Okay, this is a little bit different
And you get your choice, the physics
of it will be exactly the same
They just correspond to choosing linear
combinations of the four entries in the
And there's no real difference
It's as physically interesting as rotating coordinates
What you're doing is rotating
coordinates in this four dimensional space
Which is not four dimensional space-time
These four entries here do not
have to do with the four
They're not direct the same
as the four dimensions of space-time
They're just the smallest
representation of this algebraic structure
Okay, that's what the Dirac equation is
Here it is, the Dirac equation
It can be summarized in a form like this
Where this really means just this
And here are the matrices
What I want to do, the only
thing I want to point out is that
I'm going to talk a lot about it tonight
Is that there are two kinds
of two by two-ness to this
One is these blocks
And the other is within each block
This, by, what shall I call it
This doubling of the two by two-ness
Corresponds to a doubling of
the two by two-ness in physics
One of the two by
two-nesses is positive and negative energy
The other is spin
Alright, so there are particles of positive energy
With all possible spins
There are positive particles with negative energy
Alright, we can see this
And that's why there are four
by four matrices if you like
Roughly speaking, there's an entry
for positive energy with positive spin
Positive energy with negative spin
Negative energy with positive spin
Negative energy with negative spin
Those are the four possibilities
That's why, when I say positive spin and negative spin
I mean spin along the z-axis
Half spin along the z-axis
That's why there are four components to the Dirac equation
Positive and negative energy
Exactly as in the one-dimensional example that we described
And spin
Up spin and down spin if you like
That's why there are four entries in the Dirac spinner
In the Dirac equation
And perhaps the easiest way to see what's going on
Is to look at a Dirac particle with zero momentum
Just take a particle with zero momentum
That means k is equal to zero
In that case, we can
just throw away the alphas altogether
And we get a very simple equation
When the momentum is zero
That means that psi is constant in space
Is what it means
It has no derivatives with respect to space
k is absolutely zero
In that case, the whole Dirac equation just becomes
Uh
I
D psi by dt
Is equal to im beta
D psi by, uh, psi
That's it
That's the Dirac equation
For a particle at rest
Particle with momentum equals zero means a particle at rest
If it's at rest, the
wave function has no space dependence
It's just completely constant
With respect to space
And this is the whole thing
And it tells you what the possible frequencies are
We can write it a different way
We can write it
Uh, maybe
Yeah
No i here
No i there
Let's see what it says
Okay, so
Here's the way we'll think about it
We'll take these
Psi's
Psi one
There are four entries
One, two, three, four
And we'll divide it
Same kind of division into blocks
And each half of it
The upper half and the lower half
I'll put a two
A thing with two entries
We'll call it psi plus
And psi minus
Let's set up plus and minus
Minus and minus
Does that mean positive and negative?
No, they don't
They don't mean anything right now
Just plus and minus
Nothing special
But each psi plus
What is psi plus?
This is equal
Psi plus is psi upside down
And the bottom one here I think is
Something else
Two others
This corresponds to an electron
What's
What is that column
The last column that you're trying to do?
Okay
We're just writing the column vector
In a notation which is similar to the way I
Divided up matrices
Divided up matrices by just drawing some red lines
And doing two by two matrices in here
We'll divide up
The spinners
The column vectors
By just dividing them in half
And in each place put a two component object
Okay
So psi plus and psi minus are themselves two components
Two two component objects make a four component object
It's just a pretty way to organize the Dirac indices
The Dirac structures here
Okay
Then we can write this equation very nicely
This equation is pretty simple
What does it say?
It says that
The spinners are two components
And the two components are two components
Data
is the matrix
zero, one, one, zero
What does this matrix do
When it hits a two component object?
Psi plus, psi minus
What it does is it swaps
the upper and lower one
When this matrix hits a vector like this
It just interchanges psi plus and psi minus
All right
as a two-component object, psi plus, really
a four-component object, but two two-component objects.
And now we can see what the equation says. What the
equation says is that I d by dt of psi plus
equals m psi minus, and I d by
dt of psi minus equals m psi plus.
That's the whole upshot of the
Dirac equation for particles at rest.
It's even simpler than that. You can, the next step...
Anybody got a good idea what
to do with this to simplify it?
Take another derivative and respect the time.
That's one thing you could do.
Add them and subtract them. Add them and subtract them.
So what happens if you add them?
I d by dt of psi plus plus psi minus
equals m psi plus plus psi minus.
Right?
That's adding them and subtracting them.
I d by dt of psi plus plus psi minus.
Right?
So we can see that now, what
you're doing is the inverse serve of mme
plus m psi plus minus psi minus.
Right?
So I've sorted that out for you.
I've solved it.
They satisfy equations which are
completely independent of each other.
How about the frequencies of this one?
What can you say about the frequency of this one?
ID by DT is just omega, right?
If the wave function has a definite frequency,
then ID by DT just gives you its frequency.
So this object here has a frequency, this one
has a frequency omega, which is just equal to m.
This one has a frequency omega equal to
minus m, because of the minus sign here.
What does it say about
the energies of these two solutions?
One of them is a positive energy solution,
and one of them is a negative energy solution.
All right.
So just exactly the same
as the one-dimensional example we gave,
there are positive energy
electrons and negative energy electrons.
I don't expect you to remember all of this, and to be
able to deal with all of this from one sitting with it.
It's worth going back now, finding a little
book on the Dirac equation, and going through it.
But basically, the two-by-two blockiness here has
to do with positive and negative energy.
Psi plus plus psi minus are positive energy things.
Psi plus minus psi minus are negative energy things.
But that still leaves the
two-by-two-ness of the individual entries here.
Each one of these is a two-by-two entry.
So let's forget psi plus and psi minus.
We've taken care of that
by adding them and subtracting them.
But now let's look at
the entry of the two-by-two block.
This is the entry of just one of them.
It also is a two-by-two thing.
What is that two-by-two thing?
It's the spin.
It's the spin which is
described by these Pauli matrices here.
If we completely forgot about the two-by-two-ness
associated with the upper and lower pieces here,
and just worried about the two-by-two-ness within here,
that's the same as the
two-by-two-ness within the two-by-two matrices here.
That's the spin.
So the Dirac equation predicts that positive
energy electrons come in two different kinds.
The two different kinds have to
do with the upper and lower components,
or the up and down
components within a psi plus here.
And that's the spin.
It also predicts that there's a positive energy,
a positive and negative energy-ness to it.
That comes from here.
That has to do with the existence of positrons.
Okay?
Holes in the negative energy C are positrons.
That's what the four-by-four is about.
You can either think about it as positive
and negative energy spin up and spin down,
or you can think about it as electrons and positrons,
each of which are half-spin particles.
So...
So, yeah.
Can you portray it the opposite way around,
where the big ones are spin
and the small ones are energy?
Yep.
You're asking whether you can...
Yeah, absolutely.
You can.
Yep, you can put the positive
and negative energy-ness into the smaller matrices
and the spin into the bigger matrices.
Yes, you can.
Either way.
They're kind of equivalent to each other,
and they just correspond to reshuffling of the indices.
Could you go through that one
more time on the positron explanation?
Yeah.
You can see from here that there
are both positive frequency and negative frequency solutions.
The things which have positive frequency
are the sums of these two,
and the things which have negative
frequency are the difference between the two.
Negative frequency means negative energy.
Positive frequency means positive energy.
So, if there are positive energy
solutions, that means positive energy electrons.
If there are negative energy
solutions, that means negative energy electrons.
What do you do with a negative energy electron?
You fill it up.
You fill up the Dirac C
with all states of negative energy.
You always lower the energy by
putting in a particle of negative energy.
If you want to lower the
energy down to the absolute minimum,
you fill every negative energy state.
Among others, you fill in negative
energy states which have no momentum.
I just worked that out for zero momentum.
But you fill all the negative
energy states, and that's the vacuum.
You take a negative energy electron and
stick it into a positive energy state,
you've made an electron and a
hole, or an electron and a positron.
So, in exactly the same way
as for the positive energy state,
for the one-dimensional example,
the positive and negative energy
electrons become electrons and positrons.
The other doubling becomes the spin.
So, they're half-spin particles
which come in particle-antiparticle pairs.
And that was the prediction of the Dirac equation.
It's one of these marvelous examples
of just fiddling with abstract mathematics.
Diddle, diddle, diddle, diddle.
And then out comes this
very, very dramatic, incredible prediction,
positive and negative energy particles with spin.
And remember that spin had only been
discovered as in a sort of empirical fact
from that chart up there a couple of years before.
I mean, just a few years before
Dirac did this, a very short time before.
And so, yeah, it was a very dramatic event.
Are you saying that negative energy,
electrons or positrons?
No, I'm saying the absence of
a negative energy electron or positron.
We went through this before.
You fill up all the negative energy
particles and you call out the vacuum.
Okay?
You can't put more than one
negative energy particle in a state.
So, the vacuum takes all the negative energy,
E less than zero, E greater than zero,
and fills them up.
You put an electron into every one of those states.
That has the lowest energy because
all the negative energies are filled.
That's the vacuum.
That's empty space.
Now you remove an electron from
here and put it over here,
not necessarily at the same place up here.
What is that?
Well, now there's a positive energy electron
and the absence of a negative energy electron.
The absence of a negative energy
electron is a positive energy positron.
Okay?
It's exactly the same as in
the one-dimensional example that we did,
where the absence of a negative energy electron,
a hole in the Dirac C becomes
a particle of opposite charge and, yeah.
Why don't the higher energy
negative electrons above that fall down?
Into here?
Into there.
They won't fall down to here.
Right.
Why don't they fall and fill
that little gap you just said?
They do.
And that's called positron-electron annihilation.
And it creates photons.
Well, the first thing it
has to do is conserve energy.
Now, how much energy does
an electron and a positron have?
Both the positron and the electron have positive energy.
Why does a positron have positive energy?
Because it's the absence of a negative energy.
Okay?
It's the absence of a negative energy,
so it has negative energy.
has positive energy. All it is is a
positive charge and a negative charge. When the positive
charge and the negative charge come together,
you can either describe it as the annihilation
of the positive charge with a negative charge,
but energy has to be conserved, so photons
have to go off. The other way to think about
it is as an atom, you know, where an electron,
an excited electron dropping down to a
lower state. What happens then? Photons go off.
Right. Yeah.
Just a question on the mathematics. So
we hear you very clearly, cleanly show how
in a zero-elemental state with this particular
representation of beta, you get the positive
and negative interpretations of the psi. To
get the spin representations in a zero-elemental
state, would you take the different alpha, beta, and beta?
Yeah.
I have a hard time seeing how you
get that cleanly because there's three alpha matrices.
Say it again.
There's three alpha matrices. There's more...
Oh, and those three alpha
matrices become the three spin matrices.
But in a zero-momentum state, you don't see
them. So to look at spin in a zero-momentum
state, how does the mathematics show that simply?
Well, the zero-momentum positive energy
state, let's say. A zero-energy positive
energy state, that would correspond to a spinner
of the form, let's call it psi plus,
with the same psi plus here. We want to
set psi minus equal to zero because we don't want
any negative energy part of the solution. So
that means psi plus, psi plus. All right.
Well, alpha, for example, alpha is not quite...
Alpha is not really... Are you asking me how
you make the spin operators
from the direction of the spin?
No, not really. I'm just asking how... If
there's a way, simply as you've shown, negative
energy states, you show how
you discover spin from this point.
Well, you've discovered that the positive energy
particles come in a pair, one which
you can call up and one which you couldn't
call down. Now you want to see that that pair
really has angular momentum.
Yeah, that it really has the same. Now
you can see that these Pauli matrices do come
into it.
Right.
Okay. But to see that it really corresponds
to angular momentum, you have two ways of
going about it. One is through the
connection between angular momentum and rotation symmetry,
and the other is through the fact that
angular momentum is conserved. Okay. So what you would
want to show, let's use the conservation definition. What
you would want to show is that in any
kind of collision where an electron comes
in and scatters off something else, that if
you assign the electron an angular momentum
whose description is in terms of this twofoldness
within here, that that angular momentum together
with all the other angular momentum in the
problem would be conserved. All right. This is a
little too much for us to do tonight anymore.
So we've already worked on this. What we
can do more easily is show the connection
with rotation symmetry, but I don't want to
do this. I'm, uh, I think we've all reached
a certain limit by now.
So there happens to be another electron around.
It can annihilate with the positron even if
it doesn't have the same energy.
Yes. Yes.
And then you just get a different number of photons.
Or photons coming out with... I'll
tell you what happens. Okay, supposing you
Then you have two electrons with the same energy.
Two electrons coming in in the
center of mass frame, let's say.
Well, I'm assuming that you had the
particle pair, and then another half electron happens
to be around.
Oh, it doesn't matter which electrons annihilate.
I mean, the electrons don't remember which one…
Except that one may have a certain energy
and the other may have a different energy.
Yeah, but when you kick this electron out of
here, you can kick it up to any energy.
It doesn't necessarily have the same energy as the positron.
Yeah, when you hit that electron, you don't
necessarily kick it up to the same energy.
You just hit it.
You hit it and it
goes somewhere to some other energy.
And then there's no memory of which…
Let's suppose there was another electron around.
Their axi is filled, and now a positron…
Not a positron…
Yes, a positron is formed and another electron.
Then this electron can fall into the hole,
or this electron can fall into the hole.
In either case, you'll get photons out.
I'm feeling unclear.
So if you have…
Let's say that the positron was the
eighth level or whatever, negative eight, right?
Why wouldn't negative seven and negative six drop into that?
And why would it have to be an electron?
Oh, no, that can happen.
That's what I'm saying.
It's a process.
It's a perfectly good thing to happen.
But photons…
All right, so let's see.
We start…
Let's see what that says.
We start with negative seven over here, a hole.
That means a positron, one positron,
one E plus, a positive charged electron.
Notation for a positron is E plus.
Notation for an electron is E minus.
All right, so we have one E plus.
Let's see what it does.
So let's see.
So I start this process.
I have antezium and that is this Isaac.
I have two citriol in here.
So I'll just plant a been death electron in there.
I broke it.
I've got two likely الا and that's
only one electron because we've detected that
blocked.
Why is that?
Because…
Why can't one of these fall down to here?
What would that mean?
You would start with a positron
and you would end with a positron
but you would end with
a positron of a different energy
This hole was a positron
Now an electron from here
comes and falls into this hole
There's a negative energy electron falls into this hole
That's what you're asking
So you started with a positron
Here it was
the hole
and you ended with a positron
It's just a positron of a different energy
So a positron has changed its energy
When a positron changes its energy, it
can only do so by emitting photons
Right
How do you make an electron change its energy?
By emitting photons
Slamming it into something and having it emit
So a positron from here, under the right conditions
Sorry, an electron from here can fall down to here
That's just another way of saying the positron
scattered from one state to another and radiated
some photons
Okay, so wouldn't they just always, you
know, because there's always higher energy electrons
Wouldn't they all fall down and the only
thing you'd be left with is a positron?
The reason it doesn't happen, so
you're saying why is the positron stable?
Why doesn't that?
No, the answer is because you
have to conserve both energy and momentum
And the conservation of energy and
momentum doesn't allow it to happen
Okay, so we can work that out, but again
Alright, so why don't you ask me
that at the beginning of next week
And I'll show you why the...
Look, you could have asked exactly
the same thing about the original electron
Why can't an electron always
lower its energy and radiate photons?
Why can't an energy...
An electron just...
An electron just drop down in
energy till it's the lowest energy electron
And the answer is because it can't
simultaneously conserve energy and momentum and emit photons
Just so it just doesn't happen
So I will get in touch with
you and give you the exact schedule
We will definitely meet ten times this quarter
Next quarter I have less obligations
So I won't be...
I won't be disappearing on you next quarter
Thank you
Thank you for your patience
For more, please visit us at stanford.edu