Stanford University
Alright,
a mathematical interlude we're going to begin with.
Mathematical interlude is again about linear algebra,
about vector spaces,
but about the idea of operators.
But before we do,
before we get to operators,
I want to say a few more things about vectors.
A few more bits about the mathematics of vectors.
Most of these bits have to do not
so much with deep mathematics as with good notation.
Good notation is worth an awful lot when you can
just manipulate symbols in ways that are sort of prearranged
and do it easily and comfortably.
There's an enormous benefit in that.
For doing things like this,
you can do things like abstract mathematics,
certainly,
but also the abstractions,
the mathematical abstractions of physics.
The abstractions that we're going to
talk about are largely due to Dirac,
Paul Dirac,
who really was the one who saw into
the way that quantum mechanics really fits together.
So let's talk about that.
We have a space of states.
The space of states,
which we'll come back to,
is,
as I said,
a linear vector space,
meaning to say that you can multiply states,
by numbers,
to get new states,
and these are abstract vectors.
Abstract vectors,
maybe I throw too much in
when I say space of states,
just abstract vectors,
you can multiply them by numbers,
in our case complex numbers,
and you can add them,
and there are two kinds of vectors.
There are the Bra vectors and the ket vectors.
They're,
roughly speaking,
related by complex conjugation,
and a vector space has a dimensionality.
The dimensionality is the maximum number of orthogonal
vectors that you can find in that space,
and once you know what
the dimension of the space is,
you can look for a basis of vectors.
The basis of vectors is
a mutually orthogonal collection of normalized,
get the terminology down,
orthonormal basis.
Ortho means that they're all orthogonal to each other.
Normal,
the word normal means normalized,
and normalized simply means that
the vectors are of unit length.
A collection of them that is maximal,
in other words,
that you can't find anymore,
because there are no more directions left,
that defines a basis,
and the number of them is
equal to the dimensionality of the space.
Given such a basis,
you can make,
you can write any vector in the space
as some kind of sum over those basis vectors.
So,
we can write for any vector in the space,
vector A,
that it's equal to sum over I.
I here stands for the basis vectors.
Of course,
a basis is not a unique thing.
Just as there are many sets
of mutually orthogonal vectors in three-dimensional space,
there are many sets of mutually
orthogonal vectors in an abstract vector space,
but we pick one.
We pick a set.
Having picked that set,
and we label it I,
we can,
we can write any vector
as a sum alpha sub I,
exactly those alphas which we referred to a moment ago.
Alpha sub I,
a set of complex numbers,
a set of complex coefficients,
times the ith basis vector.
The ith basis vector,
I'm labeling I.
This is a ket representation,
but now what we can do with this
is we can take the inner product with it.
I want to try to calculate these alpha sub I's
in terms of some
quantities involving the vectors themselves.
Alright,
so what we do is we take the
inner product of both sides of the equation
with the basis vector J,
the ket vector J.
On the left-hand side,
we get the inner product
of the vector A,
which is the thing we're trying to express.
And that's equal to the sum over I,
alpha sub I,
times the inner product of the vector J,
with the vector I.
But the inner product of the
vector J with this vector I
is either 1 or 0.
It's 1 if I and J are the same vector,
and it's 0 otherwise.
Why?
Because they're orthogonal if I is not equal to J,
and they're normalized,
namely of unit length,
if I does equal J.
So,
this bracket over here,
this product of bras and kets,
is just the Kronecker symbol delta Jk,
sorry,
delta J I,
0 or 1,
and when you do the sum,
it just picks out one and only one contribution,
the contribution in which I is equal to J.
So,
on the right-hand side,
you just get alpha J.
No sum.
The sum is collapsed to one term,
and that's now equal to J A.
Alright,
so what have we learned?
We've learned that the coefficient here,
in the expansion of any vector,
is just the inner product of the Jth vector
with the target vector,
with the vector we're trying to describe.
The fact that I wrote a J there is irrelevant.
It could also be alpha J.
It doesn't matter which I or which J.
The Ith coefficient is an inner product.
Now,
I can use that to rewrite the sum up here.
I now know what the alpha sub I's are.
They're these guys over here.
So,
let's rewrite this.
Sum over I.
I'm going to start with alpha I.
Sorry,
with I.
And then write alpha sub I.
I'm going to write alpha sub
I next to it over here
in the opposite order.
That's allowed.
Nothing noncommutative at this stage.
Now I want to write alpha sub I.
So,
I write I A.
That's a basic formula
that any vector can be rewritten
in terms of its coefficients
or in terms of its inner product
with the basis vectors
times the basis vectors themselves.
Summed over I.
It's kind of a pretty formula.
And it comes back over and over again.
What it says is whenever you see this summation
of I times I in that form,
you can sort of throw it away.
It's just A equals A.
But it's an expression for a vector
in terms of its components.
All right.
So that's one simple fact.
The same thing is true for bra vectors.
Exactly the same thing is true for bra vectors.
And you would write it in the following form.
A bra vector is also a sum over I
of the inner product of the bra vector
with the basis vectors
times the basis bra vectors.
The basis bra vectors are just the complex conjugates,
if you like,
of the basis ket vectors.
Both of these equations are true.
And we're going to find out that they're enormously useful.
They're enormously useful and powerful,
even though they were very,
very simple.
All right.
Now we come to the notion of linear operators.
States in quantum mechanics are vectors.
And we saw a little bit about how that works
in the case of a single spin.
Observables.
Observables mean the things that we measure.
The things that we measure,
the objects that we measure,
the quantities that we measure.
The observables are related to
linear operators in the space.
All right.
So what is a linear operator?
And it'll take us the rest of the evening
to understand that.
And in any detail what
it has to do with observables.
So put that out of your head for the moment.
We're just doing a mathematical interlude now.
What is the notion of a linear operator?
A linear operator is a process,
if you like,
which you apply to vectors.
Somebody or other,
I can't remember who it might have been,
John Wheeler,
liked to describe these things as machines.
He would say,
a linear operator is a machine
with two little ports in it.
Into one port you put an input vector,
and then you turn the wheel,
and out comes an output vector.
So it's a thing which acts on an input vector
to give an output vector.
So let's call m a linear operator.
Linear is a linear we'll come to.
So far we're just talking about operator.
A machine.
In goes one end,
out comes another end.
And we'll talk about what it means
for it to be linear in a minute.
Alright,
so m is some operator.
And that means that given any vector,
when m acts on it,
it simply gives another vector.
Unique.
Given any a,
it gives a unique b.
Unique.
It does not mean,
the converse may not be,
converse,
opposite,
I don't know,
may not be true.
It may not be that
given a b on this side,
that there's only one unique a
that gives rise to that b.
But it is true that
m applied to any vector a
gives a unique reflection of a,
which is the process m acting on a.
Now what does it mean for
m to be a linear operator?
Well,
first of all,
m can act on z times a,
where z times a is a vector.
In fact,
let's write that m can act on z times a.
Z times a is itself a vector,
because you're allowed to
multiply vectors by complex numbers.
Z is a complex number.
The rule about linear operators,
is if they apply on constants times a vector,
they just give back the constant times
what they would have given on a.
So it just means that a z,
a complex number,
a complex number can be brought through m.
m acting on twice a gives twice
what m would have given on a.
m acting on three times a gives three
times what a would have given on a.
m gives on a.
m acting on i times a,
the complex number of i just gives
i times whatever m would give on a.
That's the first rule about linearity.
And the second rule about linearity is
that if m acts on the sum of two vectors,
a plus b,
then what you get is just a sum
of what the machine spit out for a
and what the machine spit out for b.
What the machine spits out when
you put in a plus b
is just the sum of what comes out
m times a plus m times b.
And that's it.
That's the notion of a linear operator.
There's no more to it than that.
Or at least that's the full
set of rules about linear operators.
Now let's see if we
can be more concrete about them.
And see if we can learn to manipulate with them.
Let's suppose that m times a equals b.
Here I've used b as a piece of the input,
but now b is the output.
a and b are just letters.
I can use them any way I want.
m times a equals b.
I'm interested in the component
of b along the axis i.
By that I mean these objects over here,
the alphas,
they are the components of the vector a
along the various basis vector directions.
So alpha sub i's are the components of the vectors.
And I'm interested in the components of the output vector.
I would like to know in a
concrete way what are the components of b.
So to find out,
I just project them onto the direction i.
a m i.
All I've done is in both
sides of the equation project or to,
project this to,
take the inner product with the vector i.
This by definition is beta i.
In other words,
if I were to expand b
in the same way I expanded a,
I would use the coefficients beta i.
That's what we learned up on the top board.
This is beta i.
How about over here?
What can I do with this
to rewrite things in terms of components?
I want to rewrite everything in terms of components
so they actually become
arithmetical operations that you can do.
Well,
here's where we use this trick.
Now whenever you see a vector a,
you can substitute for it
a sum.
Let's do that right in here.
Where a is,
let's substitute i.
I haven't substituted yet.
Now,
the summation variable is not i in here.
It's a j in this case.
i I've used as the external non-summation variable here.
So let's sum over j.
It doesn't matter what we call the summation variable.
j a.
I've stuck in for a the sum of the components
times the jth vector.
Times the jth basis vector.
But now,
a times j,
go up to the top again,
that's just alpha j.
So,
we now have a formula
completely in terms of components.
This is i m j.
I'll get to this in a minute,
but it's a number.
Inner products are numbers.
m times j is a vector,
and you can take its inner product with i.
and vectors,
ket vectors,
have inner products with basis vectors.
Times j a,
or times alpha j,
that's equal to beta i.
So all we have to do
is give this object a name.
What is this object?
I'll tell you again.
You have some operator,
it's an abstract entity.
You have a collection of basis vectors.
You apply the abstract operator
to the vector j,
and take its inner product with i,
and call the thing m i j.
It's a number.
It may be a complex number,
but it's a number.
In other words,
it's possible to characterize linear operators
by
what are called their matrix elements.
These are called the matrix elements
of the linear operator m.
This times alpha j summed over j.
I left out the sum over j here.
Let's put it back in.
Sum on j is equal to beta i.
If somebody hands you
the collection of m i j's,
and somebody hands you a vector
in the form of its components,
you can then start sweeping through it
and calculating what the components
of the output are in terms of the input.
m i j is a matrix.
It has two indices.
It's a square matrix.
If the dimensionality of the space is n,
then m is an n by n matrix.
A square matrix.
It's a square matrix,
and it's a square matrix.
Alpha can be regarded as a column.
Alpha can be regarded as a column,
and the output is also a column.
It's a column because a was a ket vector
and b was a ket vector.
All right,
so another way to write the same thing,
this is one way to
write m times a equals b.
Well,
here's one way to write it,
abstract.
Here's another way to write it as a concrete sum,
and the third way is to recognize
that this is just the multiplication
of a matrix times a column vector.
You write the matrix m
by displaying all of its components,
m one one,
m one two,
m one three,
dot dot dot,
m two one,
m two two,
dot dot dot,
dot dot dot dot dot dot.
It's just an array that exhibits
the matrix elements,
we'll now learn to call these
the matrix elements of m,
times the column vector a,
alpha one,
alpha two,
dot dot dot,
alpha n.
And what is the rule?
This,
of course,
is supposed to result
in an output which is beta one,
beta two,
dot dot,
beta n.
All right,
what's the rule that's implied
by this equation over here?
It's very simple.
If you want the first entry over here,
you take the first row,
and you take its inner product
with the column here.
Not the inner product,
you can call it the inner product.
m one one,
alpha one,
plus m one two,
alpha two,
plus m one three,
alpha three,
right down to the bottom.
That's exactly this formula.
m one two,
sorry,
m one one,
alpha one,
plus m one two,
alpha two,
and so forth,
is exactly the standard rule
for multiplying a matrix by a column vector.
All right,
so now we have a third way
to represent the action of a matrix
on a vector.
This is less abstract.
It's concrete.
If you know the matrix elements,
you know exactly what to do with them.
The only thing about it is it does depend
on a particular choice
of your basis vectors.
The specifics of the matrix elements here
and the column vector will depend
on your choice of,
once you pick a basis,
you stick with it.
But you could have chosen a different basis,
in which case these components
would have been different.
The matrix elements would have been different.
After all,
the matrix elements
are themselves related to the basis vectors.
And so you lose something
and you gain something
by going to a matrix type representation.
What you lose is the geometric idea
of a relationship between two vectors
that's independent of the basis choice.
What you gain is a computational,
actual mechanical algorithm
for producing,
or for the machine itself.
Here is the machine.
The machine is a matrix,
and what it does is it grinds through
m11,
alpha1,
blah blah blah blah blah,
then it goes to the next row,
does the thing again,
goes to the next row,
and just spits out a final answer.
These things are of course also true
for ordinary vectors in three-dimensional space.
They're not specific.
We tend not to use them as much
in three-dimensional ordinary vectors.
But they're quite essential
in quantum mechanics.
Yes,
Martha?
This may be getting ahead.
Could the choice of basis vectors
ever make a difference to whether or not
you can see the solution to a problem?
Well,
alright,
the precise way you ask it,
whether it can make a difference
to the way you see through a problem,
certainly a wrong choice of basis
can leave you completely confused.
I think what you really meant is,
can different choices of basis
lead to different physical answers?
And that had better not be.
Then you're doing something wrong.
You have to be smart.
Yeah,
yeah.
It's often the case that a convenient choice of basis
will make your computations especially simple.
And a bad choice of basis
might make them horribly complicated.
That's true.
But at the end of the day,
the answer should not depend on it.
The result of an experiment.
Okay?
So now we have the idea
of a linear operator
operating on a,
and several different versions of it.
Question?
Yeah.
Is it legitimate,
it seems that within the definition
of a linear operator,
you have an operator that gives you
a ket vector from a bra vector,
or vice versa.
Linear operators act on ket vectors
to give ket vectors.
The complex conjugation is not allowed.
That's right.
Complex,
ah,
very good.
All right.
Well,
let's,
yeah.
The simplest kind of linear operator
is just multiplication by a complex number.
I just multiply A by a complex number
and get another vector.
It's basically the same vector,
but twice as long or something.
That is a linear operator.
You might ask whether complex conjugation
is a linear operator.
I take,
I take the components of a vector
and replace them by their complex conjugates.
The answer is no.
It is not.
And you can check the definitions.
Multiplying the components of a vector,
or not multiplying them,
but complex conjugating them is not.
What it does do is it takes a vector,
it's a different kind of machine,
complex conjugation.
It's a machine which takes a vector,
it just takes a bra vector to a ket vector,
or a ket vector to a bra vector.
And that's strictly,
it's called an anti-linear operator.
It's not anti-linear.
I mean,
it's just,
it's not the opposite of linear.
It's just a word.
Well,
the reason it's a word,
the reason it was called an anti-linear
is because the process of complex conjugation
is in some deep way related to anti-particles,
but we're not there yet.
Yeah.
All right,
now let's talk,
let's talk about ket,
sorry,
bra vectors.
So far,
we have defined our linear operators
to act only on ket vectors.
But every linear operator can also be given a definition.
We need a definition,
of course.
We haven't defined it yet.
We need a definition.
But there is also a definition
of any given linear operator
acting on a bra vector.
Okay,
let's see if we can
concoct a definition,
and then we'll stick with that definition.
What might be the rules
for the action of that same linear operator
when it acts on a bra vector?
First of all,
the standard notation,
and it's very,
very good to keep track of notation
and to use the same notation over it.
It's not only neat,
but it keeps things in order.
When you act on a bra vector,
put the corresponding operator
on the right side of it.
It gives something.
Take that something
and take its inner product.
Let's put a bracket around it
to indicate that M acting on A
is itself an entity.
And now let's take its inner product,
with another vector,
B.
Well,
if I removed the bracket here,
I would have a symbol
which would look like this,
A,
M,
B.
And I really wouldn't know
if what I'm supposed to do
is act with M on B
and then take the inner product with A,
or act with M on A
and then take the inner product with B.
The answer is,
with the standard definition
of how linear operators act to the left
on bra vectors,
it doesn't matter.
In other words,
we define the action of an M on an A
to the left,
such that,
and I'll show you that we can always do this,
such that it doesn't matter
which way we do it.
A,
M,
B is the same as A,
B,
that you can remove the brackets.
Okay,
let's see that we can do this.
In order to see it,
let's start with a definition this way.
Let's start with a definition this way.
Where's my...
Ah,
okay.
Start with a definition this way,
and then we'll do this.
Now,
I'm going to use that trick up on the top,
where you write a vector by inserting...
There's a name for this operation here.
It's called inserting a complete set of states.
Complete simply means it's a basis.
It did nothing.
It took A and it rewrote A,
but it rewrote A in terms of its components.
So let's do that over...
on B over here.
We can do the same thing over here.
We can write that this is equal to B,
J,
J summed over J.
I'm not going to write the summation signs.
Maybe I'll put them at the end out here.
Summation I and J.
All right,
so this is the same vector as B.
Then put M there.
Let's put the bracket around it.
Put M there,
and now do exactly the
same thing on the ket vector.
Remember,
the ket vector can also
be expanded in the same way.
So here we go.
A,
I,
I.
What do we see here?
We see this is alpha star I.
Why did I put the star there?
Because the bra vectors are complex conjugates.
Alpha sub star I.
There's an M,
I,
J.
I in a product of I,
M times J.
And then there is beta J.
That's all we have here.
This is summed on I and J.
M with I on the
left and J on the right.
That's M,
I,
J.
J beta,
alpha I.
And you can see from
the way that we've written this
that it doesn't matter if I first sum over J
and think of M as
acting on the ket vector beta,
or I sum over I and think of
M as first acting to the left on alpha.
You get the same answer.
It's just a double sum over I and J.
And so if you define,
in other words,
you can,
you can define M in such a
way that it doesn't matter which order,
which order or where you put the brackets.
That eases your life.
You don't have to remember whether
you meant M acts on B
and then you take the inner product with A,
or M acts on A and then
you take the inner product with B.
Same thing.
Okay,
but there is a,
there is,
that's,
that's the power of a nice notation.
But now let's consider another question.
Supposing that the linear operator M on A gives B.
Incidentally,
I'm using A and B all
over the place in different ways.
There it was just two vectors.
Here,
A is the input vector,
B is the output vector.
So let's suppose that the machine M,
when you stick A into it,
out spits B.
We could ask what's the corresponding
bra vector relationship.
Is there a linear operator which has the property
that when it acts on,
I'm not going to call it a vector,
I'm going to call it M yet.
It's not M.
Let's call it scripty M.
Is there,
for every M,
which acts on A to give B,
is there a corresponding scripty M
which acts on the corresponding bra vector,
B,
to give the corresponding bra vector over here?
Well,
yes there is,
and we're going to figure out how
to figure out what it is soon enough.
But it is not the original M.
One example would be,
what if M was just multiplication by a complex number?
Then what would scripty M be?
Multiplication by the complex conjugate number.
So,
whatever M is,
is not necessarily the same as scripty M.
It would be the same as scripty M,
if it was multiplication by a real number.
But if it's multiplication by a complex number,
then in general,
well,
in general it will not give the same relationship.
We would normally just put a complex conjugate sign
if we wanted to operate on the other direction.
All right,
the notation that is standard
is to say that the operator
which when acting to the left,
is the reflection,
if you like,
is the dual of the
operator M acting to the right,
that is not called M,
it is called M dagger.
The dagger is a operator version of complex conjugation.
It's an operator version of complex conjugation,
or a matrix version of complex conjugation.
It's called Hermitian conjugation,
but we'll get to these fancy words soon enough.
Well,
okay,
this is abstract,
but let's see if we
can get to a concrete notion.
M i j,
the abstract operator,
is equivalent to a concrete matrix.
If I give you the concrete matrix,
then I'm giving you M.
The question is,
in terms of that concrete matrix,
is there a concrete matrix for M dagger?
And the answer is yes.
How do we find it?
We find it just by proceeding dead ahead.
I would like to know what the matrix elements,
let's see which way I did it.
Yeah.
This is what I would call
the ijth matrix element of M dagger.
I don't know what M dagger is yet.
I have a suspicion that it's
something to do with complex conjugates.
But this is its matrix elements,
concrete set of numbers.
Can we find out what they are?
All right,
yeah,
I think I have to step back for a minute.
Let me suppose that M acts on
the basis vector to give i prime.
i prime is just the result of
sticking the basis vector into the machine,
into the M machine,
and this is what comes out.
Let's suppose that's the result.
Okay.
Now let's take j M i.
That's equal to j M i.
That's equal to j i prime.
All I've done is take the inner product with j.
Here's the matrix element of the matrix M,
and it's just this inner product.
That was a trivial operation.
I didn't do anything.
Okay.
I didn't do anything very significant.
If this is true,
then by definition,
if M dagger acting to the left,
what does M dagger acting
to the left give on i?
Okay.
Look at this equation here.
M dagger,
when it acts to the left,
gives the bra vector b.
All right.
So that's what all that dagger does,
is it sort of turns the equation over.
So what does M dagger acting on i give?
It gives the bra vector i prime.
If M dagger acts on the bra i,
it must give the bra vector i prime.
It just flips the equation from bras to kets.
So what we have over
here then is i prime j.
That's the matrix element.
That's this matrix element over here.
Okay.
So let's look at what we have.
We have the matrix element of M
is the inner product of j with i prime.
The matrix element of M dagger
is the inner product of i prime with j.
What's the relationship between these two?
Transpose.
Transpose and complex conjugate.
Just a complex conjugate.
If you take two vectors,
a and b,
and you think of them in the opposite order,
the bra a times the ket b
versus the bra b times the ket a,
the relationship between them is just complex conjugation.
So this here is just a complex conjugate of this.
So what we've derived is that the matrix element,
the i jth matrix element of M dagger
is the complex conjugate of j.
So what we have here is the matrix element
of the j i th matrix element of M.
So if I know the matrix elements of M,
what do I do to get
the matrix elements of M dagger?
It's very simple.
You complex conjugate,
but that's not quite enough.
and you interchange i's and j's.
You interchange i and j.
Okay?
Another way to write it
is that M dagger i j
is equal to M j i star.
So now we know a lot.
We know how to construct operators
which act to the left to do the same mapping
that they did when they went to the right.
They map the bra a to the bra b
if the original operator did
the same thing on the kets.
All right,
that's the notion of Hermitian conjugation.
This is called Hermitian conjugation.
The word Hermitian is named after some mathematician
whose name was Hermitian.
So Hermitian conjugation is the process
of interchanging i and j and taking its complex conjugate.
In terms of matrices,
if I have a matrix,
this is an easy way to remember it,
M one one,
M one two,
dot dot dot,
M two one,
M two two.
If that's the matrix representing M,
then the matrix representing its conjugate,
its Hermitian conjugate,
is to simply interchange rows and columns.
That means reflecting it about the diagonal
and then complex conjugating.
Interchanging i and j,
that's like interchanging M one two with M two one.
You just flip it about the diagonal
and you complex conjugate it.
So if I want the matrix elements
of the Hermitian conjugate,
well,
I can't say it anymore,
just do what I said,
you interchange rows and columns
and you complex conjugate.
Interchanging rows and columns
is the same thing as reflecting about the diagonal.
You reflect about the diagonal,
let's do it,
and then you complex conjugate.
Let me give an example.
Supposing I have the matrix
two,
six plus i times seven,
four minus i and nine.
Nine plus i,
okay.
Nine plus i.
What's the Hermitian conjugate of that?
Alright,
you first flip it.
Flipping it leaves the diagonal elements in place
and interchanges the off-diagonal elements.
So you flip it,
two,
nine plus i,
six plus i times seven,
four minus i.
What is that process called of flipping it like that?
Transpose.
That's called a transpose.
So flipping it is a transpose,
but then you have to complex conjugate it.
Complex conjugating just means
wherever you see i,
put minus i.
So this becomes four plus i,
one minus seven i,
and nine minus i.
And that's the matrix that represents
the Hermitian conjugate of the original matrix.
So it's easy.
It's easy,
it's concrete,
and it's also abstract.
It has an abstract side.
The Hermitian conjugate just allows you to turn an equation
from a bra ket,
a bra vector to a ket vector.
And in terms of concrete matrix elements,
you flip i and j,
and you complex conjugate.
And that defines m dagger.
Now as I said,
in general these matrices
are thought of as complex objects.
And the notion of complex conjugation
is replaced by this Hermitian conjugation.
Simultaneous flipping and...
Now what is a real number?
A real number is one
which is its own complex conjugate.
If I write that z is equal to z star,
you jump up and you say,
that is a real number.
So,
there's a corresponding notion for operators.
It's the notion of an operator
which is its own Hermitian conjugate.
An operator which is its own Hermitian conjugate,
that means you interchange and complex conjugate
and you get back to the same thing.
That is called Hermitian.
Hermitian is the analog for matrices
or the analog for operators
of real.
Alright,
so what it says,
a Hermitian matrix.
Now let's specialize to the case of
Hermitian matrices.
Let me just spell out Hermitian for you.
Hermitian for matrices
is the analog of real for numbers.
A Hermitian operator or matrix
is one which is its own Hermitian conjugate.
One which is equal to its own
Hermitian conjugate.
In terms of matrices,
it's Mij
is equal to Mji star.
Let's try to see if we can construct
a Hermitian matrix.
Yeah,
let's see if we can construct
a Hermitian matrix.
The first thing about Hermitian matrices
is their diagonal elements are not the same.
They're always real.
Take a diagonal element.
For a diagonal element,
i and j are equal.
ij is the same as ji
if on the diagonal.
So that says that
for the diagonal elements,
they're always real.
So a Hermitian matrix
first of all has real
diagonal elements.
I don't know,
I like 7.
Minus 2.6
on the diagonal.
Often,
if you have a diagonal
with a diagonal
they have the property that when you reflect them
they simply complex conjugate.
So if we were to put i over here
we would put minus i over here
for a Hermitian matrix.
If you were to put
4 minus i over here
you would put 4 plus i over here
and if you had 5 over here
you'd put 5 over here.
So a Hermitian matrix
has the property first of all
the diagonal elements are real
and the off diagonal elements
not symmetric
but a different kind of symmetry
a symmetry where
when you reflect them
they complex conjugate.
That's called a Hermitian matrix.
A Hermitian matrix
has an enormous importance
Hermitian matrices have enormous importance
in quantum mechanics
they represent
the observable quantities
the measurable quantities
the things that you can measure.
We're going to come to that
and we're going to do a bit of that
especially for the single spin
I hope tonight.
But before we do
we have to know a little more
about Hermitian matrices.
In particular we need a concept
the concept of eigenvector and eigenvalue.
I know that I'm going fast
and I know I'm quite aware
that if you don't know these ideas
you're going to have to
struggle tonight to keep up
but they're standard ideas
there are lots of textbooks on linear algebra
you can find it
and you can sit down quietly
and learn these ideas in about two hours
I would say
two,
three hours
Okay,
so
let's talk about Hermitian
well let's first talk about
eigenvectors and eigenvalues
we can even think about these things
incidentally in ordinary three dimensional space
where the vector space is just
a space of ordinary three vectors
there are operators
they're represented by matrices
and those operators operate on vectors
to give other vectors
and typically if a matrix
is at all interesting
or if an operator is at all interesting
whatever you mean to be interesting
or if it's at all a little bit complex
it will generally have the property
that if you put a vector into the machine
the vector that comes out
will be pointing in a different direction
that will be generally true
generically true
so directionality
is not preserved
by linear operators as a rule
on the other hand
there may be particular vectors
and typically there are particular vectors
that
when you apply
a matrix
those vectors will depend on which matrix
you're talking about or an operator
there may be specific vectors
associated with a specific operator
that do
simply get multiplied by numbers
in other words they come out in the same direction
an example
of a operation
a linear operation
on a vector is a rotation about an axis
that can be represented by a matrix
a matrix
in three dimensions
if you rotate the vector space
about some axis
then generally speaking
an arbitrary vector will wind up in a different direction
however there is one
particular direction for which
that doesn't happen namely along the axis of rotation
if you rotate about the axis of rotation
the vector
comes out pointing in the same direction
it comes out a multiple of itself
now in this case simply equal to itself
alright
so that's the notion of
the eigenvectors of an operator
they are the vectors
if there are any
there are not necessarily any
for example in rotations
about two and two dimensions
there are no eigenvectors
there are no directions which come out
no directions which come out unaffected
but
so in general
there may or may not be
eigenvectors
but if there are eigenvectors they're defined
in the following way
so let's use m for the generic operator
m acts
on an eigenvector
let's call the eigenvector i
i for eigen
now of course i is not for eigen
eigen begins with an e
but i'm going to call it i anyway
alright
if m
acts on one of its eigenvectors
eigenvectors are not things
which are independent of the matrices
they're just a bunch of things
given a matrix or an operator
it has certain
eigendirections or certain eigenvectors
and
the rule is
or the definition
is the set of vectors
which just get multiplied
by numbers
let's call for the i-th
eigenvector here
the eigenvalue is called lambda i
and it simply multiplies
the input
now different
eigenvectors
of the same matrix will have different
eigenvalues
there may be and in general that's
the generic situation
if there are several eigenvectors
they will have different eigenvalues
however
the eigenvectors
are not completely unambiguous
if you take an eigenvector
and multiply it by a number
the result is still an eigenvector
with the same eigenvalue
if i multiply
the equation by a complex number z
i can bring the complex number z
through and i'll find out
that any numerical
even complex numerical
multiple of an eigenvector
is also an eigenvector
ah
so
strictly speaking you should talk about
eigendirections
the set of vectors
including
or
not worrying about their length so to speak
but in any case this is the direction of
this is the definition of
an eigenvector
alright some matrices have eigenvectors
other matrices don't have eigenvectors
there is something important about
Hermitian matrices
or Hermitian operators
Hermitian operators not only have eigenvectors
they have a complete set of eigenvectors
complete means
that there are enough of them
to expand any vector and even better
they have
an orthonormal family
of eigenvectors
in general
the different eigenvectors will have different eigenvalues
as i said
but it will be true
that if a matrix is Hermitian
it has
and the dimensionality
of the space is n
there will be n mutually
orthogonal eigenvectors
in other words the eigenvectors
of Hermitian matrices
define a basis
I'm going to let you prove part of that theorem
it's a very easy theorem to prove
and I'm going to prove the other half of it
I'll prove the half
that says that
if you have two eigenvectors
with different eigenvalues
and that's the generic situation
that the eigenvalues are all different
if you have two eigenvectors
with different eigenvalues
we will prove that they are orthogonal
to each other
your general hypothesis
my job is to prove
that you won't run out of eigenvectors
until you have n of them
it's not hard
in any case it's true
so let's prove
that if we have two eigenvectors
m is a Hermitian
m is Hermitian
m equals a Hermitian matrix
I use matrix and operator synonymously
which means
that m equals m dagger
okay let's suppose
that m is Hermitian
and it has an eigenvalue lambda i
the first observation
is that the eigenvalues
of Hermitian matrices are real
that even comes before what I said previously
if there is an eigenvalue
it is real
okay how do we prove that it's real
let's prove that it's real
well
let's take this equation
and flip it over into a
bra equation
to flip it over into a bra equation
I flip i
I take m and I replace it by
m dagger
well that's not going to do much
because m is equal to m dagger
and on the right hand side
I flip i
and what do I do with lambda
in general
complex conjugate
lambda i
so far we haven't proved that it's real
every time you flip
from bras to kets you have to
complex conjugate all the numbers that are there
alright but now
assumption
m is Hermitian so it's equal to it's own
Hermitian conjugate
and now we have this equation
now let's take the inner product
of both of these equations
with i
in the upper equation
we're going to take the inner product
on the left with i
and what does that give us
that gives us i i
times lambda i
let's do the same thing over here
except now
we have a product
multiplying on the right
this and this are obviously the same
m with i on the left
and i on the right
is the same as this
but this is not obviously the same
not unless
lambda is equal to lambda star
i i here is the same as i i here
that cancels out
and this is the same as
and therefore we come to the conclusion
that if a matrix is Hermitian
if it's equal to it's own Hermitian conjugate
then it's eigenvalues
are equal to their own complex
conjugates and they are real
eigenvalues of Hermitian matrices
are real
that's the first step
now let's prove that if we have
two different eigenvalues
the corresponding eigenvectors
must be orthogonal
now remember what orthogonal means from a matrix
from a physical point of view
it means physically distinct
that there's an experiment
that you can do to distinguish
the two of them unambiguously
that's what orthogonality means from
a physical point of view
let's prove
that the eigenvectors
of m with different eigenvalue
are orthogonal
different eigenvalue
physically distinguishable
you should keep that in your head
okay so here we are
let's start with m on the left
m on i
equals lambda i i
and m on j
equals lambda j j
two different eigenvectors
i and j
first thing we'll do
is turn this one over
and turn it into a ket equation
ah a bra
it is a ket equation
we'll take this one
and turn it into a bra equation
so that looks like this
j m dagger
but m dagger is the same as m
equals the real
number lambda j
eigenvalues of permission matrices
are real
times j
now
here we have
two equations
what can you do to them
so that we can
relate them
what we can do with them to relate them
is to multiply this one by j on the left
and this one by i on the right
and we will get the same expression
on the left hand side of the equation
so let's do that
j
i
what we have on the left
is the same
on the upper and lower equations
what we have on the right
is not necessarily the same
so let's require
that it's the same
requiring that it's the same says that
lambda i minus
lambda j
times the inner product
of j with i
must equal zero
I've just written
I've just written that this
is equal to this
and then transposed
so lambda i minus lambda j
times the inner product of j i
equals zero
well
if the product of two things
and I have two things
lambda i minus lambda j
and the inner product of j i with j
if the product of two things is zero
it says unambiguously
at least one of them is zero
it usually says one of them is zero
okay
the inner product of i and j
may or may not be zero
but let's take the case where we know
that the eigenvectors correspond
to different values of the eigenvectors
sorry that the eigenvalues are different
that's what I'm interested in
I'm interested in eigenvectors
corresponding to different values
of the eigenvalue
so by assumption
lambda i is not equal to
lambda j
the conclusion is
that the inner product of i
with j must be equal to zero
so what does that mean
that means
that i and j are orthogonal
so we now have a theorem
the eigenvectors
of Hermitian matrices
with different eigenvalue
are orthogonal
let's just take the generic case
where all of the eigenvalues
are different
we can come back to what happens
when some of them may be the same
it's not important right now
if all the eigenvalues
happen to be different
than each other
then all the eigenvectors
are mutually orthogonal to each other
if there are enough of them
and your job is to prove
there's enough of them
they form a basis
in other words this collection of things
called i and j here
is a special case of a kind of basis
which we labeled with small i and j
but it's the basis of eigenvectors
it's the basis of eigenvectors
of the Hermitian operator
as I said
Hermitian operators
will be identified with observable quantities
and to say that eigenvectors
are orthogonal
has something or other to do
with physical differences
that are measurable
unambiguously between those
states of the system
okay,
we are now
prepared to state
the principles of quantum mechanics
we have enough
mathematical
information
we have enough mathematical
formalism
to state
the entire show
we can put on the blackboard now
what quantum mechanics is
and what it says
and what the rules are
or what the correspondences are
what the mathematical
sorry
what the physical meaning
of these various things are
you won't get
you won't understand this the first time around
it will be foreign,
it will be peculiar
what is he talking about
of course we'll work it out in examples
and we'll see how the ideas work
so don't get disturbed
if what I throw at you now
sounds a little bit
meaningless
that's okay
by the time we're finished with some examples
it should be clear how we use this
alright,
first of all
there are measurable quantities
the result of a measurement is always a real number
it takes
at least two measurements
and somehow two compatible measurements
two measurements that can both be performed simultaneously
to measure a complex number
alright
the basic ingredients
and basic measurables
are real numbers
that's what comes out of your detector
you can measure two of them
if you can measure two of them
if it's possible to simultaneously measure two things
and put them together into a complex number
but it really is just two measurements
so each measurement,
each thing that you measure
has a real
result associated with it
the physical measurables
they're called observables
in quantum mechanics they're called observables
the things that you can measure
the observables
are identified with
Hermitian matrices
or Hermitian operators
observables,
whoops not q
where did I get q from
I won't write equals
are represented by
we'll just put an arrow
are represented by Hermitian
linear of course operators
first statement
let's just think in
studying the spin
in a
in a rough and loose way
we sort of identified
some observables
the observables that we identified
were the components of the spin
the observables that we could identify
were associated with our apparatus
point your apparatus in some direction
and measure the spin along those directions
we said
we called,
if we measured the spin along
the z-axis,
we called it sigma z
we can measure it
or we could turn
our apparatus on its side
and measure sigma x
or we can turn
our apparatus
from the x-axis
to the y-axis and measure sigma y
we talked about
those things
we didn't talk about sigma's being
Hermitian operators
in fact we didn't talk
about them being operators at all
but we did talk
about measuring them
these will become Hermitian operators
sometime
alright,
next
the possible values
that a given observable can take on
what are they for sigma z
what are the possible
plus one and minus one
right?
the possible observable
values
measured in an experiment
those observable
values are
the eigenvalues
they're real
because the matrices are Hermitian
the eigenvectors,
what about the eigenvectors
the eigenvectors correspond to states
states,
vectors
the eigenvectors
are the states in which the corresponding
quantities are
definite,
in other words
in which the measurement of them is unambiguous
oh well let's
let's follow
through on this here a little bit
for all three of these observables
the eigenvalues had better be
plus or minus one
ok now
let's come to the eigenvectors
the eigenvectors
for example,
the eigenvector
with a given eigenvalue
is a state of the system where if you measure
that particular observable
you will definitely get
the eigenvalue
associated with that eigenvector
so the eigenvectors
those are
I think I have it backwards
we should put eigenvectors on this side
and on the left
side the physical meaning of them
the physical meaning
is states
in which
observable
has unambiguous
unambiguous
result
example
we talked
for example
about the states
up and down
those are states
in which sigma z
had definite values
when you're up,
sigma z is
definitely one,
when you're down
sigma z is definitely minus one
any other vector
sigma z is statistically
either plus or minus one
but with a randomness
so
up and down
must be the eigenvectors of sigma z
left and right
were the states
in which sigma x
was unambiguously either plus one or minus one
so left and right
must be the eigenvectors
of sigma x
whatever sigma x is
we're going to try to
figure out what sigma x is
knowing its eigenvalues
and its eigenvectors
and
what was the other three,
the other two called
in and out I think
in and out
the eigenvectors of sigma y
so we have three
connections
and now a fourth connection
given a general state
not an eigenvector
given a general state a
somebody made an electron
or
a system of some sort
and left it in the state a
then we can talk about what is
the probability
that we measure the eigenvalues
of n
at different values
there may be several different eigenvalues
in this case they would be
plus one and minus one but more generally
thousand eigenvalues
million eigenvalues
whatever the number is
labeled
by the
label i
what is the probability
that when you measure
m you get
lambda i
that's the last piece of
thing here so on the left hand
side we put probability
physical meaning
probability
and I'll write it just as the probability
to measure i
no to measure lambda i
I'm sorry to measure lambda i
that there is a
the result of the experiment comes out
a particular eigenvalue
of the observable
m whatever m is
that
is related
not related to it's
essentially equal to
two pieces comes in two steps
first you calculate if you have
the vector a
the vector which you start that's the state of the
system you take it's inner
product
with the eigenvector i
the projection
of a onto i
the component of a in the i
direction now that in general
is a complex number that
is not the probability
you multiply it by its own
complex conjugate to get a real
positive number and that
is the probability
we can multiply this by its complex
conjugate or we can just write it
ia
this ia
and ai are complex
conjugates of each other
we can also write this as the absolute
value of ia squared
the individual components
before we square them are called
amplitudes they are called probability
amplitudes
probability amplitudes are things
which you multiply by their complex
conjugates to find probabilities
they are real they are positive
and
that's the fourth
the fourth postulate
of quantum mechanics
now they are not all independent
i use them because
because they are reasonably
intuitive in fact
you can probably
get rid of at least
two of them and prove them from
the others but we don't need to do that
this is a good starting
point
and these
are the basic four postulates of
quantum mechanics
the other postulate is that
when you measure a quantity
you prepare the system
in a state of definite
value of that quantity i won't bother
writing that down when you measure
something you are in effect
pushing it into
a state of definite value
of that quantity depending on what the
outcome of your experiment is
if your outcome measures
some particular
if the outcome of an experiment is some particular
eigenvalue
that means you push the system
into the state into the eigenstate
of that quantity with that eigenvalue
i won't write that down
it takes too many words to write it down
what's under the p
the probability
right here
yeah
next to the p what is that
i can't read your handwriting
prob
it's probably probable
probably probability
yeah
this reads the probability of measuring
lambda
oh it is lambda i
lambda i the probability of measuring
lambda i
is the square
of the inner product
of a with i
it's if you like
it's the projection
of a onto the i'th direction
or the component of a in the i'th direction
now there's an implication here
there's an implication here
about the nature of
state vectors
coming from the assumption
that total probabilities
are equal to one
normalize them
they have to be normalized
yeah let's work that out
if you want the total probability
to add up to one
then you want
the sums of all these objects
when you sum over i
over the various possible values
of
that you can measure
you want that to equal one
so you want the sum over i
for any allowable
state a
we want
the sum
of a
i
a
to equal one
now i is a basis
and if you go up to the top equation
there
you have equations
which tell you how to deal
with exactly this combination
what is the
sum over i of
i i a
it's just a
so what this says
is that the inner product of a with itself
should equal one
the total length of a should be equal to one
that's not too surprising that that's what this says
this says the sums of the
squares of the components of a
add up to one
for ordinary vectors that would just say
the length of the vector was one
and that's what this says
the length of a is equal to one
it's equivalent in terms of the alphas
we got rid of the alphas are up there also
it's equivalent to the sum of
alpha star i
alpha i
alpha i equals one
well i capital i
and so there is
one
combination of the alphas
this is one real equation
it's not a complex equation it's a real equation
and that means there's one real combination
of the alphas which has to be constrained
alphas are
not completely free
or the alphas are not completely free
roughly speaking the sums of their squares
or the sums of them times a complex conjugate
has to add up to one
so that means there's less
fewer independent quantities
than you thought
there is another fact
which we have not gotten to yet
we will get to it
you can sort of see it from here
all properties
probabilities any probability
that you ever may want to measure
or that you ever may want to
to calculate
or compare with experiment
is always connected
with a real quantity like this
the collection
of such real quantities
is invariant
under a certain operation
the operation is
multiplying the state vector by a phase
everybody know what it means to
multiply a number of things like that
by a phase
you multiply it by an e to the i theta
if you multiply
all the components of a
by the same overall
phase
then every probability is unchanged
every probability
is unchanged
ah
even if you rotate
bases it's unchanged
so physical quantities
don't respond to a change of
a phase
that means there are two fewer
degrees of freedom
two fewer
parameters
in the specification of a state
than the collection
of complex numbers
that would define a vector in the abstract space
two
one is the phase the overall phase
and the other is the magnitude of it
we'll come back to that
okay that's taken us a long way
you're probably
saturated but I'm not
so we're going to continue
I'm on a high
questions
yeah
some probability also has to be
negative
yeah yeah that's right so these are always positive
thing times its complex conjugate is always positive
is the evolution
part of it
is the what
the evolution part
we haven't gotten to that yet
how things change with time
yeah
no we're at the level now
of where we were in classical physics
when we just said the state of a system
is just a point in a
among a set of things
that's about where we are
that's how far we've gotten
we've not talked about how things change
in particular how the states of systems change
we'll come to that
so
back in the beginning when we had
this example of
you know measuring these cubed measures
and you had
you had the apparatus at an angle
and you got the
cosine of theta
right so
we have to do it
ok well
ok I guess my question was
we somehow got the idea that cosine of theta
is going to be the average of your measurements
should it be cosine squared
no
I see why
I see where you're going but
I'm going to do it
can you say that last
posture one more time
so I can get more
when you measure something you push it into the state
you are measuring
no when you measure something
you get a result
the result is statistically
determined
meaning to say that you may get one result
you may get another result but once you get that
result
then you know what state
the system is in
the eigenstate
of the quantity that you measured
with the eigenvalue
that came up on your
detector
remember
when we had our apparatus
and we measured
sigma z
we said that not only measures
sigma z but it prepares the
system in a state of definite
sigma z it leaves it
over in a state in which
sigma z is definite for the next
measurement that means it leaves
it in an eigenstate of
sigma z
okay
let's see if we can apply this
to
to the spin system
you get a very general
formulation
and now we want to try
it out and see how it works
alright
so I want to start with the
three observables sigma x
sigma y and sigma z and see what I can
learn about them
first of all sigma z
now let's
start
in the basis
associated with
the measurement of the spin along
the z axis let's take that as
the appropriate basis
sigma z
has two eigenvectors by
from the experiments that we talked
about we would have learned
that we done the experiment that sigma z
has two eigenvalues
and two eigenvectors
the two eigenvectors we've
called up and down and they're
associated with sigma z equals plus one
and minus one those
must be the eigenvectors of sigma z
and eigenvalues and
so we can immediately say sigma z
times up
is equal to up
plus one times up
why
because the measured value
when we measure sigma z
is going to be plus one
that's the eigenvalue
and up is the eigenvector
because in the up state
sigma z is definite
what about sigma z on the down state
what should I write there
is sigma z definite
in the down state
no
sigma z is definite
yes it's always minus one
it's going to be minus one
and that means the eigenvalue is minus one
times down
it's not sigma z times down equals up
that wouldn't be an eigenvector
an eigenvector has the property that when the
operator acts on it
it gives the same direction back
times the eigenvalue
so here is what we know
about
sigma z
okay let's see if we can
compute its matrix elements
and exhibit it as a matrix
but when I say exhibit it as a matrix
I have picked
I must pick a basis
I'm going to pick the basis
up and down
first of all
one thing
up and down are orthogonal to each other
they must be according to these
principles because
if sigma z is an observable
it corresponds to a Hermitian matrix
if there are two different
eigenvalues
the eigenvectors must be orthogonal
for a Hermitian matrix
and so up and down
first of all learn that up and down
are orthogonal
that's one fact
it doesn't matter whether we write up down
or down up
we can write it in the opposite order
let's see if we can compute the matrix elements
the matrix elements are just the array
that we get
when we consider
the four possibilities
two by two matrices
and the four possibilities
are going to be
first of all we take the inner product
of this back with up
that will be the up up matrix element
or the one one matrix element
what is that going to be
to find
I'm not sure I want to
let's do it over here
let's calculate up
sigma z up
that's equal
sigma z acts to the right
to give us up
plus one
times up
just the inner product of up
with itself
and since up is a basis vector
it's normalized
and this is just equal to one
its magnitude is equal to one
I can choose it to be equal to one
it's positive
yeah it's positive
it's real
and it's just plain one
so up here in the up up
or the one one place
it's just one
now let's
what about the off diagonal element
the off diagonal element
that's an off diagonal element there
that's going to be equal
to the inner product of down with up
what's that
zero over here
so
I would get exactly the same thing
if I put down over here
and up over here
then I would use this equation over here
let sigma z act on down
and then take its overlap with up
and I would get zero again
and the last one
is down sigma z down
what is that
well you go over to here
sigma z times down is minus down
so this is just equal to minus
down down
and what's that
minus one
so this is the matrix
that's associated with sigma z
when it acts on a vector on a column vector
in particular when it acts
what is the column vector that's associated with up
it's just a one in the
top and a zero in the bottom
alright so let's just try this
one zero
what do we get
one times one is one
zero times zero is zero
we just get the same vector back
that's good
same thing
it's guaranteed that we'll get the right
that the eigenvectors are
what they're supposed to be
namely just up and down
and that the eigenvalues are plus one and minus one
in the right way
alright so we found one of
the sigma matrices
sigma z
is of course
well not of course
they're called the Pauli matrices
sigma x,
sigma y,
and sigma z
let's see what we can find out about
sigma x
now
I'm using
if I use the x basis
if I use the basis of left and right
of course I would just find exactly the same thing
but I want to stick with the up down basis
I want to stick with the up down basis
but
find out what the matrix elements
of sigma x are
now what is the property of sigma x
the property of sigma x
is that its eigenvectors
are left and right
so for example
sigma x on right
that equals right
and what about sigma x on left
equals minus left
those are the two possible values
that sigma x can take on
left and right
are the eigenvectors
in other words the states
in which sigma x has definite values
plus one and minus one
and this is what I know about sigma x
but I want to find its matrix elements
in the up down basis
so what I really want then
let's come over to here
and see if we can compute
in the same basis
what did I do with the Pauli matrix
did I erase it
I worked so hard to get it
sigma z is equal to
one minus one zero zero
now we want to try to get sigma x
so the first step is
erase the blackboard
and let's start
one by one
there are four matrix elements
let's do them one by one
up down basis
up sigma x up
now what we have to know
is that up
is equal to left plus right
over the square root of two
you remember that
we originally defined
left and right
to be up plus or minus down
over the square root of two
but then we can solve
for up and down in terms of left and right
down
plus or minus down
is
left
sorry it's right minus left
with the notation we had last time
it was down
no sorry it's right
minus left
over root two
so all we have to do is plug them in
on the left here we have
left
you know I'm going to
use notation and just write
this as
left plus right over square root of two
this is a meaningless
symbol
but I think you know what I mean
I mean the bra vector
left plus the bra vector right
over the square root of two
but too many vertical strokes and I get confused
so let's just write it as left plus right
over the square root of two
sigma x
left plus right
over square root of two
first of all
I can take out this
is the what is this thing
this is sigma x
up up there it is it's the up up
entry
one that goes up in here
alright first of all there's a factor
of two that I can take out
square root of two from here and
a square root of two from here
that's altogether one half
and now let's look at this
what happens when sigma x hits
left
it gives back left
it gives back left except with a minus sign
what happens when sigma x hits right
it gives back right
with a plus sign
so when sigma x
acts on this
what it winds up giving
you can take the sigma x away
and just remember what it does
it gives right minus left
instead of right minus left
it hits the vector
right and gives plus one
it hits the vector left and gives minus one
again these are not things to be numerically added
these are vectors
the right vector minus the left vector
and now all we have to do is
take the inner products
well the inner product of right
with right is what
one
the inner product of right with left
is
zero the inner product of left with right
is zero and the inner product
of left with left
minus one when you
account for this minus
the result is they cancel
alright
one minus one or equivalently
the inner product
of
well okay zero
so first of all there's a zero over here
that's the up up
matrix element
it's easy to get the down down matrix element
the down down matrix element
you would do exactly the same thing
except that you would start with
right minus left
sigma x
and then you would say
that when sigma x hits right
it's plus right
when it hits left it gives minus left
so when sigma x acts
it takes right minus left to right
plus left
and what's the inner product
of right plus left with right minus left
zero again
right with right is one
left with left is minus one
and the cross terms are just zero
so there's a zero over here
now
looks like all we're going to get is zeros
but that can't be right
so let's try
let's try up down
alright
we try up down
let's put up down there
up will be right plus left
we'll have sigma x
and then down is right minus left
what happens when sigma x hits right plus left
it makes right minus left
and now what's the inner product
the inner product of
right with right is one
the inner product of minus left with minus left
is also plus one
so they add
and again the cross terms
between right and left are zero
so we get two divided by two
which is one
we get a one up here
and
if we work it out
we'll get another one over here
alright so now we've got sigma y
let's just stop for a minute and
say what is it that we have
we have a pair of linear operators
or a pair of matrices
whose eigenvectors
are
this fellow's eigenvectors here
are up and down
this fellow's eigenvectors are right and left
they're exactly what we were talking about
on the previous blackboard
the
states in which the observables have
unambiguous results are the eigenvectors
that's where we are
now
the last one is sigma y
what do we know about sigma y
I'm not
in and out
are the eigenvectors
the one we just did is sigma x
you wrote sigma y
oh sigma x sorry
actually
I don't think I wrote sigma y
I think I just wrote sigma y
I just failed to cross the x
I think I don't know maybe I wrote sigma y
alright the next one is sigma y
and here I'm going to leave
some of the algebrates
this is very easy to you but let's see
what the rules are
oh
incidentally
no I think we're okay
we know the rules
ok so there was
in and out
I cannot remember which one was which
so I'm going to fake it
and if it comes out wrong it comes out wrong
um
I think in
was up
plus I think
times down
and out
was up
minus I times down
and I think I left out
factors of square root of two
incidentally you can check that
in and out are orthogonal to each other
ok there's in and out
can we find a matrix
which
in and out are eigenvectors
with eigenvalue
plus one and minus one
it's getting late
it's very easy
I will simply tell you what that matrix is.
It's unique.
If you know the eigenvectors and you know the eigenvalues,
it's unique.
One way of doing it
is to solve for up and
down in terms of in and out.
Once you've solved for up and
down in terms of in and out,
and you know how the
matrix acts on in and out,
you're finished.
The last one in the multiplet here,
now I am writing sigma y,
similar to this one,
but it's O minus I and I.
Alright,
so a little exercise.
You don't really need to go and prove this.
You can do a different thing.
You can take this matrix and show
that these are the eigenvectors of it.
Just show that these are the eigenvectors of it.
You take this matrix and show that it's eigenvectors.
What does that mean?
It means that its eigenvectors are
one I and one minus I.
The square root of two doesn't matter.
Eigenvectors are eigenvectors.
They don't care about the square root of two.
These are the three Pauli matrices
that represent the components of
a spin in different directions.
I think that's enough for tonight.
What I was going to do,
and I have in my notes,
was exactly this question.
What happens
if you have a component
of spin along an arbitrary direction?
Can we show,
using what we know,
that the prob-
We'll do this next time.
If we have a component
of spin along an arbitrary direction,
and we want to calculate,
using the principles,
we want to calculate what the probability is
for the measurement of sigma z in various,
either plus or minus,
we should be able to do it.
We have enough information.
I think it's probably more than
we can yet handle for tonight.
I think we did a lot for tonight.
Probably more than reasonable.
Am I wrong to say that the u's need
to be negative to make those two more positive?
Does one of the u's need to
be negative to make those two more positive?
No.
You know what you're missing?
You're missing that you have to complex conjugate.
If you want the inner product of in without,
you multiply one times one,
and then add i,
not times minus i,
but i times plus i.
Yeah.
The only way that somebody like
me knows so quickly what you're thinking
is having made the same mistake,
of course.
Sometime in the past.
Okay.
All right,
we're finished for tonight,
I think,
unless there's questions.
For more,
please visit us at stanford.edu.