Stanford University.
All right,
we started to explore entanglement.
I had actually started to
think about doing Bell's Theorem tonight,
but I decided not to do it yet.
It's a complicated story,
the Bell's Theorem.
It's very lovely,
but more important than the
theorem itself is what it says.
And so I want to get as
much as possible tonight to what it says,
and what entanglement has to tell
us about the nature of systems.
Sometimes people say the nature of reality.
I don't like the word reality.
I think it's misleading.
Okay.
In looking on the Internet at the
messages you guys send back and forth,
they're very interesting,
and many of them have
some very interesting points in them.
There's a terminology which I would discourage,
at least unless you know
what it means with greater precision,
and I've seen this all over the place.
People say entanglement.
Entanglement is when two quantum systems share a state.
I've never understood what that means,
to share a state.
Quantum systems have states.
If they're composite quantum systems,
they have states.
You can say that a pair of quantum systems,
when they make a given quantum system,
share a state,
if you like,
but it just means the state of the composite system.
The quantum system is a state of the composite system.
The important idea about entanglement is not
so much that systems share a state,
that they always do,
it's the important thing is that they
are not described by a product state,
a product state being a state in
which the wave function of the system,
and we'll talk about wave functions.
Have we talked about wave functions very much?
I don't think we have.
Let's begin by talking about wave functions,
and then I want to move on
to the concept of a density matrix.
This will make it much easier
for us to think about entanglement.
First of all,
the notion of a wave function.
A wave function may or may
not have anything to do with waves.
The concept grew historically out
of the quantum mechanics of particles
and the probability description of them in terms of waves,
but the logical concept of a wave function is
one that you can apply to any quantum system,
and in general it doesn't have to
do with wave motion of any particular kind.
The basic idea of a wave function is the following.
You have a quantum state.
Let's call the quantum state...
Ah,
capital Psi.
I'll use the letter capital Psi to
denote a generic quantum state of a system.
I think previously I've been using As and Bs,
but I'm going to start using Psi as
a generic quantum state for pretty much any system.
And also I have a basis system.
The basis system is typically a
system of a set of two.
It's typically labeled by a
collection of eigenvalues of something.
It might be labeled by one or more variables.
If there are several commuting operators in a system,
you can specify simultaneously the
eigenvalues of more than one thing,
and in many cases you'll want to do that,
and the basis vectors in those cases
are labeled by a collection of observables,
or a collection of
eigenvalues of perhaps several quantities.
I'll give you an example.
If you're talking about the motion of a particle,
then the x and y and z
coordinates of the particle are commuting variables.
The things that don't commute are the
components of momentum with the components of position.
I know we haven't done this yet,
but...
On the other hand,
the three components of position
all commute with each other.
That means they can be specified simultaneously.
A useful basis for studying
the quantum mechanics of a particle
is a basis which is labeled
by the three coordinates of the particle.
I'll wait for...
Yeah,
I'll give her a hand.
All right,
so we have a basis,
and the basis is labeled by a collection of eigenvalues.
Let's label them...
I just don't have a decent pen.
All right,
a,
b,
c,
however many commuting variables there are
that need to be specified
in order to specify a system.
And the inner product of the basis
vector with the state of the system itself
is called the wave function.
In fact,
we can write that psi,
since these objects here form a basis,
we can say that this is a sum.
I still don't have a decent pen.
Uh-oh.
Ah,
a little bit better.
A sum over the basis vectors,
which means a sum over this collection of eigenvalues.
a,
b,
dot,
of the inner product of the basis vectors
with the state vector
times the basis vectors.
We've written this equation,
this kind of equation down before.
What it says is that the expansion coefficients
that you use to expand a vector in basis vectors
are just the inner products of
the vector with the basis vectors.
This object is called the wave function,
right here.
And it's a function of the a's,
b's,
and c's.
So let's give it a name.
Let's call it little psi of a,
b,
c,
and so forth.
It's called the wave function.
And it's defined in such a way
that the state vector psi
is equal to the sum over a,
over all the indices which
it takes to specify the basis,
times psi of a,
b,
and c,
and so forth.
Psi of a,
b,
and c.
Of the coordinates,
of the,
um,
what are the coordinates?
What are the coordinates of the vector?
if we're just talking about a single spin,
then a complete set of commuting variables
necessary to specify a vector
is,
for example,
just sigma z,
the z component of spin.
And then psi would just be
the probability amplitudes for the spin to
be up or the spin to be down.
It would be a function of one variable,
that variable would take on the values up and down.
If we had two spins,
then we would label a basis of
vectors with ups and downs for one
spin,
ups and downs for the other spin,
and it would take two labels to label a state
vector,
not just one.
The two labels would be
the labels of the two spins,
and that's all we're talking
about here.
Might take multiple labels to label a basis vector,
and if so,
just display them here,
and then by definition,
pure definition,
the wave function of the system,
you can think
of it two ways.
You can think of it as the set of coefficients,
the set of coefficients that you use to expand
an arbitrary vector in terms of the basis vectors,
or you can think of them as the inner
products.
Okay?
So you can think of the inner products
of the state vector with the basis vectors themselves.
That is called the wave function,
and Schrodinger's wave function is a special case of it,
which
we will not get to at the moment,
but it is a special case of it.
Question?
Okay,
so if you know the wave function of the system,
you know its state vector,
and
you can compute all sorts of things.
You can compute expectation values and all sorts of things.
Yeah?
This looks a little like
a Fourier transform in some basis.
Is a Fourier transform?
Yep.
It is a Fourier transform for
the case of position and momentum.
Yes.
Yeah.
So if you're going to do a Fourier transform,
you're going to have to do a Fourier transform.
But in that case,
you could go back and forth.
Well,
no.
The Fourier transform is going back
and forth between different basis sets.
Okay?
Here I've chosen a particular basis set.
Supposing I wanted to use a different basis,
instead of sigma z,
sigma x.
Then I would have to transform these wave functions somehow.
They look different in the x basis,
and that's the analog of Fourier transform.
Okay.
Now I want to introduce
a concept called the density matrix.
If we have just a single system,
this is the way we think
about the state of the system.
Oh,
let's talk about expectation values.
Let's talk about expectation values.
Supposing we have some observable.
Let's call it L.
Ah.
It's some observable.
And it has matrix elements.
What do matrix elements mean?
They mean,
if this is a basis vector,
I won't bother writing out multiple labels.
Let's just put one label
there to summarize all the labels.
And another label over here,
a prime.
These are called the matrix elements of the observable.
Okay.
The matrix elements of the observable,
the observable acts on a basis vector,
and then
you project it onto another basis vector.
And that's called L,
I suppose,
A prime A.
Just notation.
Okay.
Now supposing I want to calculate the expectation
value of L in a state whose wave function
is psi.
Let's see how we do that.
We take psi.
I'm going to,
as I said,
I'm just going to restrict
myself to a single A here,
but the
same thing would hold if there were multiples.
Okay.
So I'm going to take the multiple As.
All right.
So what do we do?
We take the state vector on the left,
the ket vector.
The ket vector,
maybe we should write out the ket vector here.
Sorry,
the bra vector.
The bra vector,
this is the ket vector.
The bra vector is the sum over A and B.
But you know,
I want to use different indices
here.
I want to call them A prime and B prime.
They're being summed over,
so it doesn't matter what I call them.
I just don't want to confuse them with these.
And then we're going to have bra vector.
So I'm going to call them bra vectors,
ABC or times,
and then I put psi here,
psi star.
So exactly the same kind
of expression for the bra vector,
except complex conjugated
coefficients.
Good.
Now let's calculate psi L.
That's the expectation value or the average
value of L in the quantum state psi.
And we do it just by plugging in.
The left bra vector here is
the sum of just a single index,
A prime,
psi of A
prime.
That constructs the bra vector.
The ket vector,
I will have to write another sum,
a sum over A of A prime.
So I'm going to write psi of A times A.
Summing on A turns this into the ket vector,
capital psi.
Summing over A prime turns this into the bra vector,
the corresponding bra vector.
And in between,
we sandwich L.
All right.
Now,
somebody please correct me.
What did I write wrong?
Psi star.
All right.
We take the psi's and the
psi star's out of the expression.
They're just numbers.
And so the whole thing is
the sum of A prime and A.
Psi star of A prime,
psi of A,
times the inner product or the sandwich,
A prime L A.
That's exactly the matrix element of L A.
So that's L between A and A prime.
So that's L,
which one is it?
A prime A,
I think.
And this reduces every expectation value to
a calculation in terms of wave functions,
a psi,
always a psi and always a psi star,
times a matrix element of
the observable that we're interested in.
All right.
So this is a basic formula.
For the expectation value of anything
that we might be interested in.
Okay.
Basically all of quantum mechanics is contained in there.
The expectation value of everything in the world,
that's just about everything we ever
may want to be interested in.
And so let's put this equation
over here and keep it over here.
Now,
supposing we have a composite system.
Composed of two subsystems.
Let's call them Alice's and Bob's subsystems.
All right.
Alice has control of one of them.
Bob has control of the other.
And maybe even there are times
when they don't have control of them.
But we just call them two subsystems,
Alice's and Bob's.
Then,
and in fact,
let's use A now to represent a
complete set of observables for Alice's subsystem.
Everything that Alice needs to know in order to specify a basis
for her subsystem and B are the set of variables for Bob's subsystem.
When we talk about spin,
I think we called Alice's
variable tau and Bob's variable sigma,
if I remember correctly.
But we just,
these are a complete set of things,
a complete set of variables for Alice.
And this is a complete set of variables for Bob.
Alice's states for her subsystem would look like this.
Bob's would look like that.
Maybe we want to use a different notation so
we don't wind up confusing the two vector spaces.
But then there's the composite vector space.
The composite vector space is the
vector space describing the composite system.
And that has a basis which
consists of an A and a B.
When A runs over all its values
and B runs over all its values,
we have a complete basis of the combined system.
Okay,
so now let's talk about
wave functions of the composite system.
Again,
we have a state vector.
The state vector psi is a state vector
in the composite in the tensor product space.
The space made by tensoring,
producting A's and B's together.
It has as its basis vectors a basis
vector from A and a basis vector from B.
And now I want to define in the
same way the notion of the basis vector.
It's the function of a composite wave function.
So what is it?
It's just the inner product
of psi with the basis vectors.
And what is it a function of?
It's now a function of two
sets of variables or two variables,
psi of A and B,
different B here.
This,
yeah,
okay,
here it is.
It's a function of the variables of the two subsystems.
Okay,
so that's the wave function.
Now we have notion of a
wave function of a composite system.
And let's talk about observables of a composite system.
The observables of a composite system,
first of all,
among those variables are the ones which
would describe the separate subsystems by themselves.
So let's suppose that L and M,
are two observables,
one of them having to do with Alice's subsystem,
Alice,
and the other one having to do with Bob's subsystem.
I could call them L
sub A and L sub B,
but I won't.
I'll call them L and M.
How do we represent observables acting
on the composite space of states?
The answer is simple.
The operators of states,
associated with Alice's subsystem,
act on Alice's piece of the state vector,
and leave Bob's piece of the state vector unchanged.
That's what we did when we did spins.
We said Bob's sigma matrices acted
on his half of the wave function,
or his half of the basis vectors,
and were completely passive,
or Alice's piece of the state vector was completely passive,
just bypassed by Alice's.
So what that says,
what that says,
is that Alice's observables are matrices,
they're matrices that can be written
as L of A prime B prime,
just like L here,
has a prime variable and an unprime variable,
but now the single index is replaced by two indices,
an A and B.
What does this correspond to?
This corresponds to the sandwich,
A prime B prime L A B,
whatever A,
whatever this stands for.
But L only belongs to Alice's space of states,
only belongs to Alice's system.
So the question is,
what then do we say about this matrix here,
to set,
to interpret,
to indicate that it has no effect on Bob's variables?
The answer is simple.
We make it proportional
to the identity matrix in Bob's variables.
The identity operator,
the identity operator in a space
is the operator whose matrix elements
are the Kronecker delta symbol.
That's the identity operator.
And the identity operator on a subsystem
does nothing to that subsystem.
The identity operator simply gives the same vector back.
In other words,
if you apply the identity operator,
it does nothing.
But now what we're doing is applying the identity operator
on Bob's half of the system,
but the observable that's supposed to be associated
with Alice's half of the subsystem
is represented by the same matrix,
that she would have used
had she not even known about Bob.
Had she not even known about Bob,
she would have used the matrix A,
L,
A prime and A,
to describe her observable.
How does she describe it in the bigger Hilbert space?
She says it does nothing to Bob's variables,
and so it's just the identity matrix
in Bob's half of the space.
That's Alice's variables.
We could say the same thing about Bob's.
M of A prime and
B prime and A and B
is just equal to the Kronecker delta
of Alice's variables
times the matrix that Bob would have used
to describe the subsystem,
had he not known anything about Alice.
Okay.
Let's prove
some things about the setup here.
First of all,
let's calculate expectation values
of Alice's variables in a product state.
A product state is one in which the two systems
are not entangled with each other.
And let's see what we get.
What would you expect to get
if you had an unentangled state
describing Alice's and Bob's subsystems,
and you considered the expectation value
of Alice's variable?
You'd get exactly what you would have gotten
had Bob not been there altogether.
So let's check that out.
What do I mean,
first of all,
by a product state?
I explained what a product state was,
but now let me explain what a product state is
in the language of wave functions.
It's very simple.
It means that the wave function is a product
of two wave functions,
one for Alice and one for Bob.
That's all it means.
A product state is one whose wave function
psi of a and b,
Alice's and Bob's variables,
is just a product.
So let's see,
how shall we denote that?
Let's call it,
um,
well,
let's just call it psi Alice of a
and phi Bob of b.
It factorizes.
It's a product of two functions.
It's a function of two variables,
but it's a product of two functions,
each of one variable.
It's pretty clear that if it factorizes like this,
then Alice can think of this as the wave function
for her subsystem,
and Bob thinks of this
as the wave function for his subsystem.
Okay,
let's calculate now Alice's expectation value of L
if this happens to be the wave function.
So what do we do?
We first take psi,
we're going to make a sandwich.
We're going to make a sandwich
with a psi star on one side,
a psi on the other side,
and L in between.
All right,
so psi star,
that's psi star of Alice of a,
a prime,
phi star,
Bob,
Alice,
of b prime.
This is,
where do we write it?
Here.
That's the complex conjugate of the wave function
as a function of a prime and b prime.
What next?
Next,
we put into the sandwich L of a prime,
b prime,
a and b.
It's a matrix.
One entry here,
one entry here.
But it's simple.
It's just L of a prime and a
times delta b,
b prime.
And then we close it up
with the other half of the sandwich,
which is this up here,
psi a of a,
phi b of b.
And we sum.
As always,
we sum over everything in sight.
a prime a,
b prime b.
That's the rule for calculating an expectation value.
So what do we get?
First of all,
the delta b,
b prime,
that tells us to set b prime equal to b.
So let's do that.
First off,
let's do that.
I'll just erase.
Set b prime equal to b.
I'll let you write down your notes if you want.
Set b prime equal to
b and remove the Kronecker delta.
Now b is equal to b prime.
Now notice,
the only thing that depends on b
is phi star b and phi b.
What?
The sum over b prime was done
when I set b equal to b prime.
And now there's a sum over b
of phi star phi.
What does that give?
One.
Under the assumption,
of course,
that Bob's wave function is normalized.
Under the assumption that Bob's half
of the wave function is normalized,
so that his total probability for his,
all his measurements he could do is one,
then sum over b of phi star of
b times phi of b is just one.
And what does the whole thing reduce to?
The whole thing reduces to exactly what's up there.
We can remove the phis.
Take them out.
Put them down here.
That sum is just one.
And the rest of it is just exactly what's up
on the top of the blackboard there.
In other words,
in a product state,
the expectation value of any of Alice's operators
are exactly the same as if Bob wasn't there.
And it doesn't matter what Bob's wave function is
as long as it's a product.
What about one of Bob's expectation values?
What would happen if we
stuck a Bob operator in there?
Well then,
instead of the Kronecker delta of b's,
let's go back.
We have b and b prime.
b and b prime.
Yeah,
b prime over here.
And instead of l and a prime,
we would have m of b and b prime
delta a a prime.
And now,
we would set a prime equal to a.
And we would get a sum
that would again give us one.
And we would get the same,
we would get basically the same
thing that I wrote up here.
Bob.
Except it would be
Bob's wave function phi star
Bob of b prime.
m of b prime b.
times phi Bob of b.
Which is exactly what Bob would have done
had he not known about Alice.
So,
product states are really just that.
They're states in which one party
just doesn't know about the other.
There's no correlation.
There's no information in one of them about the other.
Okay.
We can say a little bit more about correlation.
Let's suppose now that we were interested
in the product of an
Alice variable and a Bob variable.
We're interested in the expectation value of l times m.
Let's see what we get.
Expectation in the product state.
Strictly product states for the moment.
We go back up to here.
And now,
instead of writing
m b
Is this b b prime?
This should be b b prime.
Instead of delta of a and a prime
if we're taking the product of l and m
then
what do I put here?
l.
If I'm interested in the
operator which represents the product
of two variables
one for Alice and one for Bob
instead of putting the unit operator over here for Alice
I will simply put in
Alice's operator.
Not m,
Alice.
l.
Now this just factorizes.
Let's look at all the a-dependents.
Here's a-dependents.
That factorizes.
That's completely separate from the b-dependents.
I could take everything with a b-dependents
and put it on one side.
Everything with an a-dependents and
put it on the other side.
And do the a and b summations independently.
Can you see that?
That,
let's write it out.
It's sum of a prime a b prime b
of psi Alice star
of a prime l a a prime
psi Alice of a
all times
phi Bob star
of b prime
m of b b prime
and
phi of b.
The sums can be done
quite independently.
We can put the sum over here.
Same thing.
I haven't changed it.
We're summing over everything.
b's and a's.
And we see that what
we get is just the product.
We get the product of the expectation value of l
times the expectation value of m.
Not surprising.
If we have a product state
and Alice does her measurement
and Bob does his measurement
and we then come together and compare the measurements
and ask what was the product of the measurements,
the expectation value will just be the product.
The expectation value of the product operator
will be the product of expectation values.
And we can write this this way.
Let's write it
in a form
It says for product states,
for product,
what's called product states,
the expectation value of the product operator
is the expectation value of l and times m.
Now remember,
l belongs to Alice,
m belongs to Bob,
and they operate in different halves of the system.
The expectation value of l times m
is just the expectation value of l
times the expectation value of m.
Now,
is this something that we expect
to always be true for every state?
That the expectation value,
in fact,
even in classical probability theory,
if we have a probability distribution
for two variables,
in general,
is it true
that the average of the product
is the product of the average?
Only if the variables are independent.
Which means what in terms of the probability distribution?
Exactly what you've written there.
It means that it factorizes.
It means that the probability distribution
is a product of two probability distributions.
Right.
Well,
what if it's not true?
What if the probability distribution
does not factorize?
Then,
this quantity here,
the difference between the average of l times m
and the product of averages of l and m
is called the correlation between l and m.
It's called a correlation,
and it is a measure of how much
these variables are correlated.
We'll do,
we'll see some examples.
This is called the correlation,
and whenever the correlation,
whenever there is anything in the system,
an Alice variable and a Bob variable,
whose correlation is not zero,
that's an indication of entanglement.
If you can find any pair of variables,
one of Alice's and one of Bob's,
such that the average of the product
is not the product of the averages,
then you're experiencing entanglement.
I think we did an example last time.
We took what I call the singlet state,
which was up,
down,
minus down,
up,
over the square root of two.
This is psi,
and this is not a product state.
And in this state,
we took the expectation value
of Bob's variable,
sigma z.
We took the expectation value of Alice's variable,
which I think was tau z.
Do you remember what these were?
What's the average value of Bob's variable?
Let's say the first entrance here,
the first entry stands for Bob.
Here's Bob.
Bob.
Here's Alice.
What would you guess in this state
the average of sigma z is?
Not the state,
but the combined state.
No.
Zero.
Why is it zero?
Because it has as much probability
of being up as being down.
It has probability one half to be
up and one half to be down.
So the average of Bob's variable is zero.
I think we worked that out last time.
What about Alice's variable?
It's also up as much as it's down.
Okay?
It's also expectation value of zero.
What about...
All right,
so first step.
Both of these are zero in this case.
What about the product?
What about the product of sigma z and tau z?
What's its average value?
Well,
we worked it out last time.
We got an answer.
Anybody remember the answer?
Minus one.
But you can just look at this thing,
and you can say in both vectors here,
the spins are opposite.
So in either case here,
the product of the spins is minus one.
It's pretty clear that the product
of the spins is minus one.
And you can see that this whole
thing is an eigenvector of the product,
because on either vector here,
the product is minus one.
Act with sigma z.
Act with sigma z,
you'll get...
You know what will happen.
So it'll just change sign.
So yes,
this has...
The product of the sigma z is equal to one.
Minus one,
excuse me.
So they're entangled.
In this case,
they're what I'll call maximally entangled.
They're very entangled.
If you can find any pair of variables
which are correlated in this form,
the quantum state is entangled.
Do you remember now,
here it's completely obvious
that the average of sigma z is zero
for just the reasons that I said.
Sigma z and tau z.
Up appears as much as down for Bob,
and down appears as much as up for Alice.
And so it's very obvious.
So it's clear the average is zero.
What about the average of sigma x?
Do you remember?
It's zero.
But that's not obvious,
is it?
That's not obvious.
But we did it last time.
Go back to your notes,
and you'll discover that not only
is the expectation value of sigma z zero,
but sigma x is also equal to zero.
The average.
On the other hand,
you'll also find that the product
of Bob's sigma x and Alice's tau x
is again equal to minus one.
So,
the sigma z's and the tau z's are correlated.
The sigma x's and the tau x's are correlated.
And what about y?
Same thing.
Same exact thing.
You can work that out.
We know what these operators do.
You can apply them to the states
and calculate what their expectation values are.
So,
this state is a highly entangled
or a highly correlated state.
Being correlated and being entangled
are basically the same idea.
Question?
Yeah.
In the general case,
if you put the l's and the m's around,
say you put two of each other,
the new order is,
you know,
put the l's and the m's,
lm minus bracket L,
bracket equals ml minus,
is that the right way?
No.
You know what I'm saying?
They just put the l's and the m's.
Oh,
yeah.
That's equal,
right?
Yeah,
sure.
Mm-hmm.
All right.
There's a point there,
which I may not have mentioned.
All operators associated with one system
commute with all operators associated with the other system,
so it doesn't matter in which order you write them.
That's independent of whether the system is entangled.
It doesn't matter which order you write them.
Excuse me.
Yeah.
I guess I'm missing something.
When you wrote that down,
you showed us that if you have a product state
where l is a state in Alice's and M's...
Yeah.
Then this is equal to zero.
Then that's equal to zero.
Mm-hmm.
Yeah.
What does lm mean?
I mean,
you've got it written up there.
Isn't that a product state?
This?
No.
The state is...
These are the states.
These are the observables.
Right.
Doesn't that lm be a product state?
No.
L's and m's are not states.
Yeah.
There are si's in here.
Okay.
This is a statement about the state vectors.
Oh.
Okay.
Right.
One other point is worth just noticing.
When I say things are correlated,
that the spins are correlated,
correlated,
I mean it.
What I mean is that you
can learn something about one variable
by looking at the other.
If you know that this is the state,
if you happen to know that
this is the state,
then if you know Bob's,
if you measure Bob's variable,
and you find
out that it's up,
then in that component of the state,
which is the only one that's left
after you measure Bob,
Alice is down.
In a product state,
you learn nothing about one
system by measuring anything about the other.
In a highly entangled state,
you learn a great
deal about one system by measuring the other one.
Okay,
that's what entanglement means.
On the other hand,
it may also follow,
and it may also be true,
that in a highly entangled
state beforehand,
if you happen to know the state,
you may know very little about each
individual piece.
For example,
in the singlet state here,
there is,
what is the probability that Bob's variable is up?
One half.
What is the probability
that Bob's variable is down?
One half.
So in this state,
knowing everything about this
state,
you still know nothing about
whether Bob measures up or down,
if he does a measurement.
Curious.
You know nothing at all about
whether Bob measures up or down.
whether Alice measures up or down,
but you know everything
about the product of them.
That if Bob does his measurement,
Alice does her measurement,
and you compare them afterwards,
every single time,
if this is the state that you put the
system into,
the product will be minus.
So this is an example of this odd thing in
quantum mechanics that you can
know everything about a composite system,
and know nothing
about the pieces.
That's what this is telling you.
You know everything,
or when I say you
know everything,
I mean you know as much
as quantum mechanics allows you to know.
This
is the state of the system.
You're not going to do any better than that.
That's all there
is to know about it.
What you know about it is that sigma times tau,
whether it be sigma
x or tau x,
this is true for the x,
y,
or z components separately,
that the product
of Alice measures up or down,
is minus.
So you know everything about the product of Alice,
Alice's variable,
and Bob's variable is minus one.
That's a lot to know,
but it's not as
much as you would know classically.
Classically,
if you knew everything about a system,
you
would know everything about the constituents,
as well as things that you could measure about
them,
that you could combine together.
In quantum mechanics,
you can't know,
either
you can say you can't know everything,
or to the extent that everything is everything
you can know,
in this case,
you know everything about the combined system.
And you know nothing about its constituents.
That's the really odd thing about entanglement.
That's the extremely odd property of quantum mechanics,
that it allows such nonsense.
Wouldn't that just mean you can't solve the problem?
Separate,
decompose the system without destroying information?
Yeah.
Yeah,
it does mean that.
When you write lm,
I'm a little confused.
Is that measure m and then measure l?
No,
no,
no.
It's the product of lm.
All right,
let's be very clear.
Let's be very clear.
The operation
The operation,
the mathematical operation of multiplying
a state vector by an operator
is not got anything to do with
the actual physical act of measuring it.
I know,
but the syntax looks the same.
على
إذن
I'm not sure,
the syntax is not the same
I'm not sure what syntax means,
I assume it means the words
It just means,
how do I interpret L,
M on the board,
that's all
The product of the operators
Yes,
yes,
it means you act first with M and then L
Okay,
that's it
Yeah
But it doesn't mean that you've measured them,
it means this is just a mathematical thing
Right
The same is true in classical mechanics
I can multiply the momentum of
something by the position of something else
That doesn't mean I measured them just
because I multiplied the two things together
Physical act of measurement,
it's not the operators which act on the states
It's the detectors or apparatuses which act on the system
So,
in words,
when you do a measurement
A detector or a...
Or an apparatus acts on
the system and gives a result
The...
In the space of states,
a operator acts on a vector
Not a detector acting on a system
Quite different concepts
Yeah
Before we make a measurement on an electron
Mm-hmm
Unless we already have a vector,
we can't measure it,
right?
No,
we can't measure it
But we know how it's been prepared,
which is a special case where,
in that case,
we can describe the state as
a linear combination of basic vectors
Yeah
But before we make a measurement,
we might know nothing about it
We might know a little bit about it,
but no matter how much we know,
it'll have to be expressed in terms of probabilities
Mm-hmm
Not in terms of the vectors
Yes
So,
in the case where there's
a correlation between two electrons,
it's a linear combination of vectors,
right?
And let's say it's not a pure correlation,
it's a partial...
It's not a product
It's not a product,
and it's not a purely entangled state,
it's somewhere between...
It's not a what?
A...
Yeah,
a linear state of...
Exactly.
So if,
then,
after we made the sigma measurement,
and we want to describe the tau electron,
we would still have to
describe tau in terms of probabilities
We wouldn't be able to specify it in terms of...
Okay.
I'm not exactly sure what you're getting at,
but maybe this will help.
If we have the quantity,
and you have the numbers,
you're going to get a single unit,
state of a single spin.
Let's suppose somebody told us what the quantum
state of a spin was.
Then for any quantum state there is always an
observable,
in particular some component of Sigma,
which is definite,
which is
predictable.
Every part of it that's obvious
for the states up and down,
it's
obvious for the states left and right.
For the state up,
if you measure Sigma Z
it's definite.
If you measure,
if you know that the
state is right and you measure
Sigma X,
it's definite.
This is more general.
Given any quantum state whatever
of a spin,
there exists a direction,
this you can prove,
that there exists a
direction for which the spin is definite.
Okay?
Curiously,
when you combine the
system together into an entangled state like this,
there is no direction in which
the spin is definite.
In fact,
there is no direction Sigma
X for one of the spins.
Each one of the spins,
either Alice's or Bob's,
has average value zero in every direction.
No matter
what direction you pick,
X,
Y,
Z,
or anything in between,
the average of the
spin,
of Bob's spin,
in this state is zero.
So,
and here's a quantum state in which
Bob can say nothing,
whether he can know the quantum state fully,
and as I said,
has equal probability for up and down in every direction.
I'm not sure
if that's what you're addressing or not.
My question in a nutshell is
if we have a partial correlation.
Oh,
partial,
okay.
The correlation is somewhere between zero and one.
All right,
so we put a big number
here and a small number here.
Yeah,
so we mentioned one,
and then the other could
be expressed as various probabilities
of Sigma X and Sigma Z.
Yes,
yes,
yes.
We can calculate all the probabilities.
We just calculate them.
Yeah.
Okay.
Could you remind us the physical
What is that?
Singlet state?
Say it again?
What is,
what would be an example of
a physical experiment corresponding to a singlet
state?
Good,
good.
Good.
That's an important,
obviously an important question.
Another
way to ask it is
how would you prepare a state,
a system in the singlet state?
All right.
All right,
I'll tell you something about the singlet state.
The singlet state
has the property that it's
an eigenvector of a certain operator.
It's eigenvector of
many operators,
but in particular,
it's an eigenvector of Sigma X,
Tau X.
You can prove
it.
It's actually an eigenvector of Sigma X,
Tau X.
It's an eigenvector of Sigma Y,
Tau Y.
And it's an eigenvector of Sigma Z,
Tau Z.
What's the eigenvalue for each one
of these?
Minus one.
And the eigenvalue is the same for all of them.
That means that it's an eigenvector
of any linear,
any combination of these with eigenvalue minus one.
Any one of them acts
on the singlet state,
gives back minus the singlet state.
Any combination of them will
give back minus the singlet state.
So in particular,
if I take this object here,
the singlet state
is also an eigenvector of this.
Now,
this is a funny thing.
Alice and Bob can't easily measure this whole quantity here.
Why?
Because Alice can't measure Tau X and Tau Y simultaneously.
By separate measurements,
this would be hard to measure.
Can't be measured by separate measurements.
Why?
Because no
separate measurement can measure Tau X
and Tau Y at the same time,
or Tau Z at the same
time.
Now,
this object is a perfectly good Hermitian operator,
and there must exist a way of measuring
it.
But more to the point right now,
there's a way of preparing
a state which is an eigenvector
of this.
Now,
what state?
The singlet state.
The singlet state is an eigenvector of this
object with eigenvalue minus 3.
That's an eigenvalue of this one with minus one,
this
one with minus one,
and this one with minus one.
The whole thing has eigenvalues of three.
The point is,
the eigenvectors of this product,
or the sum of products here,
include the singlet
state as a particular one.
You can also write this as just sigma dot tau.
Sigma X Tau X,
sigma Y Tau Y,
sigma Z Tau Z.
These are ordinary classical vectors.
You would write it as sigma
dot tau.
Now,
if you take two electrons,
each one has its spin,
and they're very,
very far
away.
They're very,
very far away.
very far
apart.
They don't interact with each other.
There's no energy associated with the interaction
between them.
But as you bring them together,
there are all sorts of energies.
One energy,
for example,
is just a Coulomb energy between them,
product of the charges.
There is also
an energy associated with the spins.
And one of the terms in the energy associated with
the spin is just the dot product of the spins.
If the spins are aligned,
you get one value.
If they're anti-aligned,
you get the other value.
And so sigma dot tau is a piece of
the Hamiltonian of the two-spin system.
In the singlet state,
it's minimum.
There's three
other states called the triplet state,
in which it's maximum.
So the energy is lowest
in the singlet state.
The spins are trying to get to the maximum.
And the energy is trying
to get anti-aligned with each other,
but in every direction,
not just the z direction,
in every direction.
And they eventually compromise on the singlet state.
So you have two energy levels
associated with the spin of an electron.
These two energy
in hydrogen or in positronium,
even better.
In positronium,
you have the aligned and anti-aligned
spins.
And they have different energy levels,
singlet,
triplet.
If you bring two electrons together,
then any state can be
written in terms of the singlet
and triplet states.
Even the product state can be
represented as a sum of singlet and
triplet states.
What happens when you bring the
electrons together after a period if they're
in the triplet state with the higher energy?
What happens to higher energy states after
a while?
They emit a photon and
go to the lower energy state.
So if you take two spins,
which may
be in a product state,
and you bring them together and wait a long time,
a photon may
or may not be emitted.
If the system is in the singlet state,
no emission.
If it's in
the triplet state,
it emits,
gives off a photon,
and winds up in the singlet state.
So this would be a way of
preparing the system in the singlet state.
You just take the two
electrons and wait until they radiate a photon,
and wait long enough.
They either do or don't
radiate the photon,
but if you wait long enough,
you'll know that it's in the singlet state.
So that's an experiment.
That's an experiment to another way,
now this one is very,
very
far-fetched,
extremely far-fetched.
The energy in the singlet
state is less than the energy
in the other three states.
There are four states.
There are four viruses,
two Constitutional
four possible states altogether,
four possible basis states,
singlet and
three-triplet.
The energy of the singlet is lowest.
So you just take your composite
system and you put it on
a scale and you measure its mass.
Mass is energy.
When
you've measured its mass,
you've measured whether its energy is the energy of the
singlet state or the triplet state,
and that constitutes a measurement or
constitutes a preparation device or
a measurement of basically this variable,
but if you like the difference between singlet and triplet.
So,
yeah,
there are
ways of preparing systems in the singlet or triplet—in the
singlet state—or ways of,
in fact,
if you bring the systems together and you wait
a while,
it's very difficult to have anything but the singlet state.
Then once
you've made that singlet state,
if you grab the
the electrons without turning their spins,
if you grab them somehow in a way that doesn't
put any torque on their spins and pull them apart,
you now have two separated electrons,
for example,
in the singlet state.
So it's not a terribly hard thing to do.
With the speed that you can
actually assign an energy to the entanglement?
Yes,
in this case,
yes.
In this case,
But that's — well,
what you can say is
the lower energy is certainly entangled.
The lowest energy state,
the one that it seeks
to get to by — it
doesn't have to be radiating a photon.
Any mechanism by which the system
can lower its energy,
emitting phonon or doing anything else,
it's not going to be able to
interact with a crystal lattice
or anything to lower its energy.
We'll leave it in the
singlet state.
So — and I think the right thing
just to say is that the lower energy
state is entangled.
That's almost always the case,
that the states of lowest energy are
highly entangled between systems.
Okay,
so next question.
I liked this most about Hamilton,
which is the achromatic very worthless function.
I'm not aware of this.
It's not an impeccable thing.
So now we've ownership space,
and if you tracking something on aiggling chain,
the pies happen and Executive Plan,
as I said,
they'll rise and fail were not able is this
to do with wants and returns공 you
have to lay a tangent of some norm.
So you'll have to,
basically,
you're going to depend over time how you see things.
You're going to rer Huizing from the zero Madden
resolved by y than the lower down Tx going tomorrow,
I think we can do it.
Let's define an object called Alice's density matrix.
Alice's density matrix is a quantity which,
even in an entangled state,
is as complete a description of Alice's
system for the purposes of Alice's measurements
as Alice can ever get.
It's not a wave function.
If it was unentangled,
the wave function would be
the best description she could have.
But for an entangled system,
you cannot extract out a wave function
for either piece of the entangled system.
The best you could do
is something called the density matrix.
We actually had it up here.
Let me go back to it.
Let's talk about all of Alice's experiments that
she can do without measuring the density matrix.
Without measuring anything about
Bob's electron or Bob's system.
Let's imagine that they've separated their systems.
Bob has his,
Alice has her,
and Alice can do all the experiments she likes
and measure any one of these L observables.
L stands for Alice.
How does she describe all the possible expectation
values of everything that she can ever measure?
So we had a formula up before,
and I'm going to rewrite it.
The expectation value of L is psi star of alpha...
Let's see,
what was it?
Alpha prime,
beta prime,
or A prime,
B prime.
This is the combined system.
We're going back to the combined system now.
L,
A prime,
A.
Psi,
A,
B.
But we set B equal to B prime.
Or if we like,
we can leave the B prime here and
put a Kronecker delta of B and B prime.
This is one of Alice's variables.
And so as far as Bob goes,
it's just the unit operator.
It does nothing to Bob's piece of the wave function.
And that just says stick B equal to B prime.
Okay,
look at this quantity right over here.
Let's take L on the outside.
Let's take L of A prime and A out there.
Isolate it off.
We have to sum this over B.
We sum over everything.
We sum this over B.
And here's a quantity...
right here that depends on A prime,
A,
and it multiplies something else that
depends on A and A prime.
But it doesn't depend on B.
We've summed over B.
Once you've summed over B,
it doesn't depend on B anymore.
So this object over here is
a function only of Alice's coordinates,
A and A prime.
It,
of course,
to calculate it,
you may have to know more about the wave function.
But once you've calculated it,
that's all that Alice ever needs to know
to calculate anything about her half of the system.
So let's give it a name.
It's the sum over B,
psi star of A prime B,
psi of AB.
It doesn't depend on B
degrees of freedom at all anymore,
Bob's degrees of freedom.
It's called the density matrix.
And it's a function,
it's a thing,
which depends on A prime and A.
It's a matrix.
It has two entries.
Any matrix can be thought of as
a function of a row and a column.
This is a density matrix.
And if we know the density matrix,
it doesn't matter where it came from.
It doesn't matter what Bob's state was.
If we know row and A,
row,
then we know that the expectation,
let's write the formula,
the expectation value of L
is equal to the sum of
row of A prime,
and A,
L of A and A prime.
I think I have one of them backwards.
It doesn't matter.
So Alice,
if she knew this density matrix,
could forget about Bob completely,
and say,
I know everything that there
is to know about my subsystem,
and here it is.
Okay.
What is row of A and A prime?
If we start with a pure state,
supposing we started with a pure state,
Are you getting exhausted?
Well,
this is quantum mechanics for you.
Sorry,
buddies,
but this is it.
I can't make it any easier.
This is as easy as I can make it.
All right?
You got to sit down with it,
and you got to go through it,
and penetrate it.
But I'll do my best.
Okay.
This is the notion of a density matrix.
What if
psi
is a pure state?
What can we say about this density matrix?
So let's go back and see exactly what it says.
If psi is,
sorry,
what if psi is a product state?
If psi is a product state,
it means the wave function
factorizes.
So let's go back.
Here we are.
Here's the density matrix.
The wave function factorizes into a,
this is B prime.
Yeah,
that's right.
That's correct.
If the density matrix,
your sum is over A prime and A,
it's a double sum.
Not in the density matrix.
In this one,
yes.
It's a double sum.
It's a double sum,
but it only involves row.
So let's erase this for a moment.
And see what we learn about this creature called,
the density matrix,
if psi is a product vector.
It must have a special form somehow.
So let's say that psi is
a product of Alice's wave function
times Bob's wave function.
I forget which one is which now.
Was psi Alice or was psi Bob?
Psi was Bob?
Psi is Alice.
Okay,
it doesn't matter.
We'll just change them now.
So,
the complex conjugate here is Alice's wave function times,
this is not the wave function of Alice.
This is the wave function of Alice's spin,
incidentally.
But I'll call it Alice's wave function.
Alice's wave function times Bob's wave function,
the complex conjugate.
And then we multiply that
by the non-complex conjugated thing.
Let me put them in the opposite order.
Psi of B,
notice we've identified B with B here.
It's not B and B prime.
And this is prime psi A.
Each one of these factorizes.
This factorizes into a function of A prime and B,
and this one into a function of B and A.
And now we sum over B.
What is the sum of B of phi star phi?
One,
right?
Okay,
so now we can take
this out and throw it out.
And here's what we find.
We find that for a product state,
only for product state,
that rho is simply made up out
of Alice's half of the wave function
without any regard to Bob.
She doesn't need to know anything about Bob.
This is not too surprising that she
didn't need to know anything about Bob.
After all,
it is a product wave function.
And the density matrix is just a,
um,
a
product of the complex conjugate of the
wave function with the wave function itself.
Two different A's though.
An A and an A prime.
Now what can we say about a matrix like this?
Let's call this matrix,
let's call it,
I think it's actually rho of,
let's call it rho of A and A prime.
Just call it rho of A.
I've switched the order,
but that's just the definition.
Let's take this rho,
it's a matrix,
and act with it on a column vector.
How do you act,
if you know the components of a matrix,
how do you act on a column vector?
So let's suppose this is a matrix,
is,
yeah,
rho one one,
just a second,
rho one two,
so forth,
rho two one,
we make a matrix out of it.
Yeah?
Do you want to erase that
summation sign there on the far?
Yeah,
I do.
Good point.
Excellent.
Alright,
so we have rho,
it's made up out of Alice's wave function,
and I maintain that this density matrix,
thought of as a matrix,
has an eigenvector.
I maintain,
moreover,
that it has one and only one eigenvector,
with non-zero eigenvalue,
and that that eigenvalue is plus one.
Right.
Somebody say right?
Good.
Okay,
let's prove it.
I'll tell you exactly what that eigenvector is.
It's psi A.
It's psi itself.
So let's check that out.
Let's multiply this
by psi of A prime,
in fact,
and sum it over A prime.
This is matrix,
this is the process
of multiplying a column vector by a matrix.
That's the way you do it.
You write down the matrix,
you write down the column vector,
and you sum over the element between them.
Okay,
let's see if we can see what we get.
Oh,
this is the action of rho on psi.
Okay,
so let's do it.
Rho,
here's rho.
Now let's multiply it by psi of A prime.
And now let's sum over A prime.
What do we get?
Psi star of A prime times psi of A prime
summed over A prime is?
One,
right?
So?
It all comes out to just be psi.
So this is psi.
What does that tell you about eigenvectors
and eigenvalues of the density matrix?
It tells you that the original wave function
is an eigenvector of the density matrix
with eigenvalue plus one.
Let me prove now
that all vectors perpendicular,
there are n minus one,
if the dimensionality of the space is n,
then this is one eigenvector out of n
which has eigenvalue one.
Let's take any vector now
which is perpendicular,
which is orthogonal to psi,
to psi A,
to Alice's wave function.
Let's call it psi A tilde.
Tilde now means it's orthogonal
to the original Alice's vector.
Now what is this inner product?
Zero,
right?
So we find out that rho,
rho on psi twiddle is zero.
That means that any vector
perpendicular to Alice's vector
is an eigenvector with eigenvalue zero.
The original state of Alice's spin
is an eigenvector with plus one.
Conclusion,
the density matrix for a pure state
has one and only one nonzero eigenvalue
and it's equal to one.
What if it's not a product state?
If it's not a product state,
then you'll find a collection of eigenvalues.
In fact,
in general,
there will be all of the eigenvalues
in general will be nonzero
of the density matrix.
You can try this out for the
for the,
for the two-spin system.
Work out the density matrix of Alice's spin,
the density matrix of Bob's spin,
and you will find out that they're quite different.
They don't have a single eigenvector
which is nonzero.
They have a pair of eigenvectors
which are nonzero.
So what we learn
is that there's information
in the density matrix,
and in particular in the eigenvalues
of the density matrix,
which tell you whether there's a great deal
of entanglement or not.
The more eigenvectors which are nonzero,
the more entangled it is.
If there's only one eigenvector
which is nonzero,
it's not entangled at all,
and Alice's half of the wave function
is just that eigenvector.
If they're entangled,
then one finds,
and the more they're entangled,
the more eigenvalues you will find.
And the maximum entanglement
is when all the eigenvectors are equal.
When all the eigenvectors are equal,
all eigenvalues,
when all the eigenvalues are equal,
that's maximal entanglement.
Take the singlet state,
work out the density matrix
of Alice's spin,
and what you'll find is that
it has two eigenvalues,
each of which is a half,
equal and nonzero.
And equal to a half.
So that's a test,
that's the way to test whether a system
does or doesn't have entanglement.
Calculate its density matrix,
and study its eigenvalues.
The maximal entanglement is when they're all equal.
When they're equal,
they're equal to one over n.
You can prove that.
Where n is the dimensionality of the space.
One over n.
Okay,
that's entanglement quantified.
It can even be a little more quantitative.
Even be a little more quantitative.
No,
let's not do that now.
I'll write the more quantitative condition in the notes,
and I think we've done enough calculation for the moment.
Let's do it again.
Let's very quickly go through the connection
between measurement and entanglement.
There's a deep connection
Basically,
measurement is the process of entangling,
of starting with a product state,
a product state of what and what?
A product state of a system and the apparatus.
The apparatus is in a definite state to begin with,
and the system is in a definite state.
What state is the apparatus in?
Well,
the apparatus might be something
which detects something or other,
and if it's not detecting,
you might put it in some neutral state.
Some neutral state,
which is the starting state,
the undetected state,
the neutral state of the apparatus.
And now you bring the system that you're interested in
right up to the apparatus.
It does something to the apparatus.
Something happens to the system itself,
and what's left over,
is an entangled state between the two of them.
So I'll give you an example.
I'm going to think of the apparatus
as a very simple system with only two states.
Let me find my notes here.
Yeah,
my system is a spin,
and my apparatus also happens to have only two states.
You can think of it
as another spin if you like.
In fact,
it could be Alice's and Bob's,
but you can also think of
it as a more complex system.
But for simplicity,
it only has two states.
Here's the apparatus,
and it has only two states,
plus,
let's say,
zero and one now.
Zero is the state before the apparatus is switched on.
Well,
when it's switched on.
When it's switched on and it's not detected anything,
it always starts out in the state zero.
If it's not in the state zero,
give it a shove and make it,
put it into the state zero.
Otherwise,
it's not,
otherwise,
you know,
you have to start your apparatus in some known state.
Otherwise,
you're not going to be able to do a measurement.
So,
zero or one,
but it starts out zero.
And we have our spin.
Here's a spin,
and we're going to do a measurement on it.
Supposing the spin is in the up state,
and the apparatus,
of course,
begins in the zero state.
So,
we'll represent that by a combined ket vector.
A combined ket vector is in the tensor product
of the spin Hilbert space and the detector Hilbert space.
Up and zero.
If the spin comes in to begin with down,
then you start out in the
space in the state down zero.
Why?
Because you start out with
the detector in the neutral state.
Now,
I'm not going to tell you in detail
what the interaction is between the detector and the spin.
That could involve magnetic fields and other kinds of things
causing an influence between the detector.
But I am going to tell
you that if you bring the spin
into the detector and then take
the spin out of the detector,
I will tell you what state is left over.
So,
in particular,
and I'm making this up,
of course,
I'm making up a rule
which would be a good detector.
Which would be a good detector.
Namely,
if the spin,
if the system starts,
if the combined system starts in the state U zero,
then the detector feels a spin
and it jumps to state one.
It goes to state U one.
Nothing happens to the spin.
It just activates the detector.
On the other hand,
if the spin is down,
it doesn't activate the detector.
That's my rule.
So this goes to down one.
No,
down one.
Down zero.
And that's a very good detector of upness and downness.
But now let's start with
a superposition of up and down.
Let's take alpha up times
up plus alpha down times down.
Somebody now brought us a
spin in a superposition of states,
in a general quantum state.
But of course the detector starts out zero.
So that's the starting state.
What happens after the detector acts?
Well,
if the state is U zero,
it goes to U one.
So that means it goes to
alpha sub U times U one.
Plus alpha sub down.
Down zero.
This all of a sudden has become an entangled state.
It's an entangled state.
If it's up,
if the spin is up,
the detector is up.
The detector is one.
If the spin is down,
the detector is zero.
That is an entangled state.
Why is it an entangled state?
It's an entangled state because by looking at the detector,
you can tell what the spin is doing.
In fact,
that's what a measurement is.
A measurement is an interaction
between a system and an apparatus
that leaves the apparatus in
a state that depends on the,
whatever it is that it's measuring about the system.
So from one point of view,
you can just say,
well look,
this is exactly what I knew a measurement always was.
It just,
it's a constant.
It's just a process that
leaves a record on the apparatus
of what the initial state was of the spin.
But from another point of view,
it's the physics of a combined system,
the combined system being the spin and the apparatus,
which leaves them in a highly entangled state.
So entangled that by looking at the detector,
you can tell what the spin is.
So entanglement and measurement are really the same thing.
And in fact,
to measure a spin,
you really only need another spin.
This,
the detector here could just be a spin,
and one and zero could be up and down.
So we had this kind of concoction here,
where exactly this happened.
It would take only one spin
to be a detector or an apparatus
which could measure another spin.
But in general,
this is the nature of measurement
that it entangles systems together.
It entangles in particular apparatus with system.
Is that clear?
It should be very clear.
And that's all.
That's one way of thinking about measurement.
In this language in which you think of the system
and the apparatus together,
you never speak about collapse of the wave function.
You speak about the development of entanglement.
If you don't want to
include the apparatus into your system,
then the only thing to say
is that after the experiment is done,
the system is either up or down,
and which one do you pick?
You pick the one that you record.
But the one that you record
is the one recorded by the apparatus.
So thinking about just the system by itself,
you have to have this
rule that the wave function collapses.
Thinking about the system plus apparatus,
the same physics is described
by the development of entanglement
between the system and apparatus.
So in that case,
for the mixed state,
the monotate,
what do you see on the meter of your apparatus,
the one and the zero?
Okay,
the apparatus...
Now you are another detector.
This is the hierarchy of detection,
or the hierarchy of measurement.
Here's the spin.
Here's the apparatus,
but we're not finished.
We still have to look at the apparatus.
We haven't gotten anywhere until we look at the apparatus,
right?
All right,
well,
what's going to happen?
Again,
we're going to have to say,
when we look at the apparatus,
we wind up collapsing the wave function
to one of these two pieces of the entangled state.
Or we can say include the eyeball into the system.
In that case,
we should have included another system here,
the eyeball,
and the eyeball...
I don't know,
how did it start?
It started...
It also has two states.
The two states correspond to the two possible answers
that the brain up there...
There's also a brain up here.
Two states of the brain.
One state of the brain says,
I saw the apparatus with a zero.
The other state of the brain says,
I saw the apparatus with a one.
If we want to include the observer,
as well as the apparatus,
we have to include another factor here.
And that factor has to depend
on the state of the brain.
Let's call it B...
Let's call it B naught.
It starts B naught,
which is the brain before it has looked at anything.
And then it goes to B1 over here,
or B naught over here.
It's now become a system which is entangled
with the eye and brain.
You can say,
wait a minute.
We now have this entangled state.
We've described it all by the quantum mechanics
of the entanglement between spin and apparatus,
and then later on between apparatus,
spin,
and eyeball.
It's all been described by quantum mechanics.
But you may not be satisfied.
You may worry about the other fellow
who comes in the room,
takes a look,
or asks you,
what did you see?
So somebody else comes in.
And asks you,
okay,
Charlie,
what did you measure?
And in the process,
collapses the wave function
of the spin apparatus.
What's his name?
Give him a name.
No,
no,
no.
Charlie,
this is Charlie.
He comes in afterwards.
Wigner.
Wiggy.
Yeah.
This is Wigner.
This is Schrodinger,
right?
That's Wigner.
So Schrodinger.
And I don't know.
Which one of these has ears?
This is the atom.
The cat,
he doesn't look at the atom,
but he gets hit.
Something happens.
Something happens to him when the atom.
So he's the detector.
The cat is the detector.
Right?
Here's Schrodinger,
who looks into the box,
and here's Wigner,
who looks at Schrodinger.
And there's a hierarchy here.
The hierarchy,
where you decide to break the hierarchy,
determines at what stage you
will say the wave function collapsed.
If you like.
I suppose at some stage you'll
have to say the wave function collapsed,
or when the last person looked at it,
but you can always include
that last person into the system,
and then no collapse happens.
But then in order to make
sense out of the whole thing,
again,
you have to imagine some other person.
So you always have to imagine a hierarchy of observation.
And there is such a hierarchy of observation.
The world is built like an onion.
Things inside,
next thing out,
next thing out.
And each thing gets to a point.
And you observe what's in the inside of it.
What is the process whereby
we move into the classical world
and one of those people actually sees the definite value
instead of the superposed?
Well,
I don't know.
I don't think there is any sharp line.
We tend to describe big
systems as having little uncertainty.
But I'm not sure that anything really different happens
when an electron looks at another electron
or when a cat looks at an electron.
I think the physics or the mathematical science
of the physical description,
I think,
is the same description.
Or at least if we
want to say something special happened
when the cat looked that's
not well described by quantum mechanics,
we have to introduce something about cats
that isn't contained within quantum mechanics.
And personally,
I don't believe there is anything about cats
which is not contained within quantum mechanics.
So I'm happy with this description.
I'm happy with this description.
What makes me happy is that it doesn't matter
where you draw the line.
You can draw the line in
one place or the next place
or the next place and the results will be consistent.
If the cat saw the spin-up,
Schrödinger will see the cat having seen the spin-up.
And Wigner will have seen Schrödinger having seen the cat
having seen the spin-up.
That's what the nature of the state is.
So that I find satisfying,
that you don't ever have to say
where you draw the line.
And until you draw the line,
you can put the line
as far out as you like,
until you draw the line,
everything is described by the
rules of conventional quantum mechanics.
So it's like if you're the cat,
you definitely draw the line.
Well,
okay.
Yeah.
Look,
I think at some stage,
you have to decide for
yourself how you think about this.
I'm not going to try to
push my interpretation of quantum mechanics
on you,
particularly since
I don't know what to say about it except this.
This seems to disturb a lot of people,
this whole business of systems
for which you can know
as much as can be known
and know nothing about the parts of the system.
This seems to disturb people.
Is it disturbing?
You know,
when Feynman was asked,
whether he thought there was
a problem about quantum mechanics,
his answer was the problem was so big
that he couldn't tell if there was a problem.
He knew how to use it.
He knew how to predict with it.
He could predict anything that he wanted to predict
that had an answer.
And he did not expect...
I'm actually speaking about myself now,
but...
and for him.
He did not expect that
quantum mechanics would ever go wrong,
that the rules would always be satisfied,
but is there a problem
because of this sense of unreality
about where actual objective...
where objectively does something happen?
Does the objective death of the cat happen
when the cat looks at the atom,
or is it when Schrödinger looks at the cat,
or is it when Wigner looks at Schrödinger?
Where does the objective phenomenon happen?
And maybe we're just playing with words there.
Maybe.
Maybe we're playing with words,
trying to use words in
a context where they don't apply,
but you have to decide that yourself.
My goal is to give you the tools
to be able to ask the question,
and I doubt seriously that
you're going to answer the question
even for yourself.
You'll probably come away feeling as uncomfortable about it,
but you'll know why you're uncomfortable.
You'll know what it is with some precision
that's making you uncomfortable about it.
At least I hope.
At least that's my goal.
All right.
In the equation you put up there with the i,
forget about Schrödinger,
just the i,
the equation you wrote,
that implies there's a correlation of
one between the state of the system,
the apparatus,
the composite state,
and the state of the i.
Yeah.
So would it...
In other words,
the i has become entangled
with the rest of the system.
Now suppose your vision wasn't so good.
That's what you call a weak measurement.
Yeah,
look.
No,
no,
that can happen.
There can be partial entanglement for sure.
I've given you a kind of idealized situation.
Right.
No,
no,
that's...
It's a serious question.
No,
it's a serious question.
People talk...
If your i isn't so good,
you're not quite sure what the apparatus is saying.
Well,
your i...
No,
no,
okay.
There could be several reasons
why your i was no good.
First of all,
it could be that the interaction with the apparatus
was simply too weak,
that there wasn't enough oomph in the interaction.
It wasn't that your i was bad,
it just wasn't enough coupling between the two systems,
and then you only get partial information.
Or it could be that your
i is bad because you have cataracts,
let's say.
All right.
In that case,
the i did a measurement.
It became entangled with the...
with the system completely.
It's just the connection between the...
the stuff in your i
and your brain wasn't good enough
to send the signal back to your brain.
So the correlation happened,
but it was a bit messy.
Is that a detector efficiency problem?
Sometimes it's a detector efficiency problem,
and sometimes it's a problem...
Well,
detector efficiency could have to do
with the strength of interaction with the system,
or it could just be that it's
too hard to get the signal out.
So I'm not sure what detector efficiency really means,
but I could think of several things.
One is the signal is there,
it imprinted itself on the system,
and you personally have a hard time getting it out.
The other is that the interaction was not strong enough
to really establish a
full entanglement between these systems.
Both can happen.
What about a lip reader watching a Dove movie?
Right.
Would it affect our data detector?
You can think of all sorts of variants on this.
What's that?
Let's say there was a bad detector in between
that got entangled,
and then I had a perfectly good detector later on.
Would it affect the measurement of that?
Well,
I think this probably...
I guess the weakest link is where you...
Yeah.
All right,
let's talk about locality.
Let's talk about...
Let's talk about locality and entanglement,
which is really where people get hung up.
I mean...
And the villain,
the arch-villain here,
who really tangled things badly...
was Einstein.
Einstein,
and not that he asked a question.
Of course,
he asked a wonderful question
about entangled systems,
really our understanding of entanglement
and much of what we think about it
and our curiosity about it
goes back to Einstein's question in 1933,
who was very much puzzled by this idea
that you could have a
system about which you knew everything
and yet you knew nothing about the components of it.
And he wrote a paper simply complaining about it.
I don't know if he
was the first one to notice
the phenomenon of entanglement.
I have a feeling not.
He was the first one
to get really exercised by it
and say something is very peculiar here.
That I find quite okay.
He then used the term...
What was the term again?
Spooky action at a distance.
And that got everybody confused afterwards.
Because Einstein knew exactly what
action at a distance meant
and it didn't matter.
It didn't mean what he meant
when he was using it in this context.
Action at a distance literally means
forces between systems at a distance,
the ability to affect the outcome
of an experiment at one place
by doing something at another place.
Action at a distance,
the Coulomb force between electrons.
Now,
of course,
in the real world
it's not action at a distance.
But in Newton's world,
well,
Newton didn't know about electrons.
Newton knew about gravity.
In Newton's world,
the gravitational interaction
was action at a distance.
And the meaning of that,
from our point of view,
is that if something came along
and gave the sun a sudden shove,
we would know it instantly
for the simple reason that
the orbit of the Earth
would instantly react
to the change in position of the sun.
The force on the Earth would instantly react.
And so every measurement of everything
that you might want to measure
would be to some extent or another
modified by the sudden change
in the orbit of the sun.
That's what action at a distance meant.
The ability,
if you like,
to send a signal.
By shoving the sun,
you're sending a signal to Earth
and you're sending it instantaneously
if there's action at a distance.
Einstein must have known,
I am certain that he knew,
that entanglement did not entail
action at a distance in that sense.
What one can do,
what one can work out,
is supposing you start,
I'll give you something you can try to play with
and see if you can work it out.
Supposing you start with a system,
which is a two-part system,
it has a wave function,
psi of A and B,
and from that system,
you can construct a density matrix,
Alice and Bob,
you can construct a density matrix
rho for Alice.
That density matrix contains
every possible
statistical prediction
that Alice can ever make
for her subsystem A.
Now let's imagine that Alice and Bob
took their subsystems,
Alice went to a distant planet,
Bob stayed in Palo Alto,
and they're very far from one another,
so far that it would take light
four years to get from one place to another.
Bob does an experiment.
That means,
now this is,
this could be an entangled state,
this is not a non-entangled state,
Bob does an experiment,
and that has an effect
on his half of the system here,
but it has no effect whatever
on Alice's density matrix.
Perhaps I can prove that,
I'm not going to prove that tonight.
It's not too hard to prove
that any physically allowable
change in this wave function,
which only involves Bob half of it,
the process of interacting
with some other system,
or whatever it is,
Bob gives his electron a knock,
whatever he does to it,
he will not have any effect
on Alice's density matrix.
That's the way quantum mechanics
is really put together,
and the implication is that
anything that Bob does,
suddenly,
at a fixed instant of time,
will not have any effect
on any prediction,
or the success of any prediction,
it will have no effect
on the statistical probabilities
of Alice measuring anything about A.
It just will not.
So in that sense,
it was impossible for Bob
to send a message to Alice suddenly.
Now of course,
he can do an experiment
on his subsystem,
and after he's done the experiment,
he can then send a telegram
to Alice far away,
in the standard way
that you send messages,
and tell her what the result,
again,
this is an entangled state,
it could be up-down,
minus down-up.
When Bob does a measurement
on his spin,
it has no effect
on Alice's density matrix.
He can then send Alice a message
and say,
look,
I saw down,
and Alice will say,
ah,
yeah,
that's true,
that's because I saw up.
They were correlated.
I thought they were correlated,
and you just confirmed that.
I measured up a few months ago,
and in fact,
I'm now getting your telegram,
and it tells me that you got down,
and that's consistent,
everything is fine.
Nobody sent any message
faster than the speed of light.
The mere fact that when
Bob measures his variable,
he instantly knows something
about Alice's is no source
of anxiety for locality.
This would happen for nickels
and dimes,
for perfectly classical systems.
The peculiarity is different
than that.
The peculiarity has to do
with this idea that you can know
everything about a system
and yet know nothing
about its parts.
What is it then if locality,
the standard physicist definition
of locality is not at risk,
and you can't send signals faster?
What is it that Einstein meant,
and what did Bell mean,
and what did all the other people
who talk about these things mean
when they said entanglement
entails a degree of nonlocality?
So I'll try to explain to you
by imagining a game.
Yeah?
If Bob made a measurement
and Alice did not,
and Bob sent Alice a message
after his measurement,
would that information alone
be enough to change Alice's
density matrix?
Be enough to what?
To change Alice's density matrix.
Oh yeah.
If Alice sends a real,
if Bob sends a real message
and Alice hasn't looked yet,
okay,
so let's say Bob,
Alice has not looked.
She doesn't know anything yet,
and as far as she's concerned,
the density matrix is consistent with that
and basically tells her nothing.
That's a density matrix
which hasn't got very much information in it
about her spin.
And then she gets a telegram from Bob
saying,
my spin was up.
As far as Alice is concerned,
that collapses her density matrix
and tells her her spin is down.
So thereafter,
she will use a density matrix
which says that her spin is down.
So yes,
once a message has had time
to go between them,
yes,
then she will know something
that she didn't know before,
and she will therefore update
her density matrix.
But that will only take place
after there's been sufficient time
for the signal to propagate.
Yeah?
If I understand correctly,
the statements that we're making here
are about expected values
of these disturbance,
right?
Yes.
But when you realize it once,
you're actually not going to get
the expected value you're going to get.
But this also holds for every value,
not just expected values,
right?
No,
expected or expectation values
or whatever you want to call them,
average values,
if you know the average values
of all variables,
you don't need to know all,
let's,
okay.
Supposing we have one variable
that we're interested in.
Let's call it L again.
If we know the average values
of L,
the average value of L squared,
the average value of L cubed,
dot,
we know the whole probability distribution of L.
This is called knowing the moments,
all of the moments
of a probability distribution.
If we know all the expectation values
of L,
L squared,
L cubed,
actually for a single spin,
you only need the spin
and the spin squared,
then you know the full probability distribution.
Once you know the full probability distribution,
that's all you can know.
So knowing all,
knowing a full set of expectation values
like this is knowing everything
that Alice can know about the system.
But the actual realization
of the experiment when it happened was?
Oh,
that's right,
yes.
So the first one measured up
and then the second one measured down?
Yeah,
yeah,
that's right.
Then they still are guaranteed
to be opposite,
right?
They are.
They're guaranteed to be opposite,
yes.
But Alice cannot find,
Alice doesn't update her information about it
until she gets it.
Before Alice gets the information,
as far as she knows,
it's half a half.
But let's try to do it a little better.
Alice and Bob are now
going to each have many spins.
So Charlie is going to give each of them
many entangled pairs.
So Alice has spin number one,
and Bob has his spin number one,
and they are in the relationship
of being entangled.
Also,
Alice has spin number two,
which is not entangled with spin number one,
but it happens to be entangled
with Bob's spin number two.
Charlie gave him a whole series of these
so that they can do statistics.
So they can do statistical experiments
and collect statistics.
When they've collected statistics,
they will discover that every time Bob is up,
Alice is down.
Every time Bob is down,
Alice is up.
But now they can do a lot more than that.
They can,
let's see,
what's a good example for what can be done?
Yeah,
right.
Good.
Bob does all of his experiments here
at some instant of time
and finds out every one of these,
finds out exactly what every one of them is doing.
Does that convey any information at all to Alice
about which she knows that just about half of them
are up and half of them are down?
Bob goes and makes his measurement.
He does his measurement on every single one of them.
Does Alice know anything afterward
that she didn't know before?
No.
Does anything surprising happen
when she measures these things?
Does the statistics of these things over here
in any way change because Bob measured these things?
No.
There will be no statistical difference.
Bob can do his measurement,
throw his measurement in the waste paper basket,
but he's measured every single one of these.
It has no influence at all on what Alice measures.
But,
if Bob sends a message to Alice
before she does her measurement
and says,
Spin 1 came out plus,
Spin 2 came out minus,
blah,
then instantly Alice knows everything about these.
In fact,
he could say,
Sigma z equals plus 1.
But he decided over here not to measure Sigma z.
He said,
I'm going to measure Sigma x over here,
minus 1.
And over here he measures Sigma y equals plus 1.
Having made these measurements,
without informing Alice in any way,
does nothing whatever to the statistics of her measurements.
But if he now sends them,
she can now decide.
She can decide to measure anything she wants.
But if she decides to measure Sigma z,
because she knew that Bob got plus 1 here,
and Sigma x for this one,
and Sigma y for this one,
we'll find that in every case,
that they're opposite.
You keep saying Bob sends the message.
I just want to make sure I understand.
Yeah,
he sends a telegram.
It's not him sending it.
It's her receiving it that matters.
Well,
of course,
yes.
Right.
No,
the important point is that it
takes time to send a message.
Yeah.
Hmm?
What?
No,
no,
no.
I missed.
Okay.
You're going to be live.
Well,
yes,
that is a problem.
I don't know if this captures,
but it seems like this feeling about something,
about spooky action at a distance,
comes not from thinking externally
about Bob and Alice doing measurements,
but almost thinking about inside the system,
like they're these two separate entities.
Well,
I will try to give you a precise definition.
All right?
Now,
there is a theorem lurking here.
I don't know that the theorem has ever been discussed
in the computer science community.
It's a kind of computer science theorem.
Whether anybody has actually discussed it
in the language I'm going to tell you now,
I don't know.
And I don't really quite know
how to formulate it as a theorem.
I've never tried.
But I think I can capture the
essence of what this theorem would say
if only the theorem could be made precise.
We have 10 minutes to try to do this.
If we go over a little bit,
we'll do that.
All right.
Here's the game I want to play.
I want...
I'm going to write a computer program,
my computer.
My computer has a screen,
okay?
It has a screen and all
the usual things that computers have.
Over here on the screen is a little black box,
and that little black box is called spin.
You can't see inside it,
but there's something in it.
And in here is apparatus A.
And apparatus A,
you can see,
you can see what it's doing and so forth.
It's got a zero,
it can measure zero or one.
Now,
here's the game.
The memory stores two things.
The memory stores information about the spin.
This is a completely classical computer.
The game we're going to play is
I'm going to fool you into thinking
there's really a quantum mechanical system in here.
How are we going to do that?
We're going to do it by
I'm going to write a computer program
which completely simulates the classical computer program
that completely simulates what happens when
an apparatus looks at a spin.
Okay,
so here's the way it's going to go.
We're going to start,
just for convenience,
we'll start with a spin in a known state.
So the apparatus or the computer program,
it's not important,
but the computer program,
let's say it starts out with a spin.
It's going to go up or whatever it's doing.
The apparatus can either read zero or one.
There's a button over here that you touch,
and that button is M.
It means you measure,
it means measurement.
So when you touch that button over here,
the apparatus measures the spin.
The computer records two things.
It records the state vector,
the state vector of the spin.
How does it do that?
By providing two complex numbers.
Stored in the computer are two complex numbers,
alpha up and alpha down,
subject to the constraint that alpha star alpha
plus alpha star alpha is equal to one.
So it stores an information which is equivalent
to the state vector of the spin.
And the other thing it stores is the direction
that you point the apparatus.
You can move the apparatus
around by playing with the computer.
Not move it around,
but you can reorient it
in any direction that you like.
You start with a spin up.
Now this spin might be interacting with a magnetic field
or whatever's happening to it.
The computer solves the Schrodinger equation.
And solving the Schrodinger equation for the spin,
that means it updates the state of the spin.
You start with a particular state,
doesn't matter what it is,
and after a time t it updates the spin,
it updates the state,
so the computer now knows what alpha is
after a certain time has elapsed.
Then you punch the measure button.
And the computer takes the state,
turns it into a pair of probabilities,
alpha star alpha up,
alpha star alpha down.
The computer now knows the probability for up and down.
And it also has a range.
It has a random number generator.
Random number generators are a dime a dozen,
and they work very well.
With a random number generator,
it then takes the probabilities alpha up and alpha down,
and spits out a number plus or minus one
with probability alpha star alpha and alpha star alpha.
So it just simulates the quantum mechanics
by having a random number generator
that either spits out plus one or minus one,
but with a probability that's given by alpha star alpha.
But then the computer then,
whatever the answer is,
whatever the answer that the apparatus spit out,
the computer then updates once again
the state of the spin
and says it is in
the state that the apparatus measured.
So if the apparatus spits
out plus one along some axis,
you get to turn the apparatus,
but when you get to turn the apparatus,
you have to do a slightly complicated calculation
to find out what the statistics are.
But once you've done it,
whatever the answer is,
the computer goes back and
updates the state of the spin
to make it consistent with what the apparatus measured.
You can do this.
You can try to write a program.
There's a program that could be written.
It's probably not even terribly complicated.
And...
if you only got to look at the measuring button,
decide to measure,
and look at the outcome,
you would get everything exactly equivalent
to the extent that a random number generator
can be a good faithful random number generator.
You would completely simulate the
quantum mechanics of the system.
The lesson is that quantum mechanics can be
a special case of classical physics.
So what's going on?
What the...
If quantum mechanics can be
a special case of classical mechanics,
what's all this confusion
about quantum mechanics being logically different?
All right.
Now we want to play the same game
with a pair of spins.
I just have one question.
You said that quantum mechanics...
You were trying to say quantum
mechanics is a special case of classical...
But I thought in classical everything was deterministic
in introducing probability.
Okay,
but it's...
Yeah,
yeah,
yeah.
But it's only...
This is a classical computer,
and it's using a classical number generator,
a classical random number generator.
All right?
So you do have to add in...
But the difference between quantum mechanics
and classical mechanics isn't randomness.
You can generate all sorts of random number generators
that would easily fool you
into thinking they were really random.
Of course,
any real random number generator,
the numbers come from somewheres,
so they're not strictly random.
But you can sure make a random number generator
that would fool anybody.
So,
yeah,
you can build a computer program
to simulate the quantum mechanics
basically of any system that you like
by the same method.
Okay?
But now supposing you wanted to simulate
a system consisting of two electrons.
There's two electrons,
two boxes here.
And you wanted to do it with two computers,
and in the process of taking the electrons apart,
you want to take the electrons apart from each other,
so as to ask this question about the...
You want to take the computers,
you want to encode the information
about Alice's spin in one computer
and Bob's spin in the other computer,
physically separate them,
and ask,
can these computers simulate quantum mechanics?
So I'll tell you what the answer is.
As long as the spins
as long as they start in a product state
and they don't interact with each other
and therefore stay in a product state,
then you can do it.
You can put all of the information
about Bob's spin in here,
all the information about Alice's spin in here.
Likewise,
you can have Bob's apparatus over here,
you can have Alice's apparatus over here,
little black boxes,
and it's just basically two identical versions
of what I said before.
You can take the computers,
physically separate them,
do experiments on each one,
and they will completely agree
with the results of quantum mechanics
because if they're in a product state,
one doesn't care about the other.
But then you say,
what if I wanted to put these two spins
in an entangled state?
Well,
first of all,
to put them in an entangled state,
you cannot do it without bringing the computers together.
Bringing the computers together
so that they talk to each other.
You can record in the combined computer system,
now that they're brought together,
how many numbers does it take
to specify the state of a two-spin system?
Six.
So,
you record six numbers in the computer here.
Six numbers are recorded in the computer,
and some numbers to reflect the orientations
of various apparatuses that you might conceive of.
And then you try to split the computer into two.
Keeping Alice's information in here
and Bob's information in here,
separate them and try to simulate
the quantum mechanics of the entangled system.
Bell's theorem is what tells you
that you cannot do this
unless there are instantaneous action
at a distance phenomena taking place between the com...
wires between the computer,
so to speak.
Hidden wires that have to be part of the system
connecting the computers together.
You cannot simulate the quantum mechanics
with a classical computer system.
You can't simulate the quantum mechanics
of an entangled system
unless it's really just one computer.
Really,
one computer means
that signals can be transmitted back and forth
basically instantly.
That's what Bell's theorem really says.
Now,
is this a form of nonlocality?
Well,
you might think that if to...
if you really have to have these wires there
to simulate quantum mechanics,
then why can't you send an instantaneous message
through these wires?
Of course,
you can.
But not if you only allow yourself
to do the things which quantum mechanics permits.
For example,
there are things
that quantum mechanics doesn't permit.
It doesn't allow you to measure
the X and Y component of a spin simultaneously.
All kinds of things that it
does not permit you to do
because they correspond to noncommuting operators.
If you restrict yourself to the measurements
which quantum mechanics allows you to do
on either one of these or any combination of them,
then it's a very magical and special fact
that you cannot send information
faster than the speed of light.
You cannot send information instantaneously
by this computer setup.
What if you assign not probabilities
but conditional probabilities?
Doesn't matter.
If you want to simulate a quantum system
with a classical system of computers,
and you want to study entangled systems,
the computers have to be able to communicate
with each other instantaneously.
That's the content of Bell's theorem.
Now,
does that mean that there's any action,
a spooky action at a distance,
or does it just mean that you've gotten yourself
into trouble by trying to simulate quantum mechanics
with classical mechanics?
My view is that you've gotten yourself into trouble
by trying to simulate something
which just doesn't want to be described
by a classical computer system,
and it's a deep and interesting fact
about quantum mechanics.
Einstein's view was that this is basically evidence
that the description is incomplete
and that there are other variables of the system,
and Bell's conclusion was those other variables
have to be hidden wires that connect distant places.
So,
you can take it for however you see it yourself.
Yes?
If you had a quantum computer there,
and let's say when you had the states...
If you had a quantum computer,
you could do it.
And you separated it,
right?
Now,
when you observe Bob's computer,
now you know something about Alice's,
right?
But you can't really still send it...
No,
it's the same problem.
But look,
all a quantum computer is,
is an electron in this computer
and an electron in this computer.
That's all it is.
It's just a quantum system.
It's just a true quantum system,
a quantum system in each one of these
which has been entangled.
That's all a quantum computer is.
It's a quantum mechanical system
which can reflect the logical structures
of quantum mechanics,
and the way you make it
is by actually making a
pair of entangled electrons in there.
Something real has been entangled between them,
and it can't be simulated by a fake computer program
unless the computer has this property of...
But you still have the
problem of transmitting that information somehow.
Oh,
no,
you have...
Sure,
sure,
right.
You could sort of hack this problem away
if you're using your analogy.
We said that there are pseudo-random generators
who are synchronized,
so...
Yeah,
they won't...
They are actually,
you know,
not...
Yeah.
They're going to be random.
They won't be...
They'll steer to the truth if you can't do that.
Yeah,
no,
but what you can't do...
What you can't do is synchronize them in advance
and then not let them interact with each other.
That won't do it.
The random numbers have to be...
Random number generators have to be such
that what this one measures
responds to what that one measured.
Like,
for example,
what I meant to say,
maybe I didn't explain it very well,
is that the random number generators
are synchronized at the beginning,
and whenever you measure,
because they're synchronized,
they will always generate up and down,
reversed.
No,
they lose the memory.
They lose what?
They lose the memory of the state.
No,
it's simply not enough.
This is what the theorem says.
It is not enough to synchronize them in advance
and then take them apart.
They've got to continue to interact with each other.
That's what it says.
That they must continue to interact with each other
and feed information back and forth.
Yeah.
I think,
I mean,
if there's...
Somebody...
Oh,
sorry.
No,
the problem with the delayed choice
is if you put a filter in Bob's instrument,
then instantaneously Alice's correlation is affected,
even if she is four light years away,
that's actually...
I told you everything I know about the system
and what I know about it,
and what I know about it
is that there's nothing Bob can do
which can influence the statistics of Alice's measurements
without sending her a measure.
It says that you have to depend instantaneously
on the setting of the distance of instruments.
Okay.
Yeah,
um...
All right.
One more minute.
Two more questions.
For good action at a distance of two separate computers,
I just find it interesting that
if you have a single computer,
are you saying that you can't do it?
Are you saying that you
could actually classically simulate quantum mechanics?
Yes.
You can classically simulate quantum mechanics,
but you basically have to
do it within a single computer
where all parts of it speak to every other part.
You cannot physically take them apart
the way you would want
to take the quantum systems apart.
I'm a little confused on being able to measure
the statistics of all versus the parts.
It seems like you're measuring the parts of the system,
Bob's making a measurement of the part,
Alice is making a measurement of the part,
but I think one mistake that you made was that
you don't know the entire system.
No.
In an entangled system,
Bob can do his measurements,
Alice can do her measurements.
But there are other things that can be measured
besides just the things that Alice would measure
on her system or the things that Bob would measure.
For example,
neither Bob nor Alice by themselves
can measure sigma x times tau x.
It takes both of them to do it.
It takes both detectives,
it takes both apparatuses
to make a measurement of sigma x times tau x.
This is something that you cannot measure.
Now you can measure it with two apparatuses.
The question is,
are there any things that you could measure
that you couldn't measure even with those two apparatuses?
And yes,
there are.
Sigma x tau x plus sigma y
tau y plus sigma z tau z.
is something that cannot even be measured
by using both apparatuses.
It takes a new kind of apparatus,
which is not a combination of Alice's and Bob's
original apparatuses,
which each measure a Bob thing and an Alice thing.
Bob cannot measure the entanglement.
Nobody can measure entanglement.
You have to talk to Alice
to know that there's an entanglement
involved in the system.
No,
Bob can discover,
that he's got the...
Nobody can do anything with one event.
But if you have a whole replication,
like I described over here,
where did I describe it,
where we have many replicas of the same thing,
many replicas of the same thing,
then Bob can discover the fact
that his state is entangled with something.
And the way he does it is he says,
let me search around for a direction in space
for which the spins are definitely aligned
in some direction.
Here's what he knows.
He knows that all the systems
were prepared in the same way.
They're all identical.
Each pair is identical to each other pair,
is identical to each other pair.
And he's wondering,
could each one of these be in a product state?
Same product state for this one,
same product state for that one,
same product state for that one.
If they're in a product state,
then Bob can search around.
He's got enough versions of it,
enough trials that he can go on and on
with experiments forever.
And he can search around for a direction
where when he measures the spin,
his spin,
he always discovers that it's up.
Now,
the first time he may be in the wrong direction
and he'll find down.
Next time he may find up,
he'll try it again.
It'll be down,
wrong direction.
And he keeps searching around.
If it's a product state,
he will eventually find a direction
where the spin will continue to be up,
up,
up
after he's found it.
If it's an entangled state,
no matter what direction he measures,
he will always find the spins are random.
Okay,
that's the character of it.
And that's on separate measurements,
right?
On separate discrete measurements,
not the measurement of the same thing.
No,
you've got to have an ensemble
of identical spin.
You've got to have identical systems
to do anything like this.
You just prepare each one the same way.
You do an experiment.
And he doesn't care about Alice.
He's just going to measure his spin along some axis.
Another axis,
another axis,
until he finds one where he keeps repetitively
getting the same answer.
And then he says that's the direction
that that spin is polarized.
And then he keeps doing it and finds consistency.
He'll never find that unless it's a product state.
So it's pretty...
pretty interesting stuff.
Hard stuff.
For more,
please visit us at stanford.edu.