This program is brought to you by Stanford University.
Please visit us at stanford.edu.
First of all, I want to show
you what difference a sign can make.
And in particular, the sign that occurs.
We've studied an entangled state of two electrons.
We could call it up-down.
And then there are two possibilities.
Well, there's more than two possibilities,
but there are two interesting
situations with a plus or minus.
In other words, you can take your choice.
We can study plus and we can study minus.
Plus, minus, down, up.
So this is two electrons.
And the state that we're writing
down is a linear superposition of states.
When one electron, one is up,
let's call this one, two.
Electron one is up, electron two is down.
So you know what that looks like.
It looks like this.
And in the other component of the state,
you just flip them over.
And we can superpose them with
a plus sign or a minus sign.
They don't sound so different.
In either case, there's a good
deal of correlation between the two spins.
If one of them is up,
then the other one is surely down.
And if one of them is down,
then the other one is surely up.
In both cases, the probability, incidentally,
nothing I'm going to say right now
is going to depend on whether we...
We should normalize it correctly.
In fact, let's put the normalization in.
Square root of two.
To make the probabilities add up to one.
In both cases, the sums...
Well, what was I going to say in both cases?
In both cases, the spins are opposite to each other.
Or the third component of
spin is opposite to each other.
So what is the big difference between these states?
And they're quite different.
They're quite different.
And we want to spend a little bit of time.
Explaining that.
Before I do, let me write a list again.
A list of the action of the various sigma operators.
It's the same list that I wrote last...
Same table that I wrote last time.
First of all, sigma one on up equals down.
We'll make reference to this regularly.
Sigma one on down equals up.
Sigma two on...
What is it?
Sigma two on up is, I believe, I times...
Times down.
But sigma two on down is minus I times up.
And sigma three on up is up.
And sigma three on down is minus down.
That's the action of the matrices
sigma one, sigma two, and sigma three
on the eigenstates of sigma three itself.
So we'll make reference to that list.
As we go along.
Now, in both of these states,
the expectation value of any component of the spin,
let's say sigma, we're going to remember now that
sigma refers to the first electron.
Tau, which is an identical family of operators,
identical except when it acts.
It acts on the second
spin instead of the first spin.
Sigma and tau are the two spin operators.
They're the two spin operators.
There's sigma one, sigma two, and sigma three.
And in either of these states,
the expectation value of any component
of sigma or tau is zero.
So there is no direction
in which either the first spin
or the second spin is definitely polarized.
There is no direction that you can pick
that you will know that the spin
has to come out up in that direction.
So this is the state of the spin.
And then, this is the state of the spin.
And the spin can be
a state that is, of course,
different than any state that you
would make for a single electron.
And so this is some sort of entangled state
that is not a simple juxtaposition
of a spin in the state
times another spin in its own state.
They're mixed together in some entangled way.
Okay.
So first of all, every component in this
state of the sigma i's are equal to zero.
And the tau i's are equal to zero.
And so you can see that the
spin of sigma i is equal to zero.
zero in this particular state and you can
check that. I think we checked it last time,
didn't we? I think you showed that for the
minus sign. Is it also true for the plus sign?
Yes, it's also true for the plus sign.
You want to do it? We can do it.
Let's just, it's quite obvious for sigma three.
For sigma three, there's one up electron and
one down electron. No, let's do it. Let's do
it. Why do I say that? Let's do it. Let's
do, all right, so we have to take the
bra vector up, down. Let's just write up, down,
plus, which one did you say I did?
Minus. Minus, okay, so let's do plus. Plus down,
up. Let's put a bracket around it or a
squiggle around it. And now let's take, well, let's
first take sigma three. And
then over here, up, down, plus.
Down, up. No, we've got to
write the bracket the other way.
And the square root of two doesn't matter here.
If it's zero, it'll be zero if we multiply
it by square root of two or whatever. Okay,
so what happens if we multiply this by sigma
three? Sigma three,
it's up and leaves it up. Sigma three hits
down and changes the sign, all right? So this
is just going to be up, down, minus, down,
up. And I can leave out the sigma three now
because I've just acted with the sigma three.
Times up, down, plus down, up. Okay, so the
inner product of,
up, down, with up, down is one. The inner
product of up, down, with down, up is zero.
They're different. They're opposite. So right here we
get a one from here and then a minus
one from here. Down, up with down, up again
is one, but there's a minus sign, so we get
zero. Now, this does not mean that these
states are eigenvectors of sigma three with eigenvalue
zero.
It means the expectation value of sigma three
is zero. There's no eigenvectors of sigma three
with eigenvalue zero. You can never get zero for
one of the spins. You can only get plus
or minus one. So it doesn't mean that when
you measure any of the spins you get zero.
What it means is that it's a, measuring the
spin is a fair coin toss where you get ups
as much as you get
downs in equal amount, equal probability.
Okay, now, I want to come to the
difference. And the difference you can see most easily
by considering an operator which is the sum
of both spins. In other words, the spins represent
little vectors, little pointers, excuse me,
little pointers. Sigma might point that direction.
Tau might point that direction. They represent
little magnetic moments. We could think about
the magnetic moment of the combined system which
is simply the vector sum of the two
magnetic moments or the two spins. And so
it's interesting then to look at the operator
sigma one, sigma plus tau, the three components
of it, all three components of it. All right,
let's see what the, let's see what
sigma plus tau do to the spin.
So let's look at these two states. First of
all, what is the action of sigma three plus
tau three on up down plus down up? Oops,
up down, sorry, plus minus down up. All right,
the answer is zero. Why is that? Well, first
of all, let's look at the, let's look at the
spin. Well, one reason is obvious. In up,
the spin, the third component of sigma three
is up. In down, the component of tau three
is down. So they add up to zero, but let's
just check it. Sigma three acting on up gives
plus up. Tau three acting on down gives minus.
So sigma three plus tau three
acting on up down gives minus.
Now sigma three acting on up will give zero.
Sigma three acting on up gives plus. Tau three
acting on down gives minus. And so sigma
three plus tau three definitely equals 0 for the
left-hand state. And also for the right-hand one
over here. So the conclusion is that either
of these states, in fact, just the
two separate components here, are both eigenvectors of
sigma three plus tau three with eigenvalues zero.
That means if you measure sigma 3
plus tau 3, you will always get zero
for either of these states
That's not surprising, since one
is up and one is down
Now what about sigma 1 plus
tau 1? Let's do that little exercise
Sigma 1 plus tau 1, this is the sum
of the first component, the x component of spin
Let's see if we can work out what
it does to up down plus minus down up
Okay, let's start with sigma 1.
What does sigma 1 do to up?
It turns it down, right?
Okay, so sigma 1, let's
write out everything that comes here
Sigma 1 on up down gives us
down down
and sigma 1 and tau
1 on up down gives minus
No, sorry, tau 1 on down gives up, sorry
So tau 1 gives up up, plus up up
That's what we get by applying sigma
1 plus tau 1 to up down
Sigma 1 flips up down and makes down down
Tau 1 flips down up and makes up up
With a plus sign because, with a plus mark
No, with a plus sign, the
plus sign is this sign here
Then we have plus or minus
Okay, then we have plus or minus
Let's see what sigma 1 does, sigma
1 acts on down to give up
up
and then plus minus down down
Tau 1 flips up down and gives you down down
Okay, plus minus is the same plus minus that's here
Okay
Alright, so it's quite clear that
if we take the plus sign
we don't get zero
If we take the plus sign we don't get zero
we just get twice down down
plus twice up up
The implication is that if you were to measure
Well, the implication is that this is not an eigenvector
of the sum of sigma 3 plus tau 3
You will not get zero every time you measure it
even though its expectation value happens to be zero
If you measure it sometimes you'll get
What are the possible values you can get?
Sigma 3 can be plus or minus 1
Tau 3 can be plus or minus 1
So it's clear the answer
can be 2, 0 or minus
Oh, sorry
2, 0 or minus 2
Is that right? That's all you can get, right?
Yeah
But there would be no reason
and in fact it's quite clear
that you can't, that you
don't get zero every single time
because this is not an eigenvector
of tau 1 plus sigma 1
with eigenvalue zero
So we can be quite
sure then that this operator here
does not give zero every time you measure it
Just because it is not an eigenvector in this state
Just because it's not an eigenvector with eigenvalue zero
What about with the minus sign?
Well, we have a minus sign in here
With a minus sign in here
that means we should put minuses
and the answer does vanish
Down, down, minus, down, down, up, up, minus, up, up
equals zero
So the state with the minus sign in here
Let's concentrate on that one now
The state with the minus 1 here
Every single time you measure sigma 1 plus tau 1
you get zero
Every single time you measure sigma 3 plus tau 3
There's two separate electrons
One of them you measure sigma
The other one you measure tau
You add the answers
sigma 1 plus tau 1
or sigma 2 plus tau 2
or whatever it is you measure
You always get zero
for the sums of the third components
and for the sums of the first components
What about the second component?
Let's check that one
And I won't do it for plus or minus now
We've already checked that sigma 1 plus tau
1 does not kill up, down, plus, down, up
Let's see what happens if we
put sigma 2 plus tau 2
on the same vector
Up, down, minus, down, up
Alright, first of all what does sigma 2 do?
Sigma 2 multiplies the up here
and makes it i times down
So the first entry will be i times down, down
That's from sigma 2 times this
Now what about tau 2 times this?
Tau 2 takes down and flips it up
with a minus i
So that's minus i up, up
Now what about tau 2?
Tau 2 takes down and flips
it up with a minus i
So that's minus i down, down
And then with a minus sign
with another minus sign here
Tau 2 takes up to down
Let's see, am I doing what I want to do?
Where am I?
We already have two down, downs
Tau 2
Which one am I trying to do?
Tau 2 should be up, up
Up, up, that's this one
Yeah
And that should be
should be i times up up.
Plus i times up up.
So again, it gives zero.
All components of sigma
give zero. Furthermore,
if I were to take, let's call it
sigma dot tau, it's a little vector, sigma plus
tau, not that,
and dot it into some unit vector to take
the component in any direction.
Well, those things are built up out of
sigma one plus tau one, sigma two plus tau two,
and sigma three plus tau three.
So basically we've checked that all three
components of sigma plus tau are zero,
and therefore sigma plus tau in any direction,
whatever direction you measure it in,
you will get zero.
For the negative?
Yeah, for the negative sign. The
negative sign is called the singlet state.
Why it's called the singlet?
Well, the singlet state maybe we'll get to,
but for the moment it's called the singlet state.
And it has the property that
the sums of the little magnetic moments,
the sums of the spins of the
two particles are exactly equal to zero
every time you measure it in any direction.
It happens to have the
property that it's rotationally invariant.
No matter what direction you measure
it in, it always looks the same.
But we see that in particular, specifically from
looking at the various components of sigma plus tau,
they're all,
zero.
Okay.
The implication of that of course is
that if you measure
a component of sigma,
you'll instantly know what the same component of tau is.
In other words, if we have an electron over there,
Alice's electron over there, and Bob's electron over here,
and Bob measures any component of the spin,
he instantly knows what Alice will get
if she measures the same component of spin.
So he won't necessarily know what's gotten
by measuring some other component of the spin,
but what he does know is if he measures
any component of the spin and gets an answer,
he instantly knows what Alice will
get when she measures the other spin.
Why?
Because the sums of the spins
in any direction are equal to zero.
All right.
So that's a...
Yeah.
When you say same answer, you mean
literally the same
um,
one of,
minus one plus one, or
on the average, they will
get the same number of spins?
Every single time.
And the reason is, because this vector
is an eigenvector of sigma plus tau,
when it's an eigenvector, that tells
you that every time you measure it,
in that state,
you get the same answer,
equal to the eigenvalue.
What's that?
That's for the singlet state.
For the singlet state, yeah.
But not for the...
The other one is called the triplet state.
Why?
Another issue we'll come to another day.
So the singlet state has the special property
that if you measure one spin, you automatically know
that the other one is in the opposite direction.
Okay?
Meaning to say,
you know you never measure the direction of a spin,
you measure a component of a spin.
Any component of a spin that you
measure, you measure the direction of a spin.
If you measure the same component of
the other spin, you'll get the opposite answer.
Okay?
So that's a form of correlation.
It's kind of similar to the penny and the dime.
If I give Alice one
coin and Bob the other coin...
Alice looks at a coin,
she instantly knows what Bob gets.
But it's somehow deeper than that.
It's not just the third component, the up-downness,
but every single component
whichever one you happen to pick
in any direction, whatever, the two
spins will come out to be opposite
okay, that's a profound kind of correlation
that's called Einstein-Podolsky-Rosen correlation
were Einstein, Podolsky, and Rosen
the first ones to discover entanglement?
no, not at all
I believe Schrödinger first discussed it, I think
in fact, I think he called it entanglement
and I think that was before
but in any case, let's go on
I want to go slowly
I next want to come to Bell's famous theorem
I can tell you the theorem is famous, what I
can't tell you is whether or not it's profound or trivial
not Bell's theorem, but Bell's inequality and
the fact that quantum mechanics violates it
I cannot tell you, half the days of the week
I think this is the most profound thing in the world
and the other half of the days I
say, oh it's just another consequence of quantum mechanics
what I can tell you is that John
Bell had exactly the same ambivalence to it
at least when I knew him
and I can tell you also that
Richard Feynman had the same ambivalence to it
some of the times it just
seems so profound and so deep
and other times it just seems like,
well it's a trivial consequence of quantum mechanics
of course it's true
you'll have to make up your own mind
whether you think it's very very profound or not
it gets a lot of press that
it's the most profound thing since Swiss cheese
and sometimes, you know, it may well be
in the end it's going to depend on
what the consequences of it are for Feynman
and for future physics
at the moment, the consequences are
just quantum mechanics works, that's all
and so without further ado, let's discuss
the theorem itself is quite trivial
it excludes other theories
it probably, yeah
it excludes quantum mechanics
the theorem excludes quantum mechanics
the theorem excludes non-quantum mechanics
no, the theorem excludes quantum mechanics
in quantum mechanics you can
find violations of Bell's inequality
Bell's inequality is an absolutely classical theorem
it's a theorem about classical systems
completely classical systems
and when I derive it now
I don't want you to
remind me anything about quantum mechanics
because it doesn't have to do with quantum mechanics
we're going to derive a theorem about
perfectly good classical logic
what is classical logic?
classical logic is basically set theory
ummm
yes
no paradox yet
I mean, so far we've just
does that violate quantum causality?
is that a separate issue?
no
it would violate causality if you
could use it to send a message
if by Bob looking at the spin
Alice were to instantly know
something that she didn't know before
that would violate causality
but she doesn't
she doesn't know anything different than
she has no more information than she had before
for example
if in this state
her spin half the time will be
up and half the time will be down
that'll be true
Bob may measure his spin
she doesn't know anything
she'll look at her spin
half the times it'll be up
half the times it'll be down
if she gets a message from Bob
and the message says
my spin is up
then she knows that her spin is down
but she's got to get that message
and that message can't be gotten
faster than the speed of light
are there any time
any inertial time
time frames for
one is the time of the other
and one is
Bob measures first
Alice measures first
is that my fault?
no, no, no, no
whatever Bob does
if Alice doesn't get a message from Bob
if she doesn't get a message from Bob
there are no implications for anything for her
she'll still
she will have learned nothing
from the fact that Bob made the measurement
she'll know nothing
she has to get a message from Bob
to use the information that he has
if he sends her a message
I got up
then she knows it's down
but
without that message being sent
she doesn't know anything new
so
this is in no way a violation of
causality
locality
or anything like that
that's one of the reasons that
half the days of the week
I think this isn't so profound
it doesn't violate anything deep or important
in
a review
the singlet state is when you have the minus sign
and the eigenvalues are plus or minus two or zero
I
no, you measure sigma plus tau
in the singlet state you get zero
in any direction, any component
it's in the triplet state which
is the one with the plus
where if you measure it you can get
two zero
or
minus one
or minus two
excuse me
okay so let me tell you what Bell's theorem is
it's a very simple theorem
supposing we have some objects
all a collection of them
a set of things
and we look at the class
of the objects that have certain properties
and I'm going to consider three properties
I'm going to call them A, B and C
whatever they happen to be
they could stand for anything
any properties A, B and C
let me write down the inequality first
in other words each one of these little things
whatever it is
here's some set
and each member of the set has
an A, a B and a C
it has these properties
now we can
I'm interested in the number
of entities
which have property A
and
not B
not B is whatever the opposite of B is
alright so
whatever the opposite of B is
the number of things which have property A
and not B
plus the number of things
that have property B
and not C
and the classical theorem which is so easy
that I've never understood why there
are long long winded proofs of it
it's basically very elementary
is greater than or equal to
the number of things with property A
and not C
okay
the number of things with A and not B
plus the number of things with B and not C
is greater than or equal to the
number of things with A and not C
how do you prove this?
you prove it by drawing pictures
for one reason or another
in all the literature that I can find
they never draw a picture
alright
let's draw the set
or let's delineate the set
which has property A
the subset which has property A
here's the subset which has property A
well let me do it the
way I have it in my notes
so I don't
so I don't screw up
yeah
alright
here's A over here
let's call it A
now
where is the subset B?
the subset B may or may not intersect A
if it intersects A it
means they have elements in common
if it doesn't intersect A it
means they don't have elements in common
but here's the subset B
and if B has no elements in common with A
it just means that this region over here is zero
that there's nothing in here
alright
but in general there'll be something in here
which will be those things
which have both A and B
and finally C
here's C
now again C may or may not
have elements in common with A or B
if it doesn't you just
move it over a little bit
so that it doesn't have elements
in common with A, B, and C
but the most general situation is that
it does have elements in common
but you can always
you lose nothing by pretending it has elements in common
because you can always at the end say that
the elements in common are just a null set
there are just none of them
okay now
let's also label
put some color in here
let's also label all these
various individual little sub-regions here
let's see what I call them
okay this region I call the sub-region of A
and this one out here is just one
what is that?
that's all of A which is neither B nor C
and I'm just going to label
all the various sub-areas in here
three
four
five
six
and seven
and of course there may be some
elements which have neither A, B, or C
and they'll be out here
but I don't even need to write
those down because I'm not interested in them
okay
let's take the number of elements
that have A and not B
that has A but does not have B
what is that?
that's region one and two
if it has A but it doesn't have B
that means it's A but exclude anything that has B
and that means that it's the number that's
in one plus the number that's in two
everybody see that?
okay
so the first thing here is that it's a
number that's in one plus the number that's in two
so the first thing here is N1 plus N2
that's N A not B
now what about the number of
systems which has B but not C
so we go over to B
and we exclude those that have C
five and six have C
so in looking at B
the things which have B but not C
B but not C
what are those?
that's plus
things which have B but not C
four and seven
four and seven right?
plus N4 plus N7
now what about N and not
what about A and not C?
A and not C is one and four?
A and not C is one and four
did I get that right?
sorry what I want to write
here is greater than or equal to
and then seven and not C
no I wrote something wrong
A and not C
four plus N7
say it again
this one and which one which one
and seven
right?
do I have it right? I think so yes
alright
well obviously this is a number that's
in one plus the number that's in two
here's N1 here's N4
obviously N1 and all the N's are positive
I mean there's no such thing
as a negative number of elements
alright N1 plus N2 plus N4 plus
N7 is certainly bigger than N1 plus N4
or equal to it
at worst it's equal to it
that's Bell's theorem that's the whole thing
that's it
what's amazing is that it's violated
it can be violated
it's profound
the violation is profound
yeah but all of quantum mechanics
violates classical physics so I mean
yeah
I
as I said I've always been ambivalent and
I'm never going to get unambivalent about it
I'll die being ambivalent to it
so you get into a quantum
state yourself when you think about it
that's when I start thinking it's profound yeah
okay
let's now take our system to be two spins
let's take our system to be two spins
and then we'll define the various properties A and B
A, B, and C
which we'll think of
incidentally we're still doing we're doing we're
imagining let's see what we imagine well
yeah
we'll first pretend
that the spins are classical
and that you can measure them
as if they were classical objects
and we'll write down what Bell's inequality says
for the system of two spins
the only thing you need to know
and you have to keep track of
I'm going to talk about spin one
I'm only going to talk about spin one
but what I'm going to say
is we're going to say things like
here might be a proposition
a proposition might be that spin one
let's see I guess uh
how did I label this
spin one is up
along z-axis
along the third axis
that could be some proposition
well I can
the negative of it
is spin one is not up along the third axis
but of course that's the same as
saying it's down along the third axis
but if spin one is
measured down along the third axis
then you can be sure that
two is up along the third axis
so the negative
in the singlet state
in the singlet state we're putting
the electrons into the singlet state
alright
and if classical logic if ordinary logic made any sense
here's what we would do
we would measure we have a whole beam of these
of these electron pairs
zillions of them zillions of pairs
which are each correlated in this fashion
separate from each other
and you measure the first hundred thousand
of them
in every possible direction
you measure sigma one and tau one
you measure sigma three and tau three
for many many of them
and you convince yourself after
a long tedious bunch of experiments
that every time you measure a component of this spin
and you measure a component of the same
the same component of the other spin
that they're always opposite to each other
in that case I think we would all agree
that
that the negative
of saying or the opposite of saying a is up
is saying that b is up
because if a is down then b is up
so the negative of a proposition about one spin
becomes the positive statement
about the other spin
the negative of spin one
spin what is it called a or one I forgot
the negative of calling this spin one is up
the negative of calling this spin
the negative of this spin being up
is the spin down
but then it's the same as
saying that this spin is up
so we just have to keep track of what
of the relationship between these various propositions
okay we're going to write down
what a b and c are
a
and we're only going to talk about spin one
at first
but then we're going to use spin two
to tell us something about spin one
all right
so a is up
along three axis
that's a
okay
b
this equal sign here just means is the statement
is the statement
that spin one is up along the third axis
b
is that spin one is up
along a forty five degree angle
the forty five degree angle
could be in the um
in the zx plane
in the zx plane for example
let's take it to be in the zx plane
so b says spin one is up along
the forty five degree angle in the zx plane
and c
says that
one is up
along
the ninety degree direction
in the xy plane
in the uh zy
in the zx plane
okay so here's our picture
a says that the spin
is up along the third axis
b
says that it's
lies at forty five degrees along the uh
uh
zx plane
and c
says that the spin is up along the third axis
uh
along the forty
along that axis
and c says that it lies
at ninety degrees along that axis
a b c
okay
now what about
not b
let's take not
well first of all let's take not a
i don't think we need not a for anything
we will need not b
not b
says that one does not lie
reveal
b
A
it says that
is that 2 is up along the 45 degree.
Okay, you get the idea?
Same thing for C, not C,
is that 2 is up along 90 degrees.
Okay, so now we can plug into here
what these various statements say.
Hmm?
Down.
2 is down along 90.
No?
No.
Not C.
Let's see.
C says that 1 is up along the 90.
Not C says 1 is down along the 90,
but then 2 is up.
Okay?
So whatever the statement is,
the not of the statement
is the original statement
except made on the other spin.
Okay?
Is that clear?
The other spin is in the opposite direction.
That's all it says.
So whatever a not statement is,
it becomes a yes statement
about the other spin.
Okay.
So let's write down what this says.
All right, this says the number of pairs,
the entities now are pairs of electrons.
Pairs of electrons.
This becomes then
the number of
pairs
with spin up.
Let's call it
spin 1 is up
along,
up at 0 degrees.
Up
at 0 degrees.
And the other spin,
let's see, we want not B.
Not B is that the other spin
is up along the 45 degree angle.
All right?
So the second spin,
this is the first spin.
Here I'm writing in the second spin.
Up along 45 degrees.
All right?
A is that spin 1
is up along the third axis.
And not B is that spin
2 is up along 45 degrees.
It should be 2.
Hmm?
You should say 2 there.
Yeah, this stands for electron 1.
This stands for electron 2.
Okay?
The first entry here is electron 1.
The second entry here is electron 2.
Next.
B not C.
Now, I don't have to worry about B not C.
And I'll tell you why.
It's got to be exactly
the same as A not B.
Why is that?
Um, B, A not B and B not C are
simply related by rotating by, uh, by, by 45 degrees.
Anything I can say about A and not B will be exactly the same
as B and not C because they're identical to each other except for a rotation.
Okay?
And, uh, the singlet state doesn't change
if you rotate it by 45 degrees.
That's, uh, that's the main thing about it.
It doesn't change when you rotate.
We saw that by seeing that the spin,
total spin is the same in every direction.
So in fact, uh, we can
just take this to be twice.
The sum of this and this are just twice the
number of up at 0 degrees and down at 45 degrees.
So, um, I'm going to give you a little
bit of a, a little bit of a rough idea.
I'm going to give you a little bit
of a rough idea of what this is.
So, uh, I'm going to give you a little
bit of a rough idea of what this is.
So, uh, we can rotate
the spin, uh, by 45 degrees.
And we can see that the spin is always going
to be at 0 degrees and down at 45 degrees.
And Bell's theorem, if it were true, would tell
us that this is greater than, necessarily greater than,
greater than or equal to the number
of pairs with the property that they're up.
Uh.
Yeah.
Yeah, C is up along 90 degrees.
Um.
A is 1 up at, along 3.
Along 0.
What's that?
Along the Z axis.
1 up at 0.
Yeah, okay, so right.
A is 1 is up at 0 degrees.
And not C means 2 is up along 90 degrees.
2 is up at 90 degrees.
Well, now we have something we can test.
Incidentally, counting the number of them is the same
as counting the probability for these things to be true.
If we have a large number of identical things in
an ensemble, measuring the number is just measuring the probability.
Okay, if we have 100,000 pairs,
the number which has a certain property,
is just a certain percentage of 100,000, which
is given, the percentage is given by the probability.
Okay, so here's the question.
In the singlet state, what is the probability, what
are these various probabilities, the probability for, uh, for,
first electron to be up at 0 degrees and
the second electron to be up at 45 degrees.
How do we calculate that?
Alright.
I want to, here's a question.
I'm going to tell you the answer right now.
The answer right now is that this
is less than this when you calculate it.
We're going to calculate it.
But this is less than this and it simply
violates the very, very elementary theorem that, uh, that Bell,
it's hardly a theorem, it's just
a very simple observation about, uh, probabilities.
Okay.
Um.
Let's see if we can calculate these things.
What I need to do in order to calculate
them efficiently is to teach you about projection operators.
So let me tell you what a projection operator is.
And let me give you an alternative definition
of the probability, uh, uh, postulate of quantum mechanics.
A projection operator, it's labeled like
that, projection operator, P for projection operator,
has a number of properties.
But first I'm going to tell you what it,
I'll give you a picture of what it does.
What it would do, an
ordinary projection operator in three-dimensional space,
if my vector space happened to
be just vectors in three dimensions,
then there are subspaces.
A subspace of three-dimensional
space could be zero-dimensional,
that's just a point, just the origin, nothing at all.
It could be a one-dimensional subspace, which is
just a line sticking out of the origin,
or a two-dimensional subspace, which is
a plane passing through the origin.
Okay.
Um, if you like, it's the
space which is, well, you get it,
if you have a pair, a two-dimensional vector
space would be take any pair of vectors,
and think of all the vectors that you
can make by adding these two with arbitrary coefficients.
All those vectors will lie in
the plane of those two vectors.
That's the subspace which is spanned by two vectors.
If I have only one vector, and
I want it, but that's a one-dimensional subspace,
then it's all the vectors that lie along a line.
If you have a higher
dimensional subspace, then, uh, I'm sorry,
a higher dimensional space, then you can have subspaces
up to the dimensionality of one less than the, uh,
than the space itself.
All right, what is a projection operator?
A projection operator, in particular a
projection operator onto a one-dimensional space,
is a projection operator.
It's an operator which takes any vector,
and takes its projection onto that subspace,
and gives you the vector which
is the projection along the subspace,
uh, of the original vector.
It's an operator, so it will operate on a vector,
it's called alpha,
to give you the projection along the subspace,
uh, of the original vector.
It's called alpha, to give you the projection,
let's call it alpha sub p, onto the appropriate subspace.
If the subspace is this line here,
then it would act on any vector
to give you the projection onto that subspace.
Okay.
So that's what it does.
It takes away, it removes the components of a vector
in directions perpendicular to the subspace.
It just chops them out and removes them.
Okay.
Um,
let's see.
How about projection onto a two-dimensional subspace?
A simple two-dimensional subspace would just be,
let's say, the, uh, x-y plane.
Just the x-y plane here would be a two-dimensional subspace.
If I have an arbitrary vector,
then it just projects onto the plane,
and gives you the projection onto the plane.
Okay.
That's the notion of a projection operator.
Now,
suppose we have some properties,
that we're interested in.
The property is,
let's take the property to be,
the spin is up along the third axis.
There's an eigenvector that goes with that.
The up eigenvector along the third axis.
Therefore, there's a projection operator
that goes with that statement.
The statement that the spin is up along the x-axis
corresponds to a projection operator.
It's the projection operator which projects onto
the eigenvector in which the spin
is up along the third axis.
Okay.
So, what does it do?
It takes any state,
the projection operator that projects onto spin being up,
for one spin, let's just talk about one spin.
What is that?
It's an operator which takes any vector,
let's call it alpha-beta,
and what does it give?
This is projection onto sigma-3 equals one.
What does it give?
How high it is?
How far it intersects the what?
The vertical axis?
No, it just throws away beta.
It just throws it away.
Beta is orthogonal.
The state with the lower entry here is orthogonal
to the state in which the spin is up.
Okay?
So, all it does is it
takes the spin,
and it's going to project onto the third axis.
It picks out the component of the vector
along the particular property that you're interested in.
So, it just gives you alpha-0.
It throws away the piece of the vector
that has to do with spin being down.
What does P3 equal minus, sorry,
P3, P sigma-3 equals minus one
do on the same vector?
It throws away alpha.
All right, here's an alternative formulation.
What's that?
Sigma-3.
Sigma-3 equals minus one, excuse me.
Okay.
Incidentally, P is an operator.
It operates on a vector to give a new vector.
There must be a matrix that goes with it.
Let me tell you what the matrix is.
Okay.
The projection operator onto sigma-3 equals plus one.
That's the matrix one, zero, zero, zero.
Let's check that.
Suppose that acts on alpha-beta.
What does it give?
It gives one times alpha.
And zero times beta.
Zero times beta.
Okay.
So that's true.
There's another way to write it,
which is going to be very efficient.
We're going to find it very, very useful
to write this operator in the form
sigma-3 plus one divided by two.
Let's check that.
Sigma-3 is one minus one, zero, zero,
plus one, which is one, one, zero, zero.
The one place, the lower element here vanishes,
minus one plus one, and then divide by two.
Okay.
So in the upper entry here,
you get one plus one is two,
divided by two, that's one.
And every place else you get zero.
All right.
This is a useful fact,
that the projection operator onto a configuration
where the third component of spin is plus
is just sigma-3 plus one divided by two.
Okay.
What about things like sigma-1 or sigma-2?
What's that?
What about projections corresponding to sigma-1 or sigma-2?
Yeah.
Okay, so now let's ask that question.
What would you expect the answer
to be if I asked you,
what's the projection operator
that projects onto the eigenvector sigma-1 equals plus one?
Sigma-1 plus one over two?
Exactly.
This is projection operator for,
let's just call it projection operator for sigma-3.
Here's projection operator for sigma-1.
And by that I mean that
sigma-1 is equal to plus one.
That's just equal to sigma-1 plus one over two.
You can check that.
Easy to check.
It's very easy to check.
That's the projection operator.
So let me give you now an alternative definition
of the probability postulate of quantum mechanics.
If you have a state, an arbitrary state,
let's call it psi,
and you're interested in the probability
that a certain thing is true,
or that you measure it
you construct the projection operator,
and you call it the
projection operator for that certain thing.
You call it p.
The expectation value of the projection operator
is the probability for that thing.
Probability for alpha.
Let's just check that for a simple case.
Supposing again psi is just alpha beta,
is just a vector alpha beta,
and p3 is sigma-3 plus one.
So here we have alpha beta.
We have sigma-3 plus one divided by two,
and then we have alpha star beta star.
This is the expectation value of the projection operator.
What do we get?
Well, what does sigma-3 do on this vector here?
It multiplies the alpha by one
and the beta by minus one.
So what it gives,
when sigma-3 plus one divided by
two acts on this vector here,
it just gives something simple.
Sigma-3 plus one divided by
two gives plus one on alpha,
and what does it give?
It gives zero on beta, right?
It just gives zero.
We already know what it does.
It just gives this.
Times alpha star beta star.
This is just equal to alpha star alpha.
So this is an example
where calculating the expectation value
of a projection operator gives you the probability,
in this case, for the spin to be up.
So this is an alternative
definition of the probability assumption.
If you're interested in a certain proposition,
alpha is true,
you construct the projection operator for alpha
in the way that I showed you.
It's the projection operator onto the direction,
which is the eigenvector corresponding to the proposition,
and then you just calculate its expectation value.
That gives you the probability.
Very simple.
An alternative route to getting to probabilities.
All right, so now we have everything we need
to calculate the various probabilities
that are in this expression here.
Shall I stop for a minute?
Let's stop for a little bit.
I'm probably getting a headache by now.
Okay, look, let me simplify what I said
down to what you just said.
I'm going to go back to what's bare essentials.
Projection operators correspond to statements.
Well, let me go back a step.
Classical physics.
Statements are subsets.
Properties are subsets of a set.
The set of all things,
we start with the set of all things.
The set of all things such that,
that's a subset.
The basic ideas of intersection and union
and all those kind of things
about sets and subsets are classical logic.
That's what classical logic is about.
The classical logic of propositions.
Propositions mean properties.
Properties of systems in physics.
In quantum mechanics,
a very, very different setup.
Propositions do not correspond to subsets.
They correspond to subspaces of a vector space.
Subspaces of a vector space
are a very different thing
than subsets of a set.
And therein lies the very big differences.
And therein we're going to see,
allows us to calculate,
well, we're going to use the fact
that properties correspond to projection operators.
Or you can say that they correspond to subspaces.
The subspace of states which has this or that property.
And for our purposes now,
the only projection operators
that I'm going to be interested in
are the ones which correspond to spin
in a given direction being up.
Okay, so let's...
Okay, the projection operator for...
Let's start with...
Where's our...
Anybody remember what A, B, and C were?
I don't. Oh, yes, here it is.
A was the first spin is up
along the third axis.
What's the projection operator for this?
It's sigma 3
plus 1
divided by 2.
That's only half the statement, though.
The second spin is up along the 45 degree axis.
Alright, what is the projection operator for that?
Anybody know?
The 45 degree axis.
What's the spin...
What's the component of spin along the 45 degree axis,
first of all?
1 squared of 2, I don't know.
It's something like tau 1 plus tau 3, right?
I mean, it's along an
axis halfway between 1 and 3.
Alright?
So that's tau 1 plus tau 3,
but that's not quite right.
What's wrong with it?
It's normalizing.
1 over the square root of 2.
Here's what we're doing.
We're taking n, the unit vector along 45 degrees,
and dotting it into tau.
Alright, what's the components of n along 45 degrees?
They're 1 over the square root of 2.
So this is tau 1
over the square root of 2
plus tau 3 over the square root of 2.
That's the component of tau along 45 degree axis.
Alright, so it's the projection operator for...
for the second statement here,
is tau 1 plus tau 3 plus...
over the square root of 2 plus 1.
What I'm using is that the
projection operator for sigma dot n
is just...
is just sigma dot n, the projection operator,
is sigma dot n plus 1 over 2.
That projects you onto the subspace in
which sigma dot n is plus 1.
Yeah, whole thing has to be divided by 2.
Thank you.
Good.
Okay.
Now,
if you apply both projection operators,
to a state,
this one acts on the first spin,
and projects the state onto the component,
or it acts only on the first spin,
and takes away anything in which sigma
dot 3 is in the wrong direction.
And then if you act with this one second,
it takes away anything on the second spin,
which is in the wrong direction.
So the whole projection operator
that corresponds to this combined statement,
that...
that the first spin is up along 0 degrees,
the second spin is up along 45 degrees,
is just the product of these two.
You act first with one of them,
that throws away everything in the
state vector that's in the wrong...
in the wrong direction in the space of states.
And then you act with the other one,
that throws away everything that's in the wrong direction,
corresponding to the other spin.
So the product of these two
is the projection operator that projects out,
or that projects for you,
up along 0 degrees for the first spin,
and up along 45 degrees for the second spin.
And remember, that's A and not B.
Not B because B...
you remember, B corresponds to up along...
up along the 45 degree axis.
Not B corresponds to down along the 45 degree axis.
But then we look at
particle 2 instead of particle 1,
and particle 1 always has the opposite spin.
So it becomes up along the 45 degree axis,
for spin number 2.
This is the projection operator for this object,
for this property over here.
For the property that A and not B.
Okay?
All right, its expectation value
in the singlet state corresponds to the...
to the probability for A and not B.
All right, so all we can do...
there's only one way to do this,
and that's to just hold your breath and start writing
and working out the details one by one.
I'm going to do it.
This is tedious.
It's...
It may bore you.
You can close your eyes,
and I'll tell you what the answer is,
but you might as well see how it's done
for those who are really interested.
For those who aren't interested,
no, that's...you can go home.
Okay, so let's write down the singlet state here.
The singlet state is up down,
minus down up,
and now we better put
in the square root of 2.
Now, later on,
we're going to take the
inner product of what we have
and project it back onto the same vector.
So later on, we're going
to project back onto the singlet.
All right, but for now,
I just want to calculate what this operator does
when it hits this state.
Okay, it's actually not too bad.
First of all, what does sigma 3 do?
First of all, what does sigma 3
plus 1 do to this over here?
Hmm?
Yeah, it just throws this away.
Why?
Because in this state here, the first spin is down.
But this is the projection operator
onto the first spin being up.
So when sigma 3 plus 1 over 2
acts on a state where the first spin is down,
it just kills it.
So we might as well get rid of that.
Okay, and now we've done it.
We've used sigma 3 plus 1 over 2.
So we can now rewrite this.
I won't erase it, but I'll write it.
We can get rid of this.
We've acted with it,
and it just kills the second entry here.
The rest of it is tau 1 plus tau 3
over 2 root 2 plus 1 half,
all acting on 1 over the square root of 2.
Let's put another 1 over the
square root of 2 out here.
That's this one.
And then that acts on up down.
Okay, what does it do?
First of all, what does tau 1 do?
Tau 1 flips.
Now remember, taus act on the second entry.
Tau 1 flips down to up.
So when tau 1 acts, it gives up up here.
Okay?
What's in here?
Is there anything with up up in here?
No.
No, nothing with up up in here.
All there is is up down and down up.
So that means when tau 1 acts,
it gives something which is completely orthogonal
to what's on the left-hand side.
It won't contribute.
When we take the inner product with the singlet,
when tau 1 occurs and
acts on down to give up,
it'll give something on the right-hand side
that just doesn't appear in the corresponding bra vector.
So we can be quite sure then
that tau 1 will have no expectation,
will just not contribute to this inner product.
I can throw it away.
What does tau 3 do to this?
Does it add up?
Is it minus down?
the second state, that's sigma 3 plus 1,
and the tau operation here just gives this number.
Now that's not quite true, there's another
piece, there's the up-up piece, but the up-up
piece will not have anything to
take it in a product with.
Alright, let's write down the singlet state on this side.
The singlet state on this side is up-down
minus down-up, divided by square root of 2.
Well, the down-up configuration won't contribute.
It's orthogonal to up-down.
Down-up is orthogonal to up-down,
so this one will not contribute.
We can get rid of it.
The inner product of up-down with itself is just 1.
So the whole thing is just given by these
numbers, 1 over square root of 2, 1 over square
root of 2.
1 over square root of
2 and this beast over here.
This is the probability for A and not B.
So what is it?
1 over square root of 2, and it's 1 half,
1 half minus 1 over 2 square root of 2.
Anybody can do numbers quick in their head?
1 fourth of square root
of 2 minus 1 over 2.
Yeah, 1 fourth of, what do you have,
1 minus 1 over square root of 2?
Is that right?
Alright, 1 over square root of 2 is about 0.7?
0.7, right?
1 minus 1 over square root of 2 is 1.4.
1 over 1.4 is about 0.7.
1 minus 0.7 is 0.3.
So this is 0.3 over 4.
How big is that?
0.075, right?
But remember that we have twice that.
This one and this one are
equal, and so we have twice that.
So this number here is twice.
Twice, 0.075, which is what?
0.75 and 75 is 150.
Nice and small.
Now let's calculate this one.
Okay?
This is, alright, we'll just do
it on the same construction here.
Alright.
We still have one.
We still have electron 1 up along the zero axis.
That's this.
But now we have electron
2 is up along 90 degrees.
90 degrees means the one axis.
The projection operator for the one
axis is just tau 1 over,
tau 1 plus 1 over 2.
Now I'm not going to erase this.
I'm just going to, I'm just going to
doctor it up so that it covers the 0.5.
I'm going to do a little bit more.
So that it corresponds to the second statement over here.
So let's see.
So we can get rid of the tau 3.
It's just tau 1 over 2 plus 1 half.
That's it.
Okay.
Let's, okay.
Again, sigma 3 plus 1 over 2
again gets rid of this term here.
It picks out the component of the
state in which the first spin is up.
So nothing new as far as that's concerned.
And now let's see what tau 1 does.
Tau 1 takes up down to up.
So when tau 1 acts, it makes up up.
But there's no up up on this side here.
So this one doesn't contribute at all.
Let's see.
This is not minus.
This is just plus, plus 1 half.
All right.
So the tau 1 doesn't give anything either.
Tau 1 acting on down gives up.
You have up up here.
But you have no up up over here.
So that's dead.
And all you get is 1 half.
Okay.
This is it.
Sigma 3 plus 1 did nothing.
All you got was 1 half.
And now you got some square roots of 2.
You have a square root of 2 from here.
And you have a square root of 2 from here.
So the whole thing is 1 quarter.
This thing here is 0.25.
Well, 0.15 is not bigger than 0.25.
We went through this whole exercise to see
that the right hand side here is bigger than
the left hand side.
This is what John Bell did.
Of course, I know it's the only thing
he did in physics, but it's pretty brilliant.
The little exercise in quantum mechanics here is
one you can go home and redo for yourself.
But the upshot is that the quantum singlet
state of a pair of electrons violates the
Bell's theorem, Bell's inequality.
What does that mean?
That means that there is no possibility
that there's an underlying classical way of thinking
about quantum mechanics where properties are
somehow governed by ordinary set theory.
There's no possible underlying
description, classical underlying description.
description of quantum mechanics.
It cannot be the statistical theory
of some complicated, chaotic, jumbled classical system.
So you don't need to do any experiments
if you already have quantum mechanics and you
know Bell's inequality is not going to work.
You don't need to do those experiments.
Absolutely.
So aspect of what it was in
is, did all these experiments do nothing?
No.
No, no, no.
Well, the question is whether
or not nature follows quantum mechanics.
No, no, no, no, everybody
knew that nature follows quantum mechanics.
I mean, you know, quantum mechanics
has been tested to very high precision.
Let's put it this way.
Well it's a beautiful experiment.
I'm sure it was fun to do.
Did it teach us anything we didn't know?
Well, it might have taught us
something about the technology of manipulating electrons,
and I suspect it taught us
something about the technology of manipulating electrons.
And I suspect it did, and
I suspect it was a hard experiment.
It was a very delicate experiment, and so
it probably is part of the march toward being
able to manipulate small things.
I think in that sense
it was a piece of technology.
Was the result certain beforehand?
Absolutely.
I mean, you know.
So the Bell came out with the sole argument.
Yeah.
I mean, no, the experiment could not have,
quantum mechanics has been checked in so many
ways before that.
Right.
That nobody expected.
Now, I'll tell you what aspect it
did, which is a hard thing to do.
It's a hard thing to do.
What it checked, here's what you would want to check.
Okay, is there an out?
Is there an out?
Is there any way that classical
logic could somehow simulate quantum mechanics?
The answer is yes, but only if the
system that you're talking about sort of has wires
connected.
So the left electron to the right electron
in some way that makes the experiment on the
left not independent of the experiment on the right.
If you had somehow that when you did the
experiment over here, some signal went over here and
told it to rearrange and do something complicated.
In other words, if you have a whole bunch
of wires coming from the left and the right
and they join together and you have a
processor in the center, you can simulate quantum mechanics.
But.
It's at the cost that signals have to be
able to go faster than the speed of light.
That if you had any classical system that
could somehow detect what you did over here
and send the message quickly over
to there instantly before the second experiment.
Or in other words, if Bob could send a
message to Alice instantly and tell her what's going
on, yes, there are ways
to simulate quantum mechanics classically.
So the.
Second element of this is that the experiments
on the left and the right that measure the
two components of spin really are independent,
that they're far from each other and couldn't
have interfered with each other.
Now one way of making absolutely certain
that they couldn't have interfered with each other
is to make all of Alice's experiments take
place right at the basically at the same time
or very, very shortly after Bob's experiments.
If Alice's experiment takes place
at a time for which light.
Could not have traveled from Bob.
Then Alice's experiment must be independent.
No wire could have sent a piece of information.
There would be no way that any
classical, classical signal could have been sent from
one to the other.
So one of the things that was in
Aspect's experiment was not just that taking these
singlet electrons and measuring them and so forth,
the left one and the right one and
checking whether, whether the inequality was satisfied.
But.
He managed to do it in such a way
that there was no ambiguity that Alice's electron was
measured sufficiently soon after Bob's electron
that light could not have propagated between
them.
That was the hard part of the experiment as far
as I know to be able to, to be able to
do both experiments sufficiently simultaneously that
there was no possibility of information
flow.
From one to the other.
So the two experiments of Alice and Bob
were in that sense independent of each other under
the assumption that no signals can
travel faster than the speed of light.
Um, all attempts to simulate quantum
mechanics from classical underlying logic always make
use of some non-local assumptions.
So the first experiment was to do some
kind of thing which can process signals at one
end and send them to
the other end essentially instantaneously.
So I think that was the hard part
of Alan Aspect's experiment was the timing issue I
think.
And I think that was the sort of technological
triumph that they were able to be quite certain
that the second experiment was done within the
transit time of a light beam from the
first experiment.
Uh.
No interference between them.
Yeah.
Didn't Bell do this after Einstein died?
Oh, I suppose.
Yeah.
I'm sure.
So, but Einstein, he, he, and what did,
what did Bell do that, that clarified this, this,
this, uh.
He just made a very quantitative statement.
A very quantitative statement.
You know, Einstein had this idea,
somehow this is, this is funny.
Yeah.
So what was spooky?
What was spooky about it?
This is what was spooky about it.
That it violated a, uh, a classical logic proposition.
Now, it's not surprising that
you can violate classical logic propositions.
Quantum mechanics is not classical logic.
But he just pinned one down.
He just pinned one down very, very solidly.
And uh, was very quantitative about it.
Uh, the fact that the experiment was done
was probably less important than he put his
finger on a, uh.
On a thought experiment that could be done,
which would, if it were done, would rule out
a classical underlying basis.
He didn't have to do the experiment.
He said, no, this, this is enough.
This is enough.
I know that quantum mechanics will work for this.
And therefore, I know that quantum
mechanics cannot have an underlying classical basis.
Uh, he was very ambivalent about all of this.
I mean, some of the
times he thought this was brilliant.
Some of the times he thought, oh, it's trivial.
And then toward the end of his life, he
started to, he started to, he started to, he started
to, he thought it was so brilliant
that he began to question quantum mechanics.
And uh, began to question whether
quantum mechanics, uh, was the right theory.
But uh, yeah.
Well, why don't you address me?
This isn't a question, but it
might, maybe you can comment on it.
Uh, usually you think quantum
mechanics is really tiny things.
But here, you've got two electrons that are
flying apart, and they could be miles apart.
And I still have a gauntlet of electrons.
And I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I,
I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I,
yor just like, yor just like, it could be
a normal wave function and I still have a
common wave function.
And so now it's a really
large thing that you're talking about.
Well, it's small things far apart.
I mean.
Uh, you couldn't do it with two
bowling balls, let's put it that way.
That's it.
We all, we all, we'll bring this, we'll
just bring this, so from your point earlier, if
we process Dietrich's theory from science, then—
but I mean, you still, it's still about small things,
but the small things, you have to be careful
to keep the quantum wave function intact
when you take things apart.
When you take things apart, disturbing influences
can ruin the wave function.
For example, just the atmosphere,
interacting with the atmosphere can do things
to the wave function that ruin the experiment.
So when you take them apart, it's very delicate.
You better do it in a vacuum.
You better do it cold.
You better make sure that there's no photons around
that can interact with the electrons,
and care is required.
And the further you take them apart,
the more care that's going to be required,
because the quantum wave function
tends to get out of sync,
not by itself, but by interaction with other things,
interaction with an environment.
I think we'll try to talk a little about
So the idea that you could measure something
about that second wave function,
just by looking at the first one,
and so therefore Heisenberg's uncertainty principle,
the way I think Heisenberg understood it,
wouldn't be valid.
Well, no, I mean, this is
a trick which makes it look like
you're violating Heisenberg's uncertainty principle,
but it is still true that you cannot directly measure
certain simultaneous properties about one electron.
You really haven't done that.
You can measure the position of one of them,
and the velocity of the other one.
Yeah, nobody's going to stop you from doing that.
You can do that, but
it's not quite the same thing
as measuring the position and velocity of one electron.
And in fact, I mean, there's a theorem
that you really can't make a machine
that will replicate a quantum system
with another electron.
And you can do that
with another one just like it.
In fact, we could prove that theorem right now
if we want, although we'll do it in a minute.
Well, should we do the no-cloning theorem?
All right, do it in a minute.
Yeah.
In your argument, you use the product of two projections
to simulate the end of two propositions.
So does that mean that the product took a two-
Oh, yeah, yeah, okay.
All right, yeah, yeah, yeah,
I wanted to come to that.
I forgot about that, yeah.
Okay.
So when two propositions are independent of each other,
now, what does that mean?
That means that you can measure both of them simultaneously.
It means that the projection
operators commute with each other.
If you have two commuting projection operators,
then the and statement means something.
A projection, for example, what doesn't mean something
would be to say if you only had one electron.
If you had one electron, you could ask,
what's the probability that the spin
is both up along the end,
along the third axis, and up along the second axis?
All right.
That would be a meaningless question.
You can't do that because the two components of spin
don't commute with each other.
If you multiply them, take the two projection operators,
one of them is 1 plus sigma 3 over 2,
and the other is 1
plus sigma 1 over 2, right?
Is that the way to write it, or
should I put them in the other order?
You get a different answer.
So there's no meaningful and for the
spin is up along the third axis
and the spin is up along the first axis.
All right.
That's a forbidden kind of and.
But here we're talking about two different electrons,
and all of the operators for
one electron commute with all the operators
of the other electron.
It doesn't matter which order you apply sigma and tau.
That's because sigma acts on one of
them and tau acts on the other one,
and they completely commute.
They're completely independent measurements.
They don't interfere with each other.
Measuring one spin doesn't really
do anything to the other one,
particularly if they're far apart.
So, yes, that's something I should have stressed.
Yes, the product is the and operation,
but it only makes sense if the two projection operators
or if the two properties are compatible.
If the two properties are compatible,
which means they commute with each other,
then the product is the and.
That was your question?
Yeah, okay, good, good point.
Yeah.
One way I've heard this described
is that in terms of the measurement
of one particle imposes a constraint
or partial wave function of the class.
Okay, well, yeah.
All right.
Do you feel that's a
helpful way of looking at it?
Well, I don't know that it's particularly a helpful
way of looking at Bell's theorem and so forth,
but that's what I wanted to come to.
I wanted to come either to the no-cloning theorem
or the measurement process and
the collapse of the wave packet
or the collapse of the wave function
as being a special case of entanglement.
Which one should we do?
I think we're better off today doing the no-cloning.
And then next time we'll talk about the measurement process
as a process of entanglement.
Entanglement of what with what?
The apparatus getting entangled with
the system that you're measuring.
That's what happens when you do an experiment.
When you do an experiment, you have a,
you may have a, you know, a dial,
not a dial, a pointer that tells you
if it goes this way, the spin was up.
If it goes that way, the spin was down.
You take your electron and you put it
into the apparatus, and if the electron is up,
then the pointer points this way.
If the electron is down,
Sounds like entanglement.
Sounds like entanglement between the apparatus
and the electron, and it is.
That's what the measurement is, but we'll come to that.
I want to prove a little theorem for you.
We're going to have to introduce some additional things.
We have not talked about
how state vectors change with time.
We're going to talk about that next time, I think.
But I'm going to tell you one
fact about the time evolution of wave functions.
Namely, it's linear.
What does that mean?
That means if you start with a wave function,
a, and under time, or under some process,
it transforms into wave function, let's say, a prime.
And if we start with a wave function b,
a different one, and it goes to b prime,
then if you start with the
wave function alpha a plus beta b,
in time, it will go to
the same linear combination of a prime.
That's a postulate of quantum mechanics,
which is certainly experimentally extremely well tested.
And what it says is that the wave function, or
the state vector of a system, changes in time linearly.
Linearly means that superpositions of states,
transform into superpositions of states, in a linear way.
That's a postulate of quantum mechanics, which is
experimentally known to be true to extremely high accuracy.
It's the linearity of quantum mechanics.
So let me show you what
it says about trying to clone systems.
Here's our goal. Here's the goal of cloning.
Supposing I have a system
in any old quantum state whatever.
I want the machine that I can feed it into,
and that machine will spit
out two copies, two identical copies,
each in the same wave function
that the original one system started with.
So it's a cloning operation.
And in particular, for example,
in fact, whatever the initial state of the system is,
it should produce two systems in the identical state.
That's the cloning...
goal.
To be able to clone quantum systems.
Now, classical cloning is possible.
The Xerox machine classically clones
information on a piece of paper.
It doesn't do it exactly faithfully,
because little errors happen and so forth,
but the degree of error can be controlled,
and so you can clone classical systems.
You can build machines that whatever state on
that piece of paper you put into it,
it will produce two pieces of paper with identical states.
So you can build something...
that has only one,
that has no information,
is called an independent system.
I see that that means that there is no quantum,
there is no quantum here.
All right?
I actually rediscovered the no
cloning theorem a long time ago
and called it the no Xerox principle.
And string theorists call it the no Xerox principle.
No quantum Xerox principle.
All right, so here's...
All you have to do
is prove it for one system.
Here's my cloning apparatus.
It has a port over here that you put stuff
into and it has two ports over here that you
take stuff out of.
Alright, so in goes one in, in goes
your system, and out comes two identical copies.
Let's start with an up electron.
Supposing we start with an up electron.
So we start with one electron in the up state.
Let's just call it up.
Up.
What do we get out?
We get out two ups.
Up, up.
By assumption.
Alright, so we can say then that the
up, the single electron state, evolves in time into
a two electron state.
How it does this, nobody knows.
Incidentally that violates charge conservation,
so let's make it neutrons.
Hmm?
What?
Mass conservation.
No, no, no, no, no,
no, no, no, no, no, no.
That means energy conservation, but
energy doesn't have to be conserved.
It can borrow energy from the machine.
Okay, but it would violate charge conservation
unless it can get charged from the machine.
And that's okay.
There's nothing wrong with that.
But let's just say neutrons and make it simpler.
No electric charge conservation.
Say the machine is operated
for free so there's no charge.
What's that?
The machine is operated for free so there's no charge.
Yeah.
Okay.
So, up by itself goes
to a state with two electrons.
Okay.
So there's a state with two electrons
which I'm going to write as up, up.
There's two electrons each in the up state.
And I'm just going to write it
by putting two ups next to each other.
What if I put down in here?
What comes out?
Two downs.
Assuming that I was able
to build a quantum Xerox machine.
And two downs come out.
So, down will evolve eventually into down.
Okay.
Now, supposing I put an electron in.
This was an electron that was
pointing up along the third axis.
So we have our axes again.
Now I'm going to put in an electron which
happens not to be oriented along the third axis,
but what happens to be oriented
along the first axis, the X1 axis.
So what should I call it?
Instead of down, let's call it left.
Or right.
Right.
Up, down, up.
Down, up.
Up, down, left, right, and in, out.
Okay.
So now I want to put in
here an electron pointing to the right.
In other words, at 90 degrees
along the X axis, for example.
And if I have a faithful cloning machine,
I'm not going to redraw the cloning machine.
If I have a faithful cloning machine,
it should take right to right, right.
Right?
Right.
Okay.
But what is right?
What is the right state?
The right state is just up plus
down divided by square root of 2, right?
So what I've actually put in on the left-hand
side is up plus down over the square root
of 2.
Right?
Up plus down.
But I know what I get
out if I put in up.
If I put in up, I get up, up.
If I put in down, I get down, down.
If the evolution is linear like this, then that
already tells me what I get if I put
in up plus down.
What do I get?
Well, if I put in up, I get up, up.
If I put in down, well, let's, let's
write it as I, I get down, down.
All the square root of 2, right?
All that stuff is right.
That's because I already have
an electron pointing to the right.
So that's, that's not too bad and that's not
too bad as far as, anything can be solved.
I don't know what it's going
to be if I put in up.
What do I get?
Well, I get 1 plus down.
1 plus down.
Of course, I mean, if I put it's up.
If I put in down, well let's write it
as I get down down, over square root of 2.
So the linearity of quantum mechanics, the
fact that the evolution of states is linear,
already tells me what I get
if I put in up plus down.
I don't have any choice.
But what is right right?
Let's see if it agrees.
What does right right mean?
Right right means up plus down for the
first electron times up plus down for the second
electron.
I'm just juxtaposing them by the two electrons.
The first factor corresponds to one electron,
the second factor corresponds to the other
electron.
Sorry, over square root of 2.
Okay.
But when I multiply this
out, what do I have here?
I have a configuration with two ups, up times up.
I have a configuration with two downs, but
I also have up down and down up.
Unavoidably, if I take two electrons, each with
spin along the x-axis, I will find, if
I measure the third component of spin, that some
of the times I will find an up and a
down.
Over here.
I have two ups and two downs,
but never an up and a down.
So you see the assumption that you can
build a cloning machine which both clones ups and
downs and also clones lefts and rights is inconsistent.
It's inconsistent with the linearity of quantum mechanics.
What if you insist that the two outputs have to...
Say it again.
You seem to be assuming that the two
outputs have to be independent of each other somehow.
Yeah, I'm not sure what it would mean
to clone things unless they were cloning things
to independent things.
Well, sorry.
The assumption was that up produces two
ups and a down produces two downs.
Yeah, but then you explained the right
right would be the product of the...
That's the way you build composites.
Yeah.
That's the way you build states of independent systems
is to multiply the state vectors in that fashion.
It's called taking...
We haven't had the time to do everything.
Unfortunately, we haven't had time to do
everything, but the mathematical operation of combining
systems is called tensor product.
You take the tensor product of
state vectors, and that's what this is.
This is the tensor product of two rights, and
then you expand it out, and you see what's
you see what you get, and
what you get cannot be this
so you're right, there's a degree of assuming
that the two things are independent of each other
but I'm not sure what it would mean to
clone things if they weren't independent of each other
and then you could do independent experiments on them
so it is not possible to take
an object in an arbitrary wave function
and put it into a machine and have it
come out as two replicas of the same thing
A laser is a pretty good cloning device
so where does your argument break down for a laser?
A laser is a cloning device
You put in a photon that has a certain state
and you're going to get a bunch of them produced
That's actually not true
Stimulated emission, the polarization of the output pair of
photons is not quite the same as the input photon
The vector is a linear combination of
the initial magnetic state of the excited atom
plus the incident stimulating photon
So while the two output photons
are identical, they're not the same polarization
I have to think about the question
You may be right
So you say you take a photon with
a given polarization and you stimulate some emission
I have to think about what the...
If you analyze it from an information point of view
If the information of the excited
atom contributes to the output state
then that is noise from a cloning point of view
Yeah, exactly
You may be right
I'll think about it this week and see
if I can give you a simple argument
However, there is no controversy about the
fact that you can't build a cloning machine
I think there is... I
don't even know if it's controversy
I think there's a question
of how close you can get
How close can you get to a cloning machine?
And I've seen papers saying different amount, different...
You know, some quantitative data is not
enough to get to a cloning machine
You know, some quantitative measure
of how close you can get
And there's some number like three quarters that come out
You can have a cloning machine that's
three quarters accurate or some such thing
But that's something I don't know much about
Anyway, this is the basic
idea that you can't have a...
And the reason is simple
Multiplying two things together like this
Taking anything and squaring it is not a linear operation
It's a quadratic operation
You take any state, basically, and
replicating it is sort of square...
Is a sort of operation which is quadratic
It's a cooperation of not squaring something
but sort of multiplying it by itself
That's what's going on here
And that's simply not a linear operation
It can never be linear
It's always quadratic
And since all the evolution of state
vectors is always linear, you can't quite...
You can't do it
You can build a machine
that will clone ups and downs
But then it won't clone rights and lefts
You can build a machine
that will clone rights and lefts
It won't clone ups and downs
You can not duplicate, but you may transfer these properties
Yes, yes, yes, that's a different issue
That's a different issue
That you can transfer some
information from one thing to another
Yes
But what you can't do
is duplicate it in two systems
Right, so you might have some kind of information
For example, the electron is up
And you might want to transfer that to a photon
And send it, and the question is how
well can you transfer it to another system
And that's a separate question
Yeah
In this whole discussion, I think you have
to state somehow that you don't know the state
The particle when you try to clone it
If you know it, if you know the
state, then of course you can clone it
If you know the state, you can
build a machine that will clone it
But it will be a different machine than a...
For example, if I know the state is up,
I can build a machine that will clone it
And the same machine will clone down
If I know the state is right, I
can build a machine that will clone it
But the same machine will not clone ups and rights
So yes
if you know the state, you
can build a thing that clones it
was that the question? or answer?
if you don't know the
state, then you cannot clone it
you have a certain practical,
it is in a certain state
but let me just say it a little differently
you cannot build a machine that will clone anything
or that will clone ups, rights
or ins and outs, the
same machine cannot clone them all
so if you didn't know what the state was, somebody gave
you a state and said, no, you don't look at it
and you just say, I want to clone it
your machine may just happen to clone
it, because it may be the up thing
but the chances are
well, it wouldn't clone things
I've said it enough times, I can't say it again
I'm running out of steam
hmm?
if you write the output of the machine
would be what you wrote down last time
yes
but that's different than what the output of
the machine has to be by quantum mechanics
that's the linear result
this is the cloning result
this is the linear result
right
yeah
and they're different
so one, they can't be the same
right
in other words, just two electrons both right
having them a piece
with an up down and a down up
that's inconsistent with uh, what
the linearity of quantum mechanics says
so sorry, no clone
It seems
Yeah it seems like the amount of information
you capable of containing two independent entities
plus the entangled entity
yes its true
if anybody tried to Kongo
is it obvious that the entity underground
is is different than a tangible entity?
yes sir, from that perspective, of
information theory, right past theuna, witcheski,
that you are sure of?
Is that how you know?
I'm not sure of that. Oh
Not sure. Because it is not dont know you are
not sure ah, much of an increase in MCU government.
about it?
certainly you know about theềnite and that the body of metal so that it can wheel it up this way, this
blueberry volume of themo wide and large stuff it's hard to have a part don't you understand the smart of it?
I'm sure they have.
The last time, what I told you,
is if you have a single electron,
the state vectors are a two-parameter family.
If you have two independent electrons, which
have never been entangled or anything like that,
then the state vectors you would
expect to be a four-parameter family.
But in fact, the state vectors
of two electrons are a six-parameter family,
so there's a richer class of states.
Now, can you quantify that by information theory?
I don't know. I haven't...
I'm sure you can.
Well, I certainly know how to quantify
the degree of entanglement of two systems.
There's something which I hope we will
get to, which is called entanglement entropy.
And entanglement entropy is a measure of
the degree of entanglement of two systems.
So we can certainly quantify the amount of entanglement
between two systems.
I'm not sure if that's what you're asking.
But in any case, we'll try to
get to that concept of entanglement entropy.
Okay, any other questions before we go home?