This program is brought to you by Stanford University.
Please visit us at stanford.edu.
Yeah, the same explanation you just gave.
Yeah.
Supposing in the framework of QFT,
we have a singlet with space-time separation of
the parts of the calculation, I suppose you'd say.
Is there some sort of virtual exchange of something?
When what happens? Under what circumstance?
Well, let's say under the circumstance
that something is measured at one time.
I wouldn't say so.
I would say nothing happens at the other side.
Nothing detectable happens at the other
side of the message can get there.
The degree of entanglement remains.
Whatever you do at the other end, you may
change things at the other end, one way or another,
but that electron which is over there
will stay entangled with the system over here.
It'll stay entangled even though the system may change.
It'll still stay entangled.
Maybe we can work out an example.
Maybe at some point I'll work out exactly the example.
Supposing you rotated the spin on the right
hand by putting it in a magnetic field,
how does the state vector
change for the two-particle system?
And is there some sense in which
the measure of entanglement remains the same?
And the answer is yes.
There is.
We haven't talked about measures of entanglement.
Quantitative, how much entanglement is between systems,
but as long as those systems don't
start talking to each other again, there's
a measure of entanglement which never changes
between them, even though the
particular form of it can change.
Somebody asked me about what happens if you
take an entangled pair and you throw one of
the particles into a black hole.
What happens to the entanglement?
Well, it becomes entangled with the degree of entanglement.
with the degrees of freedom of the black hole.
The black hole evaporates.
That electron over there is still entangled
with all of the photons that come
out of the black hole and so forth.
In fact, I mean, you can think
of much simpler examples in black holes
where the whole story sounds very crazy,
but nevertheless, forget black hole.
Just take a bathtub.
In a bathtub, you have a pair of electrons.
They're entangled in a singlet state,
and the bathtub is full of water,
and you take, forget electron or atom.
It could be a water atom.
Are there water atoms?
Yeah, okay.
Two entangled water molecules,
and you drop one of them into the bathtub,
and it gets all mixed up, terribly mixed up
with all of the stuff in the bathtub here.
This electron is still entangled,
not so much with the single electron which is there,
but in the entire state of the bathtub.
You have to now treat the bathtub as a system
and talk about the entanglement of
the bathtub with the electron here.
This electron gets too mixed up with the others
to have a clear identity,
but nevertheless, the state of the entire bathtub here
stays entangled with the electron,
and then the bathtub can evaporate
so that there's no molecules left.
Uh-oh, there's nothing left to be entangled with.
Well, of course there is.
What's left to be entangled
with is all of the same,
the vapor that escapes out of the bathtub.
And that entanglement will remain there,
frozen in,
unless something from this side
actually comes over to this side
and they interact with each other again.
Then they can become disentangled.
It is quite possible to take an entangled state
and disentangle it.
Anything that can go one
way can go the other way.
So if you were to take two unentangled electrons,
let them interact for a while,
they become entangled,
there are, anything that can happen,
can happen in the opposite direction.
So disentanglement can take place,
but only if the systems are close enough
to actually interact with each other.
So if something from over here comes over to here,
it can get disentangled, but only then.
Yeah?
In experiments we've been talking about,
let's say you have entangled electrons,
and you're going to measure them on the z-axis
for up and one down.
When you make both of those measurements,
are they still entangled, those two electrons?
Or does the measurement kick them out?
No, the measurements kick them out.
Would one measurement disentangle them?
It can.
We're going to talk about that.
Those measurements are called measurements.
They're called observations.
And we're going to talk tonight about how observations
or measurements have the interplay between
the measurement concept, the collapse of the wave packet,
and the concept of entanglement.
I want to get to that.
But before I do, I want to
just spend a little bit of time,
because I don't think I did it very well,
talking about projection operators
and just review a little bit of the mathematics.
Just very briefly discuss subspaces
and the mathematics of subspaces and projection operators
at a very elementary level.
I don't like to do anything more advanced,
to use more heavy hammers than
I'm necessary to explain an idea.
All right.
First of all, when you have a space,
a space of the kind that we're talking about,
where you have a concept
of vectors and their complex conjugates,
their formal conjugates,
which are normally called dual,
the bra vectors and the ket
vectors are called duals of each other.
We're inclined to sort of think
of them as like complex conjugates.
We have a concept of orthogonality between those vectors.
As long as we stay in
vector spaces which have finitely many dimensions,
and so first of all, what's the
definition of the dimension of a vector space?
The definition of the dimension of a vector space,
we ought to give it.
Abstractly, forget for the moment using column vectors
and just counting the number of entries.
I'll give you a collection of abstract vectors
with some orthogonality relations
and in particular some relations of linear dependence.
Linear dependence means that a vector
may be linearly dependent on some other vectors.
That would mean that the first vector
can be expanded in terms of the other vectors.
That's what linear dependence means,
that you can write a particular vector
in terms of another subset of vectors,
then it's said to be linearly dependent on it.
The dimension of a vector space is very simple.
It's the maximum number of linearly independent vectors
that you can find in the space.
In other words, in three-dimensional space,
you can find, there are many, many triplets of vectors
which are linearly independent.
Linearly independent means that you cannot write
any one of them as a
sum of the other n-1 of them.
Or an equivalent way to say
it is that you can't find
any linear combination of the
vectors which adds up to 0.
If you can't, then those vectors
are said to be linearly independent.
Now obviously there's no way that these vectors
are not all in the blackboard incidentally.
This one's sticking out of the blackboard.
Those three vectors are not linearly dependent.
They are linearly independent,
because there's no linear combination of
them that adds up to 0.
Another way to say it is there's
no way to expand this third one
in terms of these other two.
They don't have to be orthogonal to be linearly independent.
If I take three vectors, I'm
not very good at drawing these things,
but take three vectors which happen
not to be orthogonal to each other,
just those two, plus this one over here,
where this one is not lying in the blackboard,
and this one is in
the plane of the other two,
there is no way to write the
third one in terms of the other two.
So again, they're linearly independent.
Now on a three-dimensional, let's
start with a two-dimensional vector space.
What's the maximum number of
linearly independent vectors I can find?
The answer is two.
If I add a third one in the plane,
in the plane, if I add any third one,
and now I'll just draw exactly the same thing,
but think of it now
as a vector in the plane.
Then this third one can be
written in terms of the first two.
For example, we can add these
two and get a vector over here,
and then with a minus sign,
we're allowed to have minus signs,
we're allowed to multiply by constants,
we're allowed to add vectors, multiply them by constants.
We can certainly build this vector from the other two.
So these three vectors that I've drawn in the blackboard
are not linearly independent.
They're linearly dependent.
The maximum number of linearly independent vectors
in a two-dimensional space is two.
The maximum number in a three-dimensional space is three,
and so forth.
And that's the basic definition of
the dimension of a vector space,
the maximum number of linearly independent vectors.
Now it's a theorem which we're not going to prove,
but it's straightforward to prove
that if you can, in a d-dimensional vector space,
d-dimensional vector space,
with a concept of orthogonality in it,
that you can always find d basis vectors.
d basis vectors, the basis vectors mean that the base,
that the vectors are first of all normalized,
that means they're unit vectors,
and they're all orthogonal to each other.
You can find d of them.
So in a two-dimensional space, and in many ways,
not just in one way, in many ways,
but in particular, there exist families of vectors
which are orthogonal, mutually orthogonal,
and unit vectors.
Two of them in a two-dimensional space,
three of them in a three-dimensional space,
and so forth.
And those vectors, or a set of such vectors,
yes?
If you have a three-point particle,
does it count the same number of degrees of freedom?
If we have a three-point particle?
A three-point particle.
Does it have the same number of degrees of freedom
as the number of space dimensions?
You're talking about particles moving in space now.
Yeah, a single particle.
Well, that's a definition of
the number of degrees of freedom.
Yeah, we would say it has
But that's not got anything to do with the dimensionality
of the space of states.
Nothing whatever.
Just for spatial dimensions.
Yeah, just the spatial dimensions.
Right.
So the dimensions of the space of states
can be very, very much larger than the dimension...
Take a particle moving in a room.
There are three dimensions for it to move in,
but there's a huge, huge number of possible states
of the particle, orthogonal states.
So they're not connected in any simple way.
Okay.
Now...
Oh, I think I lost this.
All right.
So you can always find a mutually orthogonal set
of unit vectors.
They're called basis vectors.
They're not unique, but once you find the basis,
you have a basis.
And so let's imagine then that
we have a set of basis vectors.
We'll call them n,
where n is a numerical
integer that can run from one...
to the dimension of the space.
We have d such vectors,
and they're orthogonal to each other, mutually orthogonal.
So that means that m and n give zero,
unless m is equal to n,
in which case it gives one.
So the symbol for that is the Kronecker delta symbol,
and the Kronecker delta symbol simply means
the right-hand side is one
if m is equal to n,
and zero if m is not equal to n.
All right.
So that's basically the definition of a basis set,
or a set of basis vectors,
for a...
uh...
for a space of the kind we're talking about.
Now, um...
here's an interesting theorem,
which is hardly a theorem.
It's more or less obvious,
that if you have a basis set...
if you have a basis
set which has as many vectors
as there are dimensions in the space,
then it follows that any vector whatever
can be expanded
as a set of...
sum of the basis vectors
with coefficients,
with a set of coefficients.
Let's call those coefficients a sub n
times n,
summed on n.
In other words, this is just saying that any vector
anywhere can be expanded in terms of,
uh...
in three dimensions,
the three basis vectors,
or whatever.
All right.
And now,
we can relate the, um...
the expansion coefficients here
to the inner products of these sum of them.
So, let's take the inner products of these
with the basis vectors.
Let's do that.
Just take the inner product of this
equation with any vector,
uh... on the left,
with any one of the basis vectors on the left.
And so we find that m psi
is equal to sum on n,
a sub n,
m n.
Now, this is a sum on n,
but there's only one term,
because only when n is equal to m
do we get an answer,
do we get something non-zero.
When n is not equal to m,
they're orthogonal.
When n is equal to m,
uh...
then you get the answer number one,
just one.
And so you get only one term in here,
and that term is just equal to a m.
All right.
It's summed on n,
but we sort of picked out,
we've selected out m
to project onto psi,
and the whole answer then is just a m.
All right.
So that's a nice, simple fact
that the expansion coefficients here,
for a given vector,
are nothing but the inner products
of the psi vector
with the basis vectors.
That tells us what the a's are.
If we take the, uh...
Now I can rewrite the equation.
Let's rewrite this equation.
We now know what the a's are.
Let's write it in the following form.
Psi is equal to sum on n,
and now instead of writing a,
I'm going to write this inner product.
The inner product is just n psi.
That's a n times n.
I've taken the liberty of writing the coefficient
on the right side of the vector
instead of the left side of the vector.
That doesn't, uh...
You are allowed to write 3 times psi
as equal to psi times 3.
That doesn't, uh...
No objection to that.
So this is a number.
This is the inner product.
This is the nth basis vector.
It's the same formula,
except that I've used for the coefficient here, a,
the inner product.
Now I have an interesting equation.
I'm going to read this the following way.
I'm going to read this,
I'm going to separate it in the following way.
I'm going to invent a new symbol.
The new symbol is the sum
of n times n.
What on earth does that mean?
We've never defined putting vectors back to back like that.
But now I'll tell you
exactly what such an object is.
When you put vectors back to back like that,
any two vectors, it doesn't have to be basis vectors,
take any two vectors,
let's call it a and b,
put them back to back,
what you get is a linear operator.
You get an operator,
and the way that it operates
is when it multiplies a vector,
you just take the inner product
of b with psi,
and multiply it by a.
So this is an object
which when you
apply it to a vector,
with the rule
that you just take the
inner product of b with psi,
what you get back is another vector.
It's a linear operator.
It's called a dyad,
a pair of vectors back to back like that.
All dyads like that are linear operators.
And we can now read off from this equation
what this operator is.
It's an operator which does nothing.
When, let's move this over a little bit.
Let's put psi over, well,
let's think of this as an operator
which hits psi.
I've got an extra redundant vertical sign here,
but that's alright.
What does it do?
When this construction hits psi,
it just gives psi back.
So this tells you immediately
what the meaning of this object is.
It's just a unit operator.
How do you read it?
When this object over here
hits any vector at all,
it gives back the same vector.
And that's called,
what it's called is the resolution of the identity,
but any time you see this symbol,
sum over the vectors of
n's back to back like that,
it is just the unit operator.
But in that case,
n can't be just any vector.
n, n is summed over.
n is a sum over a basis.
It has to be a basis.
Yes, it has to be a basis.
It has to be a set of orthogonal,
we use that here,
when we calculated that
the coefficients were equal to psi times m,
we used the orthogonality
and the unit character of each one of these vectors.
So yes, we did use that.
These must be a basis.
Excuse me.
Can you call that the eigen...
This is just the resolution of the identity.
That's the word for it.
Yeah, I understand.
But if I look at it,
it looks to me like
it's with an eigenvalue of one.
Yes.
And the eigen...
The unit operator,
every vector is an eigenvector.
Every vector is an eigenvector of the unit operator
with eigenvalue one.
The unit operator is a special operator
that has all its...
Every vector is an eigenvector of it,
and every vector has eigenvalue plus one.
So it's...
And it just says that one on any vector
gives you back the same vector.
Why?
I is the identity.
It's called the identity.
Good.
All right, but now,
we might be interested in a subspace.
Let's define...
some subspaces,
some interesting subspaces.
Subspaces correspond to certain observable questions
that you could ask or that you might answer.
So, for example,
let's suppose that we have some operator,
some observable,
some Hermitian operator
that I'll call k.
It's something that we can measure.
It has an eigenvalue spectrum.
It's Hermitian.
It has all the properties
that we identify with an observable quantity.
And let's suppose that we have
a eigenvector A of it
with eigenvalue lambda.
That just says that if you measure k
when the system is in the state A,
you will get the answer lambda for certain.
Let's suppose there's another eigenvector
with exactly the same eigenvalue,
not a different eigenvalue,
the same one.
Different vector,
in fact, linearly independent of A,
so it's not pointing in the same direction as A.
It's not a multiple of A
with exactly the same eigenvalue.
Then, any linear combination of A and B,
let's call it alpha A plus beta B,
any combination like that
is also an eigenvector of k
with exactly the same eigenvalue.
It's easy to check.
You just apply k to this,
but each term just gets multiplied by lambda,
so the lambda comes on the outside.
If we apply k to it,
the k just goes right through
and multiplies each one of these by lambda.
The whole thing is just a multiplication by lambda.
And so any linear combination
of a pair of eigenvectors with the same eigenvalue
is also an eigenvector with that eigenvalue.
In other words,
what we're beginning to discover
is that there's a subspace.
A subspace,
ah, what does a subspace mean?
A subspace means a set of vectors
which are closed under addition
and which have the property
that they themselves are a vector space
but might be lower dimensional.
The horizontal plane here is a subspace.
It is also a vector space.
It consists of all the vectors in the plane here.
And basically it's all the vectors
that can be built out of
the two vectors in the plane.
Same thing here.
Any linear combination of these two vectors
will be an eigenvector.
And so you can talk now about the eigenspace,
the subspace,
the vector subspace of the original space
which corresponds to a particular eigenvalue.
Okay, everybody got that?
Two states that...
Two states which happen to share the same property
of having a particular value
for some particular variable.
Yeah.
For example,
here might be an example.
You have up-down,
the two-particle system,
up-down and up-up.
Both of these have the same eigenvalue for sigma 3.
They have different eigenvalues for...
No, no, I have the same thing.
Up-up.
Ah.
They both have sigma 3 equals up.
Sigma 3 equals plus 1.
They have different values of tau 3,
but the same value of sigma 3.
Any linear combination of these two
also has the same value
for the upness or downness of the first entry here.
So this...
Of course, there's other vectors which...
down-up and down-down
which have different values
for sigma 3.
But these two span a subspace
and it's a subspace in which sigma 3 is up.
Okay?
Good.
So that's the idea of a subspace.
You could have a collection of vectors.
It doesn't have to be two-dimensional.
There could be 25 vectors
all with the same eigenvalue
and then 15 others with different eigenvalues.
But if you pick out all the vectors
that correspond to the same eigenvalue,
that correspond to a given eigenvalue
of a Hermitian operator,
they form a subspace.
They form a linear subspace
that if you add vectors, subtract vectors,
multiply them by constants,
they are still in the same...
in the same subspace.
All right.
So what that tells us is that
properties such as k equals lambda,
that's whatever k happens to be,
the property that k equals lambda
is not necessarily identified
with a single vector,
but is identified with a whole subspace.
Question?
Okay.
Now once you've identified a subspace like this,
you can go a little bit further
and find a basis within that subspace.
So here's some subspace down here.
It might have actually...
Yeah, here's some subspace down here.
It's the subspace of the fluid.
It's the subspace of the floor.
Once we find that subspace,
we can find basis vectors in it.
Basis vectors that don't span the whole space,
but just span the subspace.
All right.
Good.
So just think of the subspace
as a space by itself,
and we have a set of basis vectors.
And I'm just going to call them A's and B's.
For this particular example over here,
let's call the basis vectors A's and B's themselves.
Assume that we found them.
We found A, B, C, however many we need.
In general, it'll be less than D.
D is the dimension of the whole space.
But a set of basis vectors for the subspace,
only for the subspace.
And those, by definition, have the property
that any two of them are orthogonal
unless they're the same.
Otherwise, the inner product is one.
So that's delta A, B.
But A and B now
don't run from one to D.
They run from one to whatever the dimension
of the subspace is.
Good.
So we now have the concept of
a basis for a subspace.
Good.
Let's take that basis
and construct out of it something
which looks like this.
Let's take the basis in the subspace.
And write the expression A.
Sum over A.
Sum over all the basis vectors in the subspace.
What is that object?
Now, the first thing I can tell you is
it would give you back the same,
if you hit any vector with it,
it'll give you the same vector
as long as the vector is in the subspace.
All right?
So if we have a vector in the subspace,
for all practical purposes,
the other directions don't matter.
And we're just rewriting this kind of formula over here.
If psi is in the subspace,
then we just get back psi again.
But what if psi is not in the subspace?
What do you get?
If psi is not in the subspace,
then what you get is the projection of psi
onto the subspace.
So what does that look like?
Let's put this vector over here someplace.
Sticking out of a blackboard,
I can't, I don't have enough dimensions
to draw it in properly.
The projection onto the subspace
is the projection of the vector
onto the subspace.
Ah.
We just discovered what this object A is.
It's the projection operator.
It's the projection operator onto the subspace,
which in this case corresponds to the property
that k equals lambda.
So this object over here
is the projection operator
onto the subspace, in this case,
where k is equal to lambda.
That's how you construct a projection operator.
If you have a property that you're interested in,
you find the subspace which it corresponds to,
you find a basis in that subspace,
now this is, this may or
may not be hard to do.
I mean, in any particular example,
it may be easy or hard,
but you find that basis,
and then you construct what would have been
the identity operator,
except it's not really anymore,
because it doesn't have those vectors
which stick out of the plane,
which stick out of the subspace.
It's the projection operator onto the subspace.
But the identity operator is also a projection operator.
Yes, yes, yes.
The identity operator is a projection operator.
It's a projection operator
onto the whole space,
onto the whole space.
If you only had one vector here,
it would be the projection onto some particular axis.
If you have two vectors,
two-dimensional subspace,
it would be a projection onto a plane.
If you have enough vectors,
it actually corresponds just to a projection
back onto the whole space.
But typically, it corresponds to a property.
The property that's associated with the identity operator
is a trivial property,
just that the system exists.
No information is contained.
What's that?
It is the property that doesn't change.
Now, every projection operator characterizes a property.
It's the property which is true in that subspace.
Why is it a no-change observable,
or something like that?
I'm not sure what you meant by that.
Okay, I get it.
This observable is a state.
It's in the state of the constant.
Right.
Final thing about projection operators
is the probability postulate.
The probability postulate for quantum mechanics
is most nicely expressed in
terms of these projection operators.
And what we can say then is,
if I give you an arbitrary state psi,
which is neither,
which does make sense,
but may or may not be in the subspace,
may or may not be in the subspace,
if I give you an arbitrary normalized state psi,
then the probability that psi has property k equals lambda
is just the expectation value of this projection operator.
Let's see if we can
make any sense out of that.
If I plug in for the projection operator,
its expression here,
what I find is psi A,
A psi, summed over A.
Does this make sense?
Yeah.
It says that the probability to find a particular property
is the sum of the
probabilities of all the particular ways
that you could find that,
all the orthogonal ways that you could find that,
that particular property.
So for example,
if the property corresponded to the first spin being up,
in other words,
if it corresponded to the projection operator
onto the first spin being up,
let's write down what the projection operator would be.
It would be up, up, up, up,
plus up, down, up, down.
There are two basis states in
which the first spin is up,
namely up, up, and up, down.
And if we construct the,
we're leaving out some things here,
down, down, and so forth.
But this is the projection operator onto the subspace
where the first spin is up.
Okay?
If I take the expectation value of any,
of this operator in any state,
it's the probability that the first spin is up,
but it comes from two places.
It comes from the probability
that the first spin is up
and the second spin is up,
plus the probability that the first spin is up
and the second spin is down.
Okay?
So that's the basic post,
postulate of probabilities.
Yeah?
Is the way we interpret these points in the space
to be probabilities
at the basis vectors of the space
to be the observed?
No, the observables are the operators
which have a collection of eigenvalues.
All right?
The property of having a particular value
is the property that when you measure k,
you will definitely get lambda.
So the property is characterized
by an operator and an eigenvalue.
Okay?
A projection operator
is a tool for calculating the probability
that the property is really there.
In other words, in this case,
it would be the probability that k equals lambda.
The projection operator is just a tool
and it's the thing whose expectation value
is given, it gives that probability.
Yeah?
A math question.
On the left where you have a and b
as vectors that have the same eigenvalue,
I didn't understand if those are always,
they always form an orthogonal basis
or you can derive an orthogonal basis.
Yes, you can find an orthogonal basis.
Yes.
Do so.
Once you've done so,
you now can just think of the other part,
the other directions in the space
as being incidental.
You now have a space
with a set of vectors within it
that form a basis.
Over there where you have them as being orthogonal,
then you're saying those are a and b
are basis vectors, right?
Basis vectors for the subspace.
For the subspace.
Only for the subspace.
Would it be correct to label those two bottom axes
as a and b?
Yeah, this could be a equals one.
Well, yeah, I have a funny mixed notation here.
This could be a and b, yeah.
And then the psi would
be the one that's sticking up.
Psi could be any vector.
And the projection is that.
Right.
And then in this case,
there's a third vector
which does not lie in the subspace.
You could add it in as a basis vector
for the whole space,
but it's not part of the subspace.
Okay?
All right.
And then when you project psi onto a,
and then project psi onto b,
and add the answer,
you get the projection onto the subspace itself.
So can I interchange a and b there?
Yeah, in this...
When you say k equal to lambda,
it shouldn't be uniquely a, right?
It could be also b vectors.
Where? Where?
Yeah, yeah, you do.
Yeah, in which equation?
In the first equation.
This one here?
Yeah.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
Yeah, this is just...
Okay, in this equation here,
I'm really talking about a particular vector.
Right.
In this equation,
I'm talking about a sum over vector,
so I really should use a different notation.
This is a summation variable here,
and we can call it sum over a prime
or something like that.
Or i over b.
We can decorate it with as many indices
as we want.
And it'll just get very confusing.
But when you see a sum like this,
don't think of a particular vector being picked out.
Think of summing over all the vectors.
Whereas in an equation like this,
without a summation,
it means some specific vector.
So here you are summing over a and b.
Right.
This could be a sum over a and b.
A prime could stand for a or b.
Or c or d,
depending on how many vectors you have.
Exactly.
Right.
I didn't want to make too many notations.
I didn't want to put subscripts on notations.
But yes,
you've got the idea.
A summation index like this here
is just a sum over something.
Here you've picked out the a vector
and the b vector.
You could have called it one and two.
In fact,
that would have probably made more sense
to just call it one and two.
But it's not.
It's a sum over a and b.
Right.
So you've got a sum over a and b.
And you've got a sum over a and b.
Okay.
Any other questions?
Yes.
Just another check,
so say that the probability amplitudes
No.
Probability.
Yeah.
These are probability amplitudes.
And these are probability amplitudes.
Multiplying them by the complex conjugates
gives you probabilities.
And then summing over the different ways
that you could get.
You see there are different ways
that you could get k equals lambda.
You could have it in one denominator.
vector or the other vector or the other
vector, summing over all the various ways gives you
the total probability for k equal
to lambda. Does that answer the question?
Yes. Yeah, good. OK, good. Any more? OK.
All right, so that's another way
of stating the fundamental probability postulate. Now,
if we have two commuting projection
operators, two commuting projection operators mean, well,
OK.
It means exactly what I said. Two
commuting projection operators, and I'll give you some
examples in a moment. Let's call it P
k equals lambda and another projection operator for
another property, let's say l equals mu.
These are two distinct projection operators for
two distinct properties.
OK.
But if they're going to be two different
properties, if they have the property that they commute,
then there's some simple definitions that you can
make of what you mean by and and
or.
What about and? What is the projection operator
for k equals lambda and l equals mu? What
is the projection onto the simultaneous condition that
both k equals lambda and l equals mu?
OK.
All right.
OK. OK. So, what's the projection operator for k
equals lambda and l equals mu? OK. All right.
and L equals mu. In order for there to be
an AND and to get any answer, there have to
be vectors in common in the two subspaces.
I mean the two subspaces have to intersect
with each other. They have to intersect. So
if you had two spaces which didn't intersect
at all, except at the origin, all
subspaces always intersect at the origin. So there's
two subspaces which don't intersect except at
the origin. Then let's place this one vertically
upward just for simplicity. Then clearly there
are no states which share the property associated
with this projection operator and with
this projection operator. There's nothing in common
between them. On the other hand,
if we had two subspaces which shared
another subspace, a lower dimensional subspace, then
there are vectors in the space which
share both properties, which have the property
associated with subspace number one and the
property associated with subspace number two. And
we can ask which vectors, which states
of the system, have both property one and
property two. And what is the projection operator
for the AND statement?
For the property k equals lambda and l equals
mu? Well, the answer is the product of the
two of them if they commute. If they commute,
the answer is the product of the two of them.
Let's see if we can see why that's so. Let
me just call this pk. I'm not going to call
it pk equals lambda. That's too much notation. Just
pk and pl. Now if they commute, the property
of the two of them is going to be
a vector. If they commute, it doesn't matter which order
you write them down in. Okay? Let's take
any vector whatever. Oh, oh, let's go back
a step. Can I go back a step? Yes. I'm
going to go back a step. If you take the projection
operator pk and you apply it to any vector
at all, whatever, apply it to any vector at
all, you will get a vector in the subspace,
right? So it stands to reason that the vector
in the subspace is the vector of the subspace.
Right? So it stands to reason that the vector
Right? So it stands to reason then that if
you take this whole vector here, it must
be an eigenvector of k with eigenvalue lambda.
This is a vector in the subspace k equals
lambda. And so it must be the case that k
on this just gives you lambda times pk times
psi. This isn't very deep. It just says that
pk on psi gives you a vector in the subspace.
Okay.
space where k is definitely equal to
lambda. Okay, now let's take the product
pk times pl, apply it to any
state whatever. I say that this vector will
have both the property that k is equal to
lambda and l is equal to mu. How do we
check that? Well, first of all I told
you that if you take any state and
multiply it by pk, it'll have the property
k. By property k, I mean k equals
lambda. Let's just call it the property k.
Any vector, if you multiply it by pk,
has the property k. Well, here's a vector.
I've multiplied it by pk on the left.
Therefore, it has the property k.
But if it's also true that pk and
pl commute with each other, I can also write
this as pl times pk on psi. And
now I exhibit the fact that it has the
property l. So if I have
two commuting projection operators, two projection
operators which commute with each other,
that roughly means that the two
observables are compatible with each other,
that you can measure both of them.
Independently, that you can measure them
both simultaneously. Then the product of
the two projection operators corresponds to
the and statement. In other words, it
corresponds to finding, it corresponds to
vectors, or it corresponds, excuse me,
to the projection onto the simultaneous
property k equals lambda, l equals mu.
For example, if I wanted to know
the probability that k equals lambda and l
equals mu, it's just the expectation value of
the product. Psi, pk, pl, psi is the
property, is the probability, not just that
k equals lambda or that l equals mu,
but that k equals lambda and l
equals mu. Okay? That's the and statement. You
multiply projection operators. There's also
an or statement. The or, yeah?
Also known as, well, in classical logic,
it would be the intersection. I'm not sure
that you call it the intersection in vector
spaces, but it is, it is the intersection
in that sense, yeah. In classical logic,
it would correspond exactly to that, to the,
if you have a property described by a, by a
subset of points in a, in a set, and you
have another property, then it's the
intersection which corresponds to the or
statement, sorry, the and statement. The or
statement corresponds to the sum of the
two projection operators. I'll let you try
to prove that yourself. And is product, or
is sum. So if you're interested in what
vectors either have the property that k equals l,
that k equals lambda, or l equals
mu, the or statement, then the projection operator
has to be the sum of them. But we're
going to be more interested, I think, in the product.
If they're not compatible, you just get
hash. You can't measure both things together.
I think it's clear as if they're compatible.
If they're not compatible, you can still define
it, but it's not a very good definition.
What's that?
Okay. The spin of one, if you have a
two electron system, any component of one spin is compatible
with any other component of the
other spin. Okay. We could check that.
Spin and charge, this could be another one.
Yeah. All right, but let's check, let's take
the case of two spins. You
have a bunch of, let's see.
Um.
Yeah. Yeah, because the spin operators act
completely independently on the two sets of
degrees of freedom, they always commute with
each other. If you first multiply this vector
by some sigma, and then multiply it by a
tau, you get exactly the same answer as if you
first multiplied it by tau and then
sigma. So usually, very often, compatible operators
are simply the same. So, you know, if
you have a two-sets of degrees of freedom, you
can always commute with each other.
Okay.
So, you know, if you have a two-sets of
degrees of freedom, you can always commute with each
other.
So, even when you have a two-set of
degrees of freedom, one set of degrees of freedom
is automatically compatible.
Yeah.
When you build subsystems by putting
systems together, any quantity associated with one
subsystem is automatically compatible with
the quantities for another subsystem.
Okay.
That's an example.
About subsystems, you really sort of mean
degrees or types of freedom that add both
degrees of freedom.
Yes. Yes.
I mean, I think of momentum
and spin, for instance, so those were…
Well, momentum and spin happen to be
compatible with different subsystems, so to say, you
have to have a set of degrees of freedom.
Okay.
So, you know, we could take three sets
of degrees of freedom, and then multiply them
by one.
Yeah.
But they could belong to the same electron.
But if you had two distinct electrons,
then anything associated with one electron is automatically
compatible with the other electron.
On the other hand, there can be things
associated with a single electron that are compatible.
For example, if an electron is moving in
three-dimensional space, the components of position, x, y,
and z, are also compatible with each other.
We haven't spoken about that because we
haven't done that kind of quantum mechanics.
We're doing bit quantum mechanics
and not particle quantum mechanics.
But the simplest situation for compatibility is
when two things belong to two different,
let's call them qubits.
In the case of qubits, in the case of
simple spins, the criteria would be that they belong
to different spins.
They're associated with different spins.
Then they're compatible.
You make it sound like everything's compatible.
Well, I think it's not.
It's not.
No.
No, no, no, no, no.
Something good, something which is not compatible, would
be the x component of one spin and the
y component of the same spin.
You can't measure the x component of a spin
and the y component of a spin at the same
time.
So they're not compatible.
You only got one magnetic, one direction that
you can put the magnetic field in to measure
the spin of a particular electron.
You can't put the magnetic field simultaneously in
two directions and try to measure two different
components of the same spin.
On the other hand, if you have two
electrons, and the simplest situation is just take them
apart, put one magnetic field over here
in one direction, another magnetic field over
here in another direction, and you can
measure two different components of two different
spins.
So they become compatible.
But two components of the same spin are not compatible.
So you can measure two
different components of two different spins.
Both spin are not compatible.
OK.
So, excuse me, that's just the same
way of saying that different sigma matrices, they
don't commute, right?
Yes.
It's just a statement that the sigma matrices don't commute.
Is that what you said?
Yes, .
So when you see these two sigma matrices .
Yep.
That proves that...
That's all you need.
Absolutely, yeah.
The position and momentum don't commute, right?
The position and momentum don't commute.
That's another accent, sir.
Right.
The position, although they're still
similar, they're not completely similar.
Right.
Although the position, yes, the position
in the neck is not created
Right, exactly
Alright, so we have the concept of
and, and then let me just remind you
I just want to go through this again to
make the logic clear, what we did last time
I sort of implicitly pretty much
assumed everything that I've done tonight
when I described it, and it may have
left you less than comfortable with the procedures
Let me just remind, we're not
going to go through the calculation again
Just going to remind you what
we did, this was the Bell inequality
Well first of all we proved the completely classical theorem
The completely classical theorem had
nothing to do with quantum mechanics
and it's not even true in quantum mechanics
It says if we have
some properties A, B, and C
then the number of
uh,
of number of objects which have
A but not, A and not B
plus the number of objects, and the
number of objects could also stand for probabilities
number of objects with B but not C
is greater than or equal to the
number of objects with A and not C
Now we can apply this, if electrons were
strictly classical objects, we could apply it just to
take A, B and C and
take them as the following quantities
A could stand for
electron
Z component of the electron, the
third component of the electron up
and I'll just indicated by pointing an arrow up
That's A
B could be that the electron is pointing along
45 degree axis in the 1,3 plane, to be simple
in the 1,3 plane to be simple
simple to be simple and C could
be that the electron is lying along the
horizontal axis that if you measure
along the horizontal axis you definitely
get up not a B and C or in
particular not B and not C would correspond to the
electron pointing in the opposite
direction so if B corresponds to
electron pointing in this direction then not
B corresponds to it pointing in the
opposite direction.
Can I ask a question about say up and down?
Up and down are orthogonal but up is not minus down.
They're not.
Two different things, okay, what is that minus and that just
plus and minus is just something that happens in the calculations?
Yes, absolutely.
And doesn't have physicals?
Sometimes it's sometimes influence the vector A plus B might be quite
different than the vector A minus B and I gave you an
example
up down minus down up is quite
different than a up plug you know the
sign can make a difference
but the overall sign never does.
Okay.
If Bell's theorem gets violated for any quantum properties of
anything or only for certain ones and in which cases?
I don't honestly know the complete answer to that question.
It's certainly not
violated for any state for example I can find states of the
two particle electron system for the Bell inequality will be satisfied for sure.
So the answer is that there are certainly
states for which the Bell inequality is satisfied.
You have to search a little bit to try to
find situations where it's violated but it's not very hard.
If you just throw you know just take a random guess I don't
know 60-40 60% of the times you'll satisfy the inequality 40% you won't.
Okay.
I just made that up I have no idea really but but but most likely I would
guess that it's more likely if you randomly selected a state that the inequality would be satisfied.
And that it's a sort of a smaller percentage of the space of
states that doesn't satisfy the inequality but I never checked that that's something.
You can set B up to be an angle theta.
Yes you could you could and then you could
check it you could check it as a function.
Yeah.
Solve for.
And you could also have C be a be an angle and I would guess if the angles are too close together
that they're that you don't that you don't violate the inequality but we can check that that's an interesting thing to check.
At what angles is the inequality
satisfied at what angles is it violated.
Hmm.
If you have 90 degrees of arc there's
something to do with the multiple of 90 degrees.
That you don't have any problem.
Could be.
Yeah.
I haven't checked it but.
You're talking about photons I think.
Photons or electrons.
Photons.
Okay so that's a little bit different but yeah.
Yeah there's certainly situations where
the inequality is not violated.
But but let me just remind you what we did.
All right then we what we
did was take a two electron system.
And we imagine doing many many checks.
The two electrons.
The two electrons are in the singlet state
and we do many many checks on this.
And every single time we find out.
That when.
That the.
If we measure the spin of one of them along any axis the
spin of the op of the other one is along the opposite axis.
That would suggest.
That the property B.
That the property not B.
The property not B for electron one.
Is the same as the property B for electron two.
In other words it would suggest.
That the property not B which says that electron.
One.
Is down.
Is equivalent to the property.
B for electron number two.
Okay.
So.
We could rewrite this inequality then.
As if we work in terms of pairs of electrons.
We have these pairs of electrons which have been created.
They've been created in a way
that the spins are always anti-aligned.
And we can substitute for the property.
A and B.
We can first of all.
A.
Can still be associated with electron one.
A and not B.
Would then become.
The number of pairs.
Where the first electron is up.
But the second electron.
Is at forty five degrees.
The second electron being at forty five degrees.
Would imply that the first electron.
Was in not B.
If it made sense.
To talk about.
A and not B.
For electron number one.
So that's this one over here.
Let me.
I'm sorry.
Not B should be minus.
好嘞
Not B means the electron is pointing this way.
But if electron 1 is pointing this way,
electron 2 is pointing along B.
So not B for electron 1
is B for electron 2.
Good.
Not something for electron 1.
Since they're opposite,
any not statement for one
becomes the positive statement for the other.
Good.
All right, so we can now rewrite this inequality
as the number of pairs
in which the first spin is up,
but the second spin is along 45 degrees,
plus the number of pairs
in which the first spin is at 45 degrees,
but the second spin is at 90 degrees,
is greater than...
or equal to the number of pairs
where the first spin is up
and the second spin is at 90 degrees.
All we have to do to check the inequality
for any given state
is to construct the projection operators
for these properties.
Now, this is a two-electron system now.
We've replaced the one-electron system
by a two-electron system.
If we were doing classical physics
with classical logic,
the opposition of the two-electron system
would be the opposite of the two-electron system.
The two-electron system would be
the opposite of the two-electron system.
So, the two-electron system
would tell us
that not b is the same
as b for the second spin.
So, that's the logic here.
Now, okay, so what are the projection operators?
We take any state, whatever,
and we can ask,
what's the probability for this property?
What's the probability for this property?
So, let me go back now.
We want to construct the projection operator
for this property.
This property has spin number one pointing up,
the projection operator for that is
1 plus sigma 3 over 2.
If the first spin is up,
sigma 3 gives plus,
1 plus 1 is 2 divided by
2, that's 1. Okay, so yes, that's,
if this first spin is down, then sigma 3 is minus
1, 1 plus minus 1 is 0, and we get 0.
So this is the projection
operator onto the first spin up.
The projection operator onto the second spin,
pointing in its, along its axis, is also a 1
plus something, but not 1 plus sigma, but 1 plus tau.
Because tau is the spin operator for the second electron, but not
tau along the third axis, but tau along the 45 degree axis.
What is that?
That's tau 1 plus tau 3
over the square root of 2.
That's the projection of tau on
to the 45 degree axis, and
then we should divide it by 2.
This is the projection operator for one statement, spin number 1 is
up. The projection operator for the other statement, spin number 2 is along
45 degrees is this one.
What is the projection operator for the and
statement that electron number 1 is up and
electron number 2 is along 45 degrees?
It's the product.
Okay, it's the product.
So we multiply these two
operators together. Dot just means multiplication.
We do the same for this one.
Same kind of thing for this one.
I should move this over a little bit, but
the second projection operator, let's put it over here,
would be the first spin along 45 degrees.
That's
1 plus sigma 1 plus sigma 3 over
square root of 2 all divided by 2.
But then the second spin along the horizontal axis.
So that's 1 plus tau 1 divided by 2.
That's the projection operator for the second configuration.
And the projection operator for the third configuration is
1 plus sigma 3 over 2
times 1 plus tau 1 over 2.
Well, we know how to work with these sigma and tau operators,
and if I give you any state, any state of the two-elections,
the two-electron system,
you can calculate the expectation
value of these three projection operators.
And you can simply check, is the expectation value of
this one plus the expectation value of this one bigger,
or is it not bigger than the
expectation value of this one over here?
This is the exercise that we
did last time for the singlet state.
Singlet state up down minus down up,
and we found that the inequality was violated.
There was no reason why it should not
have been violated. We're not doing classical set theory.
The derivation of this formula here
came from drawing various classical sets and
looking at the, just, you know, just counting up which
what things
corresponded to A and not B, what things corresponded, what regions corresponded
to A and not B, what regions corresponded to B and not C,
what regions corresponded to A and
not C. It didn't have to do
with the intersections of projection operators. It
had to do with the intersection of sets.
So there was no reason why the inequality should
have been satisfied in the quantum context, and it's not.
If we know that for a
particular system the Bell's theorem either
violated or not violated...
For a particular system in a particular state.
Right, in a particular state.
Then is there anything more we can say about it?
Or, or, or...
Or nothing.
The only thing you can say about
it is this is a very clear demonstration
that quantum mechanics cannot be the statistical theory of
some kind of system with classical, that's really
governed by classical logic, by classical set theory.
That's all that you learn out
of it. It cannot be and...
So if a particular quantum
state actually satisfies Bell's theorem,
Yeah.
can we say that it's some sort of,
that it's more classical than not in any way?
I think you probably, maybe. Maybe.
Remember there are many, many variables that
you could check. In this case, well,
Bell's inequality may, you may be able to check
very, very many different inequalities for the same system.
So, by choosing properties,
by choosing a particular set of three properties,
you might find for a certain system in
a certain state that the inequality is not violated,
but then choose some other properties for the
same system, you might find it is here.
And I suspect that would generally be true.
I think that would probably always be true.
That you could probably always find properties A, B,
and C that the inequality would be, would be violated.
There's a, there's a leader...
Okay.
I'm having a very good time with you.
I'm having difficulty trying to figure out
what kind of an experiment this describes.
How many magnets and populations of electrons and...
Good, okay. So that's, that's the
right question to ask at this point.
We have a beam of particles,
but the particles come out in pairs.
They come out in correlated pairs.
Here's how we might start.
We might start with a pair of electrons.
The pair of electrons are near each other.
Because they're near each other, they interlock.
They interact with each other.
And the lowest energy state
happens to be the singlet state.
And so after a while, they either do or don't
emit a photon, but they get into this singlet state.
Then the electrons are taken apart.
And that's not too hard to do.
I mean, you can send them through
some sort of system which separates them.
It could be an electron and a positron.
You put them in a field.
The field sends the electron one
way, sends the positron the other way.
And so you have well-separated electrons.
And so you have a well-separated pair.
But not just one of them,
many of them, many such pairs.
For each pair that you've made, there they are,
you measure, you take, divide them up into groups.
Divide them up into groups so
that we can do three separate experiments.
So we have 100 billion pairs.
We take a third of them.
And on the third of them, we're going
to measure the number of A and not B.
How much is a third of 100 billion?
100 billion divided by 3.
We take 100 billion divided by 3 of the pairs.
And in the first set, we measure the up
component of the electron, the vertical component of the electron,
and the 45-degree component of the positron.
Okay?
And we count up all together.
How many pairs are there in which
the first electron was up along the 3-axis,
and the second electron was up along the 45-degree axis?
We count them, and that gives us a probability.
That gives us the probability.
Forget n's.
We can just use probabilities here.
That gives us the probability that the first electron
is up and the second electron is along 45 degrees.
Then we take the second electron.
And we do exactly the same
thing, except in the second group,
we don't measure the first electron up
and the second electron at 45 degrees.
We make the second electron at 45 degrees, sorry, the first
electron at 45 degrees and the second electron at 90 degrees.
We count up the probability for that.
Okay?
We add it.
And then finally, we take the
last third of the electron pairs,
of the electron-positron pairs,
and measure the first electron up along the z-axis
and the second electron along the horizontal axis.
And count how many of them have
the property that the first electron is up,
or what percentage have the probability that the first
electron is up and the second electron is horizontal.
The theorem says, classically, if it were true,
it would say that this plus
this should be greater than this.
But your theorem is,
your theorem is dealing with a single population,
and this is three different populations.
You can take it as dealing with probabilities.
And since we have a, a
identically selected set of three populations,
we can measure the probability distributions
by looking at just the separate,
the theorem would be true if we divided the system,
identically prepared, assuming they're identically prepared,
all three populations.
In fact, every single pair here,
the theorem would be true about these subpopulations also.
As long as you prepare them in the same way.
That's right, as long as
you prepare them in identical ways.
So,
yeah.
In the year 2000, Alan Ashford,
wrote an article commemorating John Bell.
In there, there's this very neat diagram
that shows basically the distribution
that you can expect classically
versus what you get quantum mechanically.
And it shows how the quantum mechanical results
include some data points
which are outside of the classically
or inside the classically excluded region.
I haven't seen it, but...
I want to ask that.
I don't understand why you can't use this to signal.
The two led rods would be going across
very slowly.
And so, if I, Alice,
measures one of them,
if they're going across slowly,
you could measure it
and instead of a message that's the speed of light,
you could say,
I just measured this and expect yours to divide.
Right.
That was, as far as I understand,
aspect experiment
was done in such a way
that the two measurements
that a light signal could
not have been sent between them.
You could make it either way.
Yeah.
If there was time for a light signal to go
from one to the other,
then it would not be a contradiction.
You might wonder,
how the hell did the signal get across there?
What was the mechanism?
Who sent the light beam and so forth?
But you wouldn't have a contradiction with causality
or with locality or whatever you want to call it
if the second electron was measured
after a time during which a light beam
could have gone from one place to another.
You might say,
oh, I didn't see any light beam go.
I must have discovered
some new force of nature
that I didn't notice before,
but at least it doesn't exceed the speed of light.
But the trick is to do the experiment
in such a way that a light signal
could not have gone
to the second electron
when you measure it
from the first electron.
I don't think he used electrons.
I think he used photons, incidentally.
I think the way aspect had put it
was that
in order for the classical explanation
to be matched,
the quantum mechanics prediction
of signals would have had to try
to make that happen.
Right.
That's the other way to say it.
And that's, right,
that's exactly right.
So part of this whole queerness
of this entanglement
is connected with signals
not going faster than the speed of light.
When people say
that in order to have hidden variable theories,
and that means classical logic systems
which can somehow mock up
the effects of quantum mechanics,
when they say they have to be non-local,
what they mean is that signals
have to be able to go faster
than the speed of light
to send messages
between the two electrons.
I want to get to another thing,
and we're not going to get to it,
but yes, we are going to get to it.
Yeah.
I'm not giving you any freedom
to run loose in the hallways.
There's nothing sacred about the...
Hmm?
There's nothing here that...
No.
That's right.
There's nothing sacred
about conserved quantities
in this context here.
It's just a nice,
very simple system to work with.
In fact, these don't even really
have to be spins.
They could be any two system,
any system that has two states,
an upper and a level atomic state.
Yeah.
No, it was not important
that this was...
that spins are angular momentum
or anything like that.
No, not at all.
All right.
What I wanted to do next
was to talk about
the connection between
three things.
Interference phenomena,
measurement phenomena,
or how you do it,
what a measurement means,
and its connection with entanglement.
How a measurement
is really the establishment
of entanglement
between systems,
that's what a measurement is,
and how measurements
destroy interference.
How they...
and it's called
the collapse of the wave packet.
So I thought we would get
to that next.
And let's see,
let's see how far we can go.
We may want to come back to it
if I don't...
So what we're actually
going to be speaking about
is the two-slit experiment.
But I'm going to
simplify the two-slit experiment
so that we can think about it
as just having a finite number of states,
a little simpler than the two-slit experiment.
It is the two-slit experiment.
But we'll just imagine
that a photon or electron,
or whatever it happens to be,
no spin, forget spin,
now these are real particles.
They really move from one place to another.
But let's suppose that the particle
could be in any one of several voids,
or in any one of several voids,
vertical locations. Just to make life simple, some
set of, we'll call this 0, 1, 2, 3,
minus 1, minus 2, minus 3. So
the electrons, I'll call it an electron, but
forget its spin. It starts out at
0, and this is the position of
the electron along the vertical axis. The
electron is actually going to move to
the right. It might also move up or
down, but I'm just simplifying by giving it
only a finite number of places where it
can live, just so that we can use the
tools that we've been talking about
of finite dimensional spaces. So the number
of possibilities where the electron can be
is finite, in this case seven of them.
Alright, the electron moves over to the
right. Let's, there are also seven places
where it can, where it can be found over here.
Actually, from this side over here, I'm going
to select out and assume that the electron
started at this point here. So
the electron actually starts at 0.
Now it goes over to here, and when it gets
over to here, it's in one of these seven places.
Depending on which place it's in, well not
depending on which place it's in, it continues
to go, and it continues to go over to a
third place, which also has the same set of one,
two, three, four, five, six,
seven, the same set of possibilities.
We're really talking about the evolution of a
system from one instant of time to another
instant of time, but here's the game we're
going to play. It is the two-slit experiment.
I'm going to assume that if the electron
arrives at this point, that it just gets
sent back. Alright? So we're going to
ignore the possibility that electrons would go backward.
If it goes to this point over here, it
also gets, goes back. It only goes through if it
hits this point or that point. So from
the point of view of a two-slit experiment, I've
opened this slit and I've opened that slit, and
I've sent an electron to here or to here,
one electron at a time, we're sending one
electron at a time. It either goes through
the upper slit or the upper slit.
So the two-slit experiment is
going to be a two-slit experiment.
And if it goes through the upper slit or
the lower slit. And if it goes through the
upper slit, it can go, well, it can go
through either slit and arrive at any one of these
places over here. And so forth. I'm interested,
we're going to make up some rules, rules that
are consistent with quantum mechanics. A
simple example, I'm interested in the probability
the electron arrives here, here,
here, here, or here, or here?
What's the probability under various circumstances?
Now here's the assumption.
The evolution of systems, the quantum mechanical evolution
of a system is linear.
That means that if a
system starts in the state A
and evolves to a state A prime, in this case,
it could be that it starts
at any one of these places here
and gets to any one of these places here.
And if the state B would evolve to B prime,
then if we start the system
in the state A plus B,
it will evolve into A prime plus B prime.
This is the assumption of linearity.
In fact, we can do this with arbitrary coefficients,
alpha, beta.
That's the statement that states of systems evolve
in a linear way, that linear superpositions evolve
into linear superpositions.
Now this is an experimental fact.
As I said last time, it's very, very hard,
maybe quite impossible.
Nobody has ever succeeded in changing quantum mechanics
a little bit without coming to really silly conclusions.
So we'll take it as a
postulate that the evolution of state
vectors is linear.
Linear superposition evolves to
the same linear superposition
with the same set of coefficients.
All right.
That's about all I'm going to assume.
And we're going to, well, make some definitions now.
I'm going to start the electron over here.
And after a certain time, it will have
arrived at one of these places.
I'm not interested.
I might as well throw away
all the places which just reflect
the electron backward.
Because I'm not even going
to look for it back here.
So it either gets to 1 or to minus 1.
And by symmetry, just the up-down symmetry here,
if I really do have enough up-down symmetry,
if the length of this path is exactly the same
as the length of this path and so forth,
and I start the electrons symmetrically,
about the only state that
I can get to over here
is the linear combination.
So we can write it this way.
We can say.
Starting with 0, the state will evolve
to the state 1 plus minus 1.
Now, I'm not terribly interested in normalizing the state.
I'm not interested in keeping track of total probability
here.
That's not going to play any big
role in what we're going to say.
So if we start with the
electron over here, after a time,
by the time it gets to the slits over here,
it will be in a superposition
of states, with equal, or equal,
equal amplitude, with equal likelihood
of being here and here.
Just because of the symmetry of the problem,
you would expect equal coefficients here.
But now let's say what happens
if an electron starts at 1.
What happens to it when it
goes over to this side over here?
So let's make a postulate or an assumption about that.
If it starts at 0, then it's equal.
So initially, it gets to 1 plus 1
prime, or minus 1, 1 plus minus 1.
What happens if it starts at 1
over here or minus 1 over here?
What happens to the state vector over here?
So let's make the following assumption.
If you start at 1,
if an electron starts at 1,
then by the time it gets over,
we can call this the screen over here.
It's where we measure the electron, the screen.
By the time it gets to the screen over here,
I'm going to make an arbitrary assumption.
I'm going to make an arbitrary assumption that
it is in the state summation psi n n.
It has to be some linear
combination of these are basis vectors.
They correspond to orthogonal configurations.
These are different places.
They don't get mixed up with each other.
If an electron is over here, it's not here.
If it's here, it's not here.
So we have these basis vectors n.
And this is about the
only thing I can write down.
Sorry. Not 1 is 0.
But 1 goes to.
That 1 becomes, after a further interval of time,
it becomes some linear combination.
But it's not the same state either.
It's not the same state.
You've got n there and you've got a 1.
But you really need to be different.
Your notation's not just taking
a second and a third path.
Between where and when?
So you've got a 1 for your...
This 1 corresponds to starting over here.
Yeah.
Like you could fry it.
Or something like that.
And your under...
When your method is on your state register.
Oh, here.
Yeah.
Yes I could.
But I didn't want to decorate it with
too many symbols, so just this goes to just...
Once I put an arrow there,
I don't have to be so...
I'm not writing anything is equal to anything else.
I'm just saying the state 1 over here
will evolve into some state sine n times n.
What happens if it starts at minus 1?
minus one
well if it starts at minus one
it'll go to some other combination, I'm not
even going to tell you what combination it is
other than to say it's some other
phi n
times n
minus one
these are arbitrary linear combinations
over here, they could be
determined by experiment
they might be determined by mathematics
but I've written down the most general possibility
that if you start at one over here
you will get to some linear
combination characterized by a set of coefficients
if you start at minus
one you'll get to some other
linear combination
I won't even tell you what they are
what happens if you start in
the initial state one plus minus one
the linear combination of both of these
then the linearity postulate
tells you
that at the end
the final state will be the sum
over n of the sum of these two
which is phi n plus psi n
times n
in other words
by the time you get over here
the coefficients will be the sum
of the coefficients that you would get
by going through the upper root and going
through the lower root
if you go through the upper root
in fact even if you closed off the lower root
then the experiment would only involve
one going through psi n here
if you closed off the lower root
if you closed off the upper root
the experiment would only involve going from minus one
would involve this combination over here
if you open them both
and allow the electron to go either way
then
the rules is
the linearity of quantum mechanics tells you that you
should add the stakeholders for the terms, ok Sui ...
you that you should add the state vectors. If
you start with a linear sum of two vectors,
you should add the two in the
final state. So you get to here.
Question? Yeah.
Are those normalized on the right side, psi and ?
It doesn't, uh, it could be.
Because if they're not, if one of them
is way bigger than the other, it doesn't make
any sense. You've got to do something to make sense.
Why doesn't it make any sense?
Well, I mean, psi n could be in the billions,
and phi n could be very small if they're not
normalized.
It could be. For example, if you put
some obstruction here, which only let very few
electrons through, we could make the, uh,
the phi's be much smaller than the psi's.
I'm just suggesting that you haven't said what
the units are. I mean, one could be a
meters in the...
Wait, wait, wait, wait, wait, wait,
wait. Psi's and phi's are dimensionless objects.
They're squares of probabilities.
I know, but they're not.
They're not.
They have a scale factor associated
with them that you normally take out.
We can normalize them.
I didn't bother normalizing them over here. At
the moment, I didn't want to worry about
keeping track of total probability. All right?
That's something we'll do next time. That's
called unitarity, and I don't want to
worry about it right now. Whether it's normalized
or not normalized is not so important. The
important thing is that, uh, that you can
get the sum of the coefficients going through
the upper root and the lower root, and that's
the postulate of linearity that if you evolve
from one, you get psi. If you evolve from
minus one, you get phi. If you evolve from
the state one plus minus one, I don't like
to say one, this state plus this state, then
you get the sum of the two. That's the postulate
of linearity. What's the probability, then, at the
end of the day, that you measure the
electron at the nth or the mth, uh,
the mth site? Well, these are the coefficients that
add up to give you the state vector.
This is an orthonormal basis. It's quite clear
that the probability, the probability that you'll land
on the mth site over here is just
psi m plus phi m complex conjugated times psi
m plus phi m. We could either do this
through projection operators or just use the
simpler statement that the squares of the
coefficients, we take the coefficients here,
we complex conjugate them and square them,
and that gives us the probability
that we arrive at the mth site.
m could be one, two, three, and four,
and this would give us the various probabilities
for arriving at different places. Notice what we
get. We get four terms when we work this
out. We get psi star of m psi of m. Now,
what is that? That's all we would have if we closed
off the second hole. If we only had the
first hole open, the answer would just be psi star
m psi m.
The probability that had we closed off the
second hole, we would have arrived at the
mth place. On the other hand, there's
also phi star phi. That's the probability that
if we closed off the top opening and
went through the bottom one, we would have arrived
at the mth place. Classically, that's all
there would be. The probability to go from
here to here to here to here to here to here
to here to here to here to here to here to
here to here to here to here by one of
two roots would just be the sum of the probabilities
of going through the upper root and the
lower root. That's all you would have in classical
physics. If you had a random walking particle
that random walked around, you left the upper
hole open, you would have a certain probability to
get here. If you left the low-up hole open,
you would have a different probability to get
to the same place. If you left both holes
open, the probability would just be the sum
of the two probabilities. But in quantum mechanics,
there's a lot of randomness. What do we find?
Well, what we found is that writing down the
we have two other terms, psi star m,
phi m, plus phi star m, psi m.
Do I have that right? Yes.
Let me give you an example.
Let's consider the probability that we
get to the symmetric point over here.
For the symmetric point, we might
imagine that's 0, that's m equals 0.
m equals 0.
We might imagine that psi and
phi are equal to each other.
Why? Because one of them corresponds
to going through the upper hole,
the other one corresponds to going through the lower hole,
but by symmetry, we might just assume that
the amplitude to go from here to here
is the same as the amplitude to go
from here to here, and it would be.
And in that case, psi
and phi would be the same.
In other words, if we plugged in 0 over here,
the probability to get right to here,
to the central point,
The whole answer is four times the probability
that you would just go through the upper
hole if only the upper hole was open.
Now that's odd.
You would have expected
classically just twice the probability.
If you opened up both holes,
you would expect that the answer would
be twice the probability to get to here,
not four times the probability,
but you would expect that the answer would
be twice the probability to get to here.
But what you get in quantum mechanics
in this case is four times the probability,
and the reason is because you
add up the amplitudes and then square.
If the amplitudes are equal and you
square, you'll get four times the probability.
That's a little bit odd.
All right, maybe it's not that odd,
but let me give you something even odder.
By putting in the right,
little apparatus over here,
you could change,
you could make changes in the system,
basically just a little potential
or something that would have a little bit of effect
on the electron as it went from here to here.
It could have the effect of changing the sign.
If it changed the sign,
it would also change this one.
In that case,
if psi of zero was equal to phi of zero,
they would cancel,
and you would find zero probability
to get to this point over here.
This is destructive interference.
The four was constructive interference.
The zero is destructive interference.
And what does it say?
It says that there are situations
where with a certain probability,
you would get to here going through the upper root.
With an equal probability,
you would get to here going through the lower root.
But if you open up both roots,
you make it impossible to get to here.
Okay?
That is a,
that's at least,
for my money,
that is as odd as the Bell inequality.
That by opening up,
you would think you make
it easier to get to here,
and in fact,
you completely black out the possibility of getting to here.
If you open up the upper root,
you would think you would make
it easier to get to here.
If you start with the minus sign here.
Okay?
But the minus sign doesn't affect either of the
probabilities for the upper root or the lower root.
It only affects what happens when both roots are open.
When both roots are open,
it becomes completely impossible to get to here,
despite the fact that if
you only open the one root,
block this one off,
you can get to here.
Block this one off,
Equal probabilities.
Open them both,
no electron will ever get to this point over here.
That's destructive interference.
So it's clear that probabilities in quantum mechanics
are not doing the things
that they do in classical mechanics.
Can I ask a question about that?
Regarding locality,
let's suppose those two holes,
one and minus one,
were some distance apart,
and you could,
in a time less than it would take
light to go from one to the other,
turn on that little field,
so that you would change
it from constructive to destructive interference
in a very short amount of time,
so that when an electron was going
from the source to the middle screen,
it might be constructive,
but then just as it was getting there,
it would return to destructive,
and then you would accumulate the results.
In other words,
you're changing the experiment so fast
that you can't,
the electron would,
couldn't know,
I think my thought is,
even if you change it fast,
you would still get the proper result,
such as,
you know, you have interference,
you have,
Well, I would say to change the sign,
you might want to do
something in the leg over here.
Right.
All right.
So,
right,
you could do it while it's in flight,
but then it would depend
on whether you made the change
before the electron got to here
or after the electron passed it.
Just right prior to it,
but in,
in,
in a smaller amount of time.
Well, the electron is over here.
Yes, but,
and so that,
when you make that change there,
nothing could propagate at the speed of light
to the other,
other slit.
Over here?
No, to the other slit.
Yes.
No, no, I think if you make the change
before the electron gets here,
Right.
you've made the change.
And that,
and that will change the sign here.
Right.
That will change the sign.
I think his point is,
in a delayed choice type of an experiment,
where you open or close the slit,
in a random way that wouldn't,
wouldn't permit a,
somehow the correlation to be set up
at the other slit,
the quantum mechanical result is still going to hold.
Classically,
you would have to have some kind of,
in order to get the correlation that you actually meant,
find out.
Well, we have no correlation here,
just the probability,
just a pure probability on the side,
a probability distribution.
But,
but there's one slit
or two slits
that can be,
right.
Right.
So,
so,
right.
It's not just that the probability depends on whether
there's one slit or two slits,
of course it does.
It's that the probabilities don't add.
It's the probabilities don't add,
the amplitudes add.
The probabilities don't add,
you get a probability in either case,
depending on that sign,
four times bigger than,
than the probability to go through one opening
with the other one closed,
or just zero.
Right.
But you can come back and decide,
and figure out which,
which way,
you know,
which of the two wave functions,
was the actual description at the time,
and you would find that the results,
the distribution that you get,
corresponds to the,
to that,
what,
the,
the thing that you discover later on,
is the actual situation at the time.
Sure.
We'll,
we'll,
we'll.
Turbo.
It is a wave choice experiment
where you.
Well,
you don't know what you're going to do
until you actually,
until you actually do that,
until you actually ,
so,
whether is a plus or a minus sign
depends on some,
some set-up of the system
which is,
a space-lessly separated
from the other part of the system.
And then,
later on,
you go,
go back,
and reconstruct
by having .
I think,
you'll have to give a more precise
set-up in order,
trying to study very, you know, reasonably precise setups,
and we would have to investigate each one separately,
but what I really wanted to get to, we'll see if we can
get to it, I don't know, we're probably going to come back to it,
is what happens if somebody over here, if there's an
apparatus over here, which monitors which way the electron goes through,
which measures and records which way the
electron goes through? This is the interesting question.
Here, I have assumed that nobody has
recorded which way the electron has gone through.
So at the end of experiment, you can't really say
the electron went through here or it went through here,
you don't know which way it went through, and
there's no clear notion of being able to check afterwards
that the electron went through
the upper or the lower hole.
But suppose that the electron went
through the upper or the lower hole,
suppose that the electron went through
the upper or the lower hole,
supposing you set the problem up in
a way that afterwards you can check,
there's something which records whether the electron goes
through the upper hole or the lower hole,
then what happens to the probability distribution?
Well, you might think, well, who
cares whether you measure it or not,
careful, measure it in such a
way that doesn't disturb anything very much,
do some very minimal, gentle detection of the
electron, whether it goes through there or not,
you shouldn't disturb the system very much.
But in quantum mechanics, it's not always,
it's not always possible to do minimal, gentle experiments,
and if you do an experiment which
does record which way the electron goes,
you will change the answers in a
rather dramatic way and basically destroy this interference,
basically destroy either the positive
interference or the negative interference,
and so let me show you how that works.
And this is an issue of entanglement, this
is entanglement of the electron with the apparatus,
which measures it.
So let's invent an apparatus.
It's a very simple apparatus, when
the electron goes through the upper hole,
well, let's just put an upper hole
over here, a lower hole over here,
the electron either goes this
way or it goes over here,
and here's my assumption, if the electron passes by
this hole, well, we're going to put an apparatus,
the apparatus is going to be very simple, it's
going to be a spin, it's either up or down,
this spin is either up
or down, along the third axis,
we're going to start with a spin down.
If the electron goes through the upper hole here,
it records its presence by
spinning, by flipping the spin up.
If it goes through the lower
hole, it does nothing to the electron.
This is the apparatus which
records which way the electron goes,
and this is the apparatus which
one extra spin, it could be another electron, or
it could just be some abstract system with two states,
and if the electron goes through the upper hole here,
it records its presence by flipping the spin to up.
Let's do that problem, I think we can, I think
we, we'll see if we can get the problem done,
but we will go through it again,
I think, because it's probably the most interesting.
What's that?
We could put a detector in the other hole too, but
I don't think we need a detector in the other hole,
because if it doesn't go through here, it does
go through here, so we would have a funny situation,
we would have a very funny situation
if we put a detector at both places,
and both of them didn't record,
but the electron got over to here,
so presumably that's forbidden.
You really only need a detector in one place to
tell you that the electron either did go through here,
or it didn't go through here.
Why can't it go through both?
Because it's an electron, an electron can't go through both,
it's not big enough to go through both,
it either goes through one or the other, right?
But if you measure it, it
goes through one or the other, right?
If you measure it, it will
go through one or the other, right,
if you monitor it, you will find
that it goes through one or the other,
if you don't monitor it, there's no way
that you can know which one it went through,
if you do monitor it, at the end
you can go back and check that electron.
Now you could put another one
over here too and analyze it,
but that way we have two electrons
and it gets a more complicated apparatus,
but we could certainly do it, it would be
fun to do it and see what we get.
Okay, so let's then start.
We start with the electron over here.
It starts in the state
zero, but that's not enough information.
We also have to specify the state of the spin.
So now this is a
composite system composed of two parts,
the electron, which can be
at any one of these sites,
but happens to start at zero, and the spin,
and the spin starts down.
So let's put in the coordinate of the spin here.
That's the initial state, spin down, electron at zero.
The electron comes over to here.
Now what happens if it goes through the upper state?
Let's close off this one
and forget it for a moment.
If it goes through the upper configuration,
then the electron comes out, or
the configuration of the whole system,
forget the electron, the whole system
then comes out in the state one.
That's because this is position number
one, this is position number minus one.
It comes out one, but what
happens to the electron, to the spin?
It's up.
So if we go through the upper hole,
the state of the system is one up.
What happens if we go through the lower hole?
I hate this notation, one and minus one.
I should not have done that.
Minus one and down, I'll put a comma in there.
What happens if I open both holes?
If I open both holes,
by the linearity of quantum mechanics,
the state that comes out the other
side here is the sum of these two.
One plus configuration of electron at minus one,
with spin down.
So, by the time the electron comes
out, or the electron arrives at this point,
it arrives at this point, and
again we have a superposition of states,
but notice that it's entangled now.
The position of the electron
has become entangled with the spin.
It's very much like down up plus up down.
We have an entanglement between the recording apparatus
and whether the electron went through
the upper hole or the lower hole.
That's what a measurement is.
It's an entanglement between the apparatus,
and the apparatus is just an electron spin here,
and the system, the system being the
position of the electron that went through.
Now, what happens after that?
What happens by the time it
gets over to the screen over here?
Let's see.
Let's use this blackboard.
Well, let's assume that nothing happens to the spin.
If the spin is up,
it's up and it stays up,
but the electron proceeds to do
exactly what it would have done
after it passes through here.
All right?
Let's assume that, that it just continues on its way,
leaving the spin up,
but remember, previously,
one went to summation over n,
psi n, n.
That's what we found over here.
Well, if nothing happens to the spin
during the journey of the electron over to here,
we can just stick in the spin coordinate
and just say,
electron in the upper configuration with the spin up
evolves exactly as it did before
without the spin doing anything.
The spin just stays up.
What happens if we start with
the electron in the lower state here?
That was minus one.
That evolved into some phi sub n, n.
But now, we should put in
the coordinate of the spin, d.
What happens if both roots are open?
If both roots are open,
then the final state is sum on n,
psi n with n up,
plus phi n with n down.
Again, it's an entangled state.
The,
the,
the coordinates of the position of the electron
are entangled with the apparatus,
with the upness and the downness.
We can now calculate,
I'm getting a little bit tired,
I think we'll probably go on next week,
but here's the problem.
What is the probability
that we arrive at a particular n?
Now we have a different situation.
We have two orthogonal possibilities for the spin.
To calculate,
well, I'm going to quit now,
because I think I've probably given
you more than enough for tonight.
Here's our problem.
To calculate the probability
that we've arrived at the mth site,
in particular,
the probability that we've arrived at the origin,
zero.
Anybody know what the answer's going to be?
Just the sum of the two.
And the reason is there are no cross terms
because the cross terms involve the inner
product of a down with an up.
And the inner product of a
down with an up is zero.
The cross terms won't be there anymore
because when we go to calculate the probabilities,
ups and downs are orthogonal to each other,
and the cross terms will not be there.
I'm going to go through this.
I'm going to go through this in detail.
We'll use projection operators.
I don't know, we'll do it a dozen different ways.
But what you will see
is that
the presence of the recording device over here
destroys the interference.
So if you actually did a measurement
to determine which way the electron went,
then probabilities would add as
they do in classical physics.
It's only if you don't record
which way the electron goes
so that nobody will ever know,
so that there's no record left in the system
of which way the electron went,
that the interference takes place.
But the message for the moment
just for the moment
is that making a measurement
is establishing entanglement
between a device and the system.
It's establishing entanglement
between the device and the system.
And in this case,
where is it?
Adding these up,
adding the state vectors up
has an entanglement
between whether you're at one and minus one,
and whether the electron spin
or whether the spin degree of freedom
is up or down.
So, and the destruction of the interference
is what is called the collapse of the wave function.
In particular, it's the collapse
of the interference part of the wave,
of the probabilities,
the part which has to do with the cross terms
between the si's and the fi's.
They're destroyed by the measurement.
In the experiment you did before,
before you flipped the spin,
you did the spin to label
whether it went through the top or the bottom.
Yeah.
You had a couple of entangled states there also.
What's that?
Your two states were entangled there also.
Before we did what?
Before you changed the experiment
so that you were...
We didn't have any.
All we had was this.
Okay.
Yeah.
All right.
This state was exactly the same as this state.
Yeah, okay.
The state that those evolved from,
just one plus minus one.
Right.
That's the way we're going to do that.
You're going to have some bounds there.
Okay.
You're not calling those entangled?
No.
No, no, no, no, no, no.
To have entanglement,
you have to have entanglement
with something.
No, those aren't entangled.
That's just a simple superposition of states.
Simple superposition of states.
Yeah, there's only one system.
There's only one system
and it's the electron
and it's in a superposition of states.
In the other case,
there are two systems,
electron and spin,
and the two systems are entangled.
Now, let me ask you this.
What's the process of the state
when it's entangled?
It's the process of the state
when it's entangled.
In the other case, there are two systems,
electron and spin, and the two systems are entangled.
You learn something about one of
them by looking at the other.
So you learn something about which orbit
you went through by looking at the spin.
And then when you have it interact with
that middle screen there by flipping a spin,
that introduces another system or
subsystem or object into it.
Yes, it introduces another subsystem into it,
and it introduces a system into which
the electron gets entangled.
It's that establishment of entanglement between
system and apparatus which constitutes the measurement.
Professor, let's imagine the same setup, and it's
physical, so the hole at the top has,
there are all sorts of atoms
around there, so there's always an electron.
So couldn't an electron just, I mean,
in the original case where you have interference,
an electron becomes entangled with
the one that passes through.
What I'm trying to do is separate the knowledge
verb and the testing verbs from the physical apparatus.
Okay?
Yeah.
I think, if I'm not mistaken.
Supposing these are real things.
Can't this electron get entangled with an atom
in the, yes, the answer is it could.
And if it does, it destroys the interference pattern.
So that's why you cool down your apparatuses.
That's why you don't want to have a lot
of gas around that the electron can bump into.
Photons are not so bad because
photons don't interact very strongly with anything.
They're much more weakly interacting than electrons.
If you really do it with electrons, an electron passing
through here, its electric charge might disturb something over here.
And that disturbance, if this
disturbance was enough, here's the criteria.
If the disturbance is sufficient, that
when you look at the disturbance afterwards,
you can tell definitely that the electron is not
going to be able to get into the atom.
You can tell definitely that the
electron went through the upper slit.
Then you completely destroy the interference pattern.
Now you might have a situation like this.
You might have a situation where
there's some degree of freedom in there,
which initially had some probability
distribution which looks like this.
Some degree of freedom in here,
position of some atom or something,
and it has some probability, quantum
probability distribution that looks like this.
The electron goes through here.
If it shifts the probability
distribution so that it's not overlapping,
then when you look afterwards at
the system, you know, yes, no,
whether it went through the
upper one or the lower one.
You following me?
Right.
Under that circumstance, that
will destroy the interference pattern.
But there's a less severe situation where
the electron going through the upper hole here
may just shift the probability distribution a little bit.
And then you can't tell uniquely
whether by looking at the final situation
where the electron went through
one hole or the other hole,
then the interference pattern
will not be completely destroyed.
But it is a matter of degree.
It's a matter of degree, yeah.
It's a matter of how much of a
disturbance and how much that disturbance tells you.
Now if you really freeze things, make them
real cold and put everything into its ground state
so there's nothing that is easily disturbed,
then you can create pretty much the idealized situation
where after you've gone through,
there's just nothing that's been recorded.
In particular, if the system has an energy gap,
if it takes some energy to
make an excitation in the system,
to excite it or to disturb it,
and the electron or the photon is very low energy,
it may not have enough energy to make the disturbance.
In that case, you have the interference pattern.
So it can be a question of energetics,
whether if there's an energy gap that it takes
a certain minimum amount of energy to disturb the system,
then a low energy photon or a
low energy electron just can't disturb it,
and you would have the perfect interference pattern.
So you get the interference pattern with single electrons?
Well, you can't see an interferon-
you can never see a
probability distribution with just one electron.
But what you can do is
send one electron through at a time.
One electron through at a time.
Every 20 years, you send an electron through.
And after many, many electrons go through,
you look at the probability distribution here.
And it's the probability distribution
that has the interference pattern.
One electron just goes blip somewhere.
There's not much you can read off that.
As always, an experiment always really means
either repetition of the same
experiment over and over again,
or many, many
identical experiments performed simultaneously.
But it means the recording of statistics
after many events of the same kind.
Right.
So, you know, to be clean about it,
and we don't want to have to
worry about two electrons at the same time,
we send the electrons through once every 20 years
and make sure they don't talk to each other
and don't give anything away to each other.
So the effect of measurement
is always to destroy interference?
Yes.
It always has an effect of destroying interference.
It destroys entanglement.
No, it creates entanglement.
No, the measurement on the screen.
After you determine which particular element is landing at.
Yeah, once you... Right.
It destroys interference.
Right.
It creates entanglement.
Well, it's the entanglement which
corresponds to the measurement itself,
the formation of entanglement.
But once it becomes entangled with the apparatus here,
and you...
Well, we'll talk more about measurement.
Yeah, I don't think of the
middle as much as the middle.
It's just the fact you're
letting it interact with the middle.
So it splits now by magnetic field,
which is changing the spin, perhaps, but...
Yeah, you can do another measurement over here.
And that measurement over here
would further collapse the wave function
and throw away some of the entanglement.
You're right.
But this measurement over here
is the establishment of entanglement.
The second measurement could be establishment
of entanglement with yet another system,
if we put another electron over here.
You know, it's a question
of observers observing observers observing observers.
We could even have an electron which would...
which would monitor the spin over here.
And...
It's sort of like you went
through the whole discussion of exactly...
when it's interacting with the middle screen.
Yeah.
And it's...
You're changing, perhaps, the spin, but
you could do it a little bit...
Now, you can turn this thing from zero to one.
So that means you're increasing the amount of entanglement.
Yes.
And that makes sense.
Yeah.
You could...
You can turn up the interaction
between the electron and the spin.
Yeah.
So, for example, if you had a very weak interaction,
then most of the time that the electron went through,
it would not flip the spin.
You can have coefficients in front
of that one and minus one.
You've got a very top of third.
Yeah.
You could certainly...
That's right.
You can...
We could make up some other game, but the game
that I made up is that we did a complete measurement.
We did an accurate measurement that told us whether
we went through the upper slit or the lower slit.
Now we can talk about weaker measurements,
where we only get some partial knowledge,
where we find out that it was more likely that
it went through the upper one than the lower one.
Your wave function here on the other
side will have states with down and down.
That's right.
Instead of this one being up, there will be a
piece with a down and another piece with an up.
Right.
And the one with a
down might be the bigger one,
in which case you mostly do have the interference.
Yeah.
So there are weaker and stronger measurements.
I had a question about...
The preceding program is copyrighted by Stanford University.
Please visit us at stanford.edu.