This program is brought to you by Stanford University.
Please visit us at stanford.edu.
I just want to go very
briefly over the two-slit experiment again.
I don't think we ever quite
finished, so let me finish that discussion.
The two-slit experiment, and we made a
very simple version of the two-slit experiment.
There's a source, and I called it an electron.
It could be a photon, it
could be any kind of particle, whatever.
But let's call it an
electron since I'm used to it.
The electron is emitted from the source.
Now if you like, you can imagine that the
electron can be emitted from any one of several
places.
So, let's do that.
Okay.
So, there is a barrier to
the electron over here with some openings.
Again, the openings could be in any one
of any several places, but for simplicity, let's
just suppose that there are only two openings.
I don't remember what I called them last time.
I think I might have called
them plus one and minus one.
I hate that.
That doesn't sound good.
So let's call them.
Let's call them A and B this time.
A and B. I think I called this point zero.
And the rest, the electron can go through the
little hole at A, it can go through the
little hole at B, and just imagine that the
rest is blocked off so that if an electron
hits any one of the other sites, for
simplicity, you can just pretend that it gets reflected
back.
If it arrives at A,
it can go through the slit.
It could be A0 and cherry and cherry.
What does that mean?
Well, Well, it could be a very
kinds blank spot, and then the other side.
But still, the electron can pass over lot of sala.
So it requires both of these
elements but let's do it again.
One, two, three, I think I did an contact
about here and you can see the what, a dot
over here, and a dot over here, and I think
the first set this time is going to pass back
to the point where I said no.
Take overirty, you can't drive over here.
It's two dashes.
Right?
And two one.
So, what's going to happen is you're going
to have total indicator A of the insgesamt.
but eventually we will.
But the most important thing is
that states change in a linear way.
That means if you start with
a linear superposition of two states
with coefficients,
what it evolves into is the same linear superposition
of whatever any one of them evolved into.
So if, for example,
well, let's start.
We start with an electron in state 0.
Incidentally, for the present purposes,
the electron has no spin.
We don't have to worry about the electron's spin.
That's irrelevant for the moment.
It just is at a place.
And so the states of the electron are simply characterized
by which one of these vertical positions they're at.
So we start the electron right
at the center at point 0.
It evolves.
And it evolves into a linear
superposition of states at A and B.
The electron has no particular preferred reason
to go to either A or B.
And let's suppose it's nice and symmetric.
So it has equal amplitude.
Equal amplitude to get to A or B.
So 0 goes to A plus B.
What does A plus B mean?
It means a state.
So it's a state in which
the electron could be at A.
You could find it with
a probability of half at A.
And you could find it with
a probability of half at B.
And it's just a quantum
superposition of the two configurations.
Now, when it gets to A,
it then, if it gets to A,
it then moves on, and it
moves on to the screen here.
So we can say that A evolves into some superposition,
arbitrary superposition, nothing special.
A sum on N of some coefficients,
which represent the probability amplitudes,
psi sub M,
of the electron now being at the Mth place.
That's what happens if you were to have started.
The way you can think about it is,
forget the whole B altogether.
Start an electron at A,
and wait a while,
and it will arrive at a superposition of states,
which is the same as the superposition of states,
with different amplitudes,
psi sub M, M.
Or, if you started at B,
it will also evolve,
and I think I called the coefficient here,
phi M times M.
Okay, so let's first begin with one hole completely closed.
The electron can only go through A.
If it can't go through B altogether,
we can forget this, we close it up,
and the probability that it's going to go through A,
that the electron arrives at the Mth site here,
is just going to be psi star M, psi M.
And I'm focused on the Mth site.
Don't worry about any of the others.
Just the amplitude that the electron gets to point M,
is psi M, and the probability that it gets there,
we can just call P M,
is psi star M, psi M.
That's assuming it goes through the root A.
In other words, if we have blocked off hole B,
maybe we should give it a name,
maybe I should stick an A over here,
to indicate that it went through the opening A.
Likewise, if I close up the hole A,
and open up the hole B,
then the probability is,
phi star M, phi M.
Now in classical logic,
classical statistics,
classical probability theory,
statistical mechanics,
if you had a beam of particles,
which was not made with enough precision,
so, you know, with some uncertainty in it,
some of the particles might go through A,
some of them may go through B,
but our expectation would be that
the probability to get to M,
would be the sum of
the probabilities of going through A,
or going through B.
We would just add those probabilities.
Not so in quantum mechanics.
In quantum mechanics,
what we have to write,
is that if we start
at A, we get to here,
if we start at B, we get to here,
but if we start at A plus B,
if we start with the state A plus B,
which the electron is sort of equally between these two,
then what we have to get to, A plus B,
we'll go to,
summation of N,
psi sub N times N,
oops, psi sub M times M, I guess,
sum of M,
plus phi sub M times M,
and I can just represent
that by adding psi to phi,
so it just becomes sum of
psi M plus phi M,
times M.
Alright, let's forget for the moment the sum.
Let's just focus on a particular point, M.
Not even interested in the sum here,
just focus on a particular point, M.
What is the probability that the electron gets to M?
And the answer is the square of this amplitude,
or the square, it times its complex conjugate,
and so the answer is,
P M, the probability to get to M,
when both A and B are both open,
is, well, let's just square that out,
which will give four terms,
psi star M, psi M,
plus phi star M, phi M,
plus,
psi star M, phi M,
plus, psi M, phi star M.
Alright, so the answer is,
the sum of the two original probabilities,
plus an extra term,
and the extra term is called the interference term,
the interference between the two trajectories,
one of them going through the upper hole,
and one of them going through the lower hole.
This is no analog in any kind of classical statistics,
this extra term,
and to see how weird it is,
I mean, for example,
if M happened to lie
right on the symmetry point here,
then you'd expect,
you'd expect,
psi and phi to be equal, by symmetry,
and this would give you four times
the probability of going through either hole.
It's not hard to arrange by going off-center here,
you can find, well,
you can either go off-center,
or you can do other little tricks,
in the beam of particles here,
to make psi equal to minus phi,
and then you would just get zero probability.
So despite the fact that the electric field
of the electron can get to M through A,
or through B,
if you open A and B in that particular circumstance,
the electron just won't get there.
As I said, that's as weird
as anything I know in quantum mechanics,
and it's very, very simple.
But now comes the question,
which we started to talk about last time,
I think we may have even finished it,
but I want to review it again.
What happens if somebody actually is present,
and actually watches whether the electron
goes through one hole or the other,
and even records whether it goes
through one hole or the other?
Then what happens?
Surely then, you must know whether
the electron went through A or B.
So we made up a little system,
we added another element here,
we added a spin.
The spin can either be up or down.
It could be the electron's spin itself.
There's no reason why it couldn't be the electron's spin,
but I simply wanted to
think of it as an external
measuring apparatus that could record
the presence of the electron,
so I didn't want to think
of it as part of the electron.
Let's not think of it as part of the electron.
We add another degree of freedom over here,
which is a spin which can be up or down.
Up or down.
And let's not ask exactly how it happens,
but when the electron
pans
through the hole A,
there's no spin at B,
when the electron passes through the hole at A,
whatever it does is it
gives a kick to the spin,
and it flips it.
That's an assumption.
An assumption about the way the spin is located,
how it interacts with the electron.
We measure over and over again
that when the electron does pass by the spin,
it does kick it over.
So we know what happens.
An electron passing by the spin kicks it over,
kicks it from, let's say, from down to up.
And that's what happens.
All right, now let's reanalyze the experiment.
We don't just have an electron.
We have an electron and another spin.
So we have to add
something into the state vector here.
We can't just describe it
as an electron at point zero,
but we have to describe it
as an electron at point zero
with the spin down,
or our apparatus unactivated.
We can think of it as the apparatus being unactivated,
and so that's our initial state.
If the electron goes through the upper hole,
then it becomes state A.
The electron is at point A,
but the spin gets flipped up.
If it goes through hole B,
the spin doesn't see the electron,
and it stays pointing down.
So now we have something like this.
Now we have something new.
The two states A and B
are correlated and entangled with a spin.
They're entangled with a spin
such that by measuring the spin,
you can tell whether the
electron went through the upper hole
or the lower hole.
Well, what happens to A up?
Once A, once the electron departs from here,
it no longer interacts with the spin,
assume,
I assume that it will
not kick the spin over again,
and so all that will happen is A will evolve
exactly as A evolved before,
except the spin will remain up.
This is not a measurement, though.
This is a measurement.
Are we collapsing a wave packet?
Mm-hmm.
Collapsing the wave packet simply
means destroying the interference pattern.
No, I mean at A and B,
when you're changing the spin, possibly.
You're flipping a spin.
Yes.
That constitutes a measurement of the electron,
and it constitutes a collapse of
the wave packet of the electron.
When thought of as the
composite system of electron and spin,
no, it doesn't collapse the wave packet.
The only way to collapse the
wave packet of a combined system
is for something else to look at it.
Forget collapsing the wave packet.
No, no, no.
There are two things in there.
If you had collapsed the wave packet,
you wouldn't have A U plus B D.
You don't have one or the other.
No.
You force it into the spin.
No, no, no, no, no, no, no.
Collapsing the wave packet is a language to use
if you don't want to remember
that there's this other spin there.
Then you forget the other spin,
and you just say the wave packet
got collapsed to either A or B
by the presence of the spin.
By the presence of the spin.
But if you keep the spin present,
if you keep the spin present,
in other words, if you
include the apparatus into the description,
then you don't talk about collapse of the wave packet.
You talk about establishment of entanglement.
Okay, and the apparatus in
this case is simply the spin.
It's just simply the spin.
It could be anything.
It could be a pointer that has two states.
It could be the emission of a photon,
so that up, so that
down could stand for no photon,
and up could stand for a photon being present.
So it could be anything which distinguishes
which of the two holes it went through.
I mean, even if you didn't have the spin,
you better go through the top or the bottom.
It interacted with this metal, this
metal aperture that has two holes.
Yeah.
I mean, there was some momentum.
The question is whether it
left a mark on the metal.
Okay.
Now, the answer is yes, it could leave a mark,
but it could leave a mark,
but that depends on details
of this metal plate that's there,
and in particular, if the
metal plate has an energy gap,
if it takes some energy to excite it,
and the electron is low energy,
it may not have enough energy to excite the,
anything interesting in this system here,
and so it will not leave a mark.
But that's the criteria.
It doesn't leave a mark.
Let me say this.
I was sort of saying, well, it's going through,
and it has some momentum to get to the end,
as opposed to way up high,
but maybe we're up.
But we, yeah, but you don't have a spread.
So you have a spread of
momentum states in A and B,
but it's the same.
Okay.
There's no difference.
Wait.
Are you asking whether,
are you asking whether you can
tell which hole the electron went through
by looking at the red?
Yes.
Okay, good, good.
Let's take that care.
Good.
The electron goes through the upper hole,
and obviously it gives a little kick upward to the,
if it goes through the lower hole,
it gives a little kick downward.
All right?
So it changes the momentum of the screen here.
All right.
Now, we're getting a little bit ahead of ourselves
into a little more complex situation, obviously,
but let me tell you what the answer is.
The answer is that the,
that the electron is going to be,
it's going to be,
it's going to be
our top level incident
and we find that the,
that the,
that the screen here itself
has an uncertainty in its momentum.
and it's pretty well spread, and
the reason it's pretty well spread
is because the location is very, very nicely definite
so it's pretty well spread
then the electron goes through the upper hole
if it goes through the upper
hole it gives a little kick
and it shifts this distribution a little bit
if it went through the lower hole it
was shifted the other way a little bit
but you can't tell uniquely
and in fact as long as the kick is small by
comparison with the spread in the momentum space wave function here
you basically, it almost completely overlaps with it
and you don't get kicked into
an orthogonal state of the motion
so that's a very, very good question
but there is a very, very good answer
so in the last case where
you're not purely in the motion
you're only in the motion
and up or down
right, right, so that's right
it's exactly the same thing as if instead of saying
when the electron goes through
here it kicks down to up
instead it kicks it to almost
down plus a little bit of up
or the other way, whatever
and that will allow you to have
different degrees of destruction of the interference pattern
but I want to take the extreme example now
where you do a complete measurement
where you do an absolute measurement
which means that you establish a complete correlation
between A and B on the one hand
and up and down on the other hand
so that by looking at the spin
you can determine completely and uniquely
which of the two holes the electron went through
that's the notion, if you like, of an experiment
of a measurement
establishing an entanglement between
a system and an apparatus
just being the spin
okay, so let's just do the
dot all the i's and cross all the t's
and now in this situation
let's see, B, we never finished here
B did not kick the electron up
so B, if the electron goes through B
the spin stays down
and it just continues to stay down
so now we have a state, as I said
with this entanglement
between the wave function of the electron
psi or phi on the one hand
and up and down on the other hand
alright, let's just go through the formal
the very formal motions of calculating the probability
that the electron is found at point M
so, there are two ways that
the electron could be found at M
it could be found with the electron at M
with the spin up
or electron at M with the spin down
so what we have to
do is build the projection operator
onto the state where the electron is at point M
alright, remember what the rule is
if you have some property that you
want to represent by a projection operator
you take the subspace corresponding to that property
you find the basis of orthogonal states in that subspace
then you build the projection operator
as a sum of dyads
sum over all the basis vectors in the subspace
of the dyad composed out of them
alright, what are the states in
which the electron is at M
there are two states
there's M up
M up
and there's M down, M down
that's it, those are the only two states
in which the electron is found at M
so this is the projection operator
onto the state, onto the configuration
where the electron is at M
so now what we have to do
is we have to take the final state
what is the final state?
the final state is the sum of these two
we add these together
now we cannot factor out
M up and M down
and write it in this form here
because each one multiplies a different ket vector
psi M multiplies one ket vector
phi M multiplies another ket vector
alright, let's just do it
let's bite the bullet and do the whole thing
M up
I need more room
plus M down
M down
that's the projection operator
let's see
put something around it
now we take the state vector
the state vector
is
sum on N
that's a summation index there
N up
psi N
plus phi N
N down
likewise on this side over here
we have the same thing
psi star N
oops, psi star N
N up
plus phi star N
N down
put some brackets around all these things
alright, now first of all
there are the non-cross terms
the non-interference terms
the terms like psi star psi
let's just look at them
psi N here
this piece here
has an up spin
and it can only combine
with the up spin over here
it's orthogonal to the down spin
and so the inner product of
an up with a down is zero
you only get a contribution
of the up spin over here
you only get a contribution from up with up
and furthermore you only get a contribution
when N is equal to M
the inner product of up N
is only non-zero
with M up when N is equal to N
when M is equal to N
and then the inner product is one
okay, so out of here
you pick out the single term
where M is equal to N
likewise from this side
M has to equal N
and up has to equal up
otherwise you don't get a contribution
so from the direct terms
you get psi star M
psi M
okay
and also similarly
phi star M
phi M
okay, that one comes
from this term in the projection operator
but you get nothing from the cross term
the cross term
is the number of spins
coming when you try to
combine a down with an up
up here can only go with up here
but then the up over here
will kill the down over here
so the projection operator does not allow you
to combine a psi with a phi
because these spins are orthogonal in the various terms
alright, so here's the result
the result is that if you do a measurement
the result is the sums of the probabilities
exactly as you would have imagined in classical physics
so if you don't look at
the root that the electron takes
and if nothing looks, not just you
but if no mark is left
that you can ever, or anybody else
can ever determine afterwards
whether the electron went up or down
or through the upper root or the lower root
then there's an interference pattern
yeah
probably
where, here?
no
above this, probably
probably
yeah, where is it, over here?
yeah
inside the
but the main point is
the main point is you've got to match
not just
whoops
sorry
I think he's the one who's sorry
you've got to match not only the ends
but the upy downy-ness of the state vectors
and that will cancel all of the state vectors
and that is the starting point
for what we'd call, super-cars
and what are these different states and then
then you're going to argue is it's a
If you're getting no market left, then
whether it goes to A or B, then...
Then there's an interference pattern.
In other words, that means
that you have to add amplitudes.
If there's A, if there's... yes?
So you can kick the electron
also at B if you look at...
What's that?
Oh, you get exactly... if you... sorry,
if you put the spin at B?
If you kick the electron at
both A and B, then you would...
Kick the electron, kick the spin.
Yeah.
Yeah, good.
Okay, let's suppose... right, let's suppose the
spin is located in some symmetrical situation,
let's say over here, where it gets equally
kicked, whether it goes through A or B.
Then what it'll come out... let's see,
where will it come out? Over here?
Then we'll just have A up plus... let's
see, up, yeah, A up plus B up, right?
And then it'll be exactly as if...
then there will be an interference pattern.
In the end, you will not be able to tell from
the fact that the spin is up which hole it went through.
So if... if... good.
Then we... that would leave us in this situation, right?
The way you're telling how... which hole you went through is
finally measures the spin of the electron at the end, right?
Well, I don't have to do any... I do
not have to measure the spin of the electron.
The electron has measured...
The electron has done the measurement.
The electron has done the
measurement, not of the electron spin.
The electron has done the measurement
of which hole it went through.
I don't have to look at the electron... I...
sorry, I don't have to look at the spin
to know that the interference pattern will be destroyed.
I don't actually have to look at the electron.
Just the fact that the information is recorded
by a system, I could look at it,
but just the fact that it's recorded, and it's
recorded in... in the orthogonality of up and down,
that's enough to destroy the interference pattern.
So I don't ever have to look at the electron.
I just look at the
electron... sorry, I keep saying electron.
I don't ever have to look at the spin.
I just look at the electrons coming through.
I have a beam of electrons coming through.
I do this over and over again.
I send through an electron, do the experiment.
Electron arrives somewheres.
And then I put the
spin back in its original position,
do the whole experiment again.
Put the spin back in its original position,
do the whole experiment again,
and gather statistics of what the probability
is that the electron arrives in different places.
I never actually have to look at the spin.
All I have to do is look at
the electron and see where it came out,
and I will discover that there was no interference pattern.
Well, if the screen has
sufficiently little mass that it recoils,
then that will also destroy the interference?
Yeah, that's right.
If the... or another... yeah.
Basically, if the momentum wave function
of the screen here is narrow enough
so that when the electron goes
through, it gives it a kick,
and kicks it to a configuration
which is orthogonal to the original configuration,
then it will destroy the interference pattern.
Right.
In fact, there's another way
that interference patterns get destroyed.
If the electron... now, this is subtle.
This is very subtle.
But if the electron goes through the upper hole here,
then it may... and it's a slow electron.
Let's say it's a very slow electron, not too fast.
It will emit...
some radiation.
Every time an electron is accelerated,
and it has to be accelerated
to go from here to here,
it will emit a photon.
Right?
So... or it may emit a photon.
It may emit a photon.
Not that it will emit a photon.
If it goes through the lower
hole, it also may emit a photon.
The probability of emitting a photon,
incidentally, by an electron is very low.
It's about one part in
a hundred for a low-energy electron.
So only one part in a hundred...
does it emit an electron.
So it does leave a little
bit of information in the radiation field.
But with only emitting a
photon, one part in a hundred,
you cannot be certain when you look at the system
and discover there was no photon emitted,
you cannot be certain which hole it went through.
But on the other hand,
if you really whip the electron through there fast,
in other words, a high-energy electron,
and you really arranged it so that the
electron went through one hole way up on top
and the other hole way down on bottom,
so that it really had to
whip around and accelerate a lot,
then the likelihood of emitting a photon would be larger
and the interference pattern would be more destroyed.
So just the ability to emit photons
is enough to partially destroy interference patterns.
And it does.
Yeah?
So when you actually do the experiment,
you have to perform something.
You have to do a statistically large number of methods
in order to build up the data set
from which, in fact, you infer the probability distribution.
Yes.
Because you could...
Absolutely.
Your ability to approximate the probability distribution
is a function of how many experiments the electron's around.
So what you're saying is that
in the case of an electron with
a low probability of emitting a photon,
which in principle could be detected,
that is one source of noise in a practical experiment.
Yeah.
Or one source of interference...
one source of destruction of the interference pattern.
You can call it noise if you like.
Well, what you see practically is the experiment,
from a theory point of view, says
those detector statistics will contain dark and light areas.
Areas of the detector where you get particles
and areas where you don't get any particles.
But in fact,
um,
if you can get a thousand and one contrast,
you did really good.
And there's gonna be some residual, um,
number of particles that show up anyway
in the so-called dark or forbidden areas.
So my question is this.
If you have a large number of these things
and you have a system that maybe reads this,
what you're saying is that
if there is any possibility of determining after the fact
which hole the electron went through,
that will destroy the interference?
Yes.
But you may also have a situa-
a partial situation
where you,
by looking at something,
you may be able to say it was more probable
that you went through the
upper hole and the lower hole.
That's easy to do.
Yeah, that's easy to do.
For example,
as I said,
when the electron passes through here,
instead of kicking down to up,
it just kicks the,
it just kicks the direction of spin a little bit.
So that it's mostly still down
and just a little bit up.
That will partially,
that will destroy the interference pattern a little bit.
It'll blur it a little bit.
Yeah.
Correct.
Would you say that the one in a hundred times
that the proton does get bitten off
is the one time when that element of interference passed?
That would be one of the cases where-
Yeah.
What you could do is you could collect statistics
only for those events
in which a photon was emitted.
Okay?
And then you would find that the interference pattern worse.
Now,
it's not quite completely clear
because if a photon,
if a photon is emitted from here,
it may not be completely orthogonal
from a photon emitted from here.
The wave function of the photons
may not completely be orthogonal.
So you could still have a little bit of blurry,
blurry situation there.
But you know,
I mean,
you can destroy interference in many, many ways.
Just the atmosphere,
and this is,
this is the,
this is the biggest source of interference destruction.
In particular,
why don't you see me as fuzzy?
Why do you,
well,
I assume you don't see me as fuzzy.
I mean,
I start out here and you don't,
you close your eyes,
close your eyes.
Everybody close your eyes.
Okay?
And now open them.
You'll find me in the same place.
You don't find my wave function
having spread out all over the place.
In fact,
you could wait forever and ever and ever,
and you would not see my,
or the moon,
the moon's wave packet doesn't,
doesn't spread.
Part of the reason is,
part of the reason is the moon is heavy.
But the other reason is that it's constantly bombarded
by atmosphere,
by other things.
And so it's as if it's continuously measured.
And every time it's measured,
if you continuously keep measuring,
you're going to get a lot of things.
And so it's,
it's,
it's.
So if you continuously keep measuring a thing,
it will not spread at all.
I have a side suggestion here on your course next,
whenever you teach it.
Yeah?
I'm using terms like the Lapsley wave packet.
You're talking about measuring.
You just gave us a theory of measurement.
Yeah.
That's,
that's something that's,
that would be good to teach in a course.
I'm teaching.
Well.
It's a big,
big thing.
Forget.
Hm?
Well,
you're saying that things are
always interacting with one another,
so.
Well,
I'm trying to give you an extremely precise example
I give you an extremely precise example
and now we can extrapolate from that
we could work out some other examples
in which partial experiments are done
I think those are straightforward
but I'm trying to give you a crystal clear example
where there's no ambiguity
so that you can see the mechanism
by which the interference pattern is destroyed
Entanglement forces you to do that
I mean, 30, 40, 50 years ago
you could sort of get away with
loosely not worrying about it too much
except for the final consequence
Collapse of the wave packet
and collapse of the wave packet here means
collapse of this wave packet
which literally means that you
throw away the off-diagonal terms
the mixed terms, the phi-sci terms
that's
the way it's written
and that is
you can describe it that way
you say I did a
measurement, I collapsed the wave packet
but you also ought to be able to describe
the composite system of the electron and the detector
in a way that doesn't involve any
hanky-panky with collapsing wave packets and so forth
The corresponding correct description of a composite system
is entanglement took place
So that's what a
that's the importance of
entanglement
in doing measurements
and obviously it's a very important part of nature
Question
I don't know if this is relevant or not
if it is not relevant just ignore it
but you said that
photon will get emitted
because the path is curved
just in a theoretical case
there was a gravitational field present
so that it's actually a straight line
in the gravitational field presence
how would that change the situation
wait say again?
No, let's see
like the path from zero
to a to m is curved
yeah
so for that reason
Well, I mean there is no well-defined path
but you can more or less see that
that the electron had to accelerate
to go around the corner here
Right
Now, if there is a
mass sitting between a and b
Oh if there's a mass sitting between a and b?
Right. Now if there is a
mass sitting between a and b?
Yeah, so that it's actually a natural path
Yeah
Would it change the situation?
Or you could just have one of
the slits not be a deflection at all
Wouldn't change it
Yep, you could have one
of the slits not be deflected
but then the other one would be
uh
good
Look, we can think of a
thousand million variations on this theme
The end of the story is
if anything tags the
leaves a mark
telling you which way the electron went
that destroys the interference pattern
It'll destroy it partially
if it gives you some probabilistic information
about which way the electron went
not certain information but
biased
toward one direction or the other
I have a question
Does this definition of interference
contradict anything we learned in
continuum electromagnetics?
Multiple photons interacting with each other
in geometries and so forth
Is it the same thing?
Is it another way to look at the same thing?
Or is it radically different?
Um
The interference pattern here
when there are many many electrons
or let's say many photons to make it simpler
when there are many many photons
coming through all at once
the interference pattern is nothing but the
interference pattern of wave motion
of wave uh
of electromagnetic waves
Uh
The fact that it also happens for electrons
tells you that there's some sort of wave
associated with the electron
It's not the electromagnetic waves
It's the electron wave function
Okay let's move
Yeah one more
I just had a question about the
I missed last class so that
the parameters of the beam are that
it has an equal chance of being emitted with a
momentum that would put it between A and B
Well it's
Yeah yeah
Oh which would put it between A and B?
Well the setup is that
it's either fired at A or
Well we're just assuming that
if it arrives anywhere in between
it just bounces off
that this region is closed off
Yeah
So
It's blocked off
Yeah
So wrong with the shorting there's Tad then
The Tad really isn't a super positional I-1
No
No no no the cat is not
in a super position of alive and dead
Okay the cat is not in
a super position of alive and dead
That's exactly what is not true
What is true is the
cat is entangled with another system
What is it entangled with?
Uh
The question of whether the bullet was fired or not
So it's a composite system
Let's say it consists of uh
of uh gun and cat
So it's a composite system gun and cat
And the gun can be in two states
The two states are unfired and fired
Okay
The cat can be in two states dead or alive
You start with a live cat and an unfired gun
U for unfired
And then something happens and you wait a while
And after a while
The system evolves into
Live cat with some coefficient alpha
Live cat unfired gun
Plus some other coefficient
Dead cat fired gun
Okay
It is not in a super position
Live plus dead
It's in an entangled state with the gun
Alright
So you cannot do any kind
of interference experiment between live and dead
If you were to calculate
the probability of live and dead
You would have no cross terms
Uh
It's
The gun itself
The firing of the gun
Has left a mark
Firing or not firing
You don't
The point is you don't have to look at
the cat to find out if it's alive or dead
You can look at the gun
So that tells you it was entangled
And it is very much
It's basically exactly the same mathematics as this
So no
The cat in Schrodinger's experiment is not
in a super position of alive and dead
The composite system is in a super position of live
Unfired and dead fired
One more
The
I think you're being very careful when
you talk about the structure of the
Interference pattern
As being something different from
A measurement
Which is what goes on at the final
No no I'm saying when a measurement
takes place it destroys the interference pattern
Okay
Well
Exactly
But
Alright
My question is really
What goes on at the final screen that
lets us talk about probabilities rather than states
Say it again
What happens at
What
Why at the final screen can
we reduce this all to probabilities
Rather than having to go to the
The
Entangled states world
Well
I'll look for you
There is a probability postulate in quantum mechanics
And you construct the projection
operator and take its expectation value
And that's the probability
I don't know what to say beyond that
What happens is you get
the interference pattern or you don't
Yeah
And that's
Well
Okay I set up some experiment here
And now
And now why am I
Can I talk about the probability
of the electron being at the screen
I can watch
And not at the middle
Say it again
Why don't I talk about the probability
of the electron being at the screen
And some position
And not talking about it going through A or B
You can talk about it
Well you don't want to talk about it
at A or B unless you measure it
If you measure it
You can then go and ask this spin
Did it go through here
or didn't it go through here
And you will have a probability for it
having gone through here or having gone through here
Now what about at this end
At this end at some point
you have to do a measurement
As to where the electron was
In other words
You
The electron has to do something at this end
To record the fact that it
has arrived at one of these positions
We haven't talked about that
I just said
It either arrives at one of these positions
Or it doesn't
But if it arrives at one of these positions
Another kind of measurement can happen
The other kind of measurement
would be the blackening of a
Or it could be
We could for example
Put a spin at every one of these sites
If the electron arrives at that
point it flips this spin up
If it arrives at this
In other words at the end of the day
I am imagining that we do some experiment over here
To find out where the electron arrives
I have sort of suppressed that part of the experiment
You assume that this thing is
just putting more barriers in between
But if you have a scintillation screen
That will give off a photon
And then the electron can hinge on
You would then have it ricochet in some unknown direction
And you would again have a situation where
Sure
But I mean to complete the experiment
You actually have to measure where the electron is
Measuring where the electron is
Means that some sort of
mark is left on the system
By where the electron arrives over here
It could be because there are spins aligned along here
Or it could just be because
when electrons arrive on photographic plates
They blacken the spot on the plate
And we look at the black spot
We don't actually look at the electron
We look at the black spot
But the black spot becomes entangled with
the position of the electron along here
I think the answer is
that you are using the position
Of the projection operator
Yes
That is the measurement
But the process of separating a system into
That which is measured and that which measures
Is always ambiguous
You can always say
Alright look the experiment really doesn't
happen until I look at the spin
In that case you would add another element
Or you could either just say
This combined wave function here collapses
Or you could add another ingredient in
Me
And me also has two states
Me having seen spin up and
having recorded it in my brain
And me having seen spin down
and recording that in my brain
So we could say
Once I look at this
It evolves into something even more complicated
A up
And me having seen up
Plus B down and me having seen down
But then you could be watching me
Okay
The point is there's a degree of consistency
There's a degree of consistency
That the probability to find either
A or B with up and down
Is the same as the probability of A up
Me seeing up
B down
Me seeing down
So at some point there's no point in going further
And entangling anybody else in the experiment
But if you did you would still have consistency
In the case of the Schrodinger's cat face
There's more than the gun that's entangled with the cat
There's smoke in the box
Smoke in the box
But then Schrodinger is on the outside of the box
And he's not entangled
But then he looks in
And he sees one or the other
And so Schrodinger himself becomes the cat face
Schrodinger himself becomes entangled with the box
The gun
And the cat
And the process
And then Wigner who's waiting outside
He's going to ask Schrodinger what did you see
He becomes entangled
No, no, the whole world is a highly entangled thing
Because they're all correlated with each other
But they're correlated in a consistent way
Yeah
Yeah, there's no interference
There's no interference if
Unless
Unless there's been nothing to record which thing happened
Yeah, one more, one more
We're going to move on
Doesn't the uncertainty principle figure into this nod
The process of measuring affecting the event being measured
Absolutely
Well, one particular instance of it is the
As was pointed out
You might worry that the recoil of this screen here
Might ruin your measurement
By leaving a mark as to whether you
went through the upper hole or the lower hole
It's the uncertainty principle
And the uncertainty of the momentum of the screen here
Which doesn't allow you to determine
unambiguously which hole the electron went through
So certainly uncertainty principle plays a role here, yeah
The most important thing
Well, not the most important thing necessarily
But what you should keep in your mind
Is that the difference between a classical experiment
And a quantum mechanical experiment
A classical experiment, you always imagine
A classical experiment can be
done in a gentle enough way
That you can find out
what you want to find out
Without disturbing the system
Okay
Without disturbing the state of the system
Here you can see
That we have definitely disturbed the state of the system
The measurement is not done
Until the entanglement has been established
And establishing an entanglement
Is a significant change in the state of a system
And a measurement is not
done until that entanglement is established
Once that entanglement is established
It changes the answers
It changes the answers whether, for example,
there is or there isn't an interference pattern
So classical physics, you always imagine
That you could make your experiment gently enough
That it doesn't influence in any
way the system that you're studying
Or perhaps in an arbitrarily small
amount of change in the system
Whereas quantum mechanically you are forced to
In order to do an experiment to establish an entanglement
And that's a big change
That's a significant change in the system
Yeah
What about the distance between A and B
Let's say it gets arbitrarily large
What effect does that have on the interference pattern?
Well, that depends on your assumptions
Nothing particular, I don't think
I don't think it does anything particular
Of course, what it will do
Is it will make the probability of
going through either of the holes very small
So both the size and the
phi's will be very, very small
If you take the holes to be very far away
The overwhelming probability will be that it
hits the wall and gets bounced back
Chances of it getting out to very
far distances may be very much smaller
So it might, but apart from that
I don't think it has any special effect, yeah
It seems to me that it's not a big deal
But it's really lucky that all this superposition is linear
Well, I don't know if it's lucky, but
Is that really fundamentally true?
Yes, it's fundamentally true
No, no, no, no, no, no, no
Well, that's another question
But we've talked about this over and over again
And I keep telling you I don't know the answer
Except I know from experience how hard it is
To modify things a little bit
So I'm not going to answer that question
Because I honestly don't know the answer
It's an empirical fact
And it's the basis of quantum mechanics
But it's not easy to make a logically coherent story
Of a slight bit of nonlinearity
It becomes a mess
Now, there, well
Really it's the replacement of
one kind of logic by another
It's the replacement of logical
logic by another kind of logic
By the logic of classical sets
By the logic of subspaces
Why the Lord in his infinite wisdom
Decided on subspaces instead of something else
Maybe the Reverend Haggard knows, but I don't
Excuse me
Why?
Because the problem is that the
The target being this
Right
Yeah
Such that we would perhaps be able to determine
Which let it pass through after the event
Whether there was interference or not
Does that change the results of the
Well, I think what we could do is
We could put another set of detectors over here
And ask about interference over here
Is that what you're
Is that the sort of thing you're
So I was at first considering
That the detector was not a set of detectors
But it was a set of detectors over here
So I was at first considering
Would there be some way to
A detector in A
Based on some effect that would happen later in time
Such that
You know, but there's really no way to do that
And that occurred to me that
Is there a way perhaps after
The target where we'll be checking
Which way the electron went through?
Yeah, such that we would determine
Well, all I can say is
If there is something left in the system
That allows you to determine
But typically, no
I mean, if it got passed here
Without leaving any mark on the system
When it gets here
Offhand
Not really, no
But if there is a way to detect
Which way it went through
That will destroy the interference pattern
Even if the detection of them would happen
After the interference
Yeah, yeah, yeah
As I said, you don't
even have to do the detection
As long as the detection is implicitly
I mean, you don't have to do the detection
The order of time is not significant
Right?
Well, you mustn't violate causality
Cause must precede effect
So other than that
Yeah, but our measurement was
Obviously a little bit chosen
For the impact of the target
But if we were able to
Based on monitoring it after it hit that point
Determine which way it went through
Uh, I guess
We would have to set up
A very specific experimental situation
And analyze it
Because I can't analyze in the abstract
Without having a very, very definite concrete
Example in front of me
If you had a bubble chamber on the other side
Well, the bubble chamber on the other side
Wouldn't tell you which hole
it went through on this side
It would
It would not
Not in general, no
I mean
And you wouldn't just see it
Coming out of that hole
Let's say immediately after A and B
You have something like that
Say it again
Let's say immediately following your barrier at A and B
You have some magical, you know, ball chamber
Well, yeah, I think you could project
Oh, you mean if the trajectory remembers
Which way the electron went through
Yeah, but
If you have a bubble chamber over here
Well, let's say
Just immediately following the
Over here?
Yeah, sure
Where?
A big bubble chamber?
A little bubble chamber?
I would say it covers the whole thing
Okay, so big bubble chamber
Yeah
Okay, then what?
Well, does it
That way it would destroy the energy?
Oh, absolutely
Absolutely
Certainly
For sure
Yeah, definitely
There's automatically no
Yeah
Interference
But what if the
Well
Then it's constantly giving you
Just to be precise about it
We could put a thin wall of bubble chamber here
And then afterwards
The electron arrives over here
And we look over here and we see
Do we see a track over here
Or do we see a track over here?
The answer is that anything that
Anything that leaves a track
Will certainly destroy the interference pattern
For sure
But you got it on
the opposite side of the target
From what I was saying
So I guess
Maybe the real answer is just
The interference of the target
But
So we keep it in the main
Well, as I said
Each example has to be analyzed separately
But the rule
The rule is very general
If there is a mark left on the system
From which you can deduce
The degree of ambiguity will determine
Will determine the magnitude of the effect
But let's say
Which you can deduce unambiguously
Which of the holes the electron went through
Then there will be no interference pattern
And that's the most general way of saying it
Now you can think of all sorts of examples
And but always trace it back to that
Ask whether there is or there isn't
Anything left on the system which remembers
And always bring it back to this here
When you get out of the situation
Where you have
I'm trying to figure out
How to get out of this situation
What?
Why?
Things are already intangible to each other
Yeah
Okay
So at some point
You are able to perform the experiment
Where you do get interference
What is it that causes you to have that
That degree of uncertainty
Or whatever it is
Is it just
Uncertainty in the
For example
In the momentum of this screen here
Is that
That's what you're talking about
Previous history
Suppose I want to get an interference pattern
After running it through the bubble chamber
Oh
Now at some point
I have a definite track
Now what does the apparatus have to produce
In order to get an interference pattern to draw
Well
That is
Where did that come from in the first place
Wait a minute
If everything is intangible already
That's not
No it better not be intangible already
You have to start with
You have to start with some systems
Which are disentangled
Let's move on
And we can
And because
This
I understand
Why
It's difficult to move on
There's a zillion infinite number of questions
But I think it's a good idea
Having learned the rule
Go back
And do the exercises yourself
See if you can figure out yourself
The answer to some of these questions
Because they're good questions
It's not
They're not good questions
But I think we can go on
and on and on forever and ever
I still have a question
Where does disentanglement come from
Because obviously
Everything is going to be entangled
By making a measurement
You actually do some disentanglement
For example
By making a measurement
Of the electron over here
You
For all possible reasons
You can do some disentanglement
But you can't do it
Because
You can't do it
You
For all practical purposes
You start over again
And you start over again
With the electron definitely over here
That electron is now
From your perspective
You throw away the other possibility
Having seen the electron
Having seen the spin up
You simply forget this one here
You forget it altogether
And you say
Aha
The electron is over here
Let's start over again
And now you can say
This electron
This electron is over here
And what you start with
Is the state A up
A up is not an entangled state
You just throw this one away
You say
I made a measurement
I looked at it
I saw that this one
That the spin was up
So I know that the initial starting point
Was A up
And I throw away the other
Yeah
That's right
So we could
We could
Make a
Make greater
What if A up?
What if With this
And
nested hierarchy of different
levels of discussing the problem
As I said, the division
The division
Here's your system
Here's your detector
Here's somebody looking at it
Here's somebody looking at looking at it, and
so forth and so on and so on
And where you draw the line
between the system and the detection
is ambiguous, but depending on where you draw the line
At some point you will have
to say the wave function collapses
But in observing
this entire system here
you won't say that the electron
wave function collapses, you will say the
combination of wave function of
electron, detector, and Schrodinger, or whoever
is collapsed
by Wigner making an experiment on
This was a cat, I guess
A cat, gun, and Schrodinger
You get the idea
And the only question is whether it's consistent
Whether at the end of the day
when Schrodinger comes to Wigner and says
what did you see me think
And Wigner says, I thought I saw
you think that the cat was dead
And Schrodinger says yes, that's what
I saw, the cat was dead
That's consistent
Quantum mechanics is hooked up in such a
way that you don't know who was killed
don't run into inconsistencies in this manner.
Let's move on.
We've talked about entanglement.
Well, we want to take a break.
We have not gone as far
as I had imagined we would,
but that's fine.
That's not a problem.
Well, let's keep going a little.
Entropy.
I want to discuss entropy.
Really what I want to discuss is how
do you define a measure of the degree of entanglement
between two systems?
If I have two electrons
and both their spins are up,
they're not entangled.
They're not entangled.
You learn nothing about one by looking at the other.
There's no sense of looking at one
and finding out some piece of information you didn't
know about the other.
So that's not an entangled state.
Two spins both up.
Generally, unentangled states are called product states.
And in product states, each of the subsystems by itself
has a very well-defined state that
is entangled.
And you might as well disregard the other one altogether.
But they can get entangled.
They can get entangled.
And the amount of entanglement
is a quantitative measure of it.
There are many quantitative measures of entanglement.
But the one we're going to
talk about, and the usual one,
is called entanglement entropy.
So I want to explain what entanglement entropy is.
It is the thing.
If you want to find out whether it's
entanglement or not, some description of a composite system
involves entanglement.
The test is to calculate the entanglement entropy.
So first of all, let's talk about classical entropy.
What is classical entropy?
Imagine we have some system.
And the system has some collection of states.
Classical.
Now we're doing classical.
So logic is Boolean algebra.
It's just a classical set theory.
There's the space of all possible states of some system.
And let's take the states to be discrete.
So there's some finite number of states.
Let's call number of states capital N. Now,
entropy is not just a property of a system.
It's a property of a system together with your state
of knowledge about the system.
In other words, it's something that
has to do with both you and
your state of knowledge, on the one
hand.
And the system itself.
The less you know about
a system, the more it's entropy.
The more you know about it, the less it's
entropy, according to the definition of entropy
that we're going to talk about.
All right, so let's see.
How can we quantify that?
So there's capital N states.
And let's suppose that what we know is that
the system is in one of little N states.
One of little N states.
Capital N is not going to
play any tremendous role for the moment.
All we know is that the system
is in one of little N states,
with equal probability, with equal probability
for all those little N states.
Then we would say we're ignorant.
And our degree of ignorance is little n.
Little n, it could be
in any of little n states.
The bigger the number of states, the bigger the probability.
The bigger little n is, the
less we know about the system, right?
If we knew that little n was just one,
in other words, that would be the situation where
we know exactly what the state of the system
is, and it's in one of the states, one known
state of the system, then we
would say little n is one.
In that case, you would say the entropy is zero.
We have no ignorance.
We know everything there is to know about the system.
And so there is no ignorance.
What if little n is big N?
If little n is big N, it means we
know nothing about which state the system is in.
That corresponds to the maximum entropy.
So let me give you one definition of
the entropy, which is good for this situation here.
It is simply by definition logarithm, it's called
S, and it's the logarithm of the number
of states.
S. And it's the logarithm of
the number of states in the system.
T is the length...
Yes, you are children!
S. fratern, s&DSo if you do this, then your
state for N is one state.
It means that the entropy is large.
It's higher than Jessie 1200, 3
personally dedicated hypotheses, is a simple number
ofière, and it has the same tables.
S entity SD, yo権
That you, beg my pardon?
of states, you add entropy. That's one way of saying it.
Another way of saying it, let me give you another example.
Supposing my system is again a system of spins,
and I know something about a whole bunch of them,
ups and downs and ups and downs and so
forth, and I know nothing whatever about the system.
I know nothing whatever about the
system. How many possible states are there?
Well, the answer is two to the number, now
another completely different n, two to the number of spins.
How many spins are there? Let's call them m, m
spins. Two to the m is the total number of states.
And what's the logarithm of two to the m?
And if I knew nothing at all about the system,
then n here would just be two to the
m, any one of two to the m states.
The logarithm of the number of
states would just be proportional to m.
So what the logarithm measures is the number
of bits of information, a bit being a spin.
The number of bits, now a
bit basically means a two-level system.
The number of bits is the number of bits, but the
number of bits gets exponentiated to determine the number of states,
and it's just a unit.
It's just a useful definition to go back to the logarithm, which
is basically a measure of the number of little bits of information,
and the number of yes-no, or the number of
up-down decisions that is contained in your degree of ignorance.
Okay, so in any case, that's the definition.
S is equal to the logarithm of n.
Now, what happens if you have a more general situation?
Instead of having, oh incidentally, in this case here,
the probability, let's write down some of the probability.
The probability, let's call these states i.
Alright, let's say the probability for i,
the probability for the i-th
configuration is one over little n,
if i is in the subset n.
This is the subset n.
I've used it to label both the number of elements,
and also the subset itself.
P sub i is just one over little n,
if i is in n,
and P sub i is zero,
if i is not equal, how
do you write that, like that?
Is not equal, is not in n.
That's what it means to say we know the
system is in n, but we don't know anything else.
Alright, now why don't we
have a more interesting probability distribution,
or a more complex probability distribution.
Instead of having, oh, this
is a little bit more complex,
we can imagine a more general situation where
we just have a probability P of i, period.
It might be big in some regions
of the face of the configuration space,
it might be small in other regions,
it might approximately be such that there's
some subset here which all have equal probability,
zero on the outside,
may or may not be.
So we have just some P of i.
I would like some kind of measure of the
number of states that is included in this probability distribution,
and I would like it to be such that it
counts the state only a little bit if it's improbable,
and counts it a great deal if it's probable.
I'm going to give you
now a definition of the entropy,
and I'll show you how it works,
which is true for a general probability distribution.
For a general probability,
I'll show you why you use this in a moment,
but let's just define it first.
The entropy for a general probability distribution
is minus
the sum over all the states
of the probability of the i-th state times
the logarithm of the probability of the i-th state.
Okay.
Let's see how it works.
Let's...
Oh, first of all, do you know why it's minus?
Yeah, because those are all going to be negative logs.
Yeah.
A probability is always less than one,
so the logarithm of something
that's less than one is negative,
so this is really a positive quantity.
This is really a positive quantity.
Log of P sub i is always negative.
Let's do an example.
Let's calculate this.
Let's go back to the first example here.
In the first example,
the probability was zero if you're not an n,
and one over n, one over
little n if you are an n.
So let's calculate then, s.
S is the sum over all the places,
so let's concentrate on a point inside n here.
All right.
What's the probability?
It's one over little n.
Okay.
So, let's do an example.
Let's do an example.
What's the log of the probability?
Logarithm of one over n.
There's a minus sign,
and that's the contribution for any
one of the states in here.
All right.
For any one of them.
What about the states on the outside?
The states on the outside give
zero because their probabilities are zero.
All right.
Zero times logarithm of zero is zero.
So, the probability is infinite for when p is zero,
but p log p is zero.
So, you get for every configuration in here,
you get one over n log one over n.
Now, what's the log of one over n?
Minus the log of n.
It's minus the log of n,
so we can get rid of this
and make it just log of n.
But this is just the contribution
from one of the points in here.
How many points are there in here?
N.
So, we have to multiply this by n.
Which is just equal to log n.
So, in the case where we have
a probability distribution which is zero or one,
it reproduces the original definition
here of just logarithm of n.
All right.
What about the situation where
there is only one over n?
Well, that's the probability distribution.
So, we have to multiply this by n.
And we have to do that.
So, we have to do that.
Now, let's call this point.
So, we have to figure
out what the n-th division is.
And we have to do this.
And so, we get this point,
which has a non-zero probability.
All the others being zero.
In other words, when you know with certainty
exactly where the system is in the phase space,
in that case, only one of
the p-sub-i's is not equal to zero.
All the other p-sub-i's are equal to zero.
Okay.
So, let's go to that one point,
P sub zero log P sub zero.
Distribution is spread out over about n states.
If it makes sense to say
that it's spread out over n states,
then it's just logarithm of n.
Otherwise, a more general definition which
captures the two examples that I gave,
and that's really all it's intended
to capture, is summation over i,
P sub i log P sub i.
That's definition of the entropy.
As I said, the bigger the entropy
is, the less you know about the system.
What's the maximum entropy that this system can have?
One.
Why one?
One?
Logarithm of capital N.
Logarithm of capital N would be the
situation where you know nothing about anything,
and so each one of the n states,
each one of the states
has probability one over big N.
You know nothing, and so
it's just logarithm of capital N.
I don't know the number of
states capital N, so you know that.
Yeah, that's all you know.
You don't know which of those states is it.
That's right.
You don't know which of those states it's in.
Yeah.
You know what the system is, but you don't know
in which of the states of the system it is.
That's what maximizes the entropy.
Incidentally, the difference between the two
is that the entropy is the same.
It's the same.
The difference between maximum entropy
and actual entropy is called information.
So if you happened, if the entropy were
exactly zero, you would have a lot of information.
You have a lot of states,
and you know which one it's in.
So the difference between maximum entropy and entropy
is the amount of information available to you,
or it's defined that way.
Okay.
So in some sense, information
and entropy are opposite sides.
They're both sides of the same coin.
Entropy is the information which is unavailable to
you because either you're too stupid, too lazy,
or whatever it is that the, whatever reason, or the
object is too small to see, or you're, whatever the reason.
Okay.
That's, that is, now what does
entropy have to do with entanglement?
It's a definition of what is intangible.
As you can imagine, what we said
about the degree of entanglement, that will come.
That will come.
It is a measure of
the, of the degree of entanglement.
Before we get on that, we need a definition.
One definition, one mathematical definition.
The mathematical — I'm going to give the mathematical definition,
then we're going to take a break, because I'm getting tired.
We'll take a break, and then we're going to come
back and talk about the density matrix a little bit.
I don't think we'll actually
get to entanglement entropy tonight.
Absolutely.
basic ingredients that go into it.
Basic mathematical operation done on matrices,
and since matrices are linear operators you
can think of it as a operation on
operators. You have some linear operator, let's
just call it M, M stands for
matrix but it can also
stand for abstract operator and let's
suppose we have a basis. I'm going to assume,
well, no, I won't assume. No. Assumption.
Let's take a basis of vectors in the
and take the
I-I matrix, the diagonal matrix element of M.
If M is a matrix,
then this just stands for the I-I diagonal matrix element.
Here's the 1-1 element, the 2-2 element, the 3-3 element,
and add them all together.
That's called the trace.
That's called the trace of M.
Now, you might think that this depends awfully much
on which choice of basis vectors you choose.
There are many choices of basis vectors in a space.
You could choose, if it was three-dimensional space,
you could rotate your axes and so forth.
I'm not going to prove this.
This is something, this is an
exercise you can either do yourself.
It's easy, or you can look it
up in your favorite linear algebra book.
The trace of a matrix is independent of the choice
of the matrix element.
It's independent of basis vectors.
It's an invariant.
It's a quantity which does not
depend on your choice of basis vectors.
And so all choices of basis vectors
give the same value for the trace.
That's an important little theorem,
and it plays an important role in what follows,
but if you look it up or prove it yourself,
it's not hard to prove.
Okay, that's the definition of the trace of M.
We're going to use that.
Over and over.
But supposing the matrix in
some basis happens to be diagonal.
Since it doesn't matter what basis we compute it in,
we can look for a basis
in which the matrix is diagonal.
If M is a Hermitian operator, there will
always be a basis in which it's diagonal.
If M is not Hermitian, there may not be.
But if there is a basis where M is diagonal,
then it's diagonal.
Then the diagonal elements are nothing
but the eigenvalues of the matrix.
Remember, when a matrix is expressed in diagonal form,
if it can be expressed in diagonal form,
the entries are the eigenvalues of the matrix.
Excuse me.
No.
The question of the matrix in diagonal
form means the matrix is an inverse.
It may not have an inverse
because it may not have an inverse.
If any of the entries are
zero, it won't have an inverse.
Yeah.
But as long as the entries are
not zero, it will have an inverse.
Right.
OK.
Good.
No.
Actually, what it means is that it's a
function of a Hermitian operator, is what it means.
But if it's diagonal, it's characterized by its eigenvalues.
And then the trace is nothing
but the sum of the eigenvalues.
That's a way of describing the trace which
doesn't depend on the choice of a basis.
The eigenvalues don't depend on the choice of a basis.
Right.
It's just if you happen to use the right
basis, then the matrix will consist of a diagonal,
where the diagonal entries will be the eigenvalues.
But the concept of an
eigenvalue transcends any particular basis.
So if you know all of the eigenvalues, you
add them up, and that's the trace of a matrix.
The sum of the eigenvalues,
in particular of a Hermitian matrix,
in particular a Hermitian matrix, which always has,
a complete set of eigenvectors and eigenvalues,
the sum of the eigenvalues is the trace.
And as I said, it plays an important role.
Let's take a break now for six or seven minutes.
Let's move on.
Let me tell you what
the role of a trace is,
where, how it,
and how it's used.
Let's go back for a minute to the classical situation.
The classical probability distribution, some p of i.
Let me just remind you that
if you have a p of i,
and you have some observable, classical, ability,
a classical observable now,
a classical observable just means some function
of the points in the configuration space.
Some function which takes on
different values for different states.
So we can call it f of i.
An observable is just a function of the configurations.
It just takes on different values.
When you observe it, you find
out something about which point you're at.
The average of f, given
a probability distribution p sub i,
is of course the sum over i
of p sub i f sub i.
You just weight the different values
of f with the appropriate probability.
Remember that probabilities all add up to one.
And this is the classical
average or expectation value of f.
I'll just call it f.
I won't call it average of f.
That's the definition of average of f.
You could also call it the expectation value,
although it's not necessarily expected.
The trace, first of all, the trace
is the analog of the sum over configurations.
It replaces in quantum mechanics,
summing over all the possibilities.
So trace becomes,
or sum over configurations becomes trace.
You'll see how it works as we go along.
Now, there is a very similar
formula to this in quantum mechanics,
which of course,
involves a trace.
And the trial involves a
trace of the observable times something.
And that something is called the density matrix.
And I'm going to explain it to
you now in a very simple situation first.
Supposing somebody prepares a state of a system,
any one of the states of an orthonormal basis i,
behind your back,
somebody creates a system in some state i,
but doesn't tell you which state they've created it in.
So it's definitely an electron or
a spin or a composite system
or whatever it happens to be.
It's been created by somebody else in a particular state,
but all they have told you is a probability distribution
for what state they created the system in.
In other words, what we can
imagine is somebody creating an electron
by putting it into a magnetic field,
and that magnetic field could be up,
or it could be down.
And they tell you,
here's an electron,
it's either up or down, but
I'm not going to tell you which.
I'll give you a probability though,
75% likelihood that it's up,
25% likelihood that it's down.
This is not a situation where
you would write up plus down,
or even three quarters up plus one quarter down.
That's not right, but you know what I mean.
You wouldn't add the states together
at all with a definite phase.
You would just say you
don't know what state it's in,
and the system is described statistically
with a greater degree of statistics,
than if it had been in a,
than if you knew what state it was in.
Even if you knew what state it was in,
certain measurements would still be probabilistic.
If you knew what state it
was in, certain experiments might be definite,
and certain others might be probabilistic,
but here's an added degree of probability,
an added probability aspect of things,
that not only if the
system was in a definite state
might you not know the answer to every question,
but you might not even know
what state the system is in.
Under those circumstances, you use an object called
the density matrix instead of state vectors.
Density matrices are kind of a looser concept,
a concept when you don't know
what state the system is in,
and it's a probability distribution for different states.
Alright, so let's suppose that we have,
that somebody has prepared the system
definitely in one of the basis states, I,
with a probability, let's call it rho sub i.
I'm using rho now instead of p,
just because it's a standard convention for this situation,
to call it rho.
So that's the,
rho then is the probability for the i-th state.
Now we can make a matrix out of rho.
We can make a matrix out of rho,
and here's the way I'll
make a matrix out of rho.
I'm just going to, this is the matrix
in the i basis, so this is i equals 1,
i equals 2, i equals 3, i equals 4,
likewise with the rows.
It's going to be a diagonal matrix,
and its entries are just going to be rho.
Rho 1, rho 2, on the diagonal,
rho 1, rho 2, rho 3.
All other elements zero.
The rows are real numbers,
they're positive numbers because they're probabilities,
and they're all less than 1.
And one more thing, and this is called, incidentally,
this is called the density matrix.
It's called rho, and it's called the density matrix.
It's the analog in classical
physics of the probability density,
what we call p sub i.
But it's now just been organized into a matrix
with diagonal matrix elements.
The elements are all real,
and obviously they are the eigenvalues of this matrix,
because whenever a matrix has been written in diagonal form,
the diagonal elements are its eigenvalues.
One more thing you can say,
the trace of the density matrix is 1.
Why is that?
Because probabilities should add up to 1.
So if the sum of all
the probabilities adds up to 1,
then the trace of the
density matrix adds up to 1.
Now, let's suppose we have some observable.
Let's call the observable F.
And it's also a Hermitian operator.
Well, we have an observable F.
It's a Hermitian operator, as always.
Let me define now the average value of F.
If we had an ordinary state, in other words,
if we knew which state
we were in with probability 1,
then the average of F would just be
the expectation value of F in that state.
If we were in the i-th state,
the average of F would just
be the expectation value of F.
That's obvious, right?
All right.
I say more generally,
when you have this uncertainty about which state you're in,
that the right answer is that the average of F,
I won't indicate it the same way,
I won't indicate it by a bra and a ket,
because it's implicit in that
that I have a particular state.
I'll just write it as the average of F
is equal to the trace of
the product of F and rho.
Let's see if we can make
any sense out of that formula.
That formula is quite similar
to the corresponding classical formula,
summation over i,
of F sub i times P sub i.
Similar formula.
Trace being replaced,
or sum being replaced by trace,
classical function being replaced by an operator,
and the probability distribution being
replaced by the density matrix.
It's called density matrix
because it's like probability density.
Or probability, yeah.
Okay, let's work out what this thing is.
Let's work out what this thing is.
The trace, we can pick any basis we like,
but let's pick the basis in
which rho is diagonal for simplicity,
assuming that rho is diagonal in some basis.
Then this just becomes, the trace tells us,
where's the definition of the trace?
The trace tells us to take the basis,
take the thing whose trace we're taking,
F times rho,
and close it up again,
and sum over i.
That's the trace of F times rho.
Okay, now I'm going to do a
trick which we talked about last time,
we never really used very much,
but I'm going to use it now.
If we have a basis of states,
then the unit operator can be represented
as the sum over the states of
the dyads made up out of the basis vectors.
So let's, and what this means is you can always
stick an expression like this
between anything else
and not change it.
So in particular, I'm going to
stick it between F and rho.
Alright, so that'll give us, now
we have two sums to do,
one for the definition of the trace,
and one for resolving the identity.
This is called resolving the identity
by using a complete basis of states.
So that would give us
i, F, j, j, rho, i,
summed not only over i, but also over j.
Summed over i for the trace,
summed over j to resolve the identity.
Good, now, rho, in the basis that I'm using,
I'm assuming is diagonal.
That means that i has to equal j,
otherwise we don't get an expression.
Alright, in that case, this just becomes
the ijth matrix element, sorry,
the diagonal matrix element.
So this is the diagonal matrix element of rho.
i has to equal j.
We'll get nothing unless i equals j.
This just becomes rho sub i,
the i-th entry into the matrix,
and this becomes Fii.
Well, what is this?
This is the expectation value
of F in the state i.
This is the probability that the state was made
in configuration i.
And this is just the sum
of the expectation values of F
weighted with the probability distribution
for different states.
Okay?
So this makes sense to
call this the average of F.
But we see now a quantum mechanical version
of this formula over here,
in which, as I said, sum is replaced by trace,
and probability distribution is replaced by rho.
Here's a little theorem that you can prove.
It takes two seconds to prove.
If you have the product of two operators,
a and b,
the trace of a times b
is the same as the trace of b times a.
Work that out.
Even if a and b don't commute,
the trace of the product,
doesn't matter which way you order them,
and so in fact it doesn't matter
which way you order F and rho,
trace of F times rho is the average.
Okay.
That gives us the concept of a density matrix.
Let's just look at some analogies with P.
First of all, the sum of P sub i
should equal one.
The analog is that the trace,
is that the trace of rho is equal to one.
Trace of rho is equal to one.
So that's just another example of trace
and sum being essentially the same thing.
Good.
Now I'm going to give you the concept,
the quantum mechanical concept of entropy.
This is the quantum mechanical entropy,
and it's called the quantum mechanical entropy.
The entropy of a given density matrix.
Now first of all, the definition is such,
that if you know what state you're in,
only one of these rows is one,
and all the others are zero,
then the entropy is zero.
For any quantum mechanical state,
any real quantum mechanical state of the usual kind,
the entropy is zero.
The entropy is not zero,
not because quantum mechanics has in it
a built-in probabilistic aspect,
but because you simply didn't know
what state the system was made in.
You weren't told.
That's the source of entropy in quantum mechanics,
lack of knowledge about the state,
not lack of knowledge even if you knew the state.
Okay, the answer for the entropy,
the definition of the entropy,
given a density matrix rho,
first of all, here's how you use it
to calculate averages,
but second of all,
the definition of the density matrix,
well, let's first write down the classical formula.
The classical formula was sum on i
minus of p sub i log p sub i.
Well, the answer is trace,
minus the trace of the density matrix rho
times the logarithm of the density matrix rho.
What the hell is logarithm of a matrix anyway?
Well, there's a general answer to that.
But let me give you
the answer in the simple case
where the matrix can be brought to a diagonal form.
If the matrix in some basis is diagonal,
then the logarithm of the matrix
is just the matrix made out of the logarithms
of the eigenvalues.
Log of rho,
log rho one,
log rho two,
and so forth and so on.
All right.
So what is this?
This is, of course,
just the sum of the rho
sub i's log rho sub i's,
exactly as it is classically,
but I've written it in a form now
that is more appropriate for quantum mechanics
as the trace of rho log rho,
and so it has meaning in a vector space,
not just as a classical probability distribution.
So what is the definition of the entropy?
It has the property
that if only one and only
one of the rows are non-zero,
in which case it has to be one,
because the trace of rho has to be one,
if one and only one of them is non-zero,
then the entropy is zero.
Okay?
One times log of one is equal to zero.
If the probability distribution is uniform,
all states having equal probability,
that would be the case where this would be
proportional to the unit matrix,
then the entropy here is logarithm
of the number of states,
logarithm of the dimensionality of the space of states.
So if you know nothing about the system,
you don't know how it was prepared,
or anything like that,
then the entropy is just logarithm
of the total number of states,
which means the logarithm of the space of states,
logarithm of the dimension of the space of states,
and that's taking over
practically directly
from the classical concept of entropy,
and it plays the same role.
It's an indication of lack of knowledge of the system,
knowledge that you could have,
but that you don't have.
In other words, the knowledge
that is there to be gotten,
but which you may have been too lazy to get.
What's all of this have to do with entanglement?
Well, I think we're going to
have to do a little bit more
of that,
and I'm going to have to quit now.
Next time, I'm going to show you
what this has to do with entanglement,
but basically I'll just outline it for you.
When you have a system
which is composed of many parts,
or let's say two parts to be specific,
you may be interested in only one of the parts
and not look at the other part.
You may have a system
which consists of two entangled parts,
they may or may not be entangled,
in particular it's interesting when they are entangled,
A and B,
they're in some state which is an entangled state
of the two systems,
but you're only going to do experiments on A
and ignore B altogether.
Then the question is how do you describe A
without reference to B?
There must be some description that you can use
for A which contains all possible experimental
information that you could do on A
if you're never interested in also looking at B,
if you don't look at B.
And the answer is you use
a density matrix to describe A.
If A and B are entangled,
then the density matrix will have entropy.
If A and B are not entangled,
it will not have entropy.
So one diagnostic for looking at a system
or at a composite system
to find out if things are entangled
is to determine what's called
the entanglement entropy of the two systems.
And it's a measure of how badly entangled they are.
We'll come to it next
time and we'll work it out.
And we'll work out some examples.
I want to work out some real examples
to show you how entanglement entropy
codes the fact that systems are entangled.
The preceding program is copyrighted by Stanford University.
Please visit us at stanford.edu.