This program is brought to you by Stanford University.
Please visit us at stanford.edu.
What I want to talk, what
we were talking about last time,
was the density matrix description of probabilities.
Now the density matrix is another
way of speaking about the probability postulate,
and it's a situation which is more general
than knowing the state vector of a system.
It's roughly speaking when a system has been prepared,
but you don't know how it's been prepared,
and so it may very well have been prepared
for a situation where it's been prepared, but you don't know how
it's been prepared, and so it may very well have been prepared,
in a very definite state of some sort.
I gave you an example last time,
where an electron spin
might be prepared along a direction by
placing the electron in a strong magnetic field,
but somebody else did the preparing and didn't
tell you what direction the magnetic field was in.
Perhaps they gave you a probability distribution
for different directions of the magnetic field.
Thank you for the coffee tonight, I
really need it. I hope this is coffee.
So it's a situation where the system has been prepared,
but you simply don't know how it was prepared.
Then how do you describe it?
There has to be some description.
You may have some degree of
knowledge about how it was prepared.
You may have none.
Incidentally, if you have none, if
you have no knowledge at all,
then the density matrix has all equal eigenvalues,
it's proportional to the unit matrix,
and each eigenvalue is 1 over n,
where n is the total number of states,
and that just means complete random information.
You simply don't know.
All the possibilities are equally weighted.
But let's just go back
and discuss a little bit more,
well, not to review, to review
the basic equations and the basic concepts
that go with the density matrix.
The density matrix is the analog of
knowing the probability distribution for classical states.
Classical states have some probability distribution.
In many contexts, you would call it a probability density,
density in phase space or density in coordinate space,
a density of probability.
That's where the word density matrix came from,
and it's basically a quantum analog,
a quantum analog of the notion of
a probability density or a probability distribution.
The condition that the sum
of probabilities adds up to 1
is denoted by saying the trace of
the density matrix is equal to 1.
Remember, the trace is the sum of the eigenvalues.
The eigenvalues themselves of the
density matrix can be thought of
as the probability matrix.
So what are the probabilities for different states?
So, first of all, the trace of
the density matrix is equal to 1.
The density matrix itself is a Hermitian operator.
That's basically just the condition
that the probabilities are real.
Probabilities are real, so in classical physics,
you would assign real probabilities.
Only somebody with a very bad
disorder would assign them complex probabilities.
Wouldn't make any sense.
The analog of that for quantum mechanics
is that the eigenvalues of the density matrix
are equal to 1.
Sorry, the eigenvalues of the density matrix are real.
Let's label them lambda i,
where i is equal to i equals
1, 2, dot, dot, dot, up to n,
where n is the number
of dimensions of the vector space.
And they're all positive. Good.
And they're all positive.
Right.
Each eigenvalue goes with some eigenstate.
And in some basis, some particular basis of,
in the space of states, some orthonormal basis of states,
corresponds to the eigenvectors.
Incidentally, remember that the eigenvectors
of a Hermitian operator are all orthogonal to each other.
So they form a basis.
So there's some basis in the space of states,
which is just n mutually orthogonal vectors,
each one of them being an eigenvector,
and each one having an eigenvalue lambda sub i.
You can simply think of the lambda sub i's
as the probabilities that the system was prepared
in the i-th eigenvector of the density matrix.
If all the eigenvalues are equal,
it effectively means you know nothing.
You don't know what state the system is in.
The density matrix then is proportional to the unit matrix,
all the same eigenvalues, each eigenvalue being 1 over n.
That's one limit.
That's the limit of complete ignorance.
The limit of maximal knowledge is,
is a pure state.
That means that you know what state
the system has been created in.
In that case, we can say
the system is described by some pure state.
I won't tell you which one,
but let's assume we know which one.
Some pure state psi.
And when the system is described by a pure state,
there's still a density matrix.
You can still introduce a density matrix.
And the density matrix is simply the projection
onto that pure state.
The projection operator that projects onto that pure state.
It's written this way.
So if there's only one state,
and you know which it is,
and it has probability 1 for being in that state,
then the density matrix is just psi sine.
好
How do I express that the state could be this one with half
of a 30 and the other half being some state 45 degrees to it?
Oh, no, no, no, no,
no, that's not a good concept.
The density matrix being a Hermitian operator
has a set of mutually orthogonal eigenvectors.
And it only makes sense to discuss the
probability for which state it's in in that basis.
In that basis, and so it would
be the only situation you would talk about.
Now, we can answer the question, let me come back
to it, where you don't know how the system was prepared.
Somebody may have prepared, put the magnetic field this
way, or may have put it at 45 degrees.
We can figure that out. We'll figure
that out later. I'll come back to it.
But still, it will be the case that
the density matrix always has mutually orthogonal eigenvalues,
sometimes.
So I will take up that case
either now or, yeah, or next time.
You mentioned pure state. Do you
differentiate pure state from mixed state?
A mixed state means a density matrix
which simply has more than one non-zero eigenvalue.
Yeah. And, yeah, that's what it means.
Okay, in German it's called a gemisch.
Gemisch.
It's the word I learned
when I was a young student.
Because German was still one
of the important languages of physics.
Now it's just called a mixed state.
I think even by Germans.
And Germans?
I'm just curious whether in Germany they
call a mixed state a mixed state.
I actually don't know.
Gemisch was the word that was
invented by the fathers of quantum mechanics.
It's a good German word.
What's that?
It's a good German word, gemisch.
Gemisch.
Here.
Okay.
Now, yes, let's just point out one thing.
Take this matrix here.
Well, take this operator.
It obviously has a single eigenvector with eigenvalue 1.
What is the eigenvector of this matrix with eigenvalue 1?
It's just psi.
Okay.
The same vector.
If I take this and operate on
it, let's assume that now psi is normalized.
I assume that it's normalized.
If I apply this to psi,
then psi psi is equal to 1.
It just gives me back psi.
So, in fact, psi is an eigenvector with eigenvalue 1.
Any other state orthogonal to psi, let's take
some other state which is orthogonal to psi.
Let me call it phi.
If it's orthogonal to psi, then you get 0.
So, if the density matrix is a simple
projection operator onto one particular state, then it
has one non-zero eigenvalue.
The density matrix is representing a pure
state, and the pure state is just psi.
Now, whether or not the state is pure or gemixed,
the rule for the state of a pure state is
that it's just psi.
It's just a state.
That's obvious.
Which is a standard state for distinguishing between
Chi and A chaque times king or neighbour.
The Fried loop argument is not the base
one, and acceptably that's the answer to that.
students are understanding this.
So, they're not giving us an animal equation.
They're giving an analysis.
The EPA yo Av likelihood is
that there's a factor in the
garliceles-tiencia labor of s connective-circle
of thesein world and he doesn't.
So, the S and 86 that condition
of the key denominator may be that,
the seeds code is also
something I could make moreствие about.
So, there are four Tomatoes intensities.
Let's chose the Vehic slave別, we
call it range regional, which this się
times m. And incidentally, it's not hard to prove
that a trace of a product of two matrices,
whether or not the matrices commute, whether or not
the trace doesn't matter which order you put the operators.
So you can also write trace of m
times rho, and it will make no difference.
That's the average. And definition of the trace, let me
remind you of the definition of the trace of a matrix.
You take any basis, excuse me, you take any basis whatever, the trace
has the property that it doesn't matter which basis you calculate it in.
It's an invariant on the
changes of basis of the matrix.
It's an invariant on the vector space.
All right, but in any case, we take some basis.
It doesn't have to be the
basis in which rho is diagonal.
It can be the basis
in which the rho is diagonal.
But even if it's not diagonal in this basis,
nevertheless, the trace is defined as i rho m,
whatever the matrix in question
is, times i summed over i.
Okay, in other words, you just
take the i i-th matrix element.
You take the i-th matrix element of the operator
in question, and you sum it over all i.
That's the definition of the trace.
And let's work it out just for the very
simple case in which rho is a projection operator.
In that case, m is equal trace.
I'll write the trace in a moment.
Psi, psi m.
And now we take a complete basis, whether or not, as I said, it
does not matter whether the basis is the basis in which rho is diagonal.
i, i.
All right, so now we have
to do a little bit of gymnastics.
Oh, this is summed over i.
If I forget to write sum over i, remind me.
It's almost always the case that when
you have, in this case, a matrix,
when you have an index like i repeated twice,
almost in every equation I will ever write down,
it's implicit, or maybe I'll try to make it explicit.
If I forget, remind me.
But it's almost always the case
that it will be summed over,
so that i is really just a summation index.
It's, you can call it j if you like.
It doesn't matter.
All right, let's check this out.
Let's see if this makes sense.
So I can rewrite this by just
shifting this factor over to this side.
Let me do it.
Now let's rewrite it.
i, psi m i, i psi.
Now you have to remember the rule.
Whenever you see i and i
back to back like this, summed over,
that's the unit matrix.
That's the unit operator.
The sum of i, i is the unit matrix.
It can always be canceled out.
It's just the unit matrix.
It makes no difference.
You can just remove it, and the
result is that it's psi m psi.
Well, that's not too surprising.
The average of m is the expectation value
of m, if you have a pure state.
Now, supposing you don't have a pure state.
Let's suppose we don't have a pure.
Question?
Should that be m bar?
Yeah, this.
No, sorry.
m bar up here, yes.
Thank you.
Very good.
Yep.
OK, let's take a more general case
when we don't have a pure state.
And we'll see what we get.
But let's evaluate it.
Let's see.
Yeah.
OK, so again, we have
to take trace of rho m.
But let's do the calculation in
the basis in which rho is diagonal.
All right?
So to calculate the trace, we put
i rho m i summed over i.
I'm not going to write a summation sign.
OK.
I'm going to suppress the summation sign for now.
Just summed over i.
But now we can insert a complete
set of states between rho and m.
This is a trick we constantly keep doing.
In order to reduce the calculation to something
involving matrix elements of both rho and m,
we stick in between there a complete set of states.
And we write it in the form i.
Maybe, I guess I'll put the sum.
Sum on i.
i i rho m.
But I'm going to insert
in here a sum over j.
And now it's a sum over both i and j.
Now, if I'm working in the
basis in which rho is diagonal,
then I know what the
matrix element i rho j is.
This is just these i rho j.
What is that?
That's just the matrix.
It has an i index and a j index.
The row or the column,
let's see, which one is which?
This one is...
i is the row.
And it says here the
row and j is the column?
Whichever.
Yeah.
j would be the column.
j is the column, I think.
Yeah.
Right.
OK.
But since rho is diagonal, this object here only
has a matrix element if i is equal to j.
And then the matrix element is just lambda.
Lambda j.
The eigenvalue.
If...
So the sum over i and j
becomes a sum only over one of them.
And let's take it to be j because
i has to equal j because rho is diagonal.
And then we have...
j m j.
I've put j here because i
has to equal j in the sum.
Well, what is this?
This is just the expectation value
of m in the j-th state.
This is just the probability of the j-th state.
So this reads exactly what you might expect.
It's the average of m in the j-th state weighed
with the probability, which is the probability of the j-th state.
So you can think of the eigenvalues of rho as the probabilities to be
in the j-th state, but only in the basis in which rho is diagonal.
Yeah.
Is that really j and j
instead of j and i there?
Yes, because i has to be equal to j.
Otherwise, you don't get anything.
Right.
So for trivial reasons, it is.
You're still summing over i, right?
You're still summing over j here.
Over j.
Right.
Yeah.
Here I really broke my own rule.
This thing is repeated three times.
Right.
Okay.
Those are the rules about density matrices.
Let me remind you of one more definition.
If you're given a probability distribution, probabilities, let's
say p sub i, this is classical probabilities now,
p sub i, the i-th probability for the i-th
possibility, then the entropy is defined S, S for entropy.
I don't know why they chose S.
Why it's not E?
Probably E because you're confused with energy.
S for entropy is equal by definition.
This is the definition of it.
But we can say what it means roughly.
It's again the sum over all of the possible configurations or all of
the possible possibilities of minus p sub i times logarithm of p sub i.
That's its definition.
Again.
If only one of the p's is
non-zero, then it's got to be one.
All right.
Logarithm of one is zero.
On the other hand, all the other p's are zero.
So in that case, if you have
complete knowledge, then the entropy is zero.
So zero entropy means complete knowledge.
You know precisely that the probability
distribution is peaked at one particular point.
Zero everywhere else.
The other extreme is when you have complete ignorance.
And in that case, each p
sub i is one over n.
Let's take it to be the same n here.
Each p sub i is one over n.
And then you get S is equal to, before you
do the sum, one over n log one over n.
But it's minus log one over n.
So that's actually one over n.
So that's actually the same as log of n.
But then you have n terms in the sum.
So you have to multiply this by n.
And the answer is that the entropy
is logarithm of the number of states.
The entropy is, roughly speaking, the
logarithm of the number of states
which are important in the probability distribution.
That's as close as I can get
to give you a definition in words.
But you don't need a definition in words.
This is precisely what it is.
But nevertheless, it is true that
if you have a probability distribution
which has fairly large over some set of states
and then pretty damn small everywhere else,
that the answer for the entropy will
essentially be logarithm of the number of states
for which the probability distribution is significant.
So it's a measure of the degree of probability distribution.
It's a measure of the degree of ignorance.
The more ignorance, in other words, the more
states that the probability distribution is spread out over,
the less you know about the system.
The more you know about the system, the
fewer the states, and the smaller the entropy.
So it's a measure of ignorance.
Or a measure of, well, yeah.
Now we want to come to entanglement.
Entanglement happens when we have more than one system.
So let's suppose we have
a system composed of two parts.
And let's suppose we have some basis.
And the basis is labeled
by a state or an observable,
A for one of the
subsystems and B for the other.
Now for the case of two spins,
A and B could be up and,
A and B would both be up and down.
We could have up, up,
up, down, down, up, down, down.
Other possibilities, we could have a spin with two states
and an atom with four states or three states.
In that case, A would go from
one to two or up and down.
B would run over one
to three or one to four.
And so altogether, the total number of states
would be the product of the number of configurations
of the subsystem A times the number of subsystem B.
So if we had a spin which
could be in one of two directions,
and we were putting it together with an atom
which could be in three possible states,
the total number of states would be six,
but it would just be three times two.
Okay.
Let's, let's say that A, little a,
runs from one to capital N,
and little b runs from one to little n.
They don't have to be the same.
They could be two quite different systems.
Okay.
Then the most general state of the combined system
that we can write is a sum.
And we're going to sum over A and B
of some set of coefficients,
called a wave function,
of A and B, function of A and B.
Now A and B are discrete,
or at least for us now,
A and B are discrete variables.
In a more general context,
A and B could, might even be continuous,
but for our studies here,
where we're studying qubits and discrete systems,
A and B run over integers.
They're integer valued variables,
but we can still write psi of A and B,
sticking in any pair of integers,
that gives us a complex number,
multiplied by the state vector A, B,
summed over A and B.
That's the most general state we can write down.
If we want to normalize it,
which I do,
then we want the sum over A and B
of psi star psi to add up to one.
Okay.
So I won't write that down.
The sum over A and
B of psi star times psi
should be equal to one.
And that's our normalization condition.
Okay.
Let's now suppose that we're doing an experiment
which does not involve B.
It could be because the two systems
are separated from each other,
and Bob is down at that end of the room.
He doesn't even bother looking at his system at all.
Alice is up at this end,
and Alice is going to do an experiment,
and the experiment is going to involve
only the A degrees of A.
So the A degrees of freedom.
Okay.
The observable that she's going to measure,
let's call it M.
M is an observable
for subsystem A.
That means mathematically,
that when we're doing an experiment,
that when M acts on a state vector AB,
it may act on the A coordinate,
but it will just leave the B coordinate alone.
We've done this before.
We've done this with spins.
So M effectively is only a matrix.
In the A system here,
it acts on the A degree of freedom
and leaves B alone.
It doesn't touch B.
So whatever it does to a state vector,
B is completely passive and doesn't change.
The matrix may act on the A coordinate,
and that's all.
So that's a degree,
or a variable, sorry,
an observable that's associated with the A subsystem.
And let's calculate the expectation value of it
in the state for the combined system.
So what do we have to do?
We have to calculate the expectation value of it.
We have to take, first of all,
we have to take the bra vector associated with this.
Let's construct or rewrite it as the bra vector.
Sum over A and B.
Psi star, well, let's see,
we're going to need two sets of variables.
We're going to need primed variables
and unprimed variables.
So let's see how I did this.
Yeah.
Psi star of A prime and B prime.
A prime, B prime.
Summed over A prime and B prime.
This is the bra vector.
Now we're going to multiply that by M.
And now the ket vector,
which looks exactly the same,
well, it looks exactly the same,
except we won't have a complex conjugate.
Psi of A and B.
AB.
I'll tell you what.
Let's take the psi and
stick it on the outside here.
Now we separately have to sum
over A prime and B prime
to define the bra vector.
And A and B, we also
have to sum over A and B
to define the ket vector.
And that's the expectation value that we're interested in.
But now let's look at this matrix M.
M does nothing to B.
But it's a matrix as far as A goes.
What does that mean?
That means that B prime has to equal B.
Okay.
B prime and B,
the operator M does nothing to B.
It leaves it alone.
And if it leaves it alone,
then B prime and B must be the same.
Okay.
Because...
Can I ask you a question?
Yeah.
What are the primes on some of these variables?
I mean, above you didn't use I prime and I.
It's always been...
There I used I and J.
No, but for the expectation of rho M,
it's I rho M I.
No, okay.
Well, we're not dealing at the moment with density matrices.
We're dealing with state vectors.
So let's go back and write an expectation value
for a state vector.
Okay.
Supposing we have a wave function
psi of A times A.
Single system.
And now we want to calculate the expectation.
And this is, of course, sum over A.
Then the expectation value is M.
And now we have to write the bra vector.
That's sum over A prime of psi of A prime.
I know you do.
A prime.
Okay.
So in calculating the expectation value,
if the vectors on either side are expressed as sums,
you have a double sum to do in this case.
And I've called the left
part of the double sum prime
and the right part unprimed.
Okay.
So it's the same thing
except we have two labels here.
But now, the definition of the
idea that M is an operator
that acts on the A subsystem,
and which is passive for the B subsystem,
is simply the statement that the
matrix is diagonal in the Bs.
That B on this side and
B prime have to be the same.
Otherwise, the matrix vanishes.
In that case, this sum over B and B prime
becomes a sum only over one of them.
All right.
So let me show you
what the right idea is now.
B and B prime have to be the same.
And M is really just
a matrix in the A space.
It's a matrix with matrix elements A and A prime.
Do I want to...
I think I want to write them this way.
All right.
This is a matrix involving
two variables, A and A prime.
But B has to equal B prime.
And there's no dependence on B whatever.
No dependence on B.
And B has to equal B prime.
Okay.
So that's this matrix here.
And all we have to do is remember the instruction
in the rest of the expression here
that B has to equal B prime.
So let's do that.
Psi star of A prime B,
psi of AB.
All right.
Notice on the left, we
have psi star of A prime,
psi of A.
But as far as B goes, B...
Whoops.
B hasn't changed.
B is just passive.
This is the...
Now, let's go a little step further.
This is still summed over B.
It's also summed over A prime and A.
But I want to ignore for the
moment the sum over A prime and A
and realize that this is a sum over B.
It's also a sum over A prime and A.
So let's do that later.
All right.
Now let me group the
two things that depend on B.
Let me group them together.
So what I'm going to
do is erase this over here,
and I'm going to put it back right back here.
Psi star of A prime and B.
All right.
Now imagine holding A and A prime fixed
and just summing over B.
That gives you some expression here.
That expression no longer involves B
because B has been summed over.
Once B is summed over, it doesn't depend on B.
Let's give this a name.
What should I call this?
Psi of A B and
psi star of A prime B.
It's a function only of A and A prime.
A name for it?
Pi of A.
No.
Pi of A A prime.
Try again.
It's not the A and the
A prime that I don't like.
It's the phi.
Come on.
Give me the right letter.
Rho.
This expression is in components,
written in components, written in terms of matrix elements.
It's the trace of the product of M times rho.
All right.
Why is it the trace?
It's the trace because I'm summing over A prime,
but it's the product because I'm summing over A.
This is the formula if I had arbitrary things here,
let's say A double prime,
then this would correspond to the
A double prime A prime matrix element
of M times rho.
This is the way you multiply matrices
in terms of components.
This expression is the trace of M times rho.
Let's check that.
Let's do it by longhand calculation.
That really is the trace.
Now we're talking about a system.
We're only talking about the A system now.
We've eliminated the B system.
We've summed over it.
It's no longer even in this expression.
This might have been something that made sense
for just the pure A system
without any reference to B at all.
What would it correspond to?
Let's forget B.
It's passive.
It's gone.
We finished with it.
This is some expression only
involving the A degrees of freedom.
I assert that it's the trace of the matrix M.
Now remember, M really only
depends on A and A prime.
B is completely passive.
B prime has to equal B,
and otherwise it just doesn't depend on B.
So let's look at this.
M is the identity on B.
Yeah.
Right.
Acting on B, it does nothing.
Okay.
So let's just calculate trace of M.
We can write it as
A prime M rho A prime,
summed over A prime.
All of this is summed over A and A prime.
A and A prime.
Okay.
Back to the question.
We have to sum it.
All right.
This is the trace.
This is the definition of the trace.
But now if I insert a
complete set of states in here,
it becomes sum over A and
A prime of A prime M A,
A rho A prime.
That's just this.
M A A prime A.
That's this.
And rho A A prime.
All right.
So look what we found.
We found that by ignoring B, just ignoring it,
and asking what are the rules
when a system is a combined system
with a unique state vector,
a pure vector, a pure state.
It's a pure state for the combined system.
Nevertheless, we have to find out
when you focus only on the A subsystem,
it's described by a density matrix.
That density matrix, how do you get the density matrix?
You get the density matrix
by taking the full wave function,
letting A and A prime run freely,
not summing over them, but summing over B.
That eliminates B out of the expression,
and it just becomes a
matrix between A and A prime.
So when you have a combined composite system,
Schrodinger's cat and the gun,
the Schrodinger's cat and the gun
may themselves be described by a single state vector
in which they're entangled,
but if we just look at the cat alone,
the cat is described by a density matrix.
It's described by a density matrix,
and in general, that density matrix
will be a density matrix
of a mixed state in general.
There's a very special circumstance
under which it will be a pure state
that will describe the A system,
and I'll tell you in a moment what it is.
In fact, I suppose I should tell you right now.
Any questions up till now?
Yeah?
Isn't tracing rho just trace of n?
All right.
Trace of n rho is trace
of n times trace of rho,
and trace of rho is...
Wait, wait.
Trace of...
No, sorry.
Trace of product is not the product of traces.
No.
It can be nice if it were.
It would make things easy, but it's not true.
Trace of a product is not
the product of the traces, yeah.
You said you started with a pure state,
which was just AB.
No, no, no, no.
Psi...
No, no, not AB,
but sum over AB of psi.
Okay.
I'm not feeling that this is
the most general case that you can...
This is the most general
pure state of the combined system.
Okay, so let me say it again.
You have a combined system.
It's in the purest possible state.
Psi.
When you look at a subsystem,
the subsystem will be in a mixed state,
in a statistical state.
Now, there's no analog of this for a classical system.
If I have what would correspond to
a pure state for a classical system,
the idea of a pure
state would be a probability distribution
which has only one point that it's non-zero.
In other words, a definite piece
of information about which state you're in.
That's the analog of the pure state.
In other words, complete knowledge.
If you have complete knowledge about the combined system,
you have complete knowledge about either
of the subsystems in classical physics.
So in classical physics,
complete knowledge about a combined system is equal...
It's not equal to, but it implies
complete knowledge about either of the subsystems.
That's different in quantum mechanics.
In quantum mechanics, you may have
complete knowledge about the combined system,
and yet the subsystem by itself
must be described by a density matrix.
Now, you say, might it be
that that density matrix is special?
And that it corresponds to a pure state?
Not in general, and I'll show you some examples.
I'll show you some examples
that you're already familiar with.
We'll work out the density matrix for some familiar example.
But let me just say...
How different is this from classical mechanics
where you have velocity distribution functions
which you integrate over to get densities?
So in a way, you
integrate it over the B state.
To get a density matrix, right?
So I can think of a velocity distribution function
if you integrate it over, you get the density.
How do I get a density by integrating over?
Oh, you mean if you
have a combined velocity and position?
In a classical property
distribution function like the Boltzmann.
You have a combined velocity and position distribution,
and you integrate...
It's similar.
But the difference is that if you had complete knowledge...
In that case, the velocity and the position
would just correspond to two subsystems.
They're not really two subsystems,
but you could think of them as two different systems,
two different coordinates that...
Okay.
In that case, if you
had complete knowledge about the system,
it would mean you knew
both the velocity and the position.
And there's no problem with
knowing the velocity and the position.
And so not only would the
combined system be in a pure state,
but if you just looked at positions,
you would have definite knowledge of position
and definite knowledge of...
What's that other thing called?
Velocity.
Yeah.
Okay, so that's the difference.
That there are pure states of the combined system
which cannot be thought of
as pure states of the subsystems.
Okay, let me just tell you what is the condition.
All right, so here's an interesting condition.
What is the condition on psi of A and B
that the individual subsystems actually are in pure states?
Is there a situation or a
wave function psi of A and B
in which the two individual
subsystems are in a pure state?
The answer is yes.
Any time that the wave function
factorizes into a product of A,
a product of a function of A,
and a product of a function of B,
let's just analyze that situation a little bit
and see what it says.
That's a special case.
Not all functions of two variables are products
of functions of one variable
times a function of another variable,
but it's only when the wave function is a product
that each individual subsystem is itself in a pure state.
Okay, let's look at that a little more carefully.
Let's suppose that psi of A and B
happen to be equal to a
product of a function of A
and another function of B,
and I'm going to call
the other function chi of B.
Really all this is saying is that the combined system
is a pure state phi,
for the A subsystem,
and a pure state chi for the B subsystem.
We'll assume that phi and chi are normalized
so that chi star chi when summed over B
is equal to one,
phi star phi when summed
over A is equal to one.
Those conditions are equivalent to
the normalization of psi itself.
So phi is phi of A
that's proposed only of the A chest.
Well, functions aren't composed of cats,
but yes, that's right.
Yeah, I know what you're...
The state itself is a linear
combination of all of the A chest.
Yeah, that's right.
It's a product state.
It's a product state, right.
Right, it's a product state.
Okay, so if phi happens to factorize like that,
then let's calculate the density matrix itself.
The density matrix for the A subsystem, right?
For the A subsystem, we have to multiply
psi of A and B times psi star...
You know something?
I think I actually have something backward.
No, that's all right.
Okay.
So we have to take psi of A
and B times psi star of A and B.
That's phi of A chi of
B times phi star of A prime.
We have A and A
prime, but B goes with B,
times chi of B, chi
star of B, summed over B.
That's the density matrix.
That's rho A A prime.
All right, same formula, except
I've substituted for psi the product.
All right, now this is very easy.
The only thing that's summed over is chi.
A isn't even in the sum.
You can pull the phi outside the summation,
since the summation doesn't involve A altogether,
and it just becomes equal to phi of A,
phi star of A,
times sum on B of chi
of B times chi star of B.
But what is that?
Sum on B chi chi star, that's just one.
That's the normalization of chi of B.
So this is all just one.
So the density matrix for a product is very simple.
It's just the product of wave functions,
phi of A times phi star of A.
Let's calculate now, in this case,
the expectation value of M.
It's just equal, where is it?
M of A prime in A.
Sorry, I missed a prime here somewheres.
I'm sorry.
Right.
m of a prime and a, phi of a, and
let me put phi star of a prime over here.
Well, this is nothing but written in components.
This is nothing but phi m phi.
In other words, the expectation value
of m, and not just m,
but any observable that involves only a,
is exactly the same as if
the state vector were just phi.
The a degrees of freedom are completely and entirely
described by the pure state phi.
So when the wave function
is a product of two factors,
each subsystem is itself in a pure state,
and the pure state is just either
phi of a or chi of b.
That's the special case.
When the combined system is in a pure state,
and each subsystem is in a pure state.
But that's hardly general.
Not at all general.
Not every function of two variables
is a product of functions of one variable.
OK.
Incidentally, in this case, the density matrix,
well, here is the density matrix.
The density matrix has one
and only one non-zero eigenvector.
It's phi at z.
It's a one-zero eigenvector.
But in the case of the wave function itself,
all the other eigenvalues are equal to zero.
And the entropy is equal to zero.
Only eigenvalues are one, and all the others are zero.
So that's the case.
That's one way of diagnosing
how pure a state vector is,
or how well the wave function resembles a product,
is to calculate the entropy...
it means you're near the situation of a product.
If the entropy is large,
somewhere near the maximum logarithm of n,
that means you're deeply entangled.
And deeply entangled means you're far from a product.
Far from a product, wave function just doesn't factorize.
Let's work out one particular example.
Maybe we can work out
some more than one particular example.
But let's do at least one example,
a familiar thing that we've already studied.
Calculate the density matrix and calculate the entropy.
We should do two.
We should make one be a...
Yeah, we're going to do two different examples.
The first example is not
going to be a pure state.
The first example is going to be
our...
Our friend, the singlet state,
the highly entangled singlet state of two electrons.
Okay.
So what is it?
It's by definition up, up...
No, sorry, up, down, minus down, up,
divided by square root of two.
All right?
But let's write that in terms
of a wave function of two variables.
All right?
Psi has two entries.
The first entry represents spin number one.
The second entry represents spin number two.
And here are the values that psi has.
Psi up, up is equal to zero.
I don't see up, up here.
Do you?
No.
Okay.
What about psi up, down?
That's the coefficient of this one.
It's equal to one over square root of two.
How about psi down, up?
Minus one over square root of two.
And then we have the other two.
And psi down, down is zero.
Okay.
Let's calculate the density matrix for the A system,
the A system now being spin number one.
So what do we have to do?
We have to write down...
Where is it?
This is the density matrix right here.
Can I write it somewhere?
Yeah, it's over here.
This is the density matrix.
Summed over B.
All right.
So we begin by writing down
a psi next to a psi star.
Let's work it out.
Let's do the elements.
Row, up, up.
Remember, row is a matrix, but it's a
matrix just in the space of one spin.
So let's calculate its up, up matrix element.
This up, up matrix element
we get by writing psi up.
Let's write it again.
Psi up.
Plus...
This doesn't make sense yet.
It will in a moment.
Okay.
All right.
Now, remember, we sum over the B coordinate.
So let's put up, up, down.
No, no.
This is...
Up, up, up, up.
We're calculating the up, up matrix element.
All right.
Come back to here.
We're calculating the A, A prime matrix element.
So in one place we
put a psi with an A.
In the other place we put
a psi star with an A prime.
This should be star.
Star.
In this case, both A and A prime are up.
So we have a psi of A and a psi star
of A, a psi of A and a psi star of A.
But we have to sum over B.
So B is up, up.
And down, down.
That's the instruction.
It's psi star psi with the A's being
evaluated as matrix elements of the density matrix and
the B's being summed over.
Up, up plus down, down.
Okay.
That's the up, up matrix element.
Let's see what it is.
Psi up, up is 0.
So this is the up, up matrix element.
And this is the Psi star.
So this is 0.
But Psi up, down is
1 over square root of 2.
So this is just 1 half.
All right.
What about rho down, down?
For rho down, down, you do exactly the same thing.
Psi down, Psi star down plus same thing.
Psi down, Psi star down.
Sorry.
Psi star down.
But then you fill in up, up, down, down.
Do I have this right?
Yeah.
Okay.
What is Psi down, up?
That's minus 1 over square root of 2.
It's squared.
So again, we get 1 half.
And down, down is 0.
So this is again a half.
Neat.
What about Psi up, rho up, down?
The matrix element of a density
matrix, the up, down matrix element.
Do the same thing.
Psi up, Psi star down.
Up, down.
Plus, write it again, Psi up, Psi star down.
But then fill in up, up.
And down, down.
Psi star down.
Okay.
What's that?
Psi up, up is 0.
And Psi down, down is equal to 0.
So that's 0.
And of course, the other one is also 0.
Rho down, up is also equal to 0.
So in this case, the density matrix is just
equal to rho is equal to a half, a half.
It's proportional to the unit matrix.
It has equal entries.
Those entries can be thought
of as probabilities if you like.
But its trace is 1.
If you add up the
eigenvalues, it adds up to 1.
And what's the entropy?
No.
Log 2.
It's 1 half log of 1 half
plus 1 half log of 1 half.
Altogether, it adds up to log of 1 half.
Log of 1 half is minus the log of 2.
But we have a minus sign
in the definition of the entropy.
So it's log 2.
That's the maximum that the entropy can be.
I haven't stressed this, but it's an easy theorem.
You might try to work that out.
That the maximum the entropy ever can be
is when all the elements
of the density matrix are equal,
maximum amount of ignorance.
And so in this case here, we
have a pure state for the combined system
and complete ignorance for either of the components.
Sorry, for either of the spins.
I concentrated on the left spin here, spin number 1.
And what we found is that
the density matrix described complete ignorance.
In this case, what is the expectation
value of the components of the spin?
In particular, spin number 1.
We could calculate them by
using the full wave function here.
Or we can calculate them using the density matrix.
The density matrix for spin number 1, rho,
is equal to 1 half times the unit matrix.
We can just call it 1 half.
It's just 1 half times the unit matrix.
The expectation value of any component of spin,
spin along any axis,
is equal to the trace of rho times,
sorry, just sigma dot n.
Sigma dot n.
Trace of rho.
That's the average,
the average of sigma dot n.
Trace of rho times the observable.
That is not trace of rho,
not the observable times trace of rho,
but trace of the product of rho times the observable.
That's the average of the observable.
Well, rho is proportional to the unit matrix.
You can take that out.
Unit matrix doesn't do anything.
It just gives you a half, factor of a half.
This gives you a half times
the trace of sigma dot n.
What's the trace of sigma dot n?
Anybody know?
Zero.
The trace of every one
of the sigma matrices is zero.
Let's just check that.
Trace of sigma 3.
Sigma 3 is 1 minus 1.
This trace is zero.
The others are all off diagonal.
They also have no trace.
So what have we learned?
We've learned that in the singlet state,
something we already knew because
we'd already worked it out,
that in the singlet state,
the trace of every component of
spin in any direction is zero,
which means in any direction whatever,
the spin is equally likely to be along that direction
or opposite to that direction.
We already knew this,
and this was an example of a highly intelligent,
highly entangled state.
We also know that for no
pure state of a single spin,
is the average of the spin
equal to zero in every direction.
So this is another way of seeing
that this cannot be a pure state.
But the easy way to see
that it's not a pure state
is that the two eigenvalues here are both non-zero.
So it has to be a mixed state.
So the singlet state is a maximally mixed state.
Let me take another one.
Let's try the following.
Let's see.
I think I want one over
the square root of 2 here.
Let me just...
Or do I want one half? Wait.
I think I want one half.
Yeah.
Yeah, sure I do.
One half and one half.
Yeah, now it's normalized, right?
I have 4 psi star psi.
We give a quarter.
A quarter plus a quarter
plus a quarter plus a quarter.
No minus. Plus.
We give 1.
So this is a normalized state
with all entries equal to a half.
Let's recalculate what we would get
here if we had this situation.
This is not the singlet state.
All right, so now what do we have?
We have up, up equals a half.
So this is a quarter, right?
Is that right?
Right.
And this is also a quarter.
Quarter plus a quarter is again a half.
No difference.
All right, so this is still a half.
This one is still a half.
But so is this one.
All the matrix elements are equal to a half.
So it's a half times a
half plus a half times a half.
They're all equal to a half this time.
And in fact, this one
is also equal to a half.
Now, this is the density matrix.
So this is the density matrix.
And this is the density matrix.
Its trace is still equal to one.
That's good.
Sums of the probabilities are equal to one.
But what are the two eigenvalues of this matrix?
Are they equal?
No, actually they're not.
Let me show you what the two eigenvalues are.
Let's calculate the two eigenvalues.
Incidentally, do you know the theorem that
says that the two eigenvalues are equal?
Does the theorem say that the two eigenvalues are equal?
Does it say that the sum
of the two eigenvalues of this matrix
is equal to its determinant?
Is it distinct given its mates are
equal every date or in a particular day.
Is it distinct given its mates are equal?
Is it apparent darker to find every entrant abut asists
is equal and distinct in HEY e?
Is it
ển
is equal and set to 1.
That's good.
The sum of the eigenvalues is equal to 1.
What about the determinant of rho?
Right.
It's 1 half times 1 half
minus 1 half times 1 half.
So the product of the eigenvalues is 0.
That means one of the eigenvalues is 0,
and one of the eigenvalues is 1.
What's that?
Yeah, this is a product state.
This is a product state.
Can anybody guess what it corresponds to?
Two unentangled electrons?
It's what?
It's two unentangled electrons, but what are the individual
electrons doing?
Yeah, they happen to be measured the same way,
but which direction?
In what direction?
Along what axis?
Z-up.
X.
OK.
Let's calculate the expectation value of sigma z.
Let's start with sigma 3.
So for that, we take the
trace of rho times sigma 3.
Let's see what we get.
Sigma 3, and it doesn't matter which order.
Sigma 3 is 1 minus 1 0
0, and rho is 1 half 1 half.
1 half 1 half.
OK, let's see what the product is.
1 times 1 half plus 0 times this.
This is equal to 1 1.
1 times 1 half is 1 half,
0 times 1 half is 1 half.
And now, minus 1 half minus 1 half.
Now I have to take the trace of it.
Trace is 0.
So the expectation value of sigma 3 is, again, 0.
The same will be true of sigma 2,
but let's calculate the trace of
the product row times sigma 1
now.
Let's put sigma 1 there and see what we get.
Sigma 1 was the matrix 1, 1, 0, 0.
OK, so on the top row times
the first column, we get 1 half.
Same thing over here.
Looks like we get a half here also.
Now we get the same thing.
Everybody's a half, right?
And the trace is equal to 1.
So the expectation value of sigma 1 is 1.
The expectation value of the other sigmas is 0.
This is a pair of spins that happen
to both be lying along the x-axis.
It's a product.
Its entropy is 0 because it has one 0 eigenvalue
and one eigenvalue equal to 1.
All right?
So if somebody gave you
this density matrix here and said,
tell me, is it a pure state?
All you have to do is calculate its eigenvalues
and calculate its entropy.
Or if they asked you, how pure is it?
You could characterize it by its entropy.
In this case, the entropy is 0.
OK.
So if you change these
numbers a little bit, for example,
make this instead of 1 half, make it 0.4,
and make this one 0.4 or something like that,
you'll change things a little bit.
And instead of finding a 0 entropy density matrix,
it will have a small amount of entropy.
In other words, there'll be a small degree of entanglement.
OK.
So entropy, entanglement go together.
And it's sometimes called the entropy
that one gets this way because systems are entangled
is called entanglement entropy.
OK, let's take a little break.
First of all, in the cases which we've been doing,
we've assumed that the combined
system is in a pure state.
The combined composite system has a definite wave function.
That means the combined system should be thought
of as having a pure state.
As far as the combined system goes,
that means that its entropy is 0.
There's no uncertainty in the wave function
or in the state vector of a combined system.
It has 0 entropy.
The entropy that we're talking about now
is the entropy of the
subsystem, the subsystem now, which we'll
be looking at, which is subsystem A.
By virtue of the fact that it's entangled with B,
A has an entropy.
If you didn't look at B, A has an entropy.
Notice one thing, and this is a general property
of this kind of entanglement
entropy or this kind of entropy.
It doesn't add.
The combined system has 0 entropy.
The two subsystems each have, as a matter of fact,
would have entropy of logger.
And this is another killed this PROC
so transfer of entropy is
sometime after Rong in less than
a notion ofeurial flow over a mean interval.
So this is ezortunism.
But this iszagging, and this is a very prefix
chain, which results in a kind ofSTEAM thing
in relation to the system.
There is certain entropy, which isительization.
It doesn't completely match what debug euphemisms
invertix is all sort ofZon.
That's anything you get in a Doyle system.
I'm sorry, rearrangement.
And the situation becomes a straight foe.
So for this reason I'm ochint.
Can I only use on 分?
OK.
So we have to distinguish between the entropy
of the subsystem and the entropy of a composite system.
And as I said, I'll say
it once more, it is not additive.
In the first statement, you
mentioned entanglement entropy.
But all the interpenetries you
would find on quantum mechanics
is all entanglement entropy?
I think it's probably fair
to say it really is always
entanglement entropy.
But sometimes it's a little bit obscure
what's entangled with what.
But if you count the magnets and the people who
prepared the system and so forth,
then the only reason there would
be for not knowing which way
a spin was prepared would be that the preparation was
entangled with the thoughts of the preparer or something.
But if we want to keep the observer
out of it, we would just say that there's
different probabilities.
That's one origin of a density matrix.
But the other origin is entanglement.
I suspect probably entanglement covers them all.
But then you would have
to think about entanglement with what.
And it can get complicated.
All right, I want to leave the subject
of entanglement for a while.
I'm pretty sure we'll come back to it.
But there's one thing we have in mind.
And I haven't talked about it all.
It's how states change with time.
In classical physics, in classical logic,
if we're dealing with a discrete system,
if we're dealing with a
discrete system with the configuration
space being a system of points,
could be just two points, heads
or tails.
The only kind of evolution that makes sense
is discrete evolution, where time occurs in steps.
And at each step, the
system moves from one state vector
to another state vector, from one configuration
to another configuration.
And you could simply represent
the evolution by a permutation.
If you start in this vector, sorry, keep saying vector.
If you start with this state, you go to here.
You might go to here.
You go to here.
Here.
And perhaps back to here.
That would define the evolution of a
system, just a permutation which tells you where
every state goes.
It doesn't have to be all connected like this.
You could have four states.
And the rule could be
this one goes to this one.
This one goes to this one.
That's also a rule.
OK.
Excuse me.
Why do it has to be discrete time?
Well, because how are you going to go
from one discrete state to another discrete state
continuously?
How are you going to go from heads to tails?
Well, you could turn it over slowly.
But no, no.
But that would mean
that there were intermediate configurations.
That wouldn't really be a two configuration system.
You're talking about discrete configurations.
If there are discrete configurations, then I think
you would have to say that you have
to be able to do that.
You're talking about that evolution
would occur in discrete steps.
In quantum mechanics, in some sense, you
can have, well, we certainly have systems which
are discrete, a finite number of orthonormal states.
But the evolution of a system can be continuous.
Now, why is that?
You can have, well, why is that?
You can continuously go from up to down.
And that's the reason why we
have this idea of the quantum system.
It's a system that's not just a system.
It's a system that's a system.
If you move the electron to down, up
means a magnetic field pointing along the up axis
has locked the electron into place.
Down means the electron has been
locked into place by a down magnet.
And, of course, you have an
infinite continuous number of possibilities in between.
So although there's only two measurable possibilities for
the up spin, so in that sense, the system
is discrete.
Nevertheless, you can continuously interpolate between them.
and so that allows the possibility then
that state vectors can vary continuously with time
even for a system which is discrete
in the sense that the dimension
of the vector space is finite.
Let's talk about how state vectors change with time.
Now, there's an assumption,
and the assumption, the basic assumption,
is that the logical relationships between states
doesn't change with time.
For example, if you start with
two states which are the same state
and allow the system to evolve,
of course, the two states
will evolve into the same state.
That's trivial.
You start with a particular
state and you let it evolve.
It evolves into some definite state.
Well,
what about if there are two states of the system
which are orthogonal to each other,
spin up and spin down?
Well, the assumption is that two orthogonal states
of the same system, if you allow them to evolve,
would evolve into two orthogonal states,
that the distinctions, the
fact that they're measurably different,
will be preserved with time.
You could imagine, incidentally,
that's also true in the classical description,
that you don't have the situation
where two different states could evolve to the same state.
That never happens in classical physics.
You would lose memory then,
and then maybe you go to here.
Starting here, you could go to here,
and maybe from here you go back to here.
Well, then you would lose memory
of whether you started here or here,
because whether you start here or here,
you wind up here.
That doesn't happen in classical physics.
There's never a loss of memory of whether...
Yeah.
So I was thinking bifurcation of nonlinear analysis,
essentially you do have multiple steady states.
Not at the microscopic level.
Right.
This is a principle of physics in classical physics.
It's called concentration.
It's a function of the conservation of phase-based volume.
That the phase-based volume stays the same,
never contracts or expands.
But in quantum mechanics, it has another name.
The other name is unitarity.
But what it says is that
the inner products between two states
stay the same with time.
If two things are orthogonal, they will remain orthogonal.
Each state will change in its own way,
but if state number one and state number two,
are allowed to evolve with time,
they will remain orthogonal.
So for example, if you start with a spin up,
and you put it into some magnetic field
that could be doing complicated things,
after a while the state will change with time.
If you started with a state down,
after a while it will
change and become some other state.
But the two final states
will remain orthogonal to each other.
So if you start with a spin up,
and you put it into some magnetic field,
it will continue to be orthogonal.
All right, so the principle...
Is that only if they're under exactly the same influence?
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Under the same influence, right.
Right.
Yes, absolutely.
Yeah?
So if one spins up,
one spins down along the z-axis,
and you put it into
a magnetic field along the x-axis,
it would continue to be orthogonal?
Yeah.
What'll happen is if you
put it into a magnetic field
along the x-axis,
and you start with either a spin up or down,
they will begin to process, they will rotate.
All right?
So they might rotate after half a period or something
to one being along this axis,
the other being along this axis.
But those are orthogonal to each other.
Okay?
So orthogonality is maintained with time.
Even stronger...
inner product is...
inner product between two vectors is time independent.
So let's...
Actually, I should say that's the second principle
of time evolution.
The first principle of time evolution
is that it's governed by a linear operator.
Let's start with the first principle first.
Start with any state psi.
It could be any state of the system.
And let's imagine it at time zero.
Okay?
After a certain amount of time,
it evolves to a new state,
which is the state at time t.
The principle of quantum mechanics
that I'm going to say now
is first of all that the evolution is linear.
This can be summarized very easily
by saying that psi of t
is always equal to some linear operator.
I'm going to call it u,
which is a function of time,
times psi of zero.
What is u of time t equals zero?
What is u of zero?
One.
The state psi at time zero
is just equal to the state at psi...
at time equal to zero.
So whatever u is,
it's equal to one when t is equal to zero.
But at some later time,
the state vector is changed,
and the assumption...
Now, this is, again,
one of these things which is justified
by its empirical success.
Right?
It's justified by its empirical success.
But you will see as we go along
how this connects to other things in physics,
and why...
why it might be...
how we know this is true.
But let's just take it as an assumption
that there exists a linear operator
which is dependent on time.
It's not just a fixed linear operator.
It evolves with time,
and whatever the state is at time zero,
you'll hit it with u of t
to find out what it's doing at a later time.
That's the first principle of time evolution.
The second principle of time evolution
is that if we have two vectors,
and now I'm writing a bra and a ket,
and we allow them to evolve with time,
both of them,
that the inner product between them
is unchanged with time.
In other words,
that it's equal to phi of zero
times psi of zero
for any value of the time.
This is the statement that distinctions
between states
are maintained with time
if they're orthogonal.
That's enough actually just to know
that orthogonal states go to orthogonal states.
From that you can prove
that inner products remain invariant.
But in particular, for example,
if phi and psi are the same,
then this is just a normalization.
Phi phi is just a normalization
which we normally set equal to one.
This is just a statement then,
if phi is equal to psi,
it's just a statement that the,
the total probability doesn't change with time.
That the normalization of the state
doesn't change with time.
On the other hand,
if phi is orthogonal to psi,
then what it says is that
psi and phi are measurably different.
There's an experiment that you can do
to distinguish them uniquely,
and that will be true either at time,
if it's true at time t equals zero,
it will continue to be true at a later time.
So the logical relations between states
stay invariant with time.
That's an assumption, of course,
but it is true.
Alright, let's see what this condition here,
and this is true for any pair of vectors,
psi and phi.
Let's see what it says about u.
Okay.
Psi is equal to u of t times psi,
but let's look at the bra vector.
What about the bra vector?
It's a few.
It's a few, yeah.
So, that's a few.
So, I write u here?
You dagger,
the Hermitian conjugate.
Remember when you,
when you Hermitian conjugate
or when you complex conjugate
an expression,
you have to put in
the Hermitian conjugate here.
Alright, now let's see what happens to
happens to phi times psi?
This is equal, well, it's equal on
the one hand to phi of 0 u
dagger u times psi of 0.
But it's also equal to just
phi of 0 psi of 0.
And this is presumed to be true for every vector,
every pair of vectors psi
of 0 and phi of 0.
Well, if an equation, I won't prove this.
This is more or less obvious.
If an equation like this is true for every vector,
every pair of vectors in the vector space,
there's only one conclusion.
And that conclusion is that u dagger u
must be the unit operator.
That's something easy to prove, very easy to prove.
I'll leave it to you to prove that if there's
an operator whose matrix element between any pair of states
is the same as just
the inner product between those states,
it follows that operator.
But is there any solution for this problem?
Let's try to do what Hart said.
Let's say if this is a specific matrix
that would have to be joined pole matrix,
or polar sporad creep, to add this piece,
then there must be not only asanth Fruit,
but aıs.
But there must also be an operator
that is the unit matrix.
We're going to show how to
let's take the matrix using this.
Oppower.
Down, esto.
Out.
conjugate is 1, what does that say about the number?
It's a phase.
It's a pure phase. It's an e to the i
theta of some sort.
On the complex plane, it says that
it's on the unit circle.
It's unit
in length.
If u dagger u
is equal to 1, if it were a number.
Matrices
with this property are called unitary.
So
one would say that the time evolution
of quantum systems
is governed by unitary operators
which depend on time.
Let's imagine a very
small time interval.
A time interval of magnitude epsilon
where epsilon is a very small number.
So small that we can ignore
the square of epsilon.
In other words, in our equations,
we're going to retain things just to first order
in epsilon.
And let's see what it says
for a matrix to be
unitary.
First of all, if t
is equal to 0,
in other words, if epsilon is equal to 0,
epsilon is a little interval of time.
If epsilon is
equal to 0,
then u is equal
to 1. So let's write down
u of epsilon
epsilon is a small interval of time.
Starts out being 1
and then there's some small correction to it
and that correction is of order
epsilon. Let's assume it's of order epsilon
times some operator, which is
the first order correction.
Alright, now I am going to
just to avoid changing definitions in midstream,
I'm gonna put a minus sign here.
But that's purely a definition.
I'm gonna call the operator here h.
And I'm also gonna put an i here.
This i so far has no special meaning.
It's arbitrary.
I could absorb it into the h if I like.
And I could also absorb the minus sign in.
And I could have just written 1 minus epsilon h.
But for later purposes, I know that
I'm going to want to define h
so that there's an i here and a minus sign.
The minus sign is completely arbitrary.
The i is a nice definition, as we'll see.
So let's see what the condition on
h is for u to be unitary.
Let's write it down.
u dagger u, or what is u dagger?
u dagger of epsilon is
equal to 1 plus i epsilon.
Remember, we have to complex conjugate
everything when we take a mission conjugate.
And then we have to
write the Hermitian conjugate of h.
The Hermitian conjugate of 1 is just 1.
The Hermitian, the complex conjugate of
i epsilon is minus i epsilon.
So the sign changes here, and we substitute for h.
We substitute h dagger.
And now we multiply the two of them
and eventually use the approximation
that we can ignore epsilon squared
and only keep things to order epsilon.
All right, so the product is
1 plus i epsilon h dagger
times 1 minus i epsilon h.
What does that have to equal?
Well, if u is unitary, that has to equal 1.
So let's expand it out.
1, now we have 1 times minus i epsilon h,
minus i epsilon h,
and then we have plus i epsilon h dagger,
and then we have something of order epsilon squared.
All of that has to equal 1,
and we're going to ignore epsilon squared.
Epsilon is so small,
that we're going to have to ignore epsilon squared.
And we can ignore it.
We don't want to ignore epsilon,
the reason being that the 1s cancel on both sides.
The 1s cancel on both sides,
and so the leading term is proportional to epsilon.
And what do we get?
We get i epsilon h dagger
minus h should be equal to 0.
Or in other words,
the leading order in epsilon h dagger,
the conclusion is that h dagger equals h.
In other words, h is her mission.
h has a name.
It's called the Hamiltonian.
It's her mission, so it's an observable.
And the observable that it corresponds to,
is the energy of a system.
The eigenvalues of the matrix h
are the energy levels of a system.
But this was the main point,
that defined in this way with the i here,
h should be her mission.
We can write this another way.
Let's write it another way, the following way.
Let's write psi of epsilon,
minus psi of 0.
What is that?
All right.
Psi of epsilon is 1 minus
i epsilon h times psi of 0,
minus psi of 0.
Well, that just means the 1s cancel.
Psi of epsilon minus psi of 0,
is just equal to minus i epsilon h psi.
It's just the difference between them,
the extra little piece in u that comes from here.
This is a difference, but let
me divide it now by epsilon.
Divide everything, both sides of the equation by epsilon.
Well, this looks like the derivative of psi.
We'll now let epsilon be very small.
Take the limit that epsilon is very small now.
This is the difference of
something at epsilon and at 0,
divided by epsilon.
This is the derivative of psi,
with respect to epsilon.
Or with respect to t.
Epsilon is just a small interval of time.
All right.
So the change in epsilon divided
by a small interval of time,
that's the derivative of the
state vector with respect to time,
is equal to minus i h on psi.
This tells you how the wave function of a system,
or how the state vector
of a system, I should say,
how it changes with time.
h being her mission guarantees that u is unitary.
If it's unitary, it guarantees that the logical relations
between states are maintained with time.
And this is the equation which governs the evolution
of every quantum system.
Of course, you may get to pick what h is.
I haven't told you what h is.
h may depend on a particular setup.
For example, h may depend on
the magnitude of a magnetic field.
It could depend on all kinds of things.
The only thing we learn from general principles
is that the Hamiltonian should be a her mission operator.
A her mission operator has eigenvalues and eigenvectors,
and the eigenvalues are called the energy levels.
So this is the way
a state vector changes with time.
In principle, h can be a function of time.
For example, if you have an electron
in a magnetic field and you change the magnetic field.
But if you have a situation where nothing is changing,
magnetic field or whatever it
happens that's governing the system
happens to be time independent,
under that circumstance, h is
simply a fixed definite matrix,
a fixed definite operator that is called the Hamiltonian.
A that contains space, Wash would say自由.
So, that's trzy Schulz's question.
And if you want to think aboutode
or say, if you compare J
by P 영화,
what would J comes back to?
It's that.
No, the only thing you can conclude
is if you have two different state vectors,
the inner product of them remains invariant with time.
Now that doesn't tell you that entanglement...
No, that is not correct, the two things.
If it were correct, you would not
be able to entangle one thing with another.
If they were unentangled, they would remain unentangled.
And measurements could not be done.
So no, that does not follow.
Do we have a unit for entanglement somewhere?
Yeah, the entropy.
That's the unit of entanglement.
And that's Jules.
It is what?
Jules.
Oh, no, no, no, no.
Entropy is a pure number.
Yeah.
It's a state description.
It describes the set relationships.
And it has no...
No dimensions.
It's measured in bits.
It's measured in bits, but bits are
measured in units of log 2 or something.
Right.
No, no, no, okay.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
No, all right, so let's go through units.
The standard thermodynamic
units, the standard thermodynamics,
let's write a thermodynamic equation.
Here's a thermodynamic equation.
The differential change in the energy
and the heat of a system
is the temperature times ds, but let's see,
we usually put a k in there or not.
No, no k in there, right?
Ah, no.
Now, what are the units of temperature?
Well, okay, degrees usually,
but let's write another equation.
Another equation would be the fact
that the kinetic energy of a particle
is the temperature of a particle.
Okay.
So, our kinetic energy of a particle
in a gas is three halves k,
which is Boltzmann's constant, times the temperature.
So, the temperature always has units of energy.
Temperature has units of
energy divided by Boltzmann's constant,
whatever the units of Boltzmann's constant are.
I mean, the units of Boltzmann's
constant are energy divided by temperature.
All right, all right.
But all...
All right.
But, you know, the only reason that
there was this stupid Boltzmann constant in physics
is because people measured temperature
with a stupid thermometer that
they bought in a hardware store.
Okay.
The natural real units for temperature are energy.
Get rid of the Boltzmann constant.
It's just a conversion factor from units of energy
to units of Celsius or whatever.
Once you make...
Once you just get rid of the Boltzmann constant
and say temperature is measured in units of energy,
then energy, energy, dimensionless.
Entropy becomes dimensionless and entropy...
Why is it dimensionless?
It's the logarithm of an integer.
How could it have dimensions?
Of course, you assign it the dimensions of bits,
but a bit is just a meaning, you know,
a number of things.
A unit, a dimensionless unit.
So, entropy is dimensionless
unless you want to put back the Boltzmann constant
and then...
And then where does it go?
I can't figure out where it goes.
It's energy for temperature.
It's energy divided by temperature in either case,
but...
Yeah, yeah.
But for all purposes, we want to define entropy,
in an information-theoretic way,
and all information theorists would call entropy
absolutely dimensionless.
It's only when they want to connect to thermodynamics
and then use for the unit of temperature a thermometer
that Boltzmann's constant enters into the story.
Good.
You know, I don't think Boltzmann ever knew
his own constant, incidentally.
It wasn't until Einstein in 1905
that Boltzmann's constant was actually measured.
Einstein figured it out, how to measure it.
And Boltzmann committed suicide the year before
because he was very discouraged
because nobody knew what his constant was.
It's one of the real sad stories of physics.
I shouldn't make fun of Boltzmann.
He was a very great physicist.
Where are we?
Yeah, I'll tell you what, I'm going to jump.
I was going to talk about the eigenvalues of H,
but I'll do that next time.
And they are, of course, just called the energies,
the energy levels.
Will you tell us why the
relationship between them is so important?
I don't know.
The relationship between H is related to energy?
Let's just call that.
Why?
Because it's conserved.
OK, let's, it goes back to Einstein.
Well, everything goes back to Einstein.
That doesn't say anything.
OK.
You know that the way
the wave function varies with time
is with an exponential phase that depends on energies?
Yes.
And that's E equals H nu, right?
Oh, there should be a Planck's constant in here
if I really want to keep track of,
where does the Planck's constant go, here?
I think the .
Right?
Yeah.
There's a Planck's constant over here,
so let's put the Planck's constant there.
No, there's no 2 pi in there.
The 2 pi is depending on
whether you use H or H bar,
and with H bar...
What's that?
Wait, let me see.
Yeah.
Ah, yes.
It's over, sorry.
D by Dt, yeah, it's over H bar.
Over H bar, yeah.
Yeah, energy levels are very
small things in quantum mechanics,
and you divide by H bar
and you can't use the time.
Okay, good.
Let's suppose that psi is an eigenvector of H.
H on psi is equal,
well, let me call it omega.
If it comes out to really
be omega, I'll be very happy.
Let's call it omega on psi.
Omega being...
Now, energy, E, energy, E for energy.
E is a number.
Psi is an eigenvector of H with eigenvalue E.
Okay?
Just assume.
That means...
I'm getting tired.
I'm beginning to fade.
Okay.
If psi is initially an eigenvector of energy,
it will remain an eigenvector of energy for all time.
Let's see if we can solve this equation.
Let's see if we can solve this equation
assuming that psi remains an eigenvector
of the energy for all time.
Okay.
Now, if it remains an eigenvector
of the energy for all time,
you say, wait a minute, wait a minute.
That means it doesn't change.
If it doesn't change, this is nonsense.
Now, psi is an eigenvector,
but remember that you can
multiply an eigenvector by a number,
in particular a complex number,
and it still remains an eigenvector.
So let's write that psi of t
is equal to a function of time,
times psi of zero,
if psi of zero is an eigenvector of the energy,
so will f of t times
psi be an eigenvector of energy,
and therefore so will the left-hand side.
It'll be the eigenvector with the same eigenvalue.
It'll just be multiplied.
And let's see if we can solve this
by seeing if we can find an f of t
which will allow this to be solved.
Okay. So what does this say?
We just factor out psi of zero,
and what it says is that the f of t
is equal to minus i.
Now, h on psi gives e times psi.
So that gives an e
divided by h-bar times f,
all multiplying the vector psi.
But we can divide.
We can just get rid of the vector psi
at time t equals zero.
This equation just becomes an equation
for the function f of t.
The f by dt is minus
i e over f of t.
So that's e times psi e to
the minus i e over h-bar f.
All I've done is substitute for psi of t
f of t times psi of zero,
and then use that h on psi over here
is e times psi.
You know how to solve this?
The solution of an equation like this
is just that f goes like e
to the minus i e over h-bar t
times psi of zero.
So what it says is if you start
with an eigenvector of the energy
or eigenvector of the Hamiltonian,
then it evolves with time
just by multiplying by a time-dependent phase.
That's all that happens.
What do you call a coefficient
in an e to the i something t?
What do you call a coefficient of t?
Time coefficient.
No, it's usually called a time constant if it's real.
Then it would be the decay constant.
You call it the frequency.
Not the frequency, but the angular frequency, omega.
So we have that the wave function evolves
with a frequency, with an angular frequency, omega,
which is equal to the energy over h-bar,
or better yet, energy is h-bar times omega.
That should be a familiar equation.
It also can be written energy is ordinary frequency
times Planck's original constant,
differs by a factor of 2 pi.
I'm getting tired, and my
cold is getting worse and worse,
so we're going to quit now.
But I thought I would just show you this,
and we'll come back to it.
But the phases and the fact that,
frequency is related to energy,
is equivalent to this equation,
which tells you how states change with time.
This equation also has a name.
The name is the Schrodinger equation.
This is the Schrodinger equation.
It's not the particular Schrodinger equation
that Schrodinger wrote down for a particular free particle.
That was a particle in a potential.
That was a special case of this.
This is the generalized Schrodinger equation
for any system.
But you have to pick a Hamiltonian.
We'll do some of that next time.
We'll pick out some examples.
Again, particle in a magnetic field,
or other examples like that.
The preceding program is copyrighted by Stanford University.
Please visit us at stanford.edu.