This program is brought to you by Stanford University.
Please visit us at stanford.edu.
All right, so for those people who are watching on Saturday night live or
wherever this thing is being broadcast.
If you have questions that you want to communicate with me about or
you want to post some interesting insight or
I'm speaking about a physics insight.
If you want to put up a interesting problem that you may have either seen or
heard of or had a professor 40 years ago give you to solve and
you've never been able to solve it since or well, that sort of thing.
Then rather than send it to me by email,
and expect me to send it out to everybody.
I thought we could put these things up on a site which I created,
which thus far I've got exactly one question on.
Suskins blog physics for everyone.
That's one word.blogspot.com.
Use it.
Don't abuse it.
No polemics, please.
I do not answer polemical questions.
I've learned not to.
It's taken me some time and polemical things will be immediately eliminated.
Serious physics questions, even if they're very simple,
they do not have to be either deep, profound, difficult,
or just some simple insights about some of the material.
That'll be fine.
Questions about physics,
even outside the scope of the class, are fine.
No questions about whether string theory is even wrong.
Anyway, let's begin tonight's lecture.
I put this up on the top for.
I tried to get to it.
I couldn't.
Did anybody else have a problem?
I don't know.
I don't have any problem getting to it.
But.
I did get to it.
Did they?
It may be that the people are having problems getting to it.
If you do have a problem, send me an email and I'll see you.
I'm a complete incompetent at this.
I just tried to do it.
It seemed to be successful.
I seemed to be able to get to it.
I put an announcement on it.
Maybe.
Is there more than one thread on there?
I don't know.
I don't even know what a thread is.
So was the question that you got recent?
No.
It came the first day.
Well, recent.
Fairly recent.
Yeah.
Anyway, let's keep going.
If you try to use it and it doesn't work, let me know.
You do have to sign in, I think.
You have to email and go through a sign-in.
Or something.
Yeah.
I don't know.
I'll try to find out.
I'll try to get somebody who knows about these things.
OK.
Let's talk about the invariance of the laws of nature
under various kinds of operations.
Of course, what I really have in mind is, of course,
Lorentz transformations.
The fact that the laws of nature do not change when we make
a Lorentz transformation.
But let's talk about the strategy for cooking up laws.
OK.
Which look the same in every reference frame.
The strategy is to express those laws in a form which really
doesn't depend on any particular choice of coordinates.
To express the laws in some physical way that, as I said,
that doesn't depend on specific coordinates.
And then choose a set of coordinates,
and rewrite what you've expressed in a language appropriate to those coordinates.
An example.
The shortest distance between two points, the definition of a straight line,
is the shortest distance between two points, the shortest trajectory between two points.
You can figure out what a straight line is, connecting a pair of points, by sticking a
thumbtack.
Please don't stick thumbtacks in the blackboards and the whiteboards, but you could.
Stick a couple of thumbtacks in, take a string, pull it as tight as you can,
and that will guarantee that you've found the shortest distance between those two points,
and that you will call a straight line.
In other words, the law for a straight line, this is not actually a law of physics now,
this is the definition of a straight line, but it's
been defined in a way that made no reference to any particular coordinates.
An example of a law of physics that's closely related to this is that the path of a light
ray between two points is a straight line.
That's a law.
And now it can be stated that the path of a light ray between two points is the shortest
distance between those two points.
That's a light ray in a vacuum.
Generally.
The generalization of that for light moving through various kinds of materials is that
the time that it takes a light ray to go from one point to another is the shortest possible
time.
Alright, so those, and notice again, I did not use any definition of spatial coordinates
in expressing those laws.
Those laws were expressed in a coordinate independent way.
But then, I
can then use coordinates to build myself up with mathematics and to solve some equations
involving those laws.
Let me give you an example.
Just exactly this law here, that light travels along the shortest path, or just the problem
of finding the shortest path between two points.
Alright, once I know that the shortest path, that's what I'm looking for, is the shortest
path, I take some coordinates, x and y, I include them in the randomization.
So, I take the coordinates, x and y, and put that in a coordinate.
So here, close the cap.
So, all right, so now, that's the story for light.
I label the two points of interest
I give them coordinates
x1, y1, x2, y2
I won't bother right now
and then I write down
well, first of all
I imagine a curve connecting them
I imagine a curve
in fact, I'm going to imagine
all possible curves connecting them
and I break up that curve
into little segments
each little segment
can be characterized by a differential
meaning a small displacement
dx and dy
so let's take a little displacement
over here
and label it dx
and dy
eventually, of course
we're going to go to the limit
where we chop it up into smaller and smaller pieces
and do some calculus
but for the moment, just call them dx and dy
and now let's write the length of the curve
the length of the curve
is just the summation
over all of these little differential elements
of the length of each differential element
the length of each differential element
we can write ds
s for length
I'm not sure why I use s for length
except it's traditional to do so
and that's equal
to the square root of dx squared
plus dy squared
that's of course the Pythagorean theorem
it does not depend
on what the orientation of the curve is
but on what the orientation of the axes are
with any orientation for the axes
as long, incidentally
as long as I use the same units
for x and y
I would get a rather bizarre expression
as I've emphasized several times
if I used meters for x
and feet for y
but as long as I use the same units
it doesn't matter which way I orient the axes
on the blackboard
I'm just going to use the same
and the length of a little differential element
is still the same
and now I add them all up
I add them up by integrating
s for the total length
becomes the integral
which is just the sum of all these little differential elements here
square root of dx squared plus dy squared
now that's a strange look
for some of you that may be a bit of a strange looking expression
a square root of dx squared plus dy squared
it's not really that strange
you're going to have to do a little bit of a test
you could think of y
you could think of x as the independent variable
and then rewrite this in another form
integral
let's take out a factor of dx
and now in the square root
since I've taken out a factor of dx
that means I should divide what's in the square root
by dx squared
and that just becomes one plus dy by dx squared
dy by dx squared
that's just a derivative of the dependent variable y
with respect to x
and this is a perfectly good integral
if you know what y of x is
that's the length between the two points
and now you can set yourself the task
let me find the curve
which gives the smallest value for this
that connects two points
this of course is very similar
to the principle of least action
which says that the trajectory of a particle in space-time
sweeps out a path of least action
again, action being some kind of integral
of a Lagrangian
very similar kind of thing
but the main point here
is that we've expressed the original law
without coordinates
and therefore we can be sure
that when we introduce coordinates
the answer will not depend on our choice of coordinates
yes sir
can you define distance without coordinates?
uh...
sure
tape measure
of course the tape measure has coordinates along it
but the point is
it doesn't matter how you reorient the axes
the tape measure will always give the same expression
so it was defined by
the string or the tape measure connecting the two points
but without regard to how I chose the x-y axes
but then
in an attempt to actually mathematically implement
the mathematical problem
I introduced a set of coordinates
to express the problem in a mathematical form
and so yes, I think the problem is expressed
without coordinates
it's a good question
but for the moment I'll leave it hang as
in the way that I said it
okay, now, so that's an example
now what went into that example
the most important thing that went into that example
mathematically was Pythagoras' theorem
that the distance between two points
is the square root of the sum of the squares
and that does not
the sum of the squares of the coordinates
and it has exactly the same form
if you were to tilt the axes
that in itself
is an expression of invariance
that the distance between two neighboring points
is invariant, meaning to say
it doesn't depend on your coordinates
and of course we're familiar with this
we've gone through it several times
dx squared plus dy squared
doesn't depend on your choice of coordinates
and the way to check that
which is exactly the sorts of things we've checked up till now
is we've taken a coordinate set
and we've rotated the coordinate system
rotated the coordinate system
x, y, x prime, y prime, theta
an angle between them
and we've discovered that the law of transformation
the mathematical law of rotation of coordinates
is the law which keeps
x squared plus y squared fixed
dx squared plus dy squared fixed
and the sums of squares
of the components of any vector
in fact any quantity
which transforms the same way as x and y
as the components of the position vector
the sums of squares will be invariant
so that's the strategy
the strategy is to find ways
to find basically all the ways
of constructing quantities
which are invariant under the operation
that you're interested in
and then express the laws of physics
perhaps in terms of action principles
action principles are very efficient ways
of expressing laws of nature
in a way that doesn't depend on coordinates
you just say
the length is minimum
or the time
for a light ray to go from one place to another is minimum
or the action is minimum
but you must check
that the expression that you've written down for the action
really doesn't depend on your choice of coordinates
and so it becomes an exercise
in figuring out how to form invariants
invariants means things which don't change
when you change the coordinates in particular ways
do you have a question?
yeah
is this dependent on the underlying geometry?
yes, this is dependent on the fact that the underlying geometry
was Euclidean geometry and that's a good point
there's a generalization of it of course
the idea of geodesic in a curved space
but I'm trying now to be as simple as possible
and give you the simplest examples
when you say transformed in the same way
as x and y
yes, yes, yes, exactly
supposing I have any pair of quantities
let's call them ax and ay
now of course secretly what I have in mind
is the components of vectors
so let's just call them ax and ay
and I assume that they transform
which means that when you look at them from different coordinates
first of all the components themselves
depend on your choice of coordinates
and let's just assume
that they transform in the form ax prime
is equal to ax
cosine theta
I think it's minus
ay
sine theta
and likewise for
ay prime
equals ax
sine theta
plus I guess ay cosine theta
this is the same way that x and y themselves would transform
this law of transformation from one coordinate system
to another defines what we call a vector
now of course let's go
we can also introduce a z-axis
and we should introduce a z-axis
I'm just too lazy to write down the more
complicated transformation law
and it is more complicated when you can rotate around in three dimensions
but this is the idea
and once you have established
that the quantities that you have
are components of a vector
it follows immediately
that the sums of the squares of them
ax squared plus ay squared
is invariant
what that means is that
if you make such a transformation
then
this will be equal to
ax prime squared plus
ay prime squared
alright
so establishing that a pair of components
transforms as a vector
allows you not only to transform them
but to write down expressions which don't change
when you change your coordinates
the sums of squares of components of a vector
are sort of the leading candidate for that kind of thing
okay so that's
dx squared plus dy squared is a special example
let's talk about
um
the same way we would say that anything
that transforms the same way
as x, y, z, and t
incidentally did we ever talk about how
y and z transform
no
well let's fill that gap in right now
it's exceedingly simple
let's fill that gap
we
found
the transformation law x prime
is equal to
x times
cosh omega
minus
t not the
not y
t sin omega
t prime
is equal to x
minus x sin omega
plus
t cosh omega
now this is
for a Lorentz transformation
where the
relative velocity
between the two frames is along the x axis
if we wanted to have the relative velocity
along some other axis we'd have to do something more complicated
but this is for where the two frames of reference
are moving relative to each other
right along the x axis
what about the y and z components of vectors
well the y and z components of vectors simply don't change
when you boost
boost is another word for doing a Lorentz transformation
along a given axis
when you do a Lorentz transformation
along the x axis
the y and z components don't change
a meter stick
oriented perpendicular to its own velocity
does not get Lorentz transformed
the arguments for that can be found
in the internet lectures
on the special theory of relativity
two or three quarters ago
and I'm not going to go through them now
but I'm going to go through them now
and I'm going to go through them now
other than to just say
that the rest of the transformation law is
y prime is equal to y
and z prime is equal to z
now of course Lorentz transformations
are not the only things we can do
that will keep our
description of physics fixed
we can also rotate coordinates
we can rotate
among x, y and z
those are spatial rotations
when you combine together
spatial rotations
with Lorentz transformations
along a given axis
if you then rotate your coordinates
rotate your coordinates
you can then use the rotation
of coordinates to boost along
a different axis
that's a complicated combination
of different kinds of transformations
the question is
what are the quantities which are
invariant when we have all four components here
ok
now the combination which is invariant
is more or less obvious
it's just
not just t squared minus x squared
t squared minus x squared
that was proper time
that was the thing which was invariant
under a boost along the x axis
if you transform along the x axis
with a standard Lorentz transformation
but supposing
I do a different transformation
instead of doing a Lorentz transformation
I just do a rotation of coordinates
rotation of x into y for example
well if I just rotate
my spatial coordinates
and do nothing to time
in other words this is just an ordinary rotation
of spatial coordinates doing absolutely
nothing to time
no velocity involved
just a change of orientation
and time doesn't change
time doesn't change if all you do is
transform the orientation
of your space coordinates
but x, y, and z transform into each other
so t squared minus x squared
cannot possibly be invariant
in fact
when you do a rotation
the quantity which is invariant
is x squared plus y squared plus z squared
that suggests
that the invariant
is t squared minus x squared
minus y squared minus z squared
and that's correct
under a Lorentz transformation
this Lorentz transformation here
t squared minus x squared
does not change
that we've already established
furthermore since y and z don't change
t squared minus x squared
minus y squared
minus z squared
doesn't change
ok
so this is the quantity
that we're going to use
to do the transformation
which Lorentz transformations
and rotations of space
keep invariant
don't change
we'll come back to that
we'll come back to that later
another time
maybe today
now any quantity
which transforms
under Lorentz transformations
and spatial rotations
in the same way as x, y, z, and t
is called a four vector
a four vector
is just a quantity which transforms
as the basic coordinates themselves
if you have a four vector
it has a time component
and it has three space components
the difference between the square of the time component
and the three space components squared
that always
is an invariant
it's the analog
of the length of a vector
but in
space-time
so if we have a general four vector
for example
just take instead of the coordinates themselves
you have a trajectory
and you have a little interval along the trajectory
then you have a four vector
which is just d t
d x, d y, and d z
and d t squared
minus d x squared
minus d y squared
minus d z squared
insert a unit
that is all inverse
so you have a one under two
but sometimes
that's part of the degree of定ing
It's extremely important to us to know how to form invariants
And in order to know how to form invariants
We have to specify how quantities transform
If we don't know how things transform
We don't know how to put them together to make invariants
Alright, so what kind of objects are there?
Well, first of all, there are four vectors
That's not the simplest kind of thing
There's an even simpler thing
That's even simpler than a four vector
It's a scalar
A scalar is a thing which doesn't transform at all
It's the same in every reference frame
Can you think of anything which is a scalar?
Sometimes called an invariant
I'm not going to distinguish between invariants and scalars for this class
Can you think of anything which is an invariant?
I heard it
Okay
Electric charge
Electric charge of a moving particle is exactly the same as a stationary particle
If you at rest watch my electron moving along
You'll ascribe to it exactly the same electric charge
I was just thinking of my name
My name is Leonardo
My name doesn't change when I start to move
It's a scalar
Some other scalars that happen in physics
Mass
Mass is a scalar
Rest mass is a scalar, yes
But here's another scalar
Well, dt squared minus dx squared minus dy squared minus dz squared
It's a thing which doesn't change under Lorentz transformation
Now, officially you would call that an invariant
But I'm just going to call it a scalar
A thing which does not change when you Lorentz transform or when you rotate
Okay?
That's called an invariant
If we can build up our laws of nature out of invariants
Then our laws of nature will be invariant
That's simply stated
If we can build up and express the laws of nature
We can express them in terms of coordinates
As long as we express them in terms of combinations of things which are themselves invariant
Alright, so we have four vectors
Let's just label the general four vector A
It has four components
And I'm going to label those four components A mu
Mu is a Greek letter
It looks like an M
It is an M, it's Greek M
And I'm going to put the index up on top
Alright?
For example
The simplest four vector would be the coordinates X mu
And what do they stand for?
They stand for four things
They stand in particular for dt
dx, dy, and dz
I hear something's ringing
Is that in my head?
That wasn't in my head
We all heard it
Okay
Alright
So dx mu just stands for the quadruple of components of the four vector
Mu can be thought of as going over four distinct values
And it's usually taken to go from z to z
0 to 3
dt is usually considered the zeroth component of the vector
1, 2, 3
That's completely arbitrary
The fact that the time component of the vector is considered its zeroth component
Rather than its fourth component
Alright?
So this is the same as dx0 dot dot dot dot dot
Same thing
Now
We multiply these things together to form invariants
But we multiply them together to form invariants
But we multiply them together with a funny sign
Alright?
The funny sign distinguishing the dt squared from the dx squared, dy squared, and dz squared
There's a notation for that
I think the notation
I'm not sure who invented the notation
Uh
Somebody probably in the 19th century
It might have been Riemann
It might have been Levi-Civiter
I'm not sure who it was
But one of the early differential geometers
I don't think it was Einstein
But I'm not sure
No, I don't think so
But Einstein invented the following notation
Supposing I invent a new object
Not dt, dx, dy, dz
But a new object which is exactly the same set of core components
Except I change the sign of the time component
dx, dy, dz
All it is is the same object
Except with the time component having its sign changed
Then the notation for that is dx with a subscript like that
It's the same object except its time component has been changed
Every time you take a vector and you change the time component by a sign
It either corresponds to raising or lowering the index
If I have the lower index object
Here it is right here
And I change the sign of the time component
It becomes the index object
The upper index object
If I take the upper index object and change the sign of the time component
It becomes the lower index object
So this is purely notation
There's no physics in it
It's purely notation for another object
But now I can rewrite that invariant
This ds squared
Or d tau squared
The proper time squared
Instead of writing it dT squared minus dx squared minus dy squared minus dz squared
Which I get rather tired of doing
I write it in the form
dx mu dx with a lower mu
Now, again, notations
This was Einstein
Who realized he was writing down too many summation signs
He realized after a while
That all of his summation signs in his various equations
Were always summations over things with upper indices and lower indices next to each other
So he got the bright idea
It was one of the brilliant extrapolations of physics
That whenever you see a thing with an upper and a lower index next to each other
Automatically sum over them
Automatically
Don't even ask the question whether you sum
You do sum
dx super mu sub mu
Is by definition the sum over the four components
Let's see what it says
dx mu mu
Let's start with the first component
The north component
The time component
That's just equal to
dt
For the upper component guy
And then for the lower component guy
It's another dt but with a minus sign
Minus dt squared in other words
Then there's the upper component dx
And the lower component dx
They're both dx
We haven't changed any sign
So that's plus dx squared
And likewise for y and z
So this object is just shorthand
For minus dt squared
Do I really want minus?
Yeah, I do
No, no, it's fine
It's the way I want it
This is shorthand
The x super mu dx sub mu
Is shorthand for the
Not the sums of squares
But the difference of squares
Where time components always come in with an extra minus sign
Now
Here's something interesting
This object is invariant
Therefore this object is invariant
This generalizes
If we generalize
If we have a four vector
Which transforms the same way as dx mu
Then we label dx super mu
The x, y, z, and t
If it transforms the same way as those things
Then we label it with an upper index
Just like dx mu is labeled here
That stands for the four components
I won't bother writing them
The four components
The four components of the vector
But we can also invent
A symbol with a lower index
The only difference
Is the time components of these two
Have the opposite sign
The space components have the same sign
If we construct the analog
Of what's written here
Namely, a mu, a mu
That's the time component squared
Minus the space component squared
That quantity is invariant
Doesn't change under Lorentz transformation
So we're beginning to build up
A calculus or a set of rules
For forming invariants
And the rules are
Keep track of your indices
Sum over repeated indices
And make sure that an upper one
Always accompanies a lower one
That will build up invariants
Made up out of pairs of vectors
Now, it's a little more general than this
I haven't told you the story in full generality
Here's an exercise for you to prove
Supposing you have two vectors
Not two dimensional vectors
But a pair of four vectors
A mu, a mu
That's the first one
That's the second one
That's the third one
That's the fourth one
That's the fifth one
A mu and b mu
A pair of them
Both of them transform the same way
As the components x, y, z, and t
Then you can make an object
A super mu, b sub mu
Again, that's intended
Let's write down what that means
It means
The time component of A
Times the time component
Well, let's
Yeah, let's
It means the time component of A
Times the time component of B
But with a minus sign
Because when you lower an index
That means a minus sign
And then plus
The x component
Times the x component of B
Plus likewise
For the y component
Plus az, bz
B, yeah
It's the analog of the dot product
Between two vectors
Except with a minus sign
For the time components
The analog of the dot product
In fact, this piece over here
Is just the dot product
Between the spatial pieces of the vector
The time pieces come in with the opposite sign
And that you can see
One of these has a lower index
The other has an upper index
And so the relative sign of the time components is opposite
In fact, there's no difference between this
And putting the lower index here
And the upper index here
It doesn't matter which of the two vectors
You flip the sign of the time component
The product of them will come in with a minus sign
So both of these objects here
Are invariants
They're like the dot product between two vectors
And the dot product between two vectors
Is something which doesn't change under rotation
The Lorentz invariant dot product
It's not called the dot product
The inner product
The Lorentz invariant inner product of two vectors
Is also something which will not change
When you do Lorentz transformation
Now this is something to check
This is something you can check
Take any two four vectors
Transform them to a new coordinate system
And then check that a mu b mu doesn't change
That it has the same value before and after the transformation
So as I said
We're beginning to build up a vocabulary
For forming invariant quantities
Yeah
Say it again
You can transform to a spherical coordinate
Mm-hmm
No, no
No, no, no, no
Not spherical
No, no
We're doing coordinate transformations
Between inertial reference frames
Okay
Inertial reference frames means Cartesian coordinates
And uniform velocity
Okay
We can rotate coordinates
And transform along some other axis
But we're not talking about things like polar coordinates at the moment
Inertial reference frames all refer to distance
And the relationship between two frames
Yeah
Well, okay
So
First of all
Inertial reference frame means the spatial coordinates are Cartesian coordinates
Okay
Conventional Cartesian coordinates
Just x, y, and z
With the usual rules for manipulating Cartesian coordinates
And it means that the two coordinate frames are in constant motion relative to each other
That's the relationship between two inertial frames
One more statement
An inertial frame, a single one
If we had one single inertial frame
Then we'd be able to define an infinite number of them
By transforming from one to another
All right
So you have to start with one inertial frame
One inertial frame means a frame where Newton's laws are satisfied
Or where Einstein's generalization of Newton's laws are satisfied
In other words, f equals m-a
Okay
Good
So that's all that goes into the idea of an inertial frame
There's one inertial frame, some of them out there
Where Newton's laws are satisfied
And any other which is related by Lorentz transformation is also an inertial frame
Okay
So that's the idea of building up invariants out of four vectors
As I said, an even more primitive and simple concept
Is the invariant that's called the invariant of the vector
In itself, there are invariants which are not built up out of four vectors
They just happen to be invariants
I mean, what's another example?
The trouble is, to find examples in relativity theory
You have to know a little more physics than that
But if we were just talking about rotation of coordinates
And not Lorentz transformation
There would be things which are scalars which would be very familiar
Temperature is a scalar
It doesn't matter if you hold your thermometer this way, that way, that way, this way or that way
In other words, it doesn't matter what axes you orient your thermometer along
You get the same temperature
Pressure, air pressure is also a scalar, an invariant
That's a little bit less obvious that if you had a pressure meter
How do you make a pressure meter?
Oh, I don't know, you make a pressure meter
It's not obvious that the pressure meter is a scalar
Here's my pressure meter
It's not obvious that if I turn the pressure meter upside down, I get the same pressure
Why?
Well, as all the air resting on it from above
You might think that it would squeeze it down more
If you hold the pressure meter this way than if you hold it that way
Well, it's not true
The air is pressing as much from underneath as it is from here
Air pressure is a scalar, it doesn't matter which way you hold it
What is a pressure meter called?
Manometer
What?
Is there a barometer?
Granometer, he said
What's a barometer?
A barometer is a column of fluid
Doesn't that measure air pressure?
Yeah, under gravity
Under gravity, yeah, yeah, yeah, that's right
But a burden gauge does that
A burden gauge is just a piece of metal that's got air inside it
And it winds or wind winds
Yeah, there's many ways to make a pressure meter
You might just take a cell, put a rubber membrane over it, seal it,
seal the rubber membrane, and then when you put a lot of pressure on it,
the rubber membrane goes this way, if you take it off, the pressure, the rubber membrane,
you know, all kinds of ways of making it
But don't you need to distinguish between the actual quantity and the way you measure it?
I mean, the quantity itself may be fixed, but the way you measure it may depend upon certain physical properties
Well, you know, sometimes the only really good definitions of quantities are through how you measure them
In fact, I think that's more or less always the case, but I get the point
When you say it's invariant, do you mean you get the same curve?
Do you mean you get the same pressure on the wind frame?
No, no, it's invariant under rotations, not under Lorentz transformations
Right, only under rotations
So with respect to the rotations, pressure, temperature are invariants
What's a weather quantity which is not an invariant?
Wind velocity
Wind velocity is what?
It's a vector
It's got a magnitude and it's got a direction
And its components do depend on your orientation
The x component will change if you change what you call the x axis
So its components are the components of a vector
Humidity is a good
But so is wind speed
Wind speed, what does speed mean?
Speed is the magnitude of the velocity
Speed is not velocity because by definition, the term speed officially means the magnitude of velocity
In fact, the speed is just the square root of the sums of the squares of the components of the wind velocity
So the wind speed is an invariant and therefore kind of qualifies as a scalar for me
The wind velocity, which has a sense of direction, is not a scalar
Alright, so we now know what we mean by vectors
Four vectors
Scalars
And we know how to make some scalars out of four vectors
If we go back to the problem of
Well, okay, that's
Now there's another quantity, another class of quantities which are interesting
Which also have four components
They are also four vectors
A little bit tricky
A little bit different
Oh, before I say that, let me just say one thing
If I have a known four vector
Let's call it A
And I have another set of objects, B mu, which I'm not sure whether they're a four vector or not
I'm not sure whether they transform as a four vector
There's a test
You calculate in every frame of reference the inner product
And if the inner product doesn't change
If the inner product is a scalar
If the inner product of two objects, one of which is known to be a four vector
And the other you're testing
If that inner product doesn't change from frame to frame
In other words, supposing somebody gave you a four vector
They told you it was a four vector
And then they gave you another set of four quantities
They gave it to you in every frame of reference
But they didn't tell you whether it was a four vector or not
Then you compute the inner product, A mu, B mu
And if it's the same in every reference frame
Then B mu is a four vector
That's a theorem, it's a simple elementary theorem
That if you have one four vector and you're testing another one
If the inner product is invariant, then B must be a four vector
Okay, let's move on to another object
The derivative
Supposing I have a scalar quantity
Such as the temperature in three dimensions
Or some other vector
Another field
Now we come to the idea of a field
A field in space
A field in space, there are many different kinds of fields
Some fields are vector fields
For example, if we're just talking about three dimensions
Wind velocity is a field
Of course it's not a field in the sense of a fundamental field of any kind
But it is a field, it varies from place to place
It can have equations which govern it
It's a vector field
Not a four vector field, a three vector field
As we said, temperature, humidity are scalars
Imagine now that we have a scalar with respect to the Lorentz transformations
Let's call it phi
Phi is Greek F and F stands for field
It's a field, it depends on position in general
X, Y, Z and T, let's just call it phi of X
Where X stands for all four components
If it's a scalar field
It means that everybody who measures it
No matter how they're moving relative to each other
No matter what their orientation of their axes
They will agree about the value of it
Now, anybody know some examples of four dimensional fields
Which are scalars?
You probably don't because they're not familiar
But nevertheless, do you know any?
Four dimensional fields
Fields in space-time, fundamental fields
Fundamental fields which happen to be
Electrostatic field?
No, electrostatic field is not a four vector
It has three components first of all
So it can't be a scalar
In fact, it can't even be a four vector
It's only got three components
The magnetic field
The Higgs field, the Higgs field, right
Is the first real fundamental scalar field
That occurs in physics
Why the Higgs field is so unfamiliar to you
Well, that's an experimental physics question
Why is the Higgs field the way it is?
It's an experimental physics question
Theoretical physics question
But the Higgs field is a scalar field
Simply means that it doesn't depend
Its value doesn't depend on how you're moving relative to it
Or how you're oriented relative to it
But the four velocity?
Well, yes, the magnitude
Good, the magnitude of any
Yeah, good
Take any four vector field
And take its magnitude
Good, that's one
Do you know any four vector field?
The four velocity?
No, no, four
I don't usually think of that as a field
By field I meant a thing like a gravitational field
Do you know any?
It took us a while to find a scalar
Somebody said Higgs
How about a four vector?
Well, the potential and the vector potential
Yeah
The electromagnetic field is built out of a four vector
Namely the components of the four dimensional vector potential
Alright
It's a little bit tricky
What its transformation properties are
But let's make it simple
The square of the
Not strictly, not the square
But the square in this sense
A mu, A mu
This could be the four vector potential
This combination then
Of the four vector potential with itself
The time component squared minus the space component squared
Would also be a scalar
How about energy and momentum?
No
Well, first of all energy and momentum are not fields
They are quantities that describe a whole system
Alright
But there are flows of energy
Energy density, momentum density, and that sort of thing
Energy density is not a four vector
Is not a scalar
It's a three dimensional scalar
It doesn't change when you rotate
But it does change when the system is moving relative to you
Alright
You take a system with a given energy
And now you look at it from a frame of reference
Where you're moving very fast
It has a lot more energy
So energy and momentum form a four vector
Not a scalar
So you've got things like the Hamiltonian
Is that it?
No, that's the energy
That's energy
Right
So it's a four, it's a component of a four vector
It's a four vector together with the momentum of a system
The energy and momentum of a system
Form a four vector
Well, we'll have to come back to that
We'll have to come back to that because it's important
But energy and momentum come together
Energy being the time component
Momentum being the space component
So it's not that there aren't that many around that are familiar
What about the gravitational field?
Gravitational field is not a scalar
It's not even a four vector
It's a tensor of some kind
We're going to come to tensors
It just means it has more indices
But we'll come to that later
So it's not so easy to find examples
Of relativistic scalars and four vectors and so forth
That you're familiar with
But the concept is easy
Just a field phi
Which no matter how you're oriented relative to it
No matter how you're moving relative to it
Always has the same value when measured
Okay?
That's called a scalar
Now you can differentiate scalars
You can differentiate them
You can take their partial derivatives
With respect to different directions
For example, you can take the partial derivative
Of phi with respect to time
Let's call that phi sub t
Well, that's not quite right
Phi, t
Ah, phi t
Just leave it phi t
Like that
That stands for the derivative of phi with respect to t
We could also indicate it by a dot on top
But I want to indicate it this way
The derivative of phi with respect to time
That's one component of something
That has some more components
The derivative of phi with respect to x
Let's just call that phi sub x
It's not the
I'm afraid I might confuse notation
This is not the t component of phi
It's the t component of a vector made out of the derivatives of phi
There are four such derivatives
Derivative of phi with respect to t
Derivative of phi with respect to x
Likewise z
And likewise y
I guess I missed
The four derivatives of phi
Can be grouped together and called
Partial of phi with respect to x mu
Notice we have a mu index now
Or with this simplified notation
I only introduced it to save myself from writing too many things
Just call it phi sub mu
The derivative of phi with respect to x mu
This is a complex of four objects
Which contain a time component
And four and three space components
It's pretty obvious
Well, at least it should be sort of psychologically obvious
That psychologically meaning to say
If I introduce it and I give it an index like that
It's pretty clear that it's some sort of four vector
Has four components, looks like a duck, acts like a duck
It's a four vector
It is a four vector
The only question is whether it should be thought of as a four vector
With an upper component or a lower component
Incidentally, the things with upper components and lower components
Transform slightly differently
There are some funny minus signs
When you transform the vectors with the lower index
In fact, if you take the Lorentz transformation
And every time you see a time component
Change the sign of it
You get the transformation properties of the object with the lower index
So lower index objects transform slightly different than upper index objects
They are different
And they differ only in the sign of the time component
Should we identify d phi by d x mu as a thing with an upper index or a lower index?
Okay
That's a question
That's an interesting question
The answer is with a lower index
Consistent with what I've written here
But how do we prove that?
How do we prove that d phi by d x mu is a four vector of the lower kind?
Incidentally, what's the name for things with upper indices and lower indices?
Anybody remember?
Covariant and contravariant
The ones with the upper indices are called contravariant?
Covariant
And the ones with the lower indices are called contravariant
Co is low
Covariant is low
Well then everybody had it backwards
I never remember
I can't remember
I just call them the upper guys and the lower guys
And
The derivatives have the same kind of coordinates?
I would have called them covariant
Yeah, I would call this covariant
But I may have it backward
And d x mu I would call contravariant
But I may, again, I may have it backward
I think I'm right
Yeah
Okay
Let's try to prove that d phi by d x mu is a covariant
Are the covariant components of a four vector
Now, here's what we need to do
We need to find out
What's the covariance of a four vector?
That's what we need to do
We
If we can find
Some known four vector
And we combine it together with the thing which we're testing
And what we get out is a scalar
Then we're assured that the thing that we're testing is a four vector
In particular, if we take a known thing which corresponds to a contravariant
Yeah
Contravariant four vector
And we combine it together with something which we suspect is a covariant four vector
And we always get a scalar
We always get the same thing out
Then we're assured that the thing with the lower index here really does transform in the right way
Alright
We have something
Yeah
You've kind of crossed a bunch of notation there
Say it again
Naive kind of question
Naive question, sorry
Yeah
The x has a mu upper
But the phi has a mu lower
This just means derivative with respect to x mu
It's trouble because x is x mu r
Oh, you're troubled because this one is upstairs and this one is downstairs
Yeah, yeah, I know
But the dx, the derivative with respect to dx is x mu r
The dx is down below the fraction bar, doesn't that convince you?
It shouldn't
The only thing that should convince you is a proper test
So let's do the proper test
I think the image that I heard is supposed to work is that the tangent co-varies with the surface
Yeah
And that's why you have the derivatives as protons
I don't get it, but let's do the test
The test is to find some known covariant four vector with an upper index
Multiply it together with this thing, sum over mu
And check whether the result is the same in every reference frame
Anybody got a suggestion for a known, yeah, here's the test
Take two points, two neighboring points
Phi is of course a field, it varies from point to point
Alright
It varies from point to point
But it's important to realize that the sum of scalars is another scalar
The difference of scalars is a scalar
Alright, so let's take these two points
Which are separated by a small distance dx mu
dx mu is the distance between the two points, right?
At the end of the seriousrick the square penalty
And d slope , at the end of the seriousrick
This is the revolution of the vector
Much soon it will be new
But what we're going to do is
According to actually the mathematician
Here we have d and h
Out of the three, all the composition is out of the four
So d mode or the incoming comunque
dx
and sum over mu
what anybody know what this quantity is?
it's partial derivative of phi with respect to t times dt plus partial
derivative of phi with respect to x dx plus partial derivative of phi with respect to y dy
it's just the difference of phi at the two endpoints
let's call this endpoint two let's call this endpoint one
you could call it just d phi
it's the difference
of phi
phi at two
minus phi at one
it's the change in phi when you move in one direction times the change in x
et cetera et cetera
it just gives you the small change in phi when you move from one point to
another
phi is a scalar
differences of scalars are scalars
so the right hand side
is a scalar
the left hand side
is the product of a known
contravariant vector
with something that we're testing
we've successfully tested
that d phi by d x mu is a four vector
of the covariant kind
of the kind with the lower index
that's because it does not change
the z is two points
equal to zero
right
so now we found some more
interesting objects
derivatives of fields
we have covariant, sorry, contravariant vectors d x mu
we have covariant vectors d phi by d x mu
and then we have the derivative of phi by d x mu
we can turn a contravariant vector
into a covariant vector
by changing the sign of its time component
so
we can invent
the covariant version
of a particular contravariant vector
in like manner
this of course is
phi sub mu
in like manner
but we can invent a contravariant version
of this derivative here
how?
just by changing the sign of the time component
in which case it becomes
phi super mu
with a superscript
the only difference is
both of these phi's
are made up out of derivatives of phi
with respect to time and space
but
the time component of this
is minus the derivative of phi
with respect to time
so this complex here
stands for d phi by d t
d phi by d x
and the others
this one stands for
minus d phi by d t
and d phi by d x
what happens
if we take
we multiply this one by this one
in other words
what happens if we take phi with a super mu
and multiply it by phi with a sub mu
and sum over mu
what does that give?
well
it gives us
derivative of phi with respect to t squared
with a minus sign
and then plus signs
the square of d phi by d x
and the square of d phi by d y
and the square of d phi by d z
is that an invariant?
yes
it's an invariant because
it's composed out of an upper
index and a lower index
and that's our rule
so for example
we've now discovered
a new scalar
the new scalar
is minus d phi by d t
squared
plus d phi by d x
plus d phi by d y squared
plus d phi by d z squared
any observer
in any inertial reference frame
any Lorentz frame
who measures
in his own reference frame
the components
of the derivatives of phi
with respect to time
with respect to space
and combine
those derivatives will not agree
in different frames of reference
they're components of a vector
but
if we take the combination
minus d phi by d t squared
plus d phi by d x squared
d phi by d y squared
d phi by d z squared
that quantity
is the same in every reference frame
and is a scalar
so we have a scalar
and
in
we'll come back
to the
waves
moving on a string
but in light of
what we've learned up till now
alright, so
let me write down on the blackboard
the scalar that we've discovered
take a scalar and begin with a scalar
and construct it
the components of its derivatives
in other words
we could call it its gradient
the four vector
d phi by d x mu
so many ways to write it
alright, we could write it this way
we could write it
this way
they all mean the same thing
and we could write it
just phi mu
all mean the same thing
ok
we can also
construct a contravariant version of this
as was pointed out by somebody here
strictly speaking
when you construct a contravariant
vector you're talking about a thing in a different space
the dual space
but let's not worry about that
that's a fine point of mathematics
which is important and interesting
but we don't need to
be so technical at this point
you just change the sign of the time component
and
I'm not going to try to
write this one
we could write
d super mu phi
let me just lower the mu
yeah I could put it down here couldn't I
a lower thing in the denominator means an upper thing
d super mu phi
or phi super mu
all mean the same thing
these two sets of objects are the same objects
with the time component having the opposite sign
and then we discovered
that
the combination
d mu phi
is also a scalar
in fact what is it
it's d t phi
squared
minus d x phi squared
minus d y phi squared
alright I'll write it
I never really understood
why neat notations were invented
until I started teaching
you get really sick of writing things like this
here it is
d sub mu d super mu
oh thank you
minus signs the other way
incidentally
the scalars no matter which way
either way
they're a scalar
but with a minus sign here
it corresponds to the definitions
that I've already used
you could just use i's for the other one
i
for the spacing
you could use i for the spacing
and mu for the fourth
oh you could yeah
yeah yeah
right
or 0 for the fourth index
and i for the
yeah
now do keep in mind
I've left out some speeds of light
I've set the speed of light equal to 1
there are a few things
there are some places
you can restore the speeds of light
just by dimensional analysis
I won't do it here and now
ok let's come back
to the problem
that we addressed last time
of a string
vibrating
in the plane perpendicular
to the orientation
of the length of the violin
we defined the vertical coordinate
of the string
by calling it phi
string is vibrating
the vertical coordinate of any point
remember the string was made up
of a bunch of points
we took a limit in which the points
became denser and denser
and basically phi sub i
which was the height
i does not stand for a direction of space
it stands for the i-th particle
along the chain
phi being the vertical direction
x being the horizontal direction
phi morphed into a field
which just became phi of x
phi of x was the displacement
in the vertical direction of the field
incidentally
we will
I hope to do it today
I don't think I'll get to it
I was going to study
strings which vibrate both vertically
and horizontally
there's an interesting point there
but
we could also do strings which vibrate
along their own direction
but I'm not going to do that tonight
alright so this phi sub i
meaning the phi coordinate
of the i-th particle
became phi of x
we also wrote down
an action principle
let me just remind you quickly
what that action principle was
it contained in a discrete form
before we took the length of the violin
before we took the limit
it contained kinetic terms and potential terms
the kinetic terms
now I'm going to use sum
because I'm not summing over indices
I'm summing over particles
sum over all the particles
phi i dot squared over 2
and then there was a mass for each particle
which I took to be epsilon
or proportional to epsilon
epsilon was the
x
which is the separation
between neighboring points on the string
or neighboring sites
and then there was another term
this was the Lagrangian I'm writing down
this was the kinetic energy
and then minus the potential energy
and the potential energy had a spring constant
which was one over epsilon
I think I put a c squared there
later on we're going to set c to one again
and then
I think it was phi i minus phi i plus one squared
okay everybody remember that?
anybody? oh it is a two
alright spring constant went like one over epsilon
mass went like epsilon
and we played with it
we worked out the equations of motion
took the continuum limit
the continuum limit is the limit
in which epsilon is equal to c
and epsilon shrinks to zero
and in which we replace the discrete variable
phi i by phi of x
and
let me remind you in particular
what happened to the Lagrangian
oh there was the Lagrangian and there was the action
here's the Lagrangian
and the action
is the integral dt
from some initial starting point
to some end point
of the Lagrangian itself
well when we talk about the Lagrangian itself
we took the limit in which we let the epsilon
shrink to zero something nice happened
let's recall what it was
we did it two ways
one way we did it
was to write the equation of motion itself
and then take the limit in the equation of motion
what we got was the wave equation
let me write down the wave equation
it was
d second phi
by dt squared
that of course is just the acceleration
of a point on the string
the vertical acceleration
the second derivative with respect to time
and that was equal
is it
c squared
let's just write it minus
second derivative of phi with respect to x squared
that was not exactly what we had
what we had was
let me remind you
well we had some discrete form of the second derivative
I'm not going to repeat it
go back to your notes
we worked out the equation of motion
and then took the limit that epsilon went to zero
replacing differences by derivatives
there was a difference of a difference
which became a second derivative
everybody remember that?
good
alright
ok
now we could have done the same operation
by figuring out what happens to the Lagrangian
in the same limit
and we did so
we actually did so
we found out that this term here
first of all the sum became an integral
dx
the phi dot squared
well that's just the derivative of phi
with respect to t squared
the fact that one half of phi
is equal to t squared
the other half is still there
and then minus
I'm going to set c equal to one
now
c in the original problem
had nothing to do with the speed of light
it had to do with the speed of propagation
up and down a violin string
of course secretly we all knew
that eventually I was going to say
it was the speed of light
not because violin strings
move with the speed of light
but because this was just a model
of the relativistic field
alright so let's set c equal to one
and this term became
minus d phi by
dx squared
integral dx
that
is the Lagrangian
but it's not the action
the action is you take
the Lagrangian and integrate it
over time
the Lagrangian itself
is an integral over space
what it's doing is it's adding
up all the points along the string
that's what this x integration
is doing here
adding up all the points
let me move the x to the back here
alright so the x integration
adds up all the points along the string
it's a stand in for the sum over i
but the integral over space
is a stand in for the sum over i
so d t that converts the Lagrangian
into an action
the thing which goes into the
principle of least action
all we have to do is write d t here
did I hear a question?
no question
he wants another integral sign I guess
no no no
one integral sign is enough
alright so this is the Lagrangian
the number of integrations
is told to you by how many d's
you have
ok you really want me to write another integral?
no
so it's an integral over space
and time
in the problem that we set up
space extended over
some finite interval
from the peg to the bridge
so space
with some finite interval
and
in the principle of least action
we also introduce
an interval in time
the time from the start
to the end of the process
we introduce initial conditions at the beginning
final conditions at the end
and we ask what is
the history of the system
which interpolates
between the initial state and the final state
and which minimizes
the action so there's also an initial
time and a final time
and the action
becomes an integral
of a certain quantity
which involves the field and its derivatives
integrated over this region
this is not supposed to represent the string
it's just supposed to
color in the region where you
do the integral
well by now of course
you've made the connection
that at least for this one dimensional problem
what goes here
is exactly the scalar
of course
that's only true if we take
c to be the speed of light
but
this has
exactly the same form
as the scalar
I've eliminated two dimensions
y and z don't play any role
in all of this
we're only talking about motion of waves
up and down a particular axis now
and it's no accident
it's not an accident
that the Lagrangian here
takes this form
of a quantity
which appears to be Lorentz invariant
which appears to be a scalar
what this tells us
well what do you think it tells us
about the equations
which follow from this Lagrangian
here's a principle
the principle is
minimalization
of the equation
minimize the action
with the action being
defined by this integral
over space and time
of a certain scalar
equations of motion
would be Lorentz invariant
are Lorentz invariant
right
that's right
if you start with a scalar for the Lagrangian
the Lagrangian
ok let's get some terminology right now
script L
by the time we went this far
well script L is the Lagrangian
let's call it capital L
but
capital L itself
is an integral
over space
the Lagrangian is an integral over space
let's get all of the things down
let me write them down in one place over here
ah
the Lagrangian
began as a sum
over i
morphed into an integral dx
the thing that went into the integral
the integrand
I can call script L
what is it composed out of
it's composed out of
the derivatives
it's a function of
of phi
with respect to the various coordinates
it could also involve phi
I mean this is not the most general thing we can write down
this is what we got
by hooking up the two
by hooking springs together with
violin strings
this is called the Lagrange density
it's called the Lagrange density
because you integrate it over space
to find the full Lagrangian
but then you go to the action
the action
is the integral of L
over time
and that becomes
the integral over x
and t
of the same quantity
of the same Lagrange density
so you can almost think
that the Lagrange density
is a kind of action density
in fact that's what it is
it's the action per unit space time volume
per dx dt
that's what this Lagrange density is
you can think of it
as a thing that you integrate over space
to find the Lagrangian
and so it's the Lagrange density
but it's also the thing
that you integrate
over space and time
and so it's the Lagrange density
over time
to find the action
so it can properly be called
the action density
but the action density in space time
not the action density in space
alright now
does that mean it's a scalar?
the Lagrange density
is a scalar
well let's put it this way
if the Lagrange density is a scalar
then the equations
are invariant under Lorentz transformation
alright
that's the criteria for an action
which will give Lorentz invariant equations
that the action itself
be invariant and that entails
the integrand being a scalar
so if the integrand is a scalar
the equations of a theory
will be Lorentz invariant
I've left out some details
even some
more details
but I'm going to
give you some logically important details
but I think we've captured the essence
of the idea of invariance
and how you build
invariant laws of nature
from invariant action principles
let's go a little bit
farther
supposing we actually wanted
to construct a field
that vibrated around
not along an axis
along a violin string
but that moved throughout
all of space and time
x, y, z, and t
the strategy is quite clear
all we have to do
in order to find the Lorentz invariant description
in four dimensional space
this is in two dimensional space
one time in one space
all we have to do is fill out
the rest of this expression
and write
the action
equals one half
and the integral now
this becomes a four dimensional integral
not a two dimensional integral
a four dimensional integral
I could write the x, dy, dz, dt
but I can also just write
d4x
that's the standard symbol
for integrating the x, dy, dz, dt
d4x
and it means an integral
over volume elements
in space time
not in space, but in space time
and then
d mu phi
now
I have something wrong here
what I have wrong here
is that the kinetic energy
comes in with a plus sign
here I've written it in such a way
that it has a minus sign
so normally you would put a minus there
with the minus there
it's just equal to
integral
let's call it phi t squared
minus phi x squared
minus phi y squared
minus phi z squared
where you know what I mean by phi sub t
and phi sub x, y, and z
just the derivatives
this is a scalar
the action itself is invariant
the same in every reference frame
and therefore
the problem that you set up
when you say let me find what minimizes
the action doesn't really depend on
the frame of reference
now let's talk about
let's see how much more time do we have
we have a little more time
you know I think I'm going to stop here
I think we've done enough for tonight
and take some questions
what I wanted to talk about
was given a Lagrange density
given
a script as
a cell
how do you generate the equations of motion
in a simple way
the overall strategy
is clear
minimize the action
but how do you convert that to differential equations
how do you convert that to wave equations
and we'll talk about that
next time but I'll just remind you very quickly
that the same question
occurs when thinking about particle mechanics
we had an action which depended
on the trajectory
of a particle
we wanted to minimize that action
that sounds like a global
problem that involves the whole
trajectory but we converted
it to a differential equation
which only involved the first and second
derivatives of the motion
and we did it by focusing on a little piece
over here and saying
if we've actually minimized the action
then we must have also minimized
the action between these two points
if everything else is kept fixed
and so we just take these two points
and we explore around
what trajectory between these two
points minimizes the action between
the neighboring points and that's
what gave us a local
differential equation
we could either concentrate on the global
issue or we could concentrate on it locally
minimize the
action between two nearby points
and that gives the local differential
equations we're going to do exactly
the same thing next time I'll probably
just write down the answer but
let me tell you what the strategy is
we have some space time region
and we want to minimize
the action
we want to know what field
configuration in other words
what history of the field
what does a history mean
in the case of the violin string
it means a history of all the points
on the string an entire motion
of the string from beginning to end
in the case of a general field
it means the entire motion
of that field and in the case of a
field in space and time
what motion of the field in space and time
minimizes
the action
we could try to solve
that by exploring all
possible functions that can fit in this
space time box but we could also do it another
way we could say supposing
we know the value of the field
on some little boundary here
if we know the
value of the field if somebody told
us that the solution of the problem
involves the field having a certain
value on a little region
on the boundary of a little region
and asked us to figure out what it was
doing inside we would
say all we have to do is minimize
the action in that little region
there subject
to the constraint that it has some
fixed value on the boundary
that gives us differential equations
in the same way that focusing
on a little piece of the trajectory
took us from
the action principle basically
to F equals M A
doing the same thing
taking a little region
and requiring that the action
be minimal within that little region
takes us from this grand action
principle to
the local differential
wave equations where are we
did we I think we erased
the wave equation
in fact I don't even think we ever wrote it down
well I'll
write it down next time
well actually you abbreviated it pretty much like that
well here's the action
well
let me remind you
what the wave equation was
I think I did write it down
yeah it was second
derivative of phi with respect to
t squared minus
second derivative of phi with respect to
x squared is equal to zero
so
we either could think of that as the
equation coming from this discrete
problem of a bunch of points connected by
springs or we
can think about it in a more
space timey kind of way
and say it's the equation that comes
by minimizing the action over
some tiny little patch of space time
given that
we had already figured out what was going on
on the boundary of that region
and that defines for us the
wave equation so it's back and forth
between grand global
principles
which have the advantage
that they tell us
manifestly that the theory doesn't depend
on the particular Lorentz frame
on the one hand and going back and forth
to differential equations which of course
in general easier to
uh
they're the things you want to write down
and solve
using differential
equation theory
okay I think we're about finished for tonight
and next time we'll get into the business
of actually writing down field
equations and solving them
from various action principles
like this
isn't the wave equation that you wrote
down just Lagrangian density
no
no no no no
these are second derivatives
these are squares of first derivatives
right
that was a perfect question to ask
because I meant to say it and I forgot
incidentally can you think of something
else we might add into this Lagrangian
here that would still keep it invariant
yeah any constant
well any constant of course
any velocity
we want
what's in here to be a scalar
phi is a scalar
we could add phi in
we could add phi squared
phi cube
phi fourth
function of phi
any function of phi we could add in there
and we will do so
okay
yeah
underneath there
the board
the last expression you wrote there
the integral
should be also d4
x
after that
good
okay d4 x
of course is just another convenient notation
that saves me
writing dt dx dy dz
that has its own transformation property
I guess
d4 x dx dy dz
that's a good point
the question is how does the differential quantity itself transform
and the answer is it's a scalar
right
the answer is that d4 x is itself a scalar
alright
we'll come back to that
that's an important point
when I said before I left out a little piece of logic
it had to do with that
it's a volume element
it's not completely obvious that that
is an invariant
but it is
the model starts out with
with the
the two constants
the string constants and the mass
for a unit string
it ends up with just one constant
c
do you ever get to break
c into two parts
yeah okay so
let's put back
the constants
of the
I always want there to be an
epsilon here and an epsilon here
because if those epsilons aren't there
then it doesn't scale correctly
when you take the limit but we could put in
another constant mu here
and we have a
constant there already so I don't need another constant
so in principle there could be
two constants there right
who has the question
I just wanted to know are they separately measurable
yeah they're separately
measurable if we know exactly
what phi means if we really know
that phi meant
height of this thing in
meters then we
could measure it yes but
we can always take phi
and absorb sorry mu
and absorb it into phi
we could take
we could invent a new variable instead of
phi
let's call it I don't know
what's another Greek letter
alpha no
I don't like alpha
nobody ever uses alpha
for fields chi
chi good chi
chi
and let chi equal
the square root of mu
times phi
alright
all I've done is taken the square root of mu
and grouped it with phi
with phi here
then did I write what I wanted
to write
yeah then chi
chi squared first of all is mu
times phi squared
and the same is true of
derivatives chi dot
squared
is mu times phi dot squared
right
it's also true
that I would have to manipulate
this over here
but by the time I'm finished
I could eliminate the constant out of here
by redefining the
field with the square root of mu there
alright
so I can redefine phi
and it'll be at the cost of changing
the constant over here
ok
when I write
let's write it this way
when I write that phi is equal to chi
over the square root of mu
and I do it everywhere
I do it here, I do it here
it'll eliminate the mu out of here
but it'll show up again over here
ok
it'll show up in the denominator over here
but then I can just combine it with c
and say it was just a change
of the c that was here
so really there's only one constant
that really enters into the propagation
of waves
and what it comes down to is the speed of propagation
that's all that's really left
over in the end after you
make use of all the freedom that you have
in changing units
it's basically a change of unit
of the phi axis
so that's the
answer to that question
there's only one... what?
instead of a propagation speed?
well it's
the propagation speed
along a string
is composed out of two things
it's composed out of the mass density
and the tension in the string
alright, and those
basically these are these two constants
but they can be combined together
into a single variable
what's that?
can you think of them as being the other way around
you can roll
your
speed
of propagation kind of into the mass
of the system
yeah
but you can always
rewrite by changing
the units of phi you can always
rewrite it so that there's only one
constant and it's over here
you could also rewrite it so the constant over here
was one and the constant shows up over here
but you have
one constant that physically
corresponds to the speed of propagation
and that's all
you can do with the wave equation
for this here
if you have another term
for example, phi squared
there could be a numerical coefficient
in front of that
and that would be new stuff
that would be a new constant
yeah
many semesters ago
in terms
when you started describing
string theory
you started with the same model
of little springs and
there's only so many different things in physics
that you can solve
is there any significance that you started with the same model
yeah it's the only thing
I know
well
is there a significance
not direct
right
um
ok good
if there aren't any other questions
let's uh
we're going to go home and we're all going to make up
physics questions
and put them on the
on the blog
music