This program is brought to you by Stanford University.
Please visit us at stanford.edu.
Let's talk about conservation of charge a little bit.
The most naive version is that
the amount of charge in the world,
whatever the world means,
doesn't change.
It just stays the same.
That's the most naive version of it.
Now,
if that were all there were to it,
then it really wouldn't say very much.
If a charge disappeared over
here and reappeared on Alpha Centauri
at exactly the same instant of time,
exactly,
of course,
we have to worry about relativity
and the fact that it's going
to be a very long time.
The same instant of time
may be a little bit confusing,
but let's get a little pre-relativistic.
If a charge disappeared over here
and reappeared on Alpha Centauri instantaneously,
we would say charge is conserved by that definition.
That total charge doesn't change.
But we aren't on Alpha Centauri.
It's too far away for
us to know what's happening there.
And so in that sense,
if that's all there was,
then we're going to be able
to do a lot of things.
But if that was the case,
if we were to go to charge conservation,
it wouldn't tell us anything.
It wouldn't tell us anything at all.
Okay,
if we could get to Alpha
Centauri and check the charges there,
we could go to Beta Centauri,
or Gamma Centauri,
or the next galaxy over,
or whatever,
and we would have exactly the same problem,
that within our laboratory,
charge conservation wouldn't mean anything.
We'd have no way of checking it.
Now,
what is the way that we check it?
Can charge disappear from the laboratory?
Yes,
charge can disappear from the laboratory.
It can reappear outside the laboratory.
But in order to do so,
it has to pass through the walls of the laboratory.
And so some detector set up at the walls
of the laboratory to monitor the flow of charge.
What do detectors do?
They would ring bells or detect.
That's what detectors do.
They detect.
They would detect,
ring bells,
and we would know that charge
passed from the inside to the outside.
That idea that conservation means more than just the
algebraic sum of the charges in the world doesn't change.
But it means that there's a concept
that when charge does disappear from a place,
it identifiably moves through the walls of the system,
through the boundaries of the system,
that gets quantified in the
idea of local charge conservation,
or the idea of a
current as well as a charge.
A current is a flow of charge.
So another way to say it
is if charge disappears from this room,
it's because a current flowed through
somehow the boundaries of the room.
That's the only way it can happen,
and a current flowing through the boundaries of the
room is detectable at the walls of the room.
So let's see if we can quantify that,
not just quantify it,
formalize it,
turn it into a mathematical statement of some sort,
and then check with our little
theory that we made up about charge,
that,
well,
we'll go back to it,
whether it satisfies that criterion.
All right,
first of all,
there's the concept of charge.
Yes?
Is this particularly different than
a similar statement about mass?
No,
it is not particularly different than statements about mass.
Now,
the difference is that,
I'll tell you what the difference is.
Mass by itself in a relativistic theory doesn't really,
is not a conserved quantity.
Energy is the corresponding conserved quantity.
All right,
energy,
and it comes along with another conserved quantity,
or three other conserved quantities,
which are called momentum,
and they form a complex.
But each one of them is separately conserved,
and each one of them has a flow.
Now,
in fact,
the momentum is the flow of energy.
But what's the flow of momentum?
And that's something else called stress.
Now,
whether we'll get to the stress,
it's called stress,
not the kind of stress that you feel
when you know you've lied to your wife,
but then she's going to catch you,
but the kind of stress that a material
object experiences when a force is imposed on it.
Did I say something about momentum?
Of you having lied and...
No,
no,
I didn't mean that.
What?
This is 2000,
you can't see that.
This is two...
2008,
you can't do that?
The 1960s.
I stopped doing it in the 1960s,
that's right.
I stopped doing almost everything interesting in the...
Yeah,
so where were we?
We were talking about charge flow,
and the first concept is charge density.
Now,
density is not the motion of charge,
it's just a local version of the
idea of how much charge is there.
Local means it's identified with a small region of space.
There's the idea of charge density.
Charge density is just locally,
at some particular location,
the charge per unit volume that's present.
Now,
to define it precisely,
we do a little bit of calculus
and a little bit of limiting notions.
We take a little box around the surrounding point.
We take the total charge in that box.
Let's say the box is of size epsilon.
It has a volume,
epsilon cubed.
We take the charge inside that box.
Let's call it...
What's a good name for charge?
Q.
Q is the standard terminology for electric charge.
Q inside the box.
This is not Q of the world.
This is Q of the box.
We divide it by the volume of the box.
And then we take the limit in which both...
in which epsilon goes to zero,
and of course also Q goes to zero.
We take the limit of Q over epsilon
as the box gets smaller and smaller,
and that's called rho.
Rho for density.
I don't know why it's called rho
and not D or delta or something else,
but it's rho for density,
and it depends on position.
Of course,
it also depends on time.
The density of charge can change with time.
So whatever rho is,
it depends on position and time.
Okay.
What do we do with rho?
Well,
if we know rho,
we can say how much charge
is in any region of space.
In any region of space,
let's take an arbitrary region of space now,
with any shape,
whatever,
then the amount of charge in there,
let's also call it Q,
but it doesn't stand for
the charge in a box now,
it stands for the charge in a general region,
is then equal to the integral over that region,
let's call it D3x,
meaning Dx,
Dy,
Dz,
over that region,
over the interior of that region of rho.
And strictly speaking,
we could take this to
be the definition of charge density.
It's the thing that you sum up
or integrate over a region of space
to find out how much charge is in there.
The total charge in the universe,
you integrate over everything in the world,
all of volume,
and that gives you the total charge in the universe,
but usually that's a fairly useless concept,
the total charge in the universe.
Better integrate over the region of the laboratory,
and that will tell you how
much charge is in your laboratory.
Now,
next concept,
the flow of charge.
The flow of charge is defined
by a thing called the current.
You're used to thinking
about currents flowing through wires.
We don't have to be
thinking about currents flowing through wires,
we're thinking about charges flowing through space,
clouds of charge flowing through space.
And to quantify the idea of a current,
we take a little area,
now this is an area in space,
a little square,
and we stand there and watch that square,
and watch the charge passing through that little square.
It's a little window,
think of it as a window,
small window,
and charges go from one side
of the window through the window
out to the other side of the window.
And we can ask how much charge
goes through the window per unit time.
We can wait one second and see
how much charge goes through the window,
count,
take that charge,
and divide it by the one second.
But we can also do calculus,
and we can go to the
limit of a very small time interval.
I think that's the last time I will say that,
that we'll take limits.
Just imagine,
you know how to take limits.
We study the amount of charge that
goes through the window per unit time.
Now that's not yet the current.
The amount of charge that will go through that window
will not only be proportional to the time element,
the little time that you allow,
but it will also be proportional to something else.
What is it?
The area of the window.
The bigger the area of the window,
the more charge will go through.
So if we take the
charge that goes through the window,
again,
let's call it q,
and divide it by the area of the window,
let's call it a,
and the little time interval,
what should we call it,
delta t?
The little time interval,
and then take the limit as the window gets small,
and as the time interval gets small,
then we call that object
the local current at that point,
the point at the center of the window there.
But it's a particular component of the current.
The current is not a scalar,
under rotations,
with respect to rotations of space,
not with respect to,
not with respect to spacetime,
but with respect to rotations of space,
the charge is a scalar.
The amount of charge in a little region
doesn't matter which orientation you draw.
But the flow of charge is more like wind velocity.
It has a direction associated with it.
So for example,
if the charge happened to
be flowing along the x-axis here,
and we took our window
to be in the y-z plane,
to be in the window along the blackboard here,
no charge would go through that window.
It's like a wind blowing,
here's a window,
and the wind is blowing in this direction,
no wind goes through the window,
but if you turn the window
so that it's facing into the wind,
then the wind goes through the window.
Charge current,
current is a vector,
a three-dimensional vector.
A vector in the sense of three-dimensional space.
And if we orient our window
so that the perpendicular to it,
let's draw the perpendicular to it,
draw a perpendicular,
let's say the perpendicular then is along the x-axis,
then the amount of charge going through,
we'll call this an x-window,
an x-oriented window,
and remember the x-axis is perpendicular to the window,
and we take the charge through the x-oriented window,
per unit area,
per unit time,
that becomes the x-component of the charge current.
So that's called J,
that's called J,
again,
J for current,
I don't know why J is used.
Is that usually called current density?
Sometimes called current density.
Yeah,
yeah,
sometimes called,
right.
Okay,
so in elementary physics,
the current is the current through the wire.
In advanced physics,
it becomes the current density,
and in super advanced physics,
we forget the word density and
we just call it the current again.
Right,
yeah,
right.
Right.
So,
in fact,
we will even come to a terminology
where we will call the
complex of J together with rho,
we'll just call that the current eventually,
but for the moment,
yeah,
this is,
we would just call this the x-component of current,
and once you hear component,
once you hear that it's a component,
you know it's a vector,
and that's a clue that it's the current density,
that's the current density,
Jx.
Incidentally,
the symbol for the current through a wire is I,
not J.
Okay,
so J is the current density,
and again,
it's a thing that you integrate,
you integrate it over time
and over the little area of the window
to find out how much total
charge flows through at a given time.
I call it small j.
It depends,
it depends.
Sometimes in some books it's capital I,
in some books it's small i,
I've seen both.
Okay,
so that's Jx,
and of course there's Jy and Jz.
What is Jy and Jz?
You take your window oriented along the y-axis,
and you ask,
notice incidentally,
that there's a sense of orientation to this window.
We're talking about the charge that flows
from the left to the right.
In other words,
the charge that flows along the positive x-axis,
from the negative to the positive x-axis.
In the same way we can define Jy and Jz,
Jy would correspond to a window oriented along the y-axis,
and we would be talking about
the amount of charge per unit time
that flows from the negative
y to the positive y regions,
and likewise Jz.
All right,
now what I maintain is that any time current disappears
out of the room,
there will be on the boundary of the room,
what did I say,
when current disappears,
charge disappears.
If charge disappears out of the room,
there will be a current on the boundary.
And the current on the boundary will exactly compensate,
the amount of charge that flows through the boundaries
of the room,
will exactly compensate for the
amount that the charge changes
within the room.
Let's see if we can quantify that
and make an equation out of it.
Let's take a little box.
It has six faces.
It's a little cube.
It has six faces,
and let's take this to be the x-axis over here.
Now let's take a small amount of time,
delta t,
and how much charge,
I think we should probably give this a size,
epsilon,
epsilon in every direction,
how much charge flows into the
box through face number one over here.
Here's face number one.
How much charge flows into the box
in a small interval of time delta t?
Flows into the box through face number one.
Okay.
And the answer is going to be
jx
at this point,
let's call this point number one over here.
It's also face number one.
jx at the center of face number one
times the area,
epsilon squared,
times the amount of time delta t.
All right,
that's how much charge flows into the box
per unit time,
per unit area from the left.
Now,
let's,
through the x face.
Now there's another x face over here.
Charge may be flowing out through there.
So how much charge flows out through here?
It's the same if it's smaller.
It's exactly the same expression.
Let's call this face number two.
And let's call the center point also point two.
What will it be?
Notice that if j is positive,
if j is positive,
that means charge is flowing into the box.
It's flowing this way.
If j is positive over here,
it means charge is flowing out of the box.
So we should subtract
jx at point two.
I hear the right answer.
Times the same factor.
Same area,
same time interval.
So the answer is,
let's write the answer,
jx at one minus jx at two.
That's the change in charge inside the box.
But wait a minute,
that's not all of it.
That's only the stuff that flew in
through the x windows.
What about the y windows?
Well,
same kind of thing.
Y window down here can admit charge
if the current is positive.
If the y component of the current is positive,
charge will flow into the box from the bottom,
and it will flow out
of the box from the top.
And so there's another term.
Let's call,
let's see,
let's call the bottom face here three,
and the top face four,
IV,
four.
And also the centers we'll
call point three and point four.
Okay.
The area of the bottom
and top faces are the same.
The unit of time is the same.
And so what are we going to get?
We're going to get jy of three
minus jy of four.
That's the charge flowing in from three
and out from four.
And then there's a last one.
The one flowing in,
well,
I'm not sure which way the z-axis goes.
The z-axis comes out of the blackboard?
Yeah,
I think so.
All right,
so we add this.
This is the stuff that flows in the x direction.
This is the stuff that flows in the y direction.
And finally,
the last term is,
let's put it over here,
plus,
oh,
yeah.
Delta t times epsilon multiplies everything.
The last term you can guess,
it's going to be jz.
Now,
we have to name the,
well,
it's jz.
It's again the difference of jc,
let's call it at five minus jz at six.
What is that?
That's the change in charge,
that's the amount of charge that flowed into the box.
Now,
imagine the box is small.
We're going to imagine the box is small.
Epsilon is going to be small in a minute.
What is that equal to?
Well,
as I said,
that's equal to the increase in charge.
That's equal to the increase in charge.
So that must,
in fact,
if we divide it by delta t,
it's the time rate of
change of charge in the box.
The time rate of change in the box.
Of charge in the box.
So that's d by dt
of the charge in the box,
q,
equal to time rate of change
of the charge inside the box.
The stuff that flew in
minus the stuff that flew out
gives us the rate of change
of the charge in the box.
Okay,
now,
this j of 1 minus j of 2,
the distance between 1 and 2
is going to be shrunk to 0.
We're going to take this little
box and make it smaller and smaller.
The difference between j at point
1 and j at point 2
is just going to turn into some kind of derivative.
Just a derivative of j between two neighboring points.
The difference between a quantity at two neighboring points
is going to be a
derivative of j at point 2.
what is it?
Let's write an equation over here.
j of 1 minus jx of 2.
That's equal to the derivative of jx
with respect to x.
Not quite,
there's a minus sign here.
It's j of 1.
1 is slightly to the left of 2.
j of 1 minus j of 2
would be the derivative of j with respect to x,
but of course we'd want to divide that by epsilon
to make a real derivative out of it.
Okay?
We're going to get epsilon cubed.
Yeah,
we're going to get epsilon cubed.
That's right.
So,
right,
that's right.
So,
this really can be reinterpreted as,
let's just reinterpret it over here,
epsilon squared.
Now,
I'm going to want to put an epsilon downstairs.
So,
let's put an epsilon downstairs,
and just as Michael said,
if we put an epsilon downstairs,
we've got to compensate by an epsilon upstairs.
Well,
that's kind of neat.
This is the volume,
epsilon cubed.
That's going to play a nice role.
Keep in mind,
the volume over here,
and then some derivatives of j.
What's it going to be?
It's going to be epsilon cubed
in three terms.
The derivative of jx with respect to x
plus the derivative of jy with respect to y
plus the derivative of jz with respect to z,
and I think I have an overall minus sign.
Uh...
What is that?
That's the time rate of change,
dq,
by dq,
by dt.
Now,
let's divide by epsilon cubed.
If we divide this by epsilon cubed,
let's divide it by epsilon cubed,
q over epsilon cubed.
q is the charge in the box.
Epsilon is the volume...
Epsilon cubed is the volume of the box.
What is q over epsilon?
q over epsilon cubed?
The charge density,
right?
So...
And this derivative,
of course,
means standing at the same point.
We stay in the same box.
We're not moving around as we're doing this.
So that really means the partial derivative
of the density with respect to time.
Partial derivative because we're
keeping the positions fixed.
So the right-hand side just becomes the partial derivative
with respect to time of the charge density.
So,
yeah,
minus sign is correct.
If I transfer what's in the
bracket over to the right-hand side,
or put everything on the same side,
then I get an equation.
It's called the continuity equation.
And what it says is the time rate of change
of density
plus the divergence of the current.
For those who know what a divergence is,
this is the divergence of the current.
I'll write it out explicitly.
dx,
jx...
Let's call it d by dx.
I said I would write it explicitly,
and I will.
Plus dy,
jy...
No,
explicitly.
It's sometimes written just like that.
Plus j...
Just a second.
Plus dz,
jz equals zero.
Say it again.
Sometimes that's just written just dj,
d,
the divergence of j.
Yeah,
yeah,
del dot j.
Without any subscripts on the current.
Del dot j.
Yeah,
del dot j.
Right.
Well,
we think of this as...
Right.
It's just a component of .
So we have...
We could write this as...
We could also write it as just a row dot,
if I wanted to save myself some symbols.
Plus del dot j is equal to zero.
What does that express?
That expresses the fact that the only
way that the charge can change in there
is by charge flowing into or out of the system.
It doesn't change by itself.
In other words,
if there's no current through the walls,
the charge doesn't change in here.
It relates the change in charge
to the flow through the boundary.
That's the deep concept of conservation.
Deep and useful concept of conservation that the time...
Oh,
and we can...
Let's see.
Why don't I put everything on the same side?
If I brought all of this to the right-hand side,
it would all be pluses,
right?
So I think we can do that efficiently
by just putting d rho by dt over here
and adding plus over here.
We're getting rid of brackets and
setting the right-hand side equal to zero.
Now,
this has an interesting look to it.
Let me write this in a rather...
No,
no minus sign in this equation.
The minus sign got eaten up by transposing...
Well,
when I was doing this,
when I transposed the d
rho dt to the left-hand side,
it picked up a minus,
and then I multiplied the whole equation by minus.
Okay.
Let's make up a new notation.
What's that?
J sub t?
Yeah.
Well,
except that we're going to change it a little bit.
We're going to call rho j super t.
Not sub t.
Or remember that sometimes we think of t,
x,
y,
and z
as x zero,
x one,
x two,
and x three.
Let's use that notation.
And we combine these all
together and call them x mu.
Now we're talking relativity,
and we're talking about four vectors
and all that kind of stuff.
All right,
so let's call rho...
Let's call it j naught.
It looks like it's got something to do with time.
It does.
Let's call j x,
the thing that I've called j x...
Let's now think of it as
an object with an upper index.
So I'm sorry I defined it this way.
I should have defined it with an upper index.
I would not have had to
switch in the middle of this argument.
Let's just define it everywhere as the same quantity
with the indices.
Now it's just pure notation.
There's nothing,
no content to it.
I've just changed my notation slightly.
Same thing for z.
But we already learned through that before
where what we used to think of as lower indices
turned out to be the things
that we want to be upper indices.
Will the sign change?
Uh...
Where we change the sign of the time component.
Yeah.
But now it's just definition.
Now it's just definition.
j x,
j y,
and j z with the upper index
are exactly the things which
I previously should have defined
in the first place as having upper indices.
I didn't realize that while I was preparing my notes,
but I should have.
All right.
So we take these four objects,
rho,
j x,
j y,
and j z,
and we can now write this whole equation
in the compact form
derivative sub mu,
the derivative with respect to x mu
of j super mu equals zero.
All right.
The first term is derivative with respect to x naught.
That means derivative with respect to time of j naught.
That's this one.
And then when mu is one,
we have the derivative of the x component of j
with respect to x and so forth.
This,
of course,
is summed over mu,
but I'm using the Einstein summation convention now.
And it becomes quite clear
that this,
that j mu is a four vector.
j mu is a four vector.
I won't prove that,
but it does transform as a four vector,
and it's pretty darn clear from this equation
that this equation wouldn't make sense
in every frame of reference.
The derivation of the argument
did not depend on what
frame of reference I was in.
It was a very general derivation.
It must be true in every frame of reference.
And the only way that an equation like this
can be true in every frame of reference
is that if j transforms as a four vector,
and it does.
So we have a new version of conservation
in terms of a Lorentz invariant continuity.
This is called the continuity equation.
And it's the powerful principle
that basically tells us
that charge cannot disappear in one place
and reappear in another
without flowing through the boundaries of the region.
So I could also write this
as d mu j mu equals zero.
Incidentally,
it would not change
if I put this index upstairs
and that index downstairs.
You can juggle the indices up and down
as long as you keep them balanced.
And I won't go through that.
But there will be times
when equations might come out
with one,
a little differently,
with this index upstairs,
that index downstairs.
It's the same equation.
Okay,
good.
Now let's go back
to the derivation from Noether's theorem
of the charge density
for a simple field theory
that had a certain symmetry.
I'll just review it for you quickly.
It provided for us a concept
of a conserved quantity,
which I called charge.
And in fact,
that charge was written
as an integral of a space.
So it's clear that the thing that we define
must be the charge density.
The question is,
does that same theorem prove
that something provide us
with a notion of J,
not of this J,
of the space components,
of the other components of the current?
And so let's go back and review.
I wrote down a particular field theory
which involved a field
with complex valued field,
complex valued field.
Complex valued field,
of course,
just means two real fields.
So I wrote phi is equal
to phi one plus i phi two.
Phi one,
phi star is equal to
phi one minus i phi two.
And you can just think if you like,
you needn't use this complex notation.
The complex notation is,
is notationally neat,
but you can just think in
terms of phi one and phi two.
You can imagine an internal space.
This is not real space.
This is an imaginary space
whose axes are phi one and phi two.
And then the value of a
field at any point of space,
or any point of space time for that matter,
is a dot.
Whoops,
that's not a very good dot.
Is a dot on the plane.
Phi one,
phi two.
Thought of as the complex plane
or just the ordinary real plane with two axes.
That's the field.
If this is phi,
then phi star is down here.
All right.
The symmetry that we're going to imagine
is a symmetry under rotating this plane.
In other words,
let's ask the question,
supposing the Lagrangian did not vary,
if we rotated the field in this plane,
we have to do it everywhere in space simultaneously.
So everywhere in space,
simultaneously and in time,
we rotate the axes of phi.
An equivalent thing to do
is to multiply the complex phi
by a phase factor.
One way of describing the rotations of the plane
is just to say that phi
is replaced by phi times e to the i epsilon,
where epsilon could be any real plane.
So if we rotate the axis of phi,
In particular,
we could take a small real number,
and this would just be
a small rotation of the axes.
So this is one way to describe
such a rotation of axes.
Another way to describe it,
in particular for a small,
for epsilon small,
in other words,
just a small angular rotation of the axes,
is just to say what happens
to phi one and phi two.
I'll tell you.
Let's write the delta phi one,
the change in phi one,
if you just change axes by a little bit,
small rotation angle epsilon,
what happens to phi one?
It gets changed by amount delta phi one,
which is proportional,
I'll just write equal,
to phi two times epsilon,
times the small angle.
And what about delta phi two?
It's of course proportional to epsilon,
but,
just phi one?
Minus phi one.
Now,
how do you look at a Lagrangian
and decide whether it's invariant under this operation?
Well,
in particular,
if it's written in complex form.
If it's written in complex form,
it's really easy.
If it contains things,
like phi star phi in it,
that's invariant.
Phi star phi doesn't change
if you multiply phi by a little phase.
The same time phi star
goes to phi star
times e to the minus i epsilon.
And so if you multiply phi by phi star,
the epsilons will just cancel out.
Phi phi star,
which is also incidentally the same as
phi one squared plus phi two squared,
phi star phi is invariant.
So if the Lagrangian,
for example,
contained phi star phi,
it could contain phi star phi squared.
In fact,
it can contain
any function of phi star phi.
This in itself is invariant,
and so that would,
that would ensure,
or this term in a Lagrangian would be invariant.
What if it contained things like
d mu phi
times d mu phi star?
Still invariant,
because
if phi changes by a phase,
the derivative of phi changes by
exactly the same phase.
What about a thing like phi squared?
Is that invariant?
No,
because phi squared,
what will happen to phi squared?
Phi squared will
get e to the two i epsilon
when you multiply phi by
e to the i epsilon.
Phi star phi,
the e to the i epsilons will cancel.
Phi squared,
they will not cancel.
So there are certainly things
which are not invariant.
If you had something like
phi one squared plus three phi two squared,
would that be invariant?
No.
But how about phi one squared plus phi two squared?
Yes.
All right,
so,
it's relatively easy
to look at a Lagrangian
and to see whether it's invariant
under this operation.
If written in terms of complex notations,
then it should involve
products of fields times complex conjugates.
If it's written in terms of the real components,
it should involve sums of squares
of things with index one
and things with index two.
Let's suppose that's the case.
Let's suppose that a Lagrangian is invariant.
Then there's a symmetry.
If there's a symmetry,
there's a conservation law.
Let's remember the form of such conservation laws.
There's a conserved quantity,
which is often called capital Q.
Sometimes it's even called small q,
and the reason it's called capital Q or small q
is because it's going to wind up being
some sort of charge.
So it's related to the thing we've already called charge.
But let's just call it q.
Sometimes called the Noether charge.
What you do is you sum over the whole system
the change.
This q is not the coordinates.
It's capital Q.
It's a charge.
You take the change
in the ith coordinate
and you multiply it
by the ith momentum.
Let's call it p sub i.
This is the canonical momentum
conjugate to q sub i.
Typically delta q sub i
will have an epsilon in it,
right?
Just drop the epsilon.
You can leave the epsilon there
and then throw it away at the end.
We don't need to worry.
It's just a numerical multiple,
a small numerical multiple of a quantity.
We could divide it.
We could divide out the epsilon.
The epsilon is of no importance,
whatever.
This is the quantity which is conserved.
I think the last time I called these delta q's,
I think I called them f.
I think I wrote that delta q
is equal to epsilon times f.
Well,
that's a redundant notation.
Just call it delta q
and forget the epsilon at the end of the story.
That's the conserved quantity,
the sum over all the variables
of the canonical momentum
multiplied by the small shift in the coordinate
when you do the symmetry operation.
So now we can write that down very quickly.
q,
for our case now,
is the integral over space.
That replaces sum.
What about p sub i?
That's the canonical momentum conjugate to phi.
There's two of them,
phi 1 and phi 2.
So we can write pi 1.
That's the canonical momentum conjugate
to the first field.
That's phi 1.
Times delta phi 1.
What is delta phi 1?
It's phi 2.
Plus pi 2 times delta phi 1.
But that's minus phi 1.
Did I say something wrong?
I think I did.
Minus pi 2 times the change here,
which is minus phi 1.
That's what Emmy Noether tells us
would be the conserved quantity,
conserved because of the symmetry.
Now,
let's go back to the original Lagrangian
that we had imagined.
The original Lagrangian that we imagined
involved time derivatives and space derivatives,
but in particular it involved time derivatives.
And the time derivatives were in the form
d phi by dt squared 1 half.
You can forget everything else for the moment.
This was the kinetic term in the Lagrangian.
Remember what the canonical momentum is.
The canonical momentum is the derivative
of the Lagrangian with respect to the velocity.
Well,
that's just the derivative of the Lagrangian
with respect to d phi dt,
and that's just d phi dt.
Pi 1 is d phi 1 by dt.
Pi 2 is d phi 2 by dt.
And so now we have an expression for the charge.
Here it is.
Equals integral over space
times pi 1,
which is,
let's just call it phi 1 dot,
times phi 2,
minus phi 2 dot times phi 1.
This quantity must be conserved.
We've proved it.
We've proved it a dozen times over.
We've proved it by proving a more general theorem.
Here's the more general theorem that this is conserved.
This is the conserved quantity,
and it's an integral over space.
Now,
to get a perspective on what this is,
on the meaning of it,
it's helpful to go back
to the analogy with the string.
I think we talked about this,
but let's do it again.
A string or a rope,
a jump rope,
something like that,
stretched between two points,
free to move around.
Our first version of the string
was that it was free
to move in the vertical plane.
Now I want to have it be
free also to move in the horizontal plane,
not move along the direction of the string,
but transverse to the direction of the string,
in both directions.
Let's call one direction phi 1
and the other direction phi 2.
Think of that thing in a model.
We're making up a model of a field theory now.
I don't want you to
think of a real jump rope.
I mean,
for the moment,
think of a real jump rope.
But ultimately,
we'll be thinking about mathematical fields
describing relativistic field theory and so forth.
But for our purposes right now,
you can actually think of phi 1 and phi 2
as the x and y coordinates
of a point on this string.
Now what is this?
What is phi 1 dot?
Phi 1 dot is the one component of the velocity.
So this is like the one component of the velocity.
This is the one component of the velocity
times the other component of position minus vice versa.
That should be familiar to many
of you as the angular momentum.
All right,
so if we really think about the mechanical analogy,
then the phi dots would be velocities,
and of course velocities are proportional to momenta,
ordinary momenta now,
just ordinary momenta.
And this would be like the x component
of momentum times y minus the y component
of momentum times x.
That would be called the angular momentum.
The angular momentum about an axis along the string.
So think of the jump rope being twirled around.
It has some angular momentum.
You don't really have to have anybody there twirling.
You can just have it anchored to some point,
and you give it a whirl,
and it continues to whirl,
and it doesn't stop unless there's friction,
of course.
Friction will stop it.
But in the absence of friction,
it will just continue to whirl around.
You can whirl it around with a node
so that half of it is over here,
the other half is over here,
and both of them are whirling around like this.
That would be positive angular momentum.
Going in the other way would be negative angular momentum.
Ooh,
I could do that.
I didn't know if I could do that.
I can't do this,
though.
Right,
so that's angular momentum about this axis.
That's the analog.
That's the analogy for charge.
That's the analogy,
the mechanical analogy,
in the jump rope case,
for charge.
But with or without the analogy,
this is the expression.
Now,
this can be written another way,
another compact way.
I'll write it in another compact way.
You can write it in terms of the complex components.
Let me write it in terms of the complex components.
It's also the integral of a space,
dx,
of,
I think there's an i,
and then there is a,
no phi 1 and phi 2,
but phi star dot phi
minus phi star phi dot.
If you work this out in terms of the components,
phi 1 and phi 2,
you get exactly the same thing.
Notice that the two terms
are complex conjugates of each other.
And when you subtract,
what do you get when you subtract two complex conjugates?
Pure imaginary,
but if you multiply it by i,
it becomes pure real.
So you can also write this if you like.
I think there's a factor of 2.
There's a factor of 2,
if I remember.
Which is not terribly important.
If a thing is conserved,
then twice it is also conserved.
But technically I think there's a factor of 2 there.
We can also write this in another form
as just the imaginary part.
The imaginary part of the integral
of phi star dot phi.
If you take two things and you subtract
a thing from its complex conjugate,
it leaves over only the imaginary part.
So it's the imaginary part of phi star phi.
If you work out,
not phi star phi,
phi star dot times phi.
That's a way to write it.
It's a neat,
efficient way to write it.
And then we can just
concentrate on phi dot star phi
and remember at the end that
we should take its imaginary part.
And that defines the charge.
Alright,
it's just a notational device
that allows us to avoid
writing so many indices and things
and just write that the
charge density is the imaginary part
of the time derivative of phi star times phi.
What about the term with phi dot times phi star?
Did I forget to write it?
No.
When you take the imaginary part of something,
you subtract the thing from its complex conjugate.
So they're both there.
Okay,
that's a useful set of notations.
Now,
our goal is,
well,
first of all,
it's quite clear that this imaginary
part of phi star dot phi
is the charge density.
It's the thing that we integrate
over space to get the charge.
If this is indeed some sort of charge.
If indeed I've accurately identified what this object is
and it's some sort of charge,
then this thing in here is the charge density.
Or this thing in here is the charge density.
Rho.
What about the sign there?
Does that matter?
Well,
it doesn't really because you can either define the charge
or negative the charge.
Uh...
Somewhere along the line,
there was a convention,
which I've forgotten right now,
but it's strictly a convention of what you call positive
and what you call negative,
and it really doesn't matter.
I'm thinking that there's a minus sign
from the left-hand side to the imaginary notation.
That could well be.
So,
um...
Let's...
Could well be.
I'm not going to try to track it now.
It'll waste time.
But it's one sign or the other.
And the important point...
The important fact is that it's not important.
It's important to be consistent,
but it's not important when you're making your definition
of what you want to call charge
to fix one sign or the other.
You fix a sign and then you stick with it.
So let's use this,
uh...
Let's use this notation with the minus sign here.
I hate carrying around the minus sign.
Oh,
I know what I can do.
I can get rid of the minus sign...
Yeah.
Yeah,
by putting the star on the other side.
good.
Okay,
so that's,
uh...
That's...
And this object,
then,
the imaginary part of this object,
what is it?
It's the charge density.
Okay,
so let me write down,
then.
We have the following ideas.
We have an idea of what the charge density is,
and we have the idea of
a four vector of charge current.
The integrand you're saying
is the charge density?
That's correct.
The charge density is the thing
that you integrate to find the charge.
All right,
so let's write it down,
then.
Rho...
What if this would be an angular momentum density?
It would be an angular momentum
per unit length along the string.
Yeah.
Right.
Angular momentum per unit length along the string,
exactly.
I think I probably mentioned last time that this,
of course,
has an important concept here that is not important now,
but will become quite important when we
do some quantum mechanics with these ideas.
And identifying the charge as
being similar to an angular momentum,
mathematically,
it has the properties of an angular momentum.
And you will,
of course,
remember that in quantum mechanics,
angular momentum is quantized.
It comes in integer multiples of h-bar,
positive or negative.
That suggests that when we apply
quantum mechanics to fields like this,
that the charge will be quantized.
And indeed it is,
for the same mathematical reasons.
You don't need to know what those mathematical reasons are.
You simply need to know
that there's a mathematical similarity,
or more than a similarity,
an isomorphism,
between the theory of charge in field theory
and the theory of angular momentum
to know that if one is quantized,
the other will be quantized.
And that's the origin of the fact
that charge comes in multiples of something.
And I won't get into quarks,
which carry a third of a unit of charge here.
This is not the place for it right now.
That's a subject.
It's a sophisticated subtlety.
Okay,
so let's see.
So where were we?
Yeah,
currents.
All right,
so let's write rho.
Rho is the imaginary part of something.
And what is that something?
Time derivative of phi times phi star.
Look at it for a minute,
and then try to guess what the
other components of the four vector are.
Now notice that this index here is a lower index.
The derivative defines a...
First of all,
this object,
the derivative with respect to t,
defines...
Is it covariant or contravariant?
I can't remember.
The covariant components of a four vector.
Phi is assumed to be a scalar field,
so this is a covariant component of a four vector.
And of course,
multiplying it by a scalar,
it is still the covariant component of a four vector.
It's pretty obvious what the other components
of the covariant components of the four vector are.
They are just imaginary part of phi star.
Let's call all four components
d by d mu of phi.
That's the completion of the four vector.
For example,
jx is equal to the imaginary
part of phi star dx phi,
and so forth.
What about the upper components?
What about the contravariant components?
What is j super x?
Same thing.
But what about j super t?
A minus sign.
Okay.
We could take all of that into account
by simply inventing a notation
which keeps track of the signs
by putting the indices upstairs.
Now all this means,
a derivative with a superscript there
just means change the sign for the time component.
So that's just a neat
little trick that you can do
to keep track of signs.
It doesn't change anything.
And then we're writing the contravariant components.
Covariant,
contravariant,
they only differ by a sign
in the time component.
Does anyone write the star on the bottom?
Say it again?
Just kidding.
You want to lower the star,
right?
Yeah,
yeah.
We'll lower the stars.
That actually does have a meaning.
We don't want to fool with it.
All right.
Now,
next step.
Can we directly prove
that this four-dimensional vector
satisfies the continuity equation?
All right.
We would like to show that this object
does really satisfy the continuity equation.
That's where we came in with the continuity equation.
And I think we'll take a little break.
But at the end,
after the break,
we will derive the continuity equations
from the field equations.
You can't get them from nowheres.
You got to get them from somewheres.
What do we have?
We know some things about how phi
moves in space and time,
how it varies in space and time.
And if we're lucky,
it will be enough to prove for us that
the continuity equation is satisfied for J.
So that'll be the next step.
Prove the continuity equation.
Notice we really have not proved the continuity equation.
What we proved using Noether's theorem
is the conservation law.
All that really tells us is that the total charge
in the universe doesn't change with time.
We have not really proved the continuity equation.
So that's a separate thing to prove,
but it is true.
So we'll come back to it in about seven minutes.
Okay,
our goal is to check the continuity equation.
Our goal,
I think,
is to wait for the remainder
of the class to come in first.
Is some called isotopic spin?
Does that have anything to do with the...
It does,
but I think not for the electron.
Um...
Yeah.
The answer is yes,
it has something to do with it,
but,
uh...
But...
It is not the same thing.
Something different.
We'll get to it.
I think we'll be able to talk about isotopic spin.
Unfortunately,
we have to talk about spinners,
which is a subtlety,
but we'll try our best.
So we have a guess
for what the four-dimensional four vector
of current flow is.
And the only thing to check,
there's only one thing to check,
and that's to check that it is conserved,
meaning to say that it satisfies continuity equation.
These days,
when a physicist says something is conserved,
he literally means that it's conserved,
that the current,
number one,
that there is a notion of current and charge density,
or
density of whatever the quantity is,
number one,
and that it satisfies the continuity
equation.
Continuity equation is always central to
what a physicist means by saying something
is conserved.
Okay,
so we ought to then check the continuity equation.
Now,
the continuity
equation has to do with the way the
components of J vary in space and time.
We're going to
differentiate them after all,
and that in turn has to
do with the way phi varies in
space and time.
What is it which controls the way
that it varies with space and time?
The field equations.
So in order to write some field equations,
let's begin with a simple
Lagrangian.
We're not going to do this for every possible Lagrangian,
although we should,
and it would be true for every Lagrangian
of the right form with the right symmetry.
But let's take a particular Lagrangian.
Our favorite,
um,
that we've used over and over again,
Lagrange density equal to,
uh,
phi dot,
let's say phi
dot squared over two minus
the space derivatives of phi squared,
same thing for y and z,
over
two.
And,
uh,
then let's add what I
have been calling a mass term,
just for fun.
This is
phi squared.
I'm sorry.
I,
I withdraw this.
It's phi star dot phi dot,
no two.
Star dx phi star.
Now remember,
you can write this in
terms of usual components phi one
and phi two,
and it's just the two Lagrangians,
one for each component of the field.
And then,
I want to add something just for fun,
or just for a little bit more completeness.
Let's see,
do I want minus or plus minus?
Minus mu squared,
where mu is just a real number,
times phi star phi.
I don't,
in previous lectures,
I might have just called this mu.
I don't remember.
It's not a,
it's just an x and a y and a z,
but we can write the whole thing.
We can write the whole thing
in the form d mu phi,
d mu,
phi star.
That's all it is.
So we have L equals phi star phi
Here?
No,
no,
just the left
First one
Here
What is that?
It's phi star dot
Phi star dot
And then what's
Phi dot
Oh,
okay
You have two stars in the middle term
Oh,
it's two stars in the middle term,
sorry,
good
One star in the middle term
Alright,
I only write it in this
form to just display the obvious symmetry
That it contains things times their complex conjugates
And so it has this
symmetry that we've been talking about
Alright,
the important thing is the
field equations which follow from this
So,
oh,
there should be a two over here
Ah,
the twos are not important
No,
no,
no two there
Okay,
the important thing is the
field equation which follows from this
The field equation is just,
we've written it before
Without the mu squared term
Just let's write it out explicitly
The second derivative with respect to time of phi
Minus the second derivative with respect to x,
y,
and z
I'm just going to include x
But we also have a term for y and z
Phi
And then from here,
let's see,
I think there's either a plus or a minus
Ah,
plus I think
Plus mu squared phi
Equals zero
This,
without the mu squared,
it would just be the usual wave
equation that we've written down many times
We make it into three dimensional wave equation
by putting a y and a z term
Adding them in
And then this mu squared term is just
another term that I'm including for completeness or semi-completeness
Just to have it there
We'll use it later,
we'll study it later
It plays some important role
in the mass of a particle
But for the moment it's just an extra term
I threw in to be a little more complete
Okay,
here's our field equation
Now I can write it in a very compact form
It is
d super mu d sub mu phi
Either plus or minus,
let me get this right
Um
I think minus mu squared phi equals zero
So this is a nice compact form for it
And it stands for the second derivative with respect
to time minus the second derivative with respect to space
Okay
That's our field equation
What we want to derive from this
field equation is the continuity equation for j
So let's write the continuity equation
for j and see if it follows
The continuity equation for j is
d mu j mu equals zero
So let's just do it
This will,
this,
if it's true,
then it means that
This is what it would mean
It means the imaginary part of d mu
on phi star d mu phi equals zero
That's what it would mean
j,
here's j,
the imaginary part anyway
We differentiate it and set it equal to zero
Well,
I'm not saying it's true
I'm saying,
is it true?
Not it is true,
but is it true?
Okay,
let's check it
Let's follow it through a little bit
It's the same thing as,
now I can differentiate
I can write that this is the imaginary part
And the derivative here consists of two terms
In one term,
the d mu hits the phi star
In the other term,
the d mu hits the derivative
Alright,
so what does it got?
We have two terms then
We have d mu phi star
d mu phi
That's when the derivative hits the phi star
Then we have plus phi star
d mu d mu phi
Does this or does this not equal zero?
That's our question
So let's look at it
First thing is,
this is real
It consists of things like
The time derivative of phi star
times the time derivative of phi
Things times their own complex conjugates
With various signs
The signs don't change,
don't turn something real into imaginary
So this is pure real
And it's imaginary part is just zero
Good
That was fast,
we got rid of that fast
This piece here is clearly related to the field equation
Where's the field equation?
The field equation has exactly that same thing in it
d mu d mu phi
And it's equal to mu squared phi
By virtue of the field equations
This becomes equal to the imaginary part of
Phi star
d mu d mu phi
That's mu squared phi
Plus or minus
I don't know,
plus or minus,
whichever
But this is just phi star phi
Mu is real
Phi star phi is real
Am I just confused or are you using mu?
Oh,
I'm sorry
Very good
Yes,
I've used mu for two different things
Index,
and let's call it m
Let's call it m
It is connected with the mass of a particle
But it differs from the mass of a particle
Described as a quantum of the field
By a factor of h bar
That's why I didn't want to call it m
But never mind,
I don't want to
You are right,
we
h bar is equal to one
m squared
Yes,
but of course since we're doing classical physics
That means h bar is equal to zero
So
But all the stars are there
Yeah
But phi star phi is also real,
pure real
And so this is also zero
So the whole damn thing is zero
The whole thing is zero
But not as an identity
But by virtue of the field equations
By virtue of setting this thing equal to this thing
That's the field equations
In other words,
for any solution
Of the equations of motion
Not for any old phi that you can write down
But for any phi which satisfies
The equations of motion
This
Derivative
D mu j mu
Is equal to zero
Again I'll repeat why
This is real
It's imaginary part is zero
This is not obviously real
But the equations of motion tell us
That it's equal to phi star m squared phi
One phi star comes from here
The other phi comes from the equation of motion
So the continuity equation is indeed satisfied
So that's
That in itself doesn't establish
That this is the electric charge of anything
What it is
Is the electric charge of the assembly of charged particles
That might be the quanta of the phi field
But it doesn't prove that this is charge
What it does is it makes this a candidate
It's a conserved quantity
A quantity which satisfies a continuity equation
And it makes it a possible candidate
For a mathematical description of charge
And we're not going to go
more deeply into that right now
Well isn't that enough to say that
It's a sum quantity or something
It's,
yes
Yes,
if we knew a little more
I would make a more complete argument
But for the moment it
just establishes it as a candidate
For an interesting quantity
That's conserved
That satisfies a continuity equation
And among such quantities in physics
Are electric charge
Now
We'll come back to this
You asked me about isotopic spin
I'll tell you very quickly
Isotopic spin of course has to do with nuclear physics
And it's connected with all of this
But I'll just tell you very quickly
We imagine the theory here
In which the field had two components
Phi one and phi two
And the symmetry was an invariance
With respect to rotation in the plane
In the theory of isotopic spin
Which is not a theory of electric charge
Well it can be partly a theory
But the theory of isotopic spin
Is just basically a theory with three
With three components
In which there are three axes to the fields
Which are rotationally invariant in three dimensions
Internal dimensions,
not real dimensions
But internal dimensions
And otherwise is extremely similar to this
So the pattern would be the same
What happens to angular momentum in three dimensional world?
Angular momentum
If there's only two axes
Is either plus or minus
Goes this way or goes this way
What about angular momentum when
you're in a three dimensional world?
It becomes a vector
Which means that that's three components
Right
Right,
three distinct components
Any one of which could be positive or negative
And the isotopic spin is a
thing which has three distinct components
And so in a certain sense it describes three charges
Not just one charge
But let's not
All right,
I want to talk a
little more about energy and momentum
In relativity
And its connection in particular with mass
And its connection with this guy over here
I don't think we'll get to the full story tonight
We'll continue it next time
But I want to get to the story
I want to go back to ordinary special relativity
Let's forget field theory
And let's talk about the motion of particles
In ordinary relativity theory
And identify in ordinary relativity theory
The energy and momentum of a particle
Oh,
I know how we can do this
We can do this by the method of Lagrangians
However,
we won't
Maybe next time
On further reflection
I think I won't
All right
There's a concept of momentum in non-relativistic physics
It's mass times velocity
The concept of momentum in relativistic physics
Is also mass times velocity
Those of you who have taken my class previously
In relativity and things
Would know that it's not mass times ordinary velocity
But it's mass times four velocity
The ordinary velocity is the components of a three vector
Mass times
What am I saying?
Ordinary momentum is a component of a three vector
And that three vector involves the three vector of velocity
The three vector of velocity is
The three components of spatial position
Their derivative with respect to time
In other words,
dx,
dt,
dy,
etc.
Let's just write dx,
dt as one of them
The four vector of velocity
Is a four vector
And it's the derivative not with respect to ordinary time
But with respect to proper time
Let's call it tau
It has four components including a time component
So there's a notion of the time component of velocity
That's the time component of velocity
And the velocity forms a four vector
Now this is obviously a four vector
Tau is proper time
It's invariant,
it's a scalar
X is a vector or dx is a vector
And so this is a four vector
But before we go on,
let me remind you what d tau is
d tau is a thing whose square
Is dt squared minus dx squared
Minus dy squared minus dy squared
I need a notion for the square of three vectors
I need a notation for the square of three vectors
Let's just call it dx vector squared
Like that
It stands for dx squared,
dy squared,
and dz squared
That's d tau squared
Now there's some speeds of light in there
Where do the speeds of light go?
I think usually it's d tau squared
I really like to put them here
Some people like to put it
in front of the dt squared
But then d tau doesn't
have the same units as dt
And so proper time and
time don't have the same units
I want proper time and
time to have the same units
So I put the c squared down here
And then since c is one
and one is zero and uh
No
Let's just
I'll tell you where the c's go when
it's important to know where the c's go
But for the moment
c is equal to one
Alright,
this is d tau squared
d tau is of course square
root of dt squared minus dx squared
But now let's divide and multiply
By dt
Let's put a dt here and a dt here
Now I've done nothing
But now I want to bring
the denominator dt into the square root
To do so I have to square it
So I'm going to do this
Okay,
dt squared over t squared
What is that?
dt squared over dt squared
That's one
One
Now what is dx squared or dx vector squared
Divided by dt squared
Three dimensional square or the three dimensional velocity
Minus v vector squared
One minus v squared
Since I'm squaring it I don't
even have to put the uh
It just means by definition the sums of the squares
Good
Now where would the speed
of light go in this formula?
Under the v
v squared over c squared
That means for ordinary velocities
Let's put it in for the moment
For ordinary velocities small by
comparison with the speed of light
d tau and dt are almost the same thing
They're almost the same thing to
within a very very small correction
But for velocities up near the
speed of light it's pretty important
Let's write this one other way
d tau divided by dt
Or better yet
dt divided by d tau
Is equal to one divided by the square
root of one minus v squared over c squared
And let's just
We'll put back the c when
we need it for various purposes
Don't you have a
Isn't it dtc on the outside?
No
To put the c inside you
have to put the c outside
No no no I'm not
No no that's right
That's right
To restore the units I realized that
tau and t have exactly the same units
So I can't put a c
out here that would change the formula
So I can't put a c out here that would change
the units of the left hand side and the right hand side
But v by itself
One has no units
One is dimensionless
And so v squared over
c squared has to be dimensionless
So that means it's got the
it's the ratio of v to c
It's right
Okay
Yeah
Good
Now let's compute the various
components of the four velocity
The first component of the four velocity
Or the zeroth component
Is dt by d tau
And here it is
One over the square root of
one minus v squared over c squared
But I'll leave that
Now what about the x component
The x component is dx by d tau
But let's write that as dx by dt
Times dt by d tau
But what is dt by d tau
It's one over the square
root of one minus v squared
So that means
Let's write the equation
Let's write the equation properly
dx by d tau
Is equal to dx by dt
Times dt by d tau
Which is the same one over
square root of one minus v squared
But what is dx by dt
Times dt by dt
That's just the x component of the velocity
vx
Alright,
let's put back the c squares
The only place there's a c squared is over here
One minus v squared over c
squared is where the c's go
Also over here
These are now the components of a four vector
Well these are the four vectors
So the first two components of a four vector
The other components would involve a vy and a vz
So here's our four vector
Yeah
算了
x mu by d tau consists of 1 over the square
root of 1 minus v squared and v over the square
root of 1 minus v squared.
That's our four vector.
One component over here and
then three more components over here.
Now let's move on to momentum.
Momentum in non-relativistic physics
is just mass times velocity.
Velocity means ordinarily dx by dt.
It's not a very good quantity from
the point of view of relativistic physics.
It doesn't have a distinct transformation property.
It's dx by d tau
that has the good transformation property.
So it was Einstein's guess,
and then he confirmed that
guess by various Godonkin experiments,
that when you go from Newton...
to special relativity,
you should replace mv,
or m dx by dt,
by m dx by d tau.
And that would wind up being the momentum,
the x component of momentum of a particle.
Just the usual three components of momentum.
All right,
so what does that mean now?
Here is dx by d tau,
and what it says then is that
this is equal to the mass times the
velocity...
Here's the three components...
Divided by square root of 1 minus v squared.
Now,
as Einstein made the guess,
based on his rule that everything should have distinct
and good transformation
properties under Lorentz transformations...
That the momentum of ordinary non-relativistic
physics would get corrected by a factor
of square root of 1
minus v squared in the denominator.
A very small correction when v is small,
especially when v over c is small,
a very small correction,
not worth very much when the
velocity of an object is small.
It gets a little bit sick when
you get up near the speed of light.
When v gets up near the speed of light,
you get a denominator,
which gets closer and closer
to zero,
so the momentum gets very much
bigger than just mass times velocity.
But that's okay.
This was his formula,
and it is the correct formula.
Now the question is,
what is the fourth component?
The fourth component here was something new.
The fourth component would be
m times dt by d tau.
And that's just the mass.
Okay?
So,
let's call it p0,
the time component of the momentum,
whatever that means.
And that will wind up being just the mass
divided by the square root of 1 minus v squared
over c squared.
That's just multiplying the mass by dt by d tau.
So Einstein said,
what is this thing?
It's a constant.
And he realized very quickly that it
was just the kinetic energy of the particle.
It was the kinetic energy,
and that indeed,
just as with Newtonian physics,
a free particle
would have four conservation laws,
three of momentum and one of energy.
Now,
if it's not quite right,
the factors of c aren't quite
in the right place to define
conventional units of energy.
What do I do?
What do I have to do to
get conventional units of energy in there?
Two powers of c in the numerator.
So,
let's,
if I call it p0,
this is correct.
But if I want to identify that with energy,
I have to write that there's another factor
of c squared,
mc squared divided by square root of
1 minus v squared over c squared.
All right.
So for particle at rest,
v equals 0.
Its energy is mc squared.
And the fact that it's c squared here,
that's a convention,
or it just makes it consistent
with non-relativistic units.
But let's leave it there.
E is equal to mc squared over the square
root of 1 minus v squared over c squared.
But basically,
what it is is the time component of
a four vector which is composed out of
the mass times the four velocity.
That's energy and momentum.
Shall we work out that what this,
let's work out a little further.
Let's calculate what this is when
v over c is very small.
When v over c,
we use the binomial theorem,
the thing that's in the denominator is 1 minus
v squared over c squared
to the minus 1 half power.
All times mc squared.
Now anybody remember the binomial theorem
well enough to expand this out?
One plus 1 half v squared over c squared.
Plus higher orders.
This is equal to 1 plus
v squared over 2 c squared.
All times mc squared.
That's the expansion of this.
Remember that v over c is very small.
v squared over c squared is very small.
And if you expand it in
powers of v squared over c squared,
the first correction to 1
starts with 1,
then v squared over 2 c squared,
and then things which are truly incredibly
small,
v to the fourth over c to the fourth,
those are really,
really small.
Much smaller than this.
Now,
let's look at the next one.
what does this give us?
This gives us mc squared.
That's good old,
famous Einstein mc squared.
Plus the mass times v squared over 2,
and the c squares cancel.
C squared in the denominator
and c squared in the numerator.
Okay,
so what do we get?
We get mc squared.
The rest of the square.
The rest energy of a
particle plus the ordinary kinetic energy.
And of course,
this was the first indication of
Einstein's idea of e equals mc squared
for an object at rest.
For an object at rest,
e equals mc squared.
And then the first correction is mv squared over 2.
And the higher corrections involve much,
notice that the c's cancel out of here.
The next corrections would truly be small.
The first correction would be small by
diminishing factors of 1 over c squared.
Okay,
I just wanted to make sure that we understood.
The first m is not the proper mass,
I guess.
It is the proper mass.
It's the rest mass.
This m?
Yeah.
Look,
physicists don't even use the term rest mass anymore.
Okay.
But the term rest mass
hasn't been used for 75 years.
Only in elementary physics classes are
the only place where the term,
and even there
I don't think of it.
Or is there a goal to mislead you?
Right.
The mass of the particle is a property
of the particle which doesn't care whether the
particle is moving or not.
Uh.
And it is the energy of the particle when.
Or.
When an object,
when the center of mass
of that object is at rest.
That's the definition of a mass.
Take an object,
it could be a pot of hot water,
it could be,
um,
whatever it happens to be.
Put it at rest,
which means make sure that its
total momentum is equal to zero.
Whatever its energy is,
is called its mass,
within a factor of c squared.
Okay.
So m means rest mass.
I will never ever talk
about rest mass or moving mass.
We'll just talk about mass and it means
what used to be called 10,000 years ago,
uh,
used
to be called the rest mass.
Uh.
Right.
Anyway,
this is energy and momentum.
Now it's kind of interesting,
you get into some very peculiar
mess when you try to think
about particles whose mass is zero.
Looks like their energy is zero.
But the problem is.
When a particle has zero mass,
it also moves at the speed
of light and so the denominator
is also zero.
You get into a nasty,
um,
zero over zero situation.
Uh.
You can see that most
clearly in fact from the momentum.
Well.
Let's,
let's concentrate on the energy.
Both the energy and the momentum have
peculiar things that happen when the velocity goes
to the speed of light.
Okay.
When the velocity goes to the speed of light,
the denominator goes to zero and we don't
like denominators which are equal to zero.
So it's not a good idea to try to
study the limit of massless particles with these equations.
But there's another thing we can do.
Instead of looking at the relationship between
energy and velocity and mass and velocity,
get the idea.
Get the velocity out of it all together
and just look at the relationship between momentum
and energy.
This is where we're going.
I want for future purposes to have the relationship
of the energy to the momentum for a particle
of,
for a particle of mass m.
Without having to worry about what its velocity is.
Alright.
So all we have to do.
Let's see.
Where are we?
Let's write them down over here
and find the relationship between them.
Incidentally.
Incidentally,
that relationship for non-relativistic
physics would just be energy,
kinetic energy
in particular,
is momentum squared divided by twice the mass.
We might also throw in mc squared,
but this would be,
this is the analog of what we're
looking for.
Relation between energy and momentum.
What does that look like in the theory of relativity?
Okay.
So here we have it.
We have energy equals m.
Divided by square root of one minus v squared.
I'll put the c's back.
I don't like carrying them around.
I get confused.
And p is equal to mv over
square root of one minus v squared.
Okay.
The square roots in the denominator are a nuisance.
So to get rid of them,
let's figure out what e squared
is in terms of p squared.
Instead of figuring out e in terms of p,
let's get e squared in terms of p squared.
That'll get rid of the square roots in the denominator.
So e squared is m
squared over one minus v squared.
And p squared is m squared v squared
over square root of one minus v squared.
No.
No square root.
One minus v squared.
Well I could solve for v.
What I could do.
I could do something complicated.
I could solve for v squared from
this equation and then plug it into here.
And that would give me the energy in terms
of the momentum or the momentum in terms of
the energy.
But it's easier to do than that.
All we have to do is
take the difference of these two.
Let's take the difference of these two.
E squared minus p squared.
Let's see what we get.
In the denominator,
we're going to get one minus v squared.
Because both terms have the same denominator.
Both terms also have m squared.
And then this term has one
and this term has minus v squared.
So one minus v squared.
Well that's lucky.
Just e squared minus p squared equals m squared.
Okay.
Now that's not so surprising.
E and p are components of a four vector.
The invariant that you make out of a
four vector is the difference of the squares of
the time components and the space components.
Here's what we have.
We found the difference of the squares
of the time components and the space components
are the square of the mass.
In other words.
The mass is simply the invariant that you
make from the four vector of energy and momentum.
That's another way to think about it.
You have a four vector of energy and momentum.
Then the invariant length of
that four vector is the mass.
Another way to say it.
If the momentum happens to be zero,
then e and m are the same thing.
Okay.
Now,
let's see if we can
figure out where the c's go.
This is pure dimensional analysis.
Where do you want to put it?
Put it here?
Numerator or denominator?
Numerator.
C squared here.
I'll tell you how I know in a minute.
C squared here and c to the fourth here.
Now,
how do we know that?
First of all,
let's forget this term.
Okay.
E squared,
if E equals MC squared,
E squared must be M squared C to the fourth.
So that makes sense.
Now,
energy is typically momentum times velocity.
Even in Newtonian physics,
MV squared,
which is twice,
sorry,
MV squared is velocity times momentum.
So in energy,
this is just unit-wise,
MV squared has units of energy,
velocity times momentum.
So energy has units of momentum times velocity.
That's the basic connection between energy
and momentum for a relativistic system,
for a relativistic particle.
Let's write it just in terms of energy.
It says that energy is equal to the square root.
of momentum squared times C squared plus
mass squared times C to the fourth.
That's a generalization of,
certainly Einstein knew it,
but it's a generalization of Einstein's E equals MC squared.
E equals square root of
M squared C to the fourth,
and then if the object is moving,
it has momentum,
you add P squared C squared to it.
So this is...
This is our basic energy-momentum relation.
And notice,
once we've gone this far,
we can now smoothly,
with no big problem,
take the limit that the mass goes to zero.
And in that case,
energy is just equal to the
square root of P squared C squared,
or just the magnitude of the momentum times C.
You might have thought that the answer ought to be,
well,
let's see,
non-relativistically.
What's the answer non-relativistically?
Energy,
which is one-half MV squared,
is equal to velocity times,
sorry,
is equal to momentum times velocity over two.
You might have taken this equation and said,
okay,
just plug in...
Velocity equals the speed of light,
and you get C times P over two.
Well,
you'd be wrong.
You'd be wrong by a factor of two.
That's the whole effect of relativity
on the formula for a massless particle,
or for a particle moving with the speed of light,
is that the energy is twice what you
might have gotten by just using Newton's equation.
Of course,
it wouldn't make any sense to use Newton's equations.
But PV over two is the relation,
non-relativistically.
PC is the relationship in relativity.
All right.
I'm not going to use this now.
We're going to use it next time
to explore the connection between waves and particles
and the relationship between the energy of a wave,
the momentum of the wave,
and the properties of waves,
and how those properties of waves are similar to,
in fact,
identical to,
these relationships here.
Something noticed partly by...
Einstein,
something...
Einstein and de Broglie,
Schrodinger,
and so forth.
That's not because we're getting into quantum mechanics now.
We're simply exploring wave motion and the
kinematics and the dynamics of moving waves.
But there is a strong sense in which a strong flavor of
the relationship between energy and momentum of particles on the one hand,
and frequency and wave number
of waves on the other hand.
So that's where we're going next time.
Good.
Thank you.