This program is brought to you by Stanford University.
Please visit us at stanford.edu.
Well,
tonight is our last class for this quarter.
And I am not going to have time to do
all the things that I would have liked to do.
What I'm going to do is show you where the,
what I will do is tell you
where the basic things of electrodynamics come from.
You can go home,
you have enough information,
you can go home and
work out the equations by yourself.
I will try to sort of outline clearly where
the various components come from and where they go.
The basic principle is always this.
The principle of least action.
But in order to use it,
you have to know what the action is.
The action is typically an integral
of a Lagrange density over all space-time.
So before I do anything else,
let me just remind you,
if you have a Lagrangian,
and a Lagrangian is composed of some collection of fields,
let's just call a generic collection of fields,
I don't want to use phi because,
what's a good,
F,
F.
F stands for field.
And there may be a whole bunch of them.
So let's label them F sub A.
A now is not a space-time index,
it doesn't refer to dimension.
It just could be the first field,
the second field,
the third field.
It could run over fields of very different type.
For example,
as A varied,
one F might be a scalar field.
Another F might be a vector field,
like the vector potential.
So this is very generic.
A collection of fields,
which depend on X and T.
Or in a relativistic notation,
they would depend just on the four components of space-time.
The Lagrangian,
in general,
is a function,
of the F's,
all of the F's,
and their first derivatives,
with respect to the X's.
So the Lagrangian,
the Lagrange density,
is a function,
which depends on the derivatives of F,
with respect to the various directions,
there are four of them,
for each A,
F A.
So this is the function,
and this notation is just meant to indicate
that the Lagrangian can depend
on all of the first derivatives,
of any one of the fields F,
and also the undifferentiated fields F also.
For example,
in the scalar field Lagrangian that we studied,
the Lagrangian was the sums of squares,
or differences of squares,
of the derivatives of F with respect to X,
and then we also threw in another one,
another term,
which I called the mass term,
which just depended on the field itself,
without derivatives.
So this is the general form.
The action is the integral
of this thing over all space-time,
but just as for a single particle,
when you think about a single particle,
and you ask what the implications
of the principle of least action are,
you can either think about the whole thing globally,
or you can just think locally,
and you can say,
what implications are there for what are going on
in the vicinity of a point?
What are the implications of the principle of least action?
And the answer is Euler-Lagrange differential equations,
which you would call field equations,
for a field.
I'm not going to derive them,
I'm just going to write
down what the general form is.
Before I do,
let me write down the form,
the ordinary form,
of the Euler-Lagrange equations for
the motion of a particle.
If you have a particle with a set of,
or a set of particles,
instead of having fA,
we would have a set of coordinates xA,
and the Lagrangian would be a function,
this would be now,
it's not,
the Lagrangian would be a function of
L of
the time derivative of x,
that's the velocity,
and the x's themselves.
Okay,
so the Lagrangian in this case
is a function also of derivatives,
now of fields,
not coordinate positions of particles,
and also the field itself undifferentiated.
It's similar to this.
That board is a generalization of this board,
in which there is not one independent variable
that a coordinate can depend on,
but four independent variables
that the,
that a field can depend on.
Okay,
let me just remind you
what the Euler-Lagrange equations are.
They say first differentiate Lagrangian,
no,
I better call this square Lagrangian,
L,
with respect to the velocity
of the eighth coordinate,
not eighth as in
one,
two,
three,
four,
five,
six,
seven,
eight,
but eighth as in little a.
You take the Lagrangian
and you differentiate it
with respect to the derivative of the coordinate.
In this case,
you have a coordinate,
there's only time derivatives.
Then you differentiate that
with respect to time.
That's the left-hand side
of the Euler-Lagrange equation
that follows from the principle of least action,
least action.
And the right-hand side
is just the derivative of the Lagrangian
with respect to x a.
How many such equations are there?
There's one,
oops,
this should be x sub a.
There's one such equation,
for each value of little a.
So if there are 100 coordinates,
then there are 100 equations.
And of course,
these equations are nothing but Newton's equations
for the several coordinates
describing the particles in the system.
The analog on this side is very similar.
This time,
you have a set of derivatives,
not just a time derivative,
but also space derivatives.
The first thing you do is differentiate the Lagrangian,
with respect to the derivatives that appear in it.
Now,
can you differentiate something
with respect to a derivative?
You bet you can.
We just differentiated the Lagrangian
with respect to a time derivative.
In the same way,
we can differentiate the Lagrange density
with respect to what it depends on,
which is the partial derivative
of f a with respect to x a.
This lower derivative
has its own P,
therefore it is in,
so it has source d by 7,
so that the constant of the linear表
is
to where
respect to t in general,
but with respect to x mu itself.
So we differentiate that with respect to
x mu.
Now this left-hand side for each a
is really a sum of four terms.
Let me write it out
explicitly,
or almost explicitly.
It's the derivative with respect to time,
which I'll call
x-naught of the derivative of the Lagrangian with
respect to the time derivative of f .
This is the time derivative of f .
This,
we could have also called this d by dt of
the derivative of the Lagrangian with respect to f dot.
In other words,
the analog of this.
But then there were more terms.
There was also...
So remember the Einstein summation convention.
Whenever you see a repeated space-time index like that,
it means you sum over it.
So there's also derivative with respect to
x1 of the same kind of thing,
derivative of the Lagrangian with respect to
derivative of fA with respect to x1,
and so forth and so
on for the other two coordinates.
That's the structure of the
left-hand side of the Euler-Lagrange equations.
The right-hand side,
we just differentiate the Lagrangian with respect to fA.
So that equals the derivative of the
Lagrangian density with respect to the field itself.
Yeah,
the dots belong,
don't they?
This is of the form,
typically this is a wave equation.
It's typically a wave equation.
If you work it out for the little
scalar field Lagrangian that we've worked out several times,
you'll find out this is just a good
old wave equation for the motion of ordinary waves.
It's the analog of this.
And having said it,
now let's put it up here.
That's the way we derive equations of motion,
differential equations,
from the principle of least action.
What equations are we interested in?
We're interested in Maxwell's equations.
We've already worked out the equations
of motion of a scalar field.
Let's come now to Maxwell's equations.
Let me just write down what they are.
There are various,
there are plenty of different conventions and units.
I'm going to write them down
in a sort of unit-free way,
where I have perfectly good units.
I forget which ones they are.
Where all the four pi's don't appear in the equations,
they appear someplace else.
They do appear,
they appear in the solutions of equations,
various constants associated,
what is it called,
mu and epsilon.
They're all set equal to one.
They're called rationalized units,
I always forget.
But here they are.
Here's Maxwell's equations.
Hmm?
It sounds rational.
Yeah,
it is rational.
All right.
What are the equations for?
The equations are for the electric and magnetic field.
All right.
The electric and magnetic fields are fields,
obviously,
they depend on space.
How many of them are there altogether?
Six.
Three components of the electric field,
three components of the magnetic field.
The electric field is E,
the magnetic field is B.
I have no idea what the
history of B for magnetic field is.
I don't know.
Why it wasn't called M,
Hmm?
M is a pretty popular magnetic field.
Yeah,
I suppose it was mass.
So I don't know why,
but we're stuck with it.
You know,
the last lecture we spent some time,
you know,
adding a term to the partial
to show how to restore gauging.
Yes,
we're going to talk about that more.
Right,
we're going to talk,
but I wanted,
here's the target.
The target is what you want to get.
And then we're going to go back to the Lagrangian and the invariances and
all that stuff and see how we would go about getting this from the principles.
Lagrangian?
Euler-Lagrange equations should produce Maxwell's equations.
It's just a regular partial up there.
It's not a,
it doesn't,
no gauge term added to it or anything.
Where?
Oh,
never mind.
This,
these things could involve the gauge fields.
I mean,
that's very general.
Right.
Okay.
Incidentally,
the electric and magnetic fields are not,
the fundamental fields like F A in this formula.
The electric and magnetic fields are more like the
derivatives of the fundamental fields with respect to the coordinates,
but we'll see why.
Anyway,
here's where we want to get to.
Everybody remember Maxwell's equations?
I remember them up to a sign.
All right.
Divergence of the electric field.
Everybody,
anybody not know what a divergence is?
Good.
Then I don't have to
write down what a divergence is.
The divergence of the electric field,
this is of course derivative with respect to x of the x component
of the electric field plus derivative with respect to y of the y component,
etc.
All right.
Three terms.
That's equal to what?
Rho.
The charge density.
And some people's,
some people's version,
there's a whole bunch of them.
There's a four pi in there.
In mine there is no four pi.
Anyway,
del dot e is equal to rho.
The curl of e.
Everybody know what a curl is?
No.
Who said no?
Ouch.
Did you mean it or should I explain it or?
I know what it is.
You do or don't?
I do.
I didn't say no.
I know.
Somebody said no,
but I couldn't hear who it was.
You said no and so did he.
All right.
I will tell you what the
curl of a vector field is.
But we'll have to do it fast because,
all right.
Any time you see the upside down triangle,
it means it's a derivative of some sort.
Okay.
You did,
you said you did know what divergence is.
Yes or no?
If not,
I will write it down.
Write it down.
Okay.
If you have a vector field.
In this case,
a vector now means a three-dimensional vector.
It has three components.
Let's call them,
let's be very,
very specific now.
X,
Y,
and Z.
The X component of the electric field,
the Y component of the electric field,
and the Z component.
All right.
The divergence of the electric field is a measure.
Remember,
the vector field is a
vector at every point in space.
And so at every point in space,
it's a vector.
At every point in space,
it points in some direction.
And the divergence is a measure of the
spreading of the electric field away from a point.
For example,
a typical vector field that has a divergence
would point away from some point like that.
It's diverging.
That's,
all right.
Now,
the mathematical expression that represents this tendency of the
vector field to point away from a point like that.
It's called a divergence.
It's del dot E.
That's the notation for it.
And it stands for the derivative of the X component with respect to X plus the derivative of
the Y component with respect to Y plus the derivative of the Z component with respect to Z.
Definition.
But it does have this property that it
tends to show you that something is wrong.
Something is spreading away from a point.
Of course,
yeah,
okay.
That's the notion of divergence.
Now,
there's another notion called curl,
which is also a kind of geometric notion.
It tells you if you take an axis,
now a three-dimensional axis.
This is a three-dimensional idea.
When spreading away from a
point is a three-dimensional notion,
spreading away in all three directions.
The curl is also a three-dimensional notion.
But it itself is a vector.
The curl itself has three components.
All right.
And it is,
each component is related to an axis.
And what the curl is,
is given an axis,
let's say the axis out of the blackboard,
it represents the tendency of the vector
field to sort of wind around that direction.
It's,
oh.
If we thought of wind velocity as the relevant field,
then a tornado would have a large curl.
Right at the center of the tornado,
the velocity field,
the wind velocity would be circulating around a point.
A hurricane would have a large,
sometimes it's called vorticity,
but curl is the right term.
And I'm going to write down what the formula is.
So let's take,
let's call this axis the z-axis.
No,
let's call that axis,
yeah,
let's call that the z-axis.
Then the symbol for the curl is del cross E.
It's related to the concept of cross product.
And I'm not going to go through cross product today,
but I'm going to assume you know what it is.
But in this particular case,
it's del cross E.
In this particular case,
I'll write down exactly what it is.
It has in itself,
it has three components.
So let's take the z component of it.
The z component,
and this is the thing which represents the tendency of
the field to wrap around or to circulate around the z-axis.
Obviously,
we could also think about the tendency
to circulate around the x-axis or the y-axis.
That's why there's three components.
This is given by the x derivative of the
y component minus the y derivative of the x component.
That's the z component of the curl.
And as I said,
it represents the tendency of the field
to wrap around that direction like that.
And now if you want to go
to the other two components of it,
you just cycle through.
Z.
And you cycle in the following sense.
X,
y,
z.
X goes to y.
Y goes to z.
Z goes back to x.
So here's what I mean by that.
You go to the next equation by substituting for z,
x.
For x,
y.
And for y,
back to z.
So here's what it would look like.
Del cross E.
All right.
Z cycles to x.
So put an x there.
Is equal.
Now x goes to y.
So that's the derivative with respect to y.
Y goes to z.
Minus dz,
ey.
And what would be next?
You cycle once more through
the three letters of the alphabet.
Del cross E.
The y component,
z,
x,
y.
Is equal x,
The next one will be z.
Y,
z.
Next is x.
And minus dx,
ey.
Sorry.
Dx,
ez.
These are the three components of a curl.
So this is an operation that you do
on a vector and gives you another vector.
This is an operation that you do
on a vector and gives you a scalar.
All right.
One of them gives you the tendency for
the field to separate out from a point.
It's a scalar,
the divergence.
And the other has three components.
The circulation of the field around the three axes,
basically.
Okay.
Now,
Maxwell's first equation is del dot E equals rho.
This is the equation that tells
you that charge densities make electric fields.
For example,
it's at the root of the fact
that if you have a point electric charge,
an electric field radiates out from it.
So what it says is that the
charge is a divergence of the electric field.
Okay.
Now,
the corresponding equation for the
magnetic field is del dot B.
And what you might think you should put on
the right-hand side is some density of magnetic charge.
So,
if you have a point electric charge,
well,
what does magnetic charge mean?
It would mean a little particle
which we call a magnetic monopole.
A magnetic monopole would be a particle that the field,
the magnetic field lines would radiate out of.
There are no known particles like that in nature,
although every physicist of my particular persuasion,
meaning my particular subject rather
than my particular belief system,
almost all theoretical physicists engaged in the
subject of particle physics and so forth
believe that magnetic monopoles really do exist.
Just to see what's involved,
imagine a bar magnet.
A bar magnet has a
north pole and a south pole,
and out of the north pole comes magnetic field lines,
and the magnetic field lines,
look something like this.
You've all seen this.
You take a magnet,
put it under a piece of paper,
sprinkle some iron filings on it,
and you make something like this.
Now,
if you take the south pole very,
very far away,
extremely far away,
and you look just at the north pole,
what you would see,
let's take that south pole and bring it to Australia,
way off the blackboard,
what you would see in
the vicinity of the north pole
would look very much like the field
of an electron or a charged particle,
except that of course it
would not be an electric field,
it would be a magnetic field.
Magnetic field.
Radiating out over the north pole,
away from the north pole.
So you might think the north pole then
is the divergent,
or the north pole is behaving like the divergence
of the magnetic field.
But if you look more carefully,
what you find is that there's also a magnetic field
running right through the magnet,
right through the magnet like that,
and then in fact,
the magnetic field is coming in here.
In other words,
the magnetic field lines
run right through the magnet
and then radiate out away from the north pole.
There really is no divergence to the magnetic field.
What comes in goes out.
So it really doesn't have a divergence
like the electric field does.
The electric field really does radiate out
away from an electron.
This magnetic divergence here
is just because we didn't look inside the magnet.
There are no known sources of magnetic field
which are point sources
in the sense that the
field radiates out away from them
in all possible directions.
Here,
in and out.
So,
the divergence of the magnetic field is zero.
Magnetic fields don't have divergences.
At least not until somebody discovers a magnetic monopole.
Now,
you can fool your friends.
You can get yourself a very,
very thin magnet.
There's another thing which will
make a magnetic field a solenoid.
If instead of a magnet,
you make an electromagnet,
in other words,
you just wrap a wire around an axis like this
and let current go through it,
then the magnetic field lines go through the solenoid
and out the end here.
Now,
you make yourself an extremely thin,
flexible solenoid.
And you grab a hold of this end
and you bring it to your friends and you say,
look,
I have a magnetic monopole.
Yeah,
you can fool your friends into thinking
you have a magnetic monopole
if you could have a solenoid
which was so thin that it
could pass between atoms and so forth.
That's actually what a magnetic monopole is.
It's a magnetic charge
which is,
in some mathematical sense,
really connected to an infinitely thin,
infinitely light,
infinitely flexible solenoid.
But,
until somebody discovers a real magnetic monopole,
the right-hand side of this equation is zero.
Alright,
now we also have equations
for the curl of the electric field.
The curl of the electric field
Now,
what's the curl of the electric field equal to?
The time derivative of the magnetic field.
This says that a changing magnetic field,
if the magnetic field in space changes,
it necessarily creates an electric field.
If B dot is not zero,
in other words,
if a magnetic field is changing with time,
it creates an electric field.
For example,
supposing we started,
let's take a solenoid,
but let's make it infinitely long in both directions.
I'm not particularly interested
now in this monopole problem.
We take the solenoid infinitely long,
we start with no current in the solenoid,
so there's no magnetic field.
Then we start increasing the magnetic field.
Sorry,
yes.
We start increasing the current.
Increasing the current creates a magnetic field
through the solenoid.
As we increase the current,
the magnetic field increases,
and for that reason,
it generates an electric field.
The electric field has a curl.
So it wraps around.
What does it wrap around?
It wraps around the solenoid.
So,
ramping up the current
through a solenoid
creates an electric field around the solenoid,
and it wraps around the solenoid.
And in fact,
in particular,
that electric field could accelerate a charged particle
and get it moving in a circle.
All right,
that's the meaning of this equation.
Whose law is this,
that a changing magnetic field makes an electric field?
I always forget.
That's one of the...
I already knew it.
I'm not sure,
I can't remember which one is which.
Okay.
That's the magnetic field making electric field.
And there's a similar equation
for the magnetic field.
The curl of a magnetic field
is related to the time derivative
of the electric field.
Minus sign in this case,
a minus sign,
electric field dot.
So this says a changing electric field
will also make a magnetic field.
For example,
you take a capacitor plate.
Capacitor plates over here
connected to wires
and if the capacitor plate...
If the capacitor plates have charge on them,
then there will be an electric field
between the capacitor plates.
Now,
we can start with an uncharged capacitor
and pump some electric charge
into the capacitor plates.
And so in that way,
ramp up the electric field.
Ramping up the electric field
must make a magnetic field.
And in fact,
the magnetic field
has to wrap around something.
It wraps around the direction
of the electric field lines.
All right,
so ramping up the charge
in a capacitor
temporarily creates a magnetic field.
And that magnetic field
would orient a compass.
So a compass
would respond to a changing...
a changing electric field
in this manner here.
This is not the complete equation.
There's another thing
on the right-hand side.
What is it?
The current.
Not the charge density,
but the current.
The current density.
J.
Both sides of this equation,
in fact,
both sides of this equation
are vectors.
The curl of the electric field
is a vector.
The magnetic field is a vector.
The curl of the magnetic field
is a vector.
The electric field
and its time derivative
are also vectors.
And the current is a vector.
Now,
this is the three-dimensional current.
Remember what it...
Let me just remind you
what that current means.
The three-dimensional current,
if you take a little window in space,
oriented so that the perpendicular to it
is along some axis,
then the amount of charge
passing through the little window
per unit time,
per unit area,
is called the component of J
in that direction.
So it's the electric charge
passing through a little window in space
per unit time,
per unit space.
And the reason it's a vector
is because you can orient
that little window
in different directions
and in that way sample
the current going
in different directions.
All right,
so that's J.
And that's on the right-hand side.
Now,
what that says is,
how do you get current...
I'm sorry,
how do you get charge
to get onto these capacitor plates?
Well,
there's only one way,
and that's to send a current into them,
right?
So you have to send an electric current into here.
That will charge up the capacitor plates.
And during the time
that the capacitor plate is being charged,
there is a current in here.
That current,
even in places,
let's say far away
from where the electric field is
from the capacitor plates,
let's go way out here,
there's an electric current
going through here,
and that electric current
also makes a magnetic field
which winds around here like that.
So it's kind of interesting.
Here's the picture.
You can have an interrupted place
where the current cannot flow
and in that way make a capacitor plate.
Like this.
It can make the capacitor very long.
The flow of current
as it's ramping up the capacitor
makes magnetic field lines
which wrap around the wire,
but it doesn't stop
at the place where the current ends.
It continues,
the magnetic field continues
into the region in the gap here,
and it continues
because the right hand side
contains both the time derivative
of the electric field
as well as the current.
This term has a,
incidentally,
Faraday didn't know about this term.
He only knew about this.
He knew that a current makes a magnetic field.
Okay.
Maxwell realized actually
that there was an,
not an ambiguity,
an inconsistency in the equations
without,
without this term here.
And Maxwell put that term in.
It's called a displacement current.
I don't know who's being displaced.
I think that one is Ampere's law.
Yeah.
That one is Faraday's law.
Well,
with the J it's called Ampere's law.
And with the,
with the,
okay.
This is called a displacement current.
Okay.
Well,
according to this,
this,
you've got the sign of E and B backwards.
Always happens.
Now am I better?
Yeah.
Good.
Of course that can be absorbed
into a change of definition very easily,
but,
if you change the sign,
the definition of the sign of the magnetic field,
it won't change this equation.
It'll change this one and change its sign.
And then if you,
and you can change J by changing
the definition of which is positive and
which is negative electric charge.
So there's no real,
there's no real content in,
uh,
Yeah.
That's right.
So,
so the signs there are conventions,
but once you fix them,
you fix them.
Who was it that fixed the
convention about positive and negative charge?
Benjamin Franklin.
Yeah.
Of course he had no way of knowing what
it was that was actually flowing in the wires.
There was no way that he could know,
uh,
that the,
the electron was the fundamental charge carrier.
He called the current negative,
meaning to say a flow
of electrons in a certain direction.
He called arbitrarily a negative flow of,
uh,
of current.
And the result of that has been
hundreds of years of confusion among the,
yeah,
I have to explain this.
Every time I teach elementary electromagnetic physics,
I have to explain,
and it drives everybody crazy,
that a flow of electrons this
way corresponds to a current that way.
Ben Franklin did some good things,
but that wasn't one of them.
Uh,
Okay.
Now,
we want to try to get these equations.
Oh,
one more equation which is central to electrodynamics.
These equations tell you how the charges and currents,
the charge and the flow of charge,
create or affect the electromagnetic field.
The other side of the coin is
the way the electromagnetic field affects the charges.
And it affects the charges by exerting forces on them.
So,
the other side of the coin
is the force exerted on a charge.
So,
the force exerted on a charged
object due to the electromagnetic field.
All right,
so let me write down what that force is.
It's called the Lorentz force law.
And it's the force on a charged particle is equal.
First of all,
there's the electric charge of the particle.
Let's call that E,
for electric charge.
Measured in some units,
and our purpose now is not to worry about units.
The measured in coulombs,
and the charge of an electron
is a horribly small number of coulombs.
What is it?
I don't remember what it is.
Hmm?
Ten to the minus 19.
Something like that.
Ten to the minus 19 coulombs for the electron,
yeah.
So,
that's a very small number.
But for an electron,
for some other object,
it may be of order,
it may be bigger.
Incidentally,
one coulomb of charge is a huge amount of charge.
If you put one coulomb of charge on a basketball,
the effect of the repulsion
would just blast it to smithereens.
So,
a coulomb of charge is a lot of charge.
But,
the force is proportional to the charge on a particle,
and then there's two terms.
One of them is just the electric field.
The force is proportional to the electric field,
the factor of proportionality being the electric charge.
So,
first of all,
in here there's the electric field.
Incidentally,
both sides are vectors
in the three-dimensional sense.
Force and electric field.
Then there's another term
which is absent unless the electron
or the charge is moving.
So,
a stationary electric charge,
this is all there is.
Then there's a velocity-dependent force.
And it's plus.
The velocity of the particle
cross-product with the magnetic field.
So,
it's proportional to the product
of velocity and magnetic field.
It points in the direction perpendicular to
both the velocity and the magnetic field.
So,
if we have a magnetic field,
let's suppose there's a magnetic
field pointing into the blackboard.
Magnetic field pointing into the blackboard
we usually represent by a bunch of little crosses.
The idea,
I'm told,
is that magnetic fields are arrows.
And looking at the arrow from behind,
you see the feathers.
So,
here's the feathers.
If you want the magnetic field to come toward you,
you just see the points of the arrows.
I'm told that's where this convention comes from.
So,
here's a magnetic field pointing into the blackboard.
V cross B.
If you don't know what a cross-product is,
I'll rough it out for you now,
but not with mathematical precision.
It's first of all a vector
which is proportional to the velocity,
proportional to the magnetic field,
and in the direction perpendicular to both of them.
So,
for example,
if it's proportional to the electric and magnetic field,
it's also proportional to the sine of the angle
between the electric and magnetic field.
Sorry,
between the velocity and the magnetic field.
That's what a cross-product is.
So,
if the velocity is in the same direction
or opposite direction to the magnetic field,
there is no force.
The sine of the angle between the velocity
and the magnetic field is zero.
If the charge is moving in this direction,
then the force is perpendicular to both the magnetic field
and to the charge.
There's only one direction that's
perpendicular to both of them,
and that would be the vertical direction.
I can't tell,
is it upward or downward,
v cross b?
Upward.
All right,
so a charged particle moving through here,
if it were moving with a velocity v,
would have a force on
it which would bend it upward.
The faster it moves,
the larger the force.
The larger the magnetic field,
That's this term.
This is called the Lorentz force law,
electric and magnetic forces.
This term is velocity dependent.
This term is not velocity dependent.
That's what we would like to get out
of a fundamental theory of electromagnetism.
So,
what do we need to do?
We need to find ourselves a Lagrangian,
which,
when we subject it to the principle of least action,
will give us these one,
two,
three,
four,
five equations.
Now,
how many equations are there?
There's a lot more than that.
This is one equation,
this is one equation,
one equation,
one equation.
How many is this?
This is three equations,
and this is three equations.
So,
these are the field equations.
That's one,
two,
six,
and two is eight.
Eight equations.
And,
um,
hmm?
Say it again?
Three of the force.
Three of the force,
right?
And three equations for the force law,
yeah.
Three equations for the force law.
And we'd like to derive them
from a principle of least action.
Why?
Among other things,
it's the principle of least action
which guarantees that there's a concept of energy
if,
in the theory of electromagnetic forces
and electromagnetic field,
there was not a good concept of a conserved energy
in the world.
There sure wouldn't be any concept
of conserved energy in the world
because so much of physics has
to do with electric and magnetic forces.
Almost everything in our,
uh,
electric,
magnetic,
and gravitational.
And the only thing in the basic principles of physics
that guarantee that there's a
concept of energy and momentum,
uh,
is the principle of least action
and the formulation of mechanics and
field theory in terms of a Lagrangian.
So it's not,
it's not just,
you know,
just because it's pretty or not just because,
uh,
we like,
ideas like the principle of least action.
It is really important to derive
theories from a principle of least action
because if you don't,
none of the rules about the connection between
symmetries and conserved quantities make any sense.
The connection between symmetries and conserved quantities,
that includes energy conservation,
momentum conservation,
charge conservation,
all of those things are dependent on the,
uh,
on the principles of mechanics
that are embodied in the Lagrangian
or in the principle of least action.
Okay,
so,
let's,
uh,
let's try to invent
a theory of electricity and magnetism
assuming some basic principles.
Two basic principles,
really.
I'm not sure in which order to write them down.
So I'll write them down in the
order that we learned about these things.
Uh,
and they're,
they're quite independent.
The two basic principles are,
first of all,
Lorentz invariance.
In other words,
Lorentz invariance,
in other words,
the special theory of relativity.
It's all,
this and this alone,
which guarantees,
for example,
that the speed of light is
the same in every reference frame.
Uh,
Lorentz invariance includes rotational invariance.
And so,
this is the basic symmetry of space and time,
if you like.
It also includes the idea that
things don't depend on the position
that you do the experiment.
If you translated everything,
it would stay the same.
If you rotated everything,
If you subject it to a velocity boost
and examine a system from a moving reference frame,
it should stay the same.
It should have the same consequences.
All right,
so Lorentz invariance,
is one basic principle.
And Lorentz invariance is very simple
from the point of view of the Lagrangian.
All you have to do is make
sure that the Lagrangian density is a scalar.
That's all.
So it's easy.
All right,
so Lagrangian density should be a scalar.
Next,
a little less familiar,
but also not very difficult,
is gauge invariance.
Gauge invariance.
Let me remind you about gauge invariance.
Where it came from was requiring
that a certain scalar field Lagrangian
should be invariant when we did
this kind of change of phase,
the E to the I epsilon,
and that epsilon be a function of position.
But let me remind you what
the bottom line in the end was.
The bottom line in the end
was that we had to invent,
in order to implement that symmetry,
we had to invent the idea of a vector potential.
What we had to do was
replace the derivative of the scalar field
with respect to position,
which is not invariant under gauge transformation.
If we multiply the scalar field by
E to the I epsilon of X,
then,
in taking the derivative here,
there are terms where the derivative
of epsilon is just not invariant.
What do we have to do?
Anybody remember what we had to
do in order to make the Lagrangian
of the scalar field gauge invariant?
You had to add another term.
Right.
We had to change from the ordinary derivative
to what is called the covariant derivative.
We had to add to this plus IE,
vector potential times phi.
If at the same time that we multiply phi
by E to the I epsilon X,
if at the same time we transform A
to A plus,
plus the epsilon by the X,
and I think I should have
a one over electric charge there.
If we change the vector potential in this way,
whenever we do such a transformation,
then this covariant derivative,
this so-called covariant derivative,
doesn't change.
It's invariant.
So if we build a Lagrangian,
instead of just that of d phi by the X,
we write the covariant derivative.
This incidentally is often represented as d mu phi.
If we build the Lagrangian not wherever we originally saw
the derivative of phi,
we write the covariant derivative of phi,
then the Lagrangian is gauge invariant.
But that was the origin of
this idea of a vector potential.
The vector potential is necessary to soak up
the change that would happen in the ordinary derivative
when we multiply by E
to the I epsilon of X.
All right,
but having,
now that we have A,
we can ask,
first of all,
what kind of Lagrangians can we cook up
which are gauge invariant?
What kind of Lagrange densities can we cook up
that are gauge invariant?
Before we do that,
we should ask what kind of structures,
what kind of combinations can we make
that are gauge invariant?
And the simplest answer,
the simplest thing that we can make,
which is gauge invariant,
out of A,
what is A?
How many components does A have?
Four.
Time component also.
This is a four vector.
Its fourth component,
its time component,
is the electrostatic,
is the electric potential.
Is what's usually called the potential.
In any case,
there are four components.
The three of them,
the three space components,
are often just called the vector potential,
but in a relativistic setting,
all,
there are four components to the vector potential.
Okay.
So,
A then,
has an index which runs over the usual space-time indices.
A itself is not gauge invariant.
How do I know?
Because it transforms.
It changes when you do a gauge transformation.
It goes to A plus something.
So A is not gauge invariant.
But to make a long story short,
the simplest thing which is gauge invariant
is a tensor,
a thing with,
a thing with two indices,
a mu index and a nu index.
And here it is.
You differentiate the mu component of A
with respect to the nu component of position.
This means derivative,
for example,
this could contain something like
derivative of AX,
with respect to Y.
The nu would be,
correspond to Y,
mu would correspond to X.
There are also terms for time components,
but let's just write down.
That's a thing with two components.
It is a tensor,
but we don't really need
to know what a tensor is
for these purposes.
It is what it is.
Derivative with respect to nu of A mu.
Now,
what happens to this object
when you subject A
to such a transformation?
What happens is it picks up an extra term.
So let's look at it.
Here's A mu.
What about the derivative of A mu
with respect to X nu?
What it does,
is it just goes to
D nu A mu
plus one over E,
and then the second derivative
of epsilon
with respect to X nu
with respect to X mu.
The second partial derivative
with respect to nu and mu.
This is the change that happens
when you do a gauge transformation
to this particular combination.
This is not gauge invariant.
It changes.
But notice that this change here
is symmetric
under the interchange of nu and mu.
The process of differentiation,
it doesn't matter which order
you differentiate.
Process of differentiation
with respect to two coordinates commute.
Commute means it doesn't matter
which order you apply those two operations.
And that means that if I
subtract from this minus,
D mu A nu,
this term will cancel.
Why?
Because this term is symmetric
when I interchange mu and nu.
And so when I subtract
the same object with the opposite
ordering of mu and nu,
or the opposite dependence on mu and nu,
this term will cancel.
And the result is that this object,
D mu A nu,
which is called F mu nu,
that's gauge invariant.
It will not change
when you do a gauge transformation.
How many such objects are there?
How many components does it have?
Well,
offhand,
mu and nu
can run from one to four.
So it looks like there's 16 independent components
of F mu nu.
Not so.
And the reason is that this is anti-symmetric.
If you interchange mu and nu,
it changes sign.
So that means,
for example,
that F1 2 is just equal to minus F2 1.
F1 3 is minus F3 1.
So the different components of F mu nu
are not independent.
It's anti-symmetric.
How many components of an anti-symmetric mu nu
matrix are there in four dimensions?
All the diagonal components are zero.
In other words,
if I said,
if nu and mu are the same,
these two terms will cancel.
F1 1,
what is F1 1?
F1 1 is equal to the derivative
with respect to X1 of A1
minus the derivative with respect to X1 of A1.
So it's zero.
The diagonal elements are all zero.
And the off-diagonal elements
have opposite sign
when you interchange the two indices.
So how many of them are all together?
Six.
Six independent.
You can think of it as a matrix.
A 4x4 matrix.
16 to start with.
Zero on the diagonal.
And all of them are independent.
The off-diagonal,
the off-diagonal,
there are six off-diagonal
above the
six over there and another six over here.
But the other six over here are just the negatives
of the ones over here.
So there are six independent components.
And those six independent components
are nothing but
the electric and magnetic fields.
The components of the electric and magnetic fields.
Let me write them down for you.
We start with F.
Let's start with F01.
By definition,
this is the derivative
with respect to X0.
X0 is time.
So it's just a time derivative
of A1.
One could stand for the X component.
So F01.
F01 would be
derivative of A1 with respect to X0
minus
the derivative of A0
with respect to X1.
Same thing
if I replace 1 by 2 and 3.
So there are three components
which are of the form
F0,
X,
Y,
or Z.
Those three components form
the electric field.
This is E1.
The X component of the electric field
would be the derivative
of the X component of the vector potential
with respect to time
minus the derivative of the time component
of the vector potential with respect to X1.
With respect to X.
So,
that's the...
We have three components of the electric field.
And now we also have three additional components.
Let me tell you their connection
with the magnetic field.
That's a little...
This one was sort of obvious...
easy.
If not obvious,
The other one is also not difficult.
First of all,
F12.
That's got to be...
For example,
the XY component.
Let's use X and Y now.
I'm only interested in space components now.
And so...
The other three components
do not involve a time index.
Why not?
Well,
these three involve a time index.
The only thing...
The other thing that could involve a time index
would be F00.
There is no F00.
So the other three components involve
pairs of space indices.
For example,
FXY.
And I'm now using X for 1
and Y for 2.
Just to make sure.
I don't have to be specific.
FXY is equal to the derivative...
Let's see which way it works.
Derivative with respect to X
of AY
minus the derivative with respect to YAX.
Now,
the only thing that's left
is the components of the magnetic field.
So this must be some component of the magnetic field.
Which component of the magnetic field?
Z.
We have a...
By some sort of symmetry,
how could...
It could only be the Z component.
It is the Z component.
So this is the Z component of the magnetic field.
And then to get the other ones,
you just cycle again.
X to Y,
Y to Z,
Z back to X.
So,
FXYZ
that's equal to
DYAZ
minus DZ.
And that's what?
That's B...
What comes after Z?
X.
And the last one,
FXYZ,
YZX
is equal to XYZ,
minus dot dot dot.
And that's equal to BY.
So,
this is the connection.
Between...
This also says that curl of A.
Another way to write this is that
curl of A is equal to B.
Alright,
so that's the other...
Electric fields involve a time
component and a space component.
They also involve a time derivative.
But the magnetic field never
has a time derivative in it.
It only has space derivatives in it.
Okay,
that's the...
That's the electromagnetic field tensor.
And the important thing about
it is that it's gauge invariant.
In fact,
it's the simplest thing that you can
make up out of the vector potential
that is gauge invariant.
Yes?
Is there any condition on A at all?
Not at this point.
At this point,
A is just an arbitrary...
Arbitrary vector.
Well,
apart from smoothness and differentiability,
right.
No,
no condition on it.
In fact,
there's an ambiguity in its definition,
because you can always do a gauge transformation on it.
So,
it's quite free to vary in any way.
Okay.
Now we want to build a Lagrangian.
Lagrangians typically involve fields
and their time derivatives.
Ah,
sorry.
Fields and their various derivatives.
The field A by itself,
if undifferentiated,
is not gauge invariant.
There's no way to put
into the Lagrangian the field undifferentiated
without destroying the gauge invariance.
A by itself is not gauge invariant.
You can make the Lagrangian out of A by itself.
It's just any combination of the F's.
Anything that involves F is gauge invariant,
since F itself is gauge invariant.
Gauge invariance is not enough to tell you what
combinations of F's to put together in what form.
The other thing that goes in is Lorentz invariance.
If we have F mu nu in our Lagrangian,
and we want to make a scalar,
the simplest scalar that we can make
is just to multiply it by F mu nu again
and contract the indices in the
way that we've learned how to do
some Einstein summation convention.
As long as the indices are contracted,
contracted means just summed over when they're repeated,
we make a scalar.
All right.
There's in fact a minus a quarter,
but that's mostly convention.
There's a minus a quarter,
but as I said,
that's simply a convention.
And it...
Of course,
whenever anybody puts a minus a
quarter in a thing like this,
you know that what it does is
it removes a 4 from some later equation.
And it does.
It removes 4s from Maxwell equations there.
But it's arbitrary.
It could be absorbed into changes
of the electric and magnetic field.
So it's not important.
The important thing is that it's gauge invariant
because it's made out of F,
and it's Lorentz invariant because
its indices have been correctly grouped
and summed over.
That's the Lagrangian of the electromagnetic field.
Okay?
Lagrangian density.
And what is it?
Let's write it out.
1 over 4.
Partial derivative of a mu with respect to x nu.
Remember what indices upstairs mean.
They mean exactly the same thing as indices downstairs,
except for the time component where you change sign.
So for example,
if there's a time component in either mu or nu,
then it flips sign relative.
So it's relative to the
original definition of F mu nu.
So it's just a question of signs,
whether the indices are upstairs or downstairs.
Minus d mu a nu.
That's the field tensor with the upstairs indices.
And we multiply it by the
field tensor with the downstairs indices.
d mu.
Do I have it right?
I think I might have the...
mu,
nu,
I think I should have mu and nu.
nu and mu.
This stands for various squares and sums of squares
of various components of the electric and magnetic field.
I'll write it out in terms of
the electric and magnetic field in a moment.
But let me just point out what it is.
It's a thing which is quadratic
in various derivatives of the field.
And the thing which is quadratic
in the derivative of the field
in that respect,
it's not so different than
d mu phi d mu phi.
It's quadratic in derivatives.
It's more complicated because it has more components.
But again,
each term is something which is the
product of a derivative of a field
times another derivative of a field.
So this is a
Lagrangian which involves quadratic expressions.
In other words,
things which are products of two field derivatives
summed in various ways.
So it's not so different
than previous Lagrangians that we've studied.
In the case of the scalar field,
without violating any symmetry,
I think we had a star here,
for example,
in the case of the complex field,
we were also able to
add m squared phi star phi,
maybe minus.
There is nothing wrong with that.
The thing that we can add to
this that doesn't involve derivatives of the field
or something like adding a squared or something like that,
no good.
a squared is not gauge invariant.
Or a mu a mu.
You might think,
well,
why can't we add a mu a mu?
It's Lorentz invariant,
but it's not gauge invariant.
It changes when you let a go
to a plus the derivative of epsilon.
So this is not gauge invariant.
Otherwise,
it's perfectly good.
Lorentz invariant,
perfectly good.
Perfectly acceptable Lagrangian from
every other point of view,
but it's not gauge invariant.
So this is the Lagrangian of electrodynamics.
Let me tell you what it has in it.
Let's look at it.
It has various squares,
various products of the components of f.
What is it?
It's f mu nu f mu nu.
It's proportional to sums of
squares or differences of squares
depending on which component we're talking about.
It comes in with a
plus sign or a minus sign.
For example,
here's f naught 1 f naught 1.
Now,
what is f naught 1 with lower index here?
Anybody remember?
E1 or Ex.
What is it with the upper index here?
When you raise a space component index,
nothing happens.
When you raise a time component index,
the sign changes.
So this is proportional to minus Ex squared.
There's a minus Ex squared.
Well,
there's another term here,
which is f 1 naught f 1 naught.
But that's exactly the same thing.
Why?
Because f 1 naught is just minus f.
You know,
this is minus this,
this is minus this.
The two terms here just double this.
The dividing by 4,
that makes it divided by 2.
And then the minus here just changes it to plus.
So the terms involving f naught 1,
f naught 2,
f naught 3,
they just give you the sums of
the squares of the electric field components.
Ey squared plus Ez squared.
That's what's in the Lagrangian
from the mixed space-time components.
What about the space-space components?
Again,
minus a quarter.
Let's look at one of them.
The mixed space-space components could have f 1 2,
f 1 2.
What is f 1 2 times f 1 2?
First of all,
what is f 1 2?
It's b 3.
b 3.
Maybe it's minus b 3.
I don't remember,
but we're squaring it so it doesn't matter.
Now,
here I've raised both indices.
What happens when you raise two space indices?
Nothing.
So f 1 2 upper is the
same as f 1 2 band lower.
This is just b 3 squared.
This is b 3 squared.
There's a minus a quarter.
So I get minus a quarter b 3 squared.
But why is it minus a
half and not minus a quarter?
Because there's another term,
which is 2 1 2 1.
So it's b 3 squared
divided by 2 plus b f.
b 3 means b z squared plus
b y squared plus b z squared.
The net offset is Lagrangian is simply
one half of e squared minus b.
One half of the electric field
squared minus the magnetic field squared.
All right.
So e squared minus b squared.
We did a little bit funny.
It involves the electric field and
magnetic field sort of almost symmetrically,
but not quite.
One comes in with a negative sign.
The other comes in with a positive sign.
Hm?
うん
Let's look at the electric field again.
The electric field
involves
I'm going to be a little sketchy right now
because we don't have time
but nevertheless
sketchy or not the argument is correct
the electric field
which is f
naught one for example
contains things like derivative with respect
to x naught that means derivative with
respect to time
times a one
it also contains another term but
it's irrelevant for my argument right now
when I square it
this gives me some time derivative squared
contains some time derivative squared
what kind of terms in
Lagrangian involve time derivative squared?
kinetic energy
so this is similar to the kinetic energy
in the Lagrangian of a system
it's similar to the
phi dot squared term
you know the time derivative of phi squared
it's similar to x dot squared
so this is
the kinetic energy of the field
now when I say kinetic
energy I just mean it contains
time derivatives squared
this contains no time derivatives
the magnetic field contains no time derivatives
things which don't contain time derivatives we think of as
potential energy
so this has the form of kinetic energy
minus potential energy
that's exactly the way Lagrangians are supposed to look
it's analogous to the scalar field of Lagrangian
which has phi dot squared time derivative squared
again a half
minus
the space derivative
squared
the Lagrangian
exactly the same kind of structure
time derivatives squared
minus things which don't contain time derivatives
what would you guess if you go through the procedures
of constructing the Hamiltonian and then the energy
what would you expect the energy
or the Hamiltonian of the electromagnetic field to be?
plus
so the energy in the electromagnetic field
is just e squared plus b squared
if you work out
you know if we go through the
entire apparatus of classical mechanics and so forth
we would actually define
discover that the energy of the Hamiltonian is this
and the Hamiltonian is conserved
it's a general principle
and so this is energy
this is energy and it's conservation
e squared plus b squared is conserved
or not conserved
should I say
is this the energy?
did I make a mistake?
I did I forgot to integrate it over space
that's the energy density
you integrate it over space
in other words you account for all the
degrees of freedom at each point in space
and that becomes the energy
so the integral of e squared
plus b squared over all space
is conserved
it's not conserved at each point of space
energy can move from one point of space to another
so without the integral what we
had originally would be the Lagrangian density?
no without the integral it's the energy density
with a minus sign it's the Lagrangian
oh yes that's right
with a minus sign it would be the Lagrangian density
and with a plus sign it's the Hamiltonian density
but that just means the energy density
ah
okay
um now
next
the equations of motion
these guys here
I'm only gonna go I'm gonna go again sketch it
the equations of motion
what do we do
we take the Lagrangian
where did I write it
I lost it
um
alright so it's
d mu a mu
minus d mu a mu
times d mu a mu
incidentally
and I said there was a minus a quarter here
alright let me wasn't
I'm sorry
alright let me round through the equation
this is placed on a chart
let's say today
I want some
our
um
squared with a plus a quarter.
Yeah.
This,
of course,
is just the square of the electric field.
All right.
Let's take the derivative of the Lagrangian
with respect to d0 a1.
What is it?
Can anybody differentiate this expression
with respect to this argument here?
No,
no,
no.
We want to differentiate with respect to the derivative.
We want to calculate the derivative of the Lagrangian
with respect to d0 a1.
In other words,
with respect to this variable here.
Right.
Well,
put a 2,
but it cancels the quarter,
so that's a half.
I think I've already...
I think there should only be a half here.
There is only a half there.
So the half goes away.
And what else do you get?
You get...
d0 a1 minus d1 a0.
The derivative with respect to this variable here...
How do you do it?
You just differentiate the square of something.
It's just a square of something.
You just differentiate.
You get twice the something.
That's it.
In other words,
it's just f0 1.
All right.
That's generalizable very easily.
I'll write down what the general formula is.
If I differentiate the Lagrangian with...
Question?
Oh,
is that e1,
ex?
It's e1.
But let me write down the general formula.
The derivative of the Lagrangian with
respect to the derivative of a mu
with respect to x nu.
All right.
That is nothing but...
It's got two indices.
Mu and nu.
What's it going to be?
What could it be except for f mu nu?
And it is.
Just like we showed that the derivative of the
Lagrangian with respect to d0 a1 is f0 1,
the general formula of this
type is just f mu nu.
Now we can work out the equation of motion.
Well,
we're supposed to be able to do that.
What we're supposed to do is
take each one of these derivatives.
Here.
Here's an example.
Here it is.
That's the formula we're using.
Okay.
We take each one of these derivatives
and differentiate it with respect to the same
index that occurs inside the derivative over here.
That means d by dx nu.
So the Euler-Lagrange equations just become...
Do I have this...
I think I have it right.
Yeah.
d by...
Just a moment.
Let me just...
This is...
Yeah,
I think it's right.
I think I have a mistake here.
Let's see.
Yeah.
Some index belongs upstairs that...
That's lower.
They don't match.
You have a mu down...
X mu downstairs and an X nu downstairs.
This is a lower index.
I guess this should be upward.
So,
oh.
wait.
So,
yeah,
yeah.
I think it's f mu nu upstairs.
Right?
This is a lower index in the denominator.
So that makes it an upper index.
And this is a lower index
in the denominator of a fraction here.
Yeah,
yeah,
yeah.
It's f mu nu,
both of them upstairs.
Okay.
So what's our equation of motion?
Differentiate with respect to X mu f mu nu.
That's the left-hand side.
But what's the right-hand side?
It's just zero.
So the Lagrangian doesn't depend
on the vector potential itself.
So that's it.
Which Maxwell equations are...
What equations are these?
These are...
This and this.
Without the J.
I have not told you what
to do if there's a current.
If there's a current,
the Lagrangian has to be modified a little bit.
Okay.
But without the current,
how many equations are these?
How many equations do I have here?
Four equations.
One equation and three more.
That's exactly what these equations are.
In particular,
if you plug in for f...
For example,
let's take a little piece of it.
Let's take d nought of f nought nu.
What else do we have?
We have plus...
d1 of f1 nu plus d2 of
f2 nu plus d3 of f3 nu.
This is what's on the left-hand side,
and that's equal to zero.
Let's see what's there.
We have to pick a nu.
Pick a nu for me.
Which nu do you want to study?
Okay.
Then if we pick zero,
this will be zero.
Because f0,
0 is zero.
And this will be d1 of f1,
0 plus d2 of f2,
0 plus d3 of f3,
0.
What is f1,
0?
It's the first component of the electric field.
So it's the derivative of the first component
of the electric field with respect to x,
y,
z.
So it's x1 plus the derivative of the second
component of the electric field with respect to x2,
plus the derivative of the third component
of the electric field with respect to x3.
This is the divergence of the electric field.
So in the absence of charges,
if we don't have any charges around,
any charge density,
that just becomes del dot e equals zero.
Let's look at another one.
Let's look at...
Let's see.
We looked at the time component.
Let's look at the time component.
Let's look at the one component.
So now,
let's look at the one component.
If we look at the one component,
we have...
derivative with respect to time of f0,
1.
I've set nu...
I'm setting nu equal to 1 now.
So d0,
f0,
1.
Plus...
Now,
we have d1,
f1,
1,
but that's zero.
f1,
1 is zero.
And then we have plus d by dx2
of f21 plus d by dx3 of f31,
I believe.
Is that correct?
I think that's correct.
Okay,
what's this term here?
That's the time derivative of the electric field.
That's this one.
What's over here?
Well,
it's a little bit complicated,
but what do we have?
f21 is b3.
So this is second derivative...
The derivative with respect to x2 of b3.
And this one,
if you work it out,
is the other term.
That corresponds to curl of b.
Curl of b.
So the Euler-Lagrange equations are
two of the Maxwell equations.
The other two Maxwell equations are identities.
They are not equations of motion.
They just follow from the definition
of the electric and magnetic field.
This is something you can check.
I'll allow you to check it.
They just follow from the fact that the
electric and magnetic fields are defined in this way.
You don't have to do any work.
It just follows from the structure you've written down.
If you work out the other components,
1 and 3.
1,
3,
yeah.
Okay.
So this is an example then that
the Maxwell equations follow from the Euler-Lagrange equations,
for an action.
And that same action has
a Hamiltonian that's associated with it,
which is e squared plus b squared.
So we have a package.
The package just comes from
the simple expression for the Lagrangian,
F mu nu squared.
Just the simplest gauge invariant
thing you could have written down.
Simplest gauge invariant,
Lorentz invariant thing.
And all of electromagnetism without charges.
Without any charges in it.
All of it follows from
this very simple minus a quarter.
Well,
here it is.
Minus a quarter,
F mu nu,
F mu nu.
Okay.
Very simple.
So while you have a load of equations here,
complicated,
it all boils down or it
all derives from one simple expression
for a principle of least action,
if you like.
All right.
The last thing I'm going to do
is tell you how currents come into this.
Now,
we could just be thinking about charged particles.
Charged particles are an example of a current.
But let's imagine now that we
have a four vector of current.
J mu.
Now,
J mu is the electric current.
In some way or another,
it has to couple to the electromagnetic field.
There must be terms in
the Lagrangian which involve J mu.
Why is that?
Well,
where is J mu in these equations?
Here's the time component.
This is nothing but the time component of J.
And here are the space components of J.
Here are the space components of J over here.
So J enters into the equations of motion.
It must enter into the Lagrangian.
What kind of simple connection,
what kind of additional term in the
Lagrangian can we put in that involves J?
J is a vector,
a four vector,
a four vector.
We've got to do something to soak up this index.
What is there around?
There's the vector potential.
That's the only four vector
that we have to work with.
So let's try J mu,
A mu.
In other words,
we just take the four
dimensional product of J with A,
sum it over the indices,
and that becomes part of
the Lagrangian of the electromagnetic field.
Now for all my purposes now,
let's just imagine somebody gave us the current.
They told us what the current was.
I'm not going to,
we don't have time to study
the equations and how J varies.
Let's just imagine somebody told us what J is.
Alright?
Is this gauge invariant?
So what do you think?
Gauge invariant or not?
You have to say how J
is going to vary with the gauge.
We have to say something about how J,
oh,
J,
sorry,
good.
Things which are gauge invariant are ambiguous.
You can change,
you can change them without changing any of the physics.
Gauge invariant,
gauge covariant,
things which vary when you do a gauge transformation
are not physically observable things.
The physical observables are the gauge invariant quantities.
Alright?
So the electromagnetic current is an observable quantity.
It's not something that changes when
you do a mathematical gauge transformation.
So J is gauge invariant.
It really is the flow of current.
You can measure it.
It had better not vary
when you do a gauge transformation.
Otherwise it would be something which would be ambiguous.
It's not ambiguous.
So given that J is invariant,
is J a gauge invariant?
Not obvious.
In fact,
obviously not.
Except if J satisfies some special property.
So let's see if it changes
when you do a gauge transformation.
Let's see,
where can we do this?
I guess we can do it down here.
What happens to J a
when you gauge transformation transform a?
J mu a mu will change to J mu a
mu plus one over the electric charge times d mu epsilon.
That's the way the vector potential changed.
One over epsilon.
In other words,
J mu a mu changes.
The change in J mu a mu is,
the change in J a is
J mu d mu epsilon integral,
I guess there's a one over electric charge.
So the answer is,
it's not gauge invariant.
It has changed by this much.
But now let me do a trial.
The trick is called integration by parts.
If you have an integral over space,
or space-time,
oh yes,
here's the integral that goes into the action.
If we integrate it over three-dimensional space,
it's part of the Lagrangian.
If we integrate it over four-dimensional space,
it becomes part of the action.
The real issue is whether the action is gauge invariant.
Or whether the Lagrangian itself.
If the action is gauge invariant,
then the physics will be gauge invariant.
Alright.
What do we do with this?
We integrate it by parts.
If you integrate a thing,
which is a product of one thing,
times a derivative of another,
you can interchange which object the derivative acts on.
Is this familiar to everybody?
Integration by parts?
Alright.
It's an identity.
You get a surface term.
Yeah,
you get a surface term,
but let's imagine integrating over all space-time,
to calculate the action over all space-time.
So assuming that very,
very far away,
the fields and the currents become zero,
far enough away,
then this is equal to minus one over E,
the integral of epsilon,
times d mu,
j mu.
Now,
this is the change
in this term in the action
due to gauge transformation.
You recognize this thing?
Say it again?
Yeah,
d4x.
But do you recognize this?
That's the continuity equation.
Remember the continuity equation.
The continuity equation was the equation that said
that if a charge changes in a box,
the only way it can change in the box
is by flowing through the surface of the box.
A time dependence of the charge
necessarily goes with a space dependence of the current,
of the space components of the current.
So,
the time dependence of the charge
And that we distilled down,
we studied it last time,
and we found out that the continuity equation,
the local conservation of charge,
was exactly this equation.
d mu,
sorry,
j mu,
is equal to zero.
This is also the equation
that says the time derivative
of the charge density
plus the divergence
of the three-dimensional,
just the usual current,
should be equal to zero.
The only way that the
charge in a region can change
is if there's a divergence of the current,
which corresponds to current flowing out of the region,
out or into the region.
So this equation here
is
d mu,
j mu equals zero.
The continuity equation
is the necessary and sufficient condition
for the action to be gauge invariant.
As long as j
is a conserved four vector,
in other words,
as long as it corresponds to a
conserved flow of electric charge,
the density together with the
space component of the current,
then this is gauge invariant.
That's a beautiful fact,
that gauge invariance requires
the current to be conserved.
We didn't even use any
equation of motion for the current.
We just used the fact,
or the assumption,
that the theory was gauge invariant,
and from that we derived
that the continuity equation must be true.
So,
this term,
is the
which is there
if there are currents and charges,
is gauge invariant
under the assumption of the continuity equation.
So let's just add it in,
plus j mu a mu.
Now,
now that it's there,
we have,
it will modify the equations
for the electric and magnetic field.
If we go back,
and calculate
the equations of motion,
there's now a new term,
it's basically the right hand side here,
of differentiating Lagrangian with respect to a.
What do I get if I
differentiate the Lagrangian with respect to a?
I get j.
So,
the answer is that there is another term
on the right hand side
of the Maxwell equations,
which involve
the current,
and charge density themselves.
I'll just tell you right now,
that it's this,
and this.
So if you go through this Lagrangian,
work out the Euler Lagrange equations,
you'll find some additional terms on the right hand side,
which are the current,
the charge density,
and the current.
I'll leave that for you to do.
The charge density is the current,
the charge density
and the charge density,
So B3,
or BZ,
I guess,
when I'm being very specific
and working only with space components,
I'll use X,
Y,
and Z.
BZ was DXAY minus DYAX,
right?
B,
Z,
X,
X goes to Y,
Y goes to Z.
B minus DZAY,
right?
And finally,
B,
what are we left out?
BY,
XYZ,
DZ,
Y,
X,
Z,
oops,
DZAX minus DXAY.
Now,
this is the definition of B.
let's check.
I've made no assumption whatever about the
way that the A's are varying in space.
In fact,
I made no assumption,
because all I did was,
I just defined something.
Okay,
now let's check whether del
dot B is equal to zero.
Well,
why should it be equal to zero?
I've made no assumption about the way A is varying.
Let's check it anyway.
That means we have to
differentiate this with respect to Z.
So let's differentiate it with respect to...
Hmm?
All right,
let's check them.
That means we have to take
another derivative with respect to Z,
and another derivative with respect to Z here.
There's no Z components.
They depend on Z.
A,
X,
and Y,
and Z all depend on Z.
They all depend on all the coordinates.
So we get DZ,
DX,
AY minus DZ,
DY,
AX.
This means multiple derivatives,
second derivatives.
All right,
let's see if we can find...
Well,
let's write them all out there.
And then we have to
differentiate this with respect to X.
That means put a derivative with respect to Z.
With respect to X there.
And another derivative with respect to X.
And finally,
a derivative with respect to Y here.
This gives us DY.
And this gives us minus DY,
DX,
AZ.
Was that it?
Okay,
let's see what we have.
In particular,
let's track this term here.
This has an AY in it.
It has DZ,
DX.
It has AY with a plus sign.
Here's another term with AY.
It has DZ,
DX.
DX,
DZ.
It doesn't matter which order.
Right.
Opposite sign.
The order of a differentiation is immaterial.
And so this term and this term cancel.
And so it goes.
Let's see.
Let's do one more.
DZ,
DY,
AX with a minus sign.
DZ.
AX with a plus sign.
These cancel.
And so it goes.
All of them cancel.
It followed from a definition of B.
The structure of B was such by the definition,
B cannot be anything.
If B,
another way of saying it,
incidentally,
some of you may recognize another way of saying it,
B is equal to del cross A.
The divergence of a,
that means B is the curl of A.
No matter what A is,
it's a rule that the divergence
of a curl is equal to zero.
For any A,
the curl of A is B.
And from that it follows that
del dot B is equal to zero.
So it just follows this equation
is not an equation of motion.
It's just the definition of B or
a consequence of the definition of B.
So is this one,
consequences of the definition of B and E.
Definition in terms of the vector potential.
That's relatively easy to prove.
I won't prove it.
We did it for one of the equations.
You can check out yourself that if you
put in the definitions of B and E
in terms of the vector potential,
that this automatically is equal to zero.
Contains a bunch of terms and
they all cancel out among themselves.
So half of Maxwell's equations
are identities that follow from definition.
And the other half are equations,
equations of motion that follow
from the principle of least action.
And it is necessary to these
equations that the current is conserved.
Incidentally,
even if we didn't use gauge invariance,
even if we didn't care about gauge invariance,
but we stuck in,
let's just look at something else.
We have the Lagrangian,
which is minus a quarter F mu nu,
F mu nu.
And then I put in plus J dot A,
J mu,
A mu.
Let's work out,
I've already worked out what the equation of motion is
that comes just from the F mu nu terms.
I'll remind you what it is.
It was D mu,
I think,
F mu nu was equal to zero.
That was the equation,
that was,
how many equations are here?
There are four equations here,
one for each nu.
And that was this equation and this equation.
Four equations,
one,
two,
three,
four.
Now,
if the right hand side,
if the vector potential
appears undifferentiated in the Lagrangian,
that means there's a right
hand side to the Euler equation,
and there's a right hand side to the Lagrangian equation.
And what would it be?
It would be the derivative of
the Lagrangian with respect to A.
The result is that there will be
a right hand side of this equation,
which will be J nu.
Here is four equations with a right hand side,
which contains the four vector of current.
The time component involves the density,
the charge density,
that's this one.
And the others involve the space component,
that's the other component.
But I just wanted to point out one thing.
This is the equation of motion that
followed from adding this term to the Lagrangian.
Supposing I didn't know,
to begin with,
that J has to be conserved.
Suppose I didn't know that J had to be conserved.
I didn't know about all this gauge invariance garbage,
and I just tried out this term in the Lagrangian.
I would get this equation of motion,
and I would find out right now
that J has to be conserved.
We can check it.
Let's just differentiate it with respect to X mu.
In other words,
let's take D mu of this.
Oh,
sorry,
D nu of it.
Let's differentiate with respect to X nu.
That would be the continuity equation.
Is it equal to zero?
Well,
it's equal to D nu D mu.
F mu nu.
How about this?
What is this?
Zero.
Zero because it contains things like D1,
D2,
F12.
I guess it's F21.
But it also contains D2,
D2.
D1,
F12.
When I sum over mu and nu,
I get things like D1,
D2,
F21,
and D2,
D1,
F12.
These cancel because F12 and F21,
the derivatives are the same.
Second derivative with respect to 1 and 2,
F12 and F21,
they cancel.
So we would have discovered right here
that the equations of motion for F require,
that J is conserved.
We don't really have the option
of not allowing it to be conserved.
The equations of motion force it to be conserved.
So there are two independent arguments.
They're closely related,
but nevertheless,
two independent arguments.
One is gauge invariance.
We did that nice little integration by parts,
and we found out that the action
was gauge invariant if F is conserved.
But even if we didn't know that,
if Weyl had never taught us about gauge invariance,
at this point,
we would say Maxwell's equations,
this set of equations over here,
is inconsistent unless the current is conserved.
We can check it right from here.
We can differentiate this with respect to time,
and we can take the divergence
of some other equation over here,
and we can check that
the current will come out conserved.
So,
that's a package,
Lagrangian of a very simple form,
simplest thing we could have written down.
I'm a little confused.
Yeah.
It doesn't mean individually that
the charge density is conserved?
No.
And so how does the whole thing get conserved?
Charge density...
It means the sum of the
charge density plus the current is...
No.
The time derivative of the charge density,
plus the space derivative of the current equals zero.
Right.
Yeah.
This is more than just charge conservation.
It's local charge conservation that tells
us that the charge in a region
can only change if currents are
flowing into or out of that region.
So it's a stronger thing than just
saying the charge in the universe can't change.
It tells us...
What it says is the
charge only changes in a region
by moving into and out of that region.
And that's what this...
That's what the continuity equation says.
Where do we have it?
We lost it.
Well,
d nu equals zero.
So Maxwell's equations,
either in this form or in this form,
immediately tell us that the charge has to be conserved
for the Maxwell equations to make any sense at all.
Well,
it's actually buried in this term.
This term here,
and we're about finished.
And if we take for the current,
the current associated with a single particle,
and then we also add to the
Lagrangian one half mv squared for that part,
we'll get the Lorentz force law.
So we don't have time,
but it's in there.
It's in there.
Yeah.
So you're talking about the
two independent arguments to get conservation?
Yeah.
Well,
they're not independent,
of course.
But,
yeah,
but...
One from field equation,
the other from the gauge invariance.
Right.
Yeah.
That's right.
So they're intimately tied together.
And the principle of gauge invariance,
of course,
is much more general than just electromagnetism.
We don't have time for it.
But it appears in general relativity.
It appears in Yang-Mills theory.
Yes,
sir.
So if you had monopoles and magnetic currents,
then the little two equations wouldn't be
tautologies that you'd have to...
Right.
So how can a tautology be wrong?
Well,
exactly.
Right.
Exactly.
Okay.
That's right.
The answer is that the right
model for a monopole is the solenoid.
Mathematically,
the way monopoles are introduced into
the theory is as infinitely long solenoids
with magnetic field going through them and coming...
Oops,
I got to...
And...
So that the net divergence of the magnetic field
is zero by virtue of the fact that what
comes in goes out.
It's like a little source of water over here.
Yeah.
You know,
it's like we have water coming into a
puddle and causing the flow of water to
diverge away from some point at the center.
Well,
if we saw that happening,
we would say,
hey,
there must be a pipe coming in somewheres.
Okay.
If we account for the water that's coming
in through the pipe and then going out away
from the pipe,
the divergence of the flow would be zero.
So basically,
get rid of the monopole.
Get rid of the monopole and replace
it by the end of a long solenoid.
Right.
So that is the mathematical way
that the monopoles enter into the theory.
Now,
are they really infinitely long solenoids?
Well,
this is called a Dirac string,
incidentally.
This is called a Dirac string.
And under the right circumstances,
which we won't have time for,
but maybe another time,
this string can be completely invisible.
So...
But the mathematics of it is to pretend
that the monopole were connected to a long solenoid
like this.
What's that?
A black hole.
What about a black hole?
Well,
I mean,
you can have an infinitely long solenoid.
Well,
I mean,
you can have an infinitely long solenoid.
But it's not a black hole.
It's a trip into a black hole.
What's that got to do with it?
Oh,
I was just thinking that that could be the tube.
The black hole.
Yeah.
Well,
not really.
I mean,
if you surround...
The point is,
if you surround the black hole...
If you surround the monopole,
you should see a net
magnetic flux coming out of it,
which is equal to zero.
So if the magnetic flux appears,
it's equal to zero.
If it appears to be coming
into or out of the monopole,
there must be a secret hidden
flow of flux away from that point.
And it doesn't really matter whether this
is a black hole or anything else.
Yeah.
Okay,
ladies and gentlemen,
thank you for your attention.
And I will see you next year.
Next year,
we do some general relativity and black
hole physics and also some quantum field theory.
Oh,
no,
wait,
what did we say?
Yes.
And also some statistical mechanics.
Yeah,
general relativity and a little bit of
black holes and all those interesting questions
about gravity,
which we haven't touched on at all.
The quantum mechanics of fields...
Quantum mechanics of fields is basically simple.
It just says wherever you had a classical field,
now replace it by a collection of fields.
So it's a collection of quanta all moving together.
So really,
we've done it.
And statistical mechanics and thermodynamics and
maybe a little about phase transitions.
The preceding program is copyrighted by Stanford University.
Please visit us at stanford.edu.