This program is brought to you by Stanford University.
Please visit us at stanford.edu.
The question is,
can you defeat the uncertainty principle in the following
way?
You measure the position of an
object first to a poor accuracy.
It's somewhere in here,
somewhere within some region of size,
let's call it delta.
And then you wait a long,
long time,
and the particle is someplace else,
presumably,
and
you measure it again with the same poor accuracy.
So it's over here,
somewhere in delta again.
How far did it move?
The distance that,
oh,
and let's say we discover after having measured it.
That the center of these fuzzy regions,
the center of these fuzzy regions are separated
by some distance,
let's call it L.
All right,
so how well do we know the position?
We know the position,
or we know the separation.
Let's talk about the separation.
We know the separation is L
plus or minus something of order delta.
In other words,
the delta is the distance.
The distance of separation is L
with a fuzziness or an uncertainty,
which is of order delta.
Two delta or a half delta,
that's not the important thing.
Now we want to find
out how fast it was moving,
so we divide it by the time.
That's the amount of time between the two measurements.
What's the uncertainty in the velocity?
The uncertainty in the velocity,
the velocity is L over T.
So it's the average velocity,
plus or minus delta over T.
And if we make T big enough,
if we make T big enough,
delta over T can be arbitrarily
small.
So it seems,
then,
that we can measure the position to accuracy delta,
but the velocity
to arbitrary accuracy,
because delta over T gets smaller and smaller.
Now,
the answer to this is.
done is we've measured,
what we wanted to do was
to measure the position and velocity
at a time just before the measurement was done.
We want to know at a particular instant
of time,
right now,
I want to try to measure
the position and velocity sort of simultaneously.
Or I want to know both position and velocity.
Well,
the problem here is that you don't know
the velocity or the momentum as accurately as you thought,
not if you meant the velocity
before you measured,
before you began the measurement.
Before you began the measurement,
the particle had a certain momentum.
And then in order to measure it to within accuracy
delta,
you had to hit it with
a photon of wavelength delta or smaller,
and that in itself
will change the velocity.
So you're measuring the velocity by an
amount which is given by the uncertainty principle,
h bar over delta.
What you're doing here is
you're measuring the velocity accurately,
but the velocity after you made
the first initial measurement of position.
That velocity
is a little bit different than the initial
velocity because in order to measure the position,
you had to hit it with a photon.
So you're not measuring what you wanted to measure,
which was the original position and
velocity simultaneously.
You're measuring the position now to some accuracy,
but then
the velocity after you gave
it a shot with the photon.
So it's not what the uncertainty
principle really talks about.
Okay,
let's...
Yeah?
Yes.
Yes,
but you don't know the velocity anymore because...
You don't know the velocity right before you hit it.
Well,
you don't know the velocity afterwards.
So if you try to repeat the measurement of
velocity to check it,
you discover that it was a little different.
It's a question of
repeatability.
You know already that with this simple,
summoned sensor,
here .
It's different since in this case the battery's on
little rut frets not equal to three Pre betrayal
bit of a kick to the
velocity and you won't know it afterwards.
It says what it says,
and you're perfectly right.
I mean,
there's something funny,
but it says what it says,
and what it says in this case is you
can't check that that was the velocity without changing
it by an amount of order h-bar over delta.
So you may think that that was the velocity.
I think I measured it,
but now you try to check it.
And in classical physics,
you can
measure the position arbitrarily gently
and not affect the velocity.
In quantum mechanics,
not so.
Okay,
so let's see.
So are we ready to begin?
Yeah,
we're ready to begin.
Okay.
What I want to do before I do anything
else is just an exceedingly quick review of complex
numbers.
Just a...
Okay.
Not because I really want to teach you complex numbers.
I presume everybody knows about complex
numbers,
but because...just for some notational reasons.
Incidentally,
we're going to be continuing
with linear vector spaces for a while.
It's a somewhat dry subject.
That's the bad news.
The good news is it's a very easy subject.
So once you get it...
You should be...it should be easy enough.
Thank you,
Michael.
But it does pay to spend
a...Michael,
say hello to your mother.
You're on TV.
Okay.
So let's just remind ourselves very quickly
about a property or two of complex
numbers.
Not all about complex numbers,
just one or two properties.
I'm going to give you
a couple of examples of some of the properties
that I want to remind you of because we'll
see things very similar to them later.
Okay.
Ah,
before we even do that,
let me just mention
about linear vector spaces.
Linear vector spaces are composed of objects which you can
multiply by numbers and add.
You can add them and multiply them by numbers.
And in fact,
complex vector spaces are things that you
can multiply by complex numbers and you can
add them.
That's the...
That's what defines a complex vector space.
The simplest complex vector space is,
of course,
just the complex numbers.
The complex numbers,
you can multiply them by other complex numbers
and you can add them.
So the complex numbers by themselves
are a very simple linear vector
space.
I just want to tell you that and
then we can examine the complex numbers a little
bit.
A complex number is just two real numbers.
Added together with i,
x plus i y,
x is called the real part,
y is called the imaginary part,
and i is the square root of minus one.
All arithmetic,
or let's call it algebra,
all
elementary algebra,
multiplication of complex numbers,
addition of complex numbers,
is exactly
the same as if they were ordinary numbers,
except you must remember that i squared is
minus one.
That's all.
That's...
That's
all.
That's all.
All of that
that's the theory of complex numbers in a nutshell.
Every complex number can be represented
as a point on the XY plane.
Don't confuse this XY plane with any vector space.
It's
just the XY plane.
So every point in the complex
plane has an x and a y,
and it can be plotted.
And it's
usual to call it z.
It's common terminology for complex numbers.
If we wanted to remember...
the complex numbers of vector spaces,
that they can be added and use the notation
that we started to use last time for vector spaces,
namely that a vector in a vector
space is often represented in quantum mechanics,
in any case,
in a complex vector space,
by a ket vector,
just a symbol,
Dirac's famous symbol that looks like this,
then we might just describe,
we might just say the complex numbers are very,
very simple vectors in a simple vector space.
In fact,
as we'll see,
it's just a one-dimensional vector space,
as we'll see.
Complex numbers,
just in the same sense that the real numbers can
be thought of as vectors on a line in one dimension.
The complex numbers are a complex vector space.
Of one dimension.
We'll find out eventually what dimension means,
but for the moment,
let's just not worry about that.
Now,
every complex number has associated
with it a complex conjugate.
The complex conjugate is usually represented
by putting a star over it,
and it's just the same real part minus Iy.
And so what it is,
is it's the reflection,
it's the reflection as if
the horizontal axis was a mirror.
Just the reflection about the x-axis,
that's called z star.
Another way that we could represent it,
if we were using the notation of complex vector spaces,
would be that way.
This is called the Bra vector.
This is called the ket vector.
When you put one next to another,
it's called a bra ket or a bracket.
Really,
the Bra vectors are really basically
just complex conjugates of the ket vectors.
So if we were just
dealing with a one-dimensional vector space,
complex vector space,
just the complex numbers,
we might easily use the notation z and z star,
or ket z and Bra z,
and they would mean essentially the same thing.
Okay,
let me just point out one
more important property that we will use,
and we'll use the analog of it for vector spaces.
The reason I'm doing this now is to do something in
a very simple context that we'll do over in more complicated contexts.
Supposing I have two complex numbers,
z1 and z2,
and I multiply them together.
Let's just do it over here quickly.
z1 is x1 plus Iy1.
z2 is x2 plus Iy2.
Thank you.
We multiply these together just to do it once.
It's x1,
x and y are both real.
x1 times x2 is x1x2.
That's real.
We have also another term in
the real part that's y1 times y2,
but it has a minus sign
because i times i is minus 1,
so that's minus y1 y2.
This is the real part of the product.
And then there's the imaginary part plus i,
and what multiplies i?
i gets multiplied by x1 y2 plus y1 x2.
x1 y2 plus x2 y1.
All right.
So here we would take the product,
and separate it into a real and imaginary part,
and that defines for us the
real and imaginary part of the product.
A very simple theorem.
It's a theorem.
It's hardly a theorem.
It's just a little exercise.
The complex conjugate of a product.
How do you get it?
What you do is you just
change each plus i to minus i.
Okay.
Each plus i becomes minus i.
That gives you the complex conjugates of z1 and z2.
And what will it do?
You work your way through this,
and it will just change the i over here.
Nothing else.
The simple Lemma theorem,
whatever it is,
is just that the complex conjugate of
z1 z2 is just z1 star z2 star.
In other words,
you multiply the complex conjugates.
Just for notational reasons,
I'm going to change the order here,
and put the 2 here and the 1 here.
Oh,
another example,
another similar fact.
What about z1 star z2?
Supposing I take z1 star z2.
That's a thing I can write down.
And I take its complex conjugate.
The complex conjugate of this product.
The rule is just complex conjugate each factor.
And that's just equal to z2 times z1 star.
So when you complex conjugate a product,
you just complex conjugate...
Did I write it right?
No.
Z...
That should just...
Yeah.
Thank you.
Z2 star z1.
Is there a way to write it here?
If you write the exponential?
Sure it is.
But I don't want to do that now.
Yeah.
Another way to write it,
to write the same thing,
which generalizes to vector spaces,
to more complicated vector spaces,
is that if I have two complex vectors,
let's call them,
instead of calling them by the notation z now,
let's just call them a and b.
All right.
The rule here is now,
think of the b's as being complex conjugates
because they're bra vectors,
and a's as being the original vector space
because they're ket vectors.
All right.
Well,
the rule that is analogous to this
is that if we interchange...
Here,
look at this for a moment.
Supposing we interchange z1 and z2,
what happens to the result?
If we interchange z1 and z2,
let's do it right here.
The interchange,
this is the interchange operation.
The interchange operation
will turn this into z1 star z2.
Just interchanging 1 and 2.
Just interchanging 1 and 2
will replace z2 by z1,
and z1 by z2.
But this is just a complex conjugate of this.
So interchanging the 1 and 2,
or the bras and the kets,
just does nothing but complex conjugates.
So,
to make it short,
if I take the...
Well,
if I take some sort of product,
we haven't defined this yet,
but I'm just writing it down for future reference.
If I think of complex numbers as vectors
in a vector space,
and I multiply the bra's and the kets,
which means multiply the complex numbers
by their complex conjugates,
then you just interchange the two complex numbers
and complex conjugate.
So when you interchange the bras and kets,
it's equivalent to complex conjugation.
We'll come back to it in some detail very shortly.
It's just a useful thing to keep in mind
that the mapping,
the mapping from bras to kets
is essentially complex conjugation.
Okay,
let's go back and very briefly,
quickly review what a complex vector space is.
As I said,
it is really the heart of the mathematics
of quantum mechanics,
and we can't do without it,
so we have to spend a little bit of time.
First of all,
it has a set of elements called A.
A,
B,
C,
and so forth.
How many of them?
An infinite number of them,
but not,
as we'll see,
infinite in a certain sense.
Just like the complex numbers,
there are an infinite number of complex numbers,
there's also an infinite number of elements
that we're going to call A.
They have the property that,
first of all,
you can multiply any one of them
by a complex number,
alpha,
and you get a new one.
Let's call it C.
So multiplication by a complex number
is an allowed operation.
It gives you another vector,
and adding them,
A plus B,
is another allowable operation.
You can put these two together,
and you can say,
given any two vectors,
any two complex vectors,
you can add them alpha A,
plus beta B,
and get another complex number.
If you can multiply them by complex numbers,
and if you can add them,
then you can add them in combination
with coefficients in front of them.
And the point is that they're closed
under these operations.
See,
alphas and betas can be any complex numbers.
Now,
for example,
this would preclude
the real numbers as being a complex vector space.
The real numbers cannot be multiplied
by complex numbers and give back real numbers.
So the real numbers are not a complex vector space.
They are a real vector space,
meaning to say that the real numbers can be multiplied
by other real numbers,
real constants,
and they can be added.
So they're a real vector space.
But what about the positive numbers?
Are the positive numbers a vector space?
Under the reals?
No,
because part of the definition
of a real vector space
is that you can multiply numbers
by any real number,
positive or negative.
So,
and that's it.
That is the definition of a complex vector space.
Let me give you two examples.
We talked about them last time,
just to review them very quickly.
One example,
oh,
ordinary vectors are vectors,
form a vector space,
and they form a vector space
which is a real vector space.
Ordinary vectors,
which are just arrows in space,
can be multiplied and added.
But multiplied only by real numbers.
Does not make sense to take an ordinary vector,
my finger,
and multiply it by a complex number.
Alright,
so ordinary vectors are a vector space,
but they're a real vector space.
Alright,
some examples of complex vector spaces.
Complex functions,
let's call it psi,
a function of a variable.
Now,
the variable does not have to be complex.
It can be complex,
but it doesn't have to be complex.
It could just be an
ordinary real argument of a function.
Argument means the thing that the function depends on.
Psi of x,
where x is real,
but psi is complex.
In other words,
psi is of the form,
some real part,
let's call it psi real of x,
plus i times psi imaginary of x.
That's the collection of complex
functions of a real variable,
for example.
Okay?
These form a vector space,
y,
you can multiply them by numbers,
and you get new functions.
You can multiply them by complex numbers.
If I take a complex function,
psi of x,
and multiply it by any complex number,
say alpha,
I get a new complex function.
Number one.
Number two,
I can add complex functions.
Two psi,
a psi and a phi,
for example.
Psi of x plus phi of x
gives me another complex function.
So,
they form a complex vector space.
Now,
we're not used to thinking,
I mean,
unless you've been doing this for some time,
you may not be used to thinking of functions,
as vectors.
But they are vectors in this mathematical sense.
Okay?
Another example that we'll use over and over,
are column vectors.
Column vectors are really functions also.
They're functions of a discrete index.
A discrete index,
instead of a continuous x,
they're functions,
perhaps of an integer,
but maybe an integer that
only goes from one to four,
or one to three,
or one to seven.
Uh,
and we can represent them by a column.
I'm going to use for these discrete kind of vectors,
I'm going to use a's and little b's,
little a's and little b's.
But if I put the entries into the column,
a1,
a2,
a3,
these are just numbers now,
complex numbers.
A4,
for example.
The set of column objects like this,
with only four complex entries,
forms a vector space.
You can add two of them,
by the following operation.
Let's call it b1,
b2,
dot dot.
And define,
this is definition of adding them.
a1 plus b1,
a2 plus b2,
a3 plus b3,
a4 plus b4,
and so on.
You can also multiply them by constants.
If I want to multiply the vector a,
by a constant,
let's call that constant alpha again,
all I do is multiply the entries by alpha.
Each entry gets multiplied by alpha.
And so alpha,
times a column vector,
is just a column vector by definition,
which is,
alpha a1,
alpha a2,
dot dot dot.
So you can multiply them by constants.
It's kind of obvious,
that this notation here,
is describing components of a vector.
We could in fact,
think of these entries here,
as kind of like the components of a vector.
If I were to give
you an ordinary vector in space,
let's say three dimensional,
three dimensional space,
I could describe that vector,
by three components,
x,
y,
and z.
And if I liked,
if I wanted to,
I could exhibit those components,
in the form x,
y,
and z.
But of course now I would
be talking about a real vector space,
and the x,
y's and z's would be real.
So there's nothing terribly unusual,
about what I'm doing here.
You can also think of these objects,
as functions of the index.
If I tell you which index,
if I tell you I'm talking about three,
then a of three,
would be a function,
well,
it would be a,
it would be a function of a discrete variable,
which goes from one to four here.
So in that sense,
even these discrete vectors,
can be thought of as functions.
Not continuous functions,
but just functions with,
whose independent variable just takes on four values,
one,
two,
three,
and four.
Okay.
Now,
what about the dimension of a vector space?
The dimension of a vector space,
can be defined,
as follows.
You can define it,
as the,
minimum number of vectors,
that you need,
so that you can write any vector,
as a sum,
with coefficients,
of that minimum number.
Let me give you an example.
Let's take a one dimensional vector space,
just the ordinary line.
Okay.
Now we can think of vectors on the line.
Vectors on the line,
are just of course real numbers,
but I can represent them,
as arrows,
from zero to,
to some real number.
If I'm allowed,
to multiply,
this vector,
this could be a unit vector,
or it doesn't have to be a unit vector,
but,
if I'm allowed to multiply this vector,
by any real number,
let's call it r,
and let's call this the vector v,
then I can,
and r can be positive or negative,
then I can get any vector out of it.
So it only takes one vector,
to get started,
and to be able to represent any vector,
by,
in this case,
just multiplying it by a constant.
Now let's go to a two dimensional vector space.
A two dimensional vector space,
and I'm thinking now about real vectors,
just to,
just so we can draw it on the blackboard.
The blackboard is a two dimensional vector space.
If I give you any two vectors,
which happen not to lie on the same line,
if I give you any two vectors,
then by multiplying this vector,
let's call this v1,
let's call this v2,
by multiplying v1 by a constant,
r1,
let's say,
times v1,
plus r2,
times v2,
I can generate any vector in the plane.
All I need is two vectors.
I could draw another vector in here,
v3,
but I don't need it,
in order to represent any vector by
summing up multiples of v1 and v2.
I don't need it,
it's redundant.
In fact,
v3 itself,
can be expressed in terms of v1 and v2.
v1 and v2 can be added
with appropriate coefficients to get v3.
So,
the question is,
how many vectors do you need?
What's the minimum number of vectors that you need
in order to be able
to add them up with coefficients
and generate any vector in the vector space?
That minimum number is the dimensionality of the space.
In this case,
it's two.
If you had a three dimensional vector space,
for example,
you could generate any vector by taking three vectors along
the mutually perpendicular axes,
or any other three vectors as long
as they don't lie in a plane.
As long as they don't lie in a plane.
So it takes three vectors,
a minimum of three vectors,
in order to be able to represent any vector
lying in a three dimensional vector space.
And that's the general definition.
How many vectors do you need
in order to be able
to add them up with coefficients
and represent any vector in the space?
Let's look at some examples.
How many vectors do you need?
Let's take,
here we have vectors,
column vectors made with four entries.
Only four entries.
I assert that that's a four dimensional vector space.
How do I see that?
Well,
there are four vectors
and you need all of them incidentally.
Any fewer than this you wouldn't
be able to represent any vector.
But you can take the four vectors to be
comma,
and of course the last one is
If you add up these vectors
with coefficients
a1
plus a2
plus a3
plus a4
then what do you get?
You just get the vector a1,
a2,
a3,
a4.
The first one will give you the vector a1,
0,
0.
The next one will give you the vector 0,
a2,
and so forth.
And when you add them up
you'll get back to this vector.
So the conclusion is
that you need,
oh incidentally,
if you threw away one of these vectors
then you would never be able to construct vectors,
there would be vectors that
you couldn't construct in this way.
Okay?
In particular,
let's suppose we threw this one away over here.
Then we'd never be able to get a
vector which had something in the bottom entry here.
So you need all four of them,
but that's all you need.
You don't need a fifth vector in order to be able
to write down every vector as a sum in this way.
So,
a vector,
a column vector space composed
of four entries is four dimensional.
And so on.
Five entries would be five dimensional,
two entries would be two dimensional.
What about just one entry?
One entry would be just the good old complex numbers.
It would be a one dimensional vector space.
So a column vector with just
one entry is just a number.
It's just a complex number.
And they form
the one dimensional vector space.
Complex vector space.
Alright,
so let's just summarize that by saying
Oh,
what about the functions?
What about the functions,
let's say the continuous smooth functions on a line.
How many functions does it take
to be able to write every function?
As a sum.
An infinite number.
Obviously an infinite number.
There's no finite set of functions
that you can add up with
coefficients that will generate every function.
If I have a few functions,
that one,
this one,
a couple of others,
it's rather limited what I can
generate by adding them up with coefficients.
In particular,
I'll never generate a function which looks like this.
So you need an infinite number of functions
in order to be able to write all functions.
Now all functions is a huge number of things.
All continuous,
differentiable,
smooth functions.
You still need an infinite number of them.
I won't try to tell
you how big that infinity is,
but you need an infinite number.
And so for that reason,
the functions are called
an infinite dimensional vector space.
But you can think of
it simply as a vector space
with an infinite number of axes.
It's a little mind-boggling.
I suggest you don't try
to think about it that way.
Okay,
so there we are.
We have functions.
Psi of x.
And we can think of them,
this symbol means think of them as.
We can think of them as vectors
in a complex vector space.
Psi of x is another vector.
These are two different vectors.
And they form an infinite dimensional vector space.
In the same way,
the column vectors,
a one dot dot,
a,
let's say six this time,
a six dimensional vector space,
can be thought of as the vector a.
The vector a which is determined
by the six small letters a,
a one through a six.
All right,
so that's the notation that we'll use
to describe vectors.
And typically,
vectors are closely related to functions,
either of continuous,
or discrete variables.
Now we come to the
idea of the dual vector space.
The dual vector space is really just
the complex conjugate vector space.
That's a secret that mathematicians don't let out.
Well,
for good reasons.
It's not arbitrary.
When they want to be general,
and they want to be rigorous,
they prefer not to think of the dual vector space
as being limited to just complex conjugation.
You can have other kinds of operations.
But for us in physics and in quantum mechanics,
basically the dual vector
space means the complex conjugates.
And we think of the complex conjugates
as forming a separate vector space,
a different one,
but related.
So,
just like for every complex number,
we have its reflection.
If the complex number is in the upper half plane,
then its reflection is in the lower half plane.
If the complex number is in the lower half plane,
then its reflection is in the upper half plane.
We actually have two,
a pair of redundant descriptions of the same plane.
One in terms of the complex numbers,
and the other in terms of the complex conjugates.
It's really the same plane,
but we think of them as two different vector spaces.
But there's a mapping between them.
For every complex number,
there is a complex conjugate.
For every ket vector z,
there is a bra vector z.
It's complex conjugate.
And so we think of a vector space
coming together with a second vector space,
which is,
in a certain sense,
identical to it,
or isomorphic to it,
contains the same...
Well,
I won't say it contains the same object.
That would be wrong.
But they're in one-to-one correspondence.
They're in one-to-one correspondence.
But let's suppose now
that the vector space is a vector space.
And they're labeled,
if A is a vector in the ket space,
then A,
with its arrow facing in the other direction,
is essentially its complex conjugate.
What does that mean?
Well,
for example,
if the vector space is the space of functions,
then the dual vector space is simply
the things made up out of the complex conjugates
of the functions.
There's a mapping between them.
For every A,
there is...
For every ket vector,
there is a bra vector.
Just as for every complex number,
there is its complex conjugate.
So one example of this
is the mapping of...
between complex conjugates.
It's always a mapping between complex conjugates.
But if we were talking about column vectors,
then the usual notation...
Now,
some of these things are just notations.
You can't ask me why,
because it's just a notation.
It turns out to be convenient.
If you represent the original ket vectors
by a column,
then the bra vectors
are represented by a row.
It's nice to keep track
of which are the bras and which are the kets
by making the kets be columns
and the bras be rows.
But the entry to the rows
are the complex conjugate numbers.
That's the important thing.
All right,
so for every column vector,
you have the complex conjugate row vector,
and those form the bras and the kets.
This can be thought of as
the bra vector,
this can be thought of
as the ket vector.
Notice we don't put a star in here.
The star is indicated simply by
drawing the ket vector instead of the original vector.
So think of ket as being a symbol
for complex conjugation.
All right,
now,
supposing we have
two vectors...
not two vectors...
we have a vector a
and its image in the dual vector space.
We have a vector a,
its bra...
no,
its ket,
and we have its image in the dual space,
which is the bra.
Now supposing we multiply a
by the complex number alpha.
What is the image of that?
You might think
that it's just alpha
times a.
What's wrong with that?
You want to conjugate it.
Because you want the
bra vector associated with alpha a
to be the complex conjugate
of the ket vector,
and that entails
complex conjugating the number
that you multiply a by.
So you really want to put a star here.
Alpha star.
Complex conjugating...
this is just a statement
that complex conjugating a product
requires you to complex conjugate
both pieces of the product.
Okay?
We had...
where was it?
Yes,
here it is right here.
Complex conjugating a product
means
complex conjugating both factors.
So the complex conjugate of alpha times a,
if a was just a number for example,
would be the complex conjugate of a
times the complex conjugate of alpha.
Notice that when I'm speaking about simple numbers,
I won't use the notation of vector spaces.
I'll just use the complex conjugation.
So when thinking about vectors,
we complex conjugate them
by turning them from bras to kets.
When thinking of them as the coefficients,
just the numerical coefficients,
we'll use the notation of complex conjugation.
Star.
Alright,
so keep that in mind
that the dual vector space,
when you multiply a vector by a constant,
the image in the dual vector space
gets multiplied by the complex conjugate.
Otherwise,
well,
otherwise,
operations on the dual space
are similar to operations on the original space.
For example,
if a and b are two vectors,
and we add them,
then
the dual,
or the complex conjugate,
will just be the sums
of the dual vectors.
That's a lot of information,
and it pretty much allows you
to reconstruct the dual vector space.
As I said,
for example,
the dual vector space to the space of function,
yeah,
good.
Is there any significance
to putting the alpha star on the right?
Oh,
no,
there's no significance to it,
no.
Uh,
there's,
there's sort of a tradition
of keeping your formulas neat
by writing them a certain way,
but in this case,
no,
there is no significance to that.
That's a good question.
Other times there will be,
other objects there will be,
when we multiply operators,
when we multiply vectors by operators,
then it does matter where we put them.
But when it's just numbers,
no,
there's no significance.
Uh,
but,
uh,
I try to keep things neat
by following a certain pattern,
but you,
you don't,
you don't need to worry about my pattern.
Okay,
that's the basic idea of linear vector spaces
and their duals,
or their conjugates.
Next,
the next construction
that you have to keep track of
is the inner product between two vectors.
The inner product is the analog
in ordinary,
of ordinary vector dot products.
Just remind you very quick,
quickly what the dot product of two vectors is.
Ordinary vectors,
you take the two vectors,
uh,
you can think of it in a variety of ways.
You can think of it as,
take the projection of one vector
and you take the projection of the other vector
onto the other.
Take the magnitude of that projection,
let's call this b,
let's call the original vector a.
This is the,
this distance here
is the projection of b onto the axis of a.
If we multiply the projection of b
by,
by the magnitude of a,
that gives us one form of the dot product.
We can do it the other way.
We can take the projection of a on b
and multiply the length of the projections.
The symmetric way to write it
is that it's a times b times what?
Cosine of the angle between them.
But if we write it in terms of components,
let's suppose we write it in terms of components,
the components,
for example,
along any set of axes,
any set of orthogonal axes,
the x and y axis,
for example,
then if we know the components of a,
let's say ax and ay,
that's a,
and bx and by,
then the dot product of a and b
is just ax bx plus ay by.
So we ordinarily write that
for ordinary vectors
that,
ordinary vectors now,
I just mean little pointers,
a dot b,
is equal to ax bx plus ay by.
What if there's a third direction?
Straightforward.
If there's a third direction
or a fourth or a fifth or a sixth direction,
you just keep going.
az bz.
So in other words,
it's just the sum of the product
of the components,
axis by axis,
x,
y,
z,
and so forth.
In parallel,
well,
not parallel,
or in analogy,
but in analogy with this,
we invent the generalized idea
of the inner product of two vectors.
Let's call them capital A and capital B.
And we write it as a times b.
Now,
this is the inner product
of the ket vector b
with the bra vector a.
Because we were dealing with
real vector spaces,
we didn't have to worry about
complex conjugating anything.
But when we're dealing with
complex vector spaces,
when we multiply two vectors,
we have to decide which one is the ket vector
and which one is the bra vector.
Once we do that,
then I'll tell you what the,
well,
then I'll tell you what the rule is.
First of all,
the inner product has some properties.
This is abstract.
First of all,
it has some abstract properties.
Uh,
the first abstract property
is supposing you multiply
the vector b by beta.
So this is beta times b.
This is the first abstract property.
This is the inner product of a
with the vector beta times b.
So let's put all of this in a bra,
in a,
in a parenthesis here.
Parenthesis.
That inner product is just beta
times the inner product of a b.
If you double,
in other words,
if you double the length of b
and not double the length of a,
then you just double the inner product.
Okay?
If you were to double both a and b,
of course you get a factor of four,
but we're just doubling,
doubling or multiplying by beta
one of the vectors.
If we do that,
then the inner product itself
just gets multiplied by beta.
Another fact is that if we multiply a
by a sum,
let's say b plus c,
the inner product of a with b plus c,
that's just given by
a inner product with b
plus a inner product with c.
The mathematical language
is that the inner product is linear,
is a linear operation on b.
These are all properties
that ordinary dot products between vectors have,
and they're properties that you can check
for the inner products between more abstract vectors
if I give you the rule.
So far I haven't given you the rule
for inner products for column vectors
or for functions.
I'm going to give you that as examples.
But before I do,
I want to finish up with the abstract properties.
Another abstract property
is that the inner product of a with b
is related to,
ket vector b,
bra vector a,
is related to,
but is not equal to in general,
the inner product of b with a.
Notice what I've done here.
Effectively,
I've complex conjugated
both a and b.
I've replaced a by the complex conjugate of b
and b by the complex conjugate of a.
What would you get,
what would you expect to get
on the right-hand side here?
A.
Yeah.
If you take two numbers and you multiply them,
sorry,
if you take a number times,
you know what I mean.
You've complex conjugated both factors,
you can expect that the result is just
the complex conjugation.
So that's the correct equation.
When you interchange bra and ket vector,
you have to complex conjugate.
And that's the rule for,
that's analogous to a rule,
let's see,
it's analogous to this one.
Z1 star times Z2 star is Z1 star Z2.
Okay,
you see what I've done.
Yeah,
I think it's the first one.
Right.
Okay,
so if you complex conjugate both factors,
then the product complex conjugates.
This is now to be taken as an abstract
part of the definition of a good inner product.
The last definition,
oh,
from this we can derive something very simply.
Supposing we take the inner product
of a vector with itself.
Then this says that it's equal
to the inner product of the vector with itself.
If I interchange A and A,
that doesn't do anything,
complex conjugated.
So it says that whatever this object is,
whatever this number is,
or the inner product is incidentally a number,
not a vector.
The inner product is a number.
The inner product of A with A
is its own complex conjugate.
What are numbers called,
which are their own complex conjugates?
They're called real.
Right,
they're numbers on the real axis.
They're their own complex conjugates.
So they're their own reflections,
and that means they're on the real axis.
So the inner product of
a vector with itself is real.
Now,
there's one more property
that the inner product actually inherits
from the complex conjugation idea.
Again,
it has to do with the complex conjugate
of a thing with itself,
or A with an A.
What do we know about the complex conjugate of A?
Sorry,
what do we know about the product
of a complex number with its conjugate,
besides the fact that it's real?
It's positive.
It's always positive.
Let's just check it.
It's x plus i y times x minus i y.
The imaginary part cancels.
i x,
both terms have an xy times an i,
but one has a plus sign,
the other has a minus sign.
But then this is equal
to x squared plus y squared.
Plus y squared because i
times minus i is plus one.
Okay,
so it's always positive.
x squared plus y squared.
Real and positive.
This is part,
or in fact,
this set of requirements
that when you multiply a bra vector,
a ket vector by a complex number,
that simply multiplies the inner product
by the same number.
You can take inner products with some
sums,
and you just get the sum of inner products.
When you interchange bra and ket,
you complex conjugate.
And one more rule that the inner product
of a vector with itself is positive.
That it's real follows from the previous one.
If it's positive,
it follows from?
It doesn't follow from anything.
As an example of where it doesn't follow,
in real vector spaces,
four vectors in relativity
can have inner products with themselves
which are positive or negative or zero.
Light-like,
space-like,
and time-like.
So it doesn't follow from anything,
but it is part of the definition
of an inner product in a complex vector space.
All right,
so what is a,
these are rules about what the inner product
has to satisfy.
Now you may be able to find more than one
construction for an inner product
which is consistent with these rules,
and in general you can.
But I'll give you the simple inner product
for functions and for column vectors
which satisfies these rules very easily.
And I'll leave it for you to go home
and prove the various properties.
These four properties here.
You do it by inspection,
it's not very hard.
For a function,
or for the vector space of functions,
the inner product of phi with psi,
phi and psi are both functions,
phi of x and psi of x,
that's equal to the integral dx.
Now of course you have to decide,
functions over what interval,
for example?
We could have functions on
the interval from zero to one,
we could have functions from
minus infinity to plus infinity,
but whatever the interval is here,
integral of phi star of x,
psi of x.
Notice that,
because phi is the bra vector,
it gets conjugated in here.
And we just multiply phi star of x
by psi of x and integrate.
Easy,
very very straightforward
to prove.
I'll leave it to you as I said.
So that's the inner product,
or the dot product,
between two functions.
The integral,
phi star,
sine.
For column vectors and row vectors,
the bra vectors,
let's call the bra vector b1,
b2,
b3,
three dimensional complex vector space.
And let's take the row vector,
no,
sorry,
this is the row vector,
let's take the column vector,
the ket vector,
to be a1,
a2,
and a3.
And I'm sorry,
I should have put complex conjugates here.
The entries to the row vector are complex conjugates.
Then the inner product between b and a
is just,
in very close analogy,
I think we've lost it off the blackboard,
but in very close analogy with
the way you take inner products,
for ordinary vectors,
it's just the sum of the products of the components.
b1 star a1 plus b2
star a2 plus b3 star a3,
dot dot dot,
however many of them there are.
Yes?
But the coordinates of the vector b
are .
The coordinates of the ket vector b are .
The entries into the bar vector are the stars.
Now,
I think what you're saying is
we would normally call this vector a,
and we would call this one just plain b.
We wouldn't put a star there.
That's a traditional notation.
The star is indicated by the backward arrow here.
But the components of it really are the complex conjugates.
Okay.
So,
that's the idea of an inner product.
All right.
Let me stop now for questions,
because I'm going pretty fast.
Questions?
Yes?
So,
the x in the inner product has to be real.
Oh,
here?
Well,
yeah,
right.
But we could,
yes,
but we could,
for example,
have more than one argument in here.
So,
it could be x and y,
x and y,
and then we would integrate the x,
the y.
Yeah,
but then they're both real.
They're both real,
assuming they're both real.
Now,
a function of two variables
can be thought of as a function of a complex,
but let's not do that.
Let's think of the arguments as real.
I think we're better off,
in most situations,
we will want to do that.
All right.
Now,
shall we take a break
for six and a half minutes?
All right.
Now I want to come to the concept
of a set of basis vectors.
For ordinary vector spaces,
let's say two-dimensional vector spaces on the blackboard,
basis vectors are just a pair of unit vectors
pointing in orthogonal directions,
which can be chosen somewhat arbitrarily,
not completely arbitrarily.
You pick one unit vector,
and then pick the other unit vector,
being perpendicular to it.
For most purposes,
it's usually convenient
to draw the basis vectors
on the blackboard so that they're horizontal and vertical,
and they're just simply vectors
that are useful in writing
any vector in terms of them,
or in taking components of vectors.
Let's define a basis set the following way.
First of all,
they're unit vectors.
Unit vectors means that they're in a product
with themselves as one,
the dot product with themselves as one.
Incidentally,
for ordinary vector spaces,
the dot product,
just real vector spaces,
the dot product is just the square of the length
of the vector,
of course.
So that's why it's always positive,
among other things.
The square of the length
of a unit vector is one.
So,
first of all,
let's imagine in our vector space
a collection of vectors which I will call,
what shall I call them?
I guess I'll just call them b,
b for basis,
little b now.
Now,
the little b's are not numbers now.
They're a collection of vectors,
b sub i.
How many of them are there?
The number is equal to the dimensionality
of the vector space.
So if it's a seven-dimensional vector space,
there are seven b's.
i equals one through the dimension
of the vector space,
d for dimension.
Okay?
b1,
b2,
b3,
b4.
Now,
they're not,
what shall I say,
uniquely fixed,
but they satisfy some unique set of assumptions.
The unique set of assumptions is,
first of all,
that they're unit vectors.
That says that every b,
the inner product with itself,
this is not summed over now.
Often,
I use the notation that,
when you sum over,
when you repeat an index,
you sum over it.
Here,
I do not mean the sum,
no sum.
Just take the i-th vector,
take its inner product with itself,
that's assumed to be one.
Alright,
so every one of these b's,
every one of these vectors b,
b1,
b2,
and so forth,
have unit length.
Next,
they're perpendicular to each other.
What does it mean to be perpendicular to each other?
For ordinary vectors,
it means that the dot product is zero.
When two vectors are perpendicular,
remember that the dot product is the projection
of one onto the other.
If they're perpendicular,
there is no projection.
So,
let's write it this way.
Yeah,
okay,
that's fine.
If I take two different vectors,
let's say b1 and b2,
or bi and bj,
for j not equal to i,
j not equal to i,
then that's zero.
That's the assumption that they're orthogonal.
A vector of unit length is called normalized,
or normal.
A normal vector is unit length.
A set of vectors which are mutually orthogonal
to each other,
are called mutually orthogonal to each other.
If they're both normalized and orthogonal,
they're called an orthonormal collection of vectors.
Orthonormal collection of vectors.
And if there are d of them,
then they're a basis.
They're a basis of vectors for the vector space.
We'll see what that means in a moment.
It means you can easily expand them.
You can expand any vector in terms of them.
Let me give you an example,
just in terms of column vectors.
I've already given you the example.
One,
zero,
zero.
There's nothing special about four dimensions here.
I've just chosen four dimensional vector spaces.
For zero,
one,
zero,
zero.
This could be b1.
Let's write it out.
Vector b1 is to be identified with the column one,
zero,
zero.
And I'll write down the fourth one,
and you can fill in the other two in between.
b4 is to be identified with zero,
zero,
zero.
One.
Each one is of unit length.
That's obvious,
because each one only has one entry,
and when you calculate the inner product with itself,
each one has only one term in the inner product,
and it's just one times one.
The inner product between any two of them
will always be zero,
because they don't have entries in the same place.
For example,
the inner product of this one
with this one will be zero.
It's one times zero,
plus zero times zero.
plus 0 times 0 plus 0 times 1.
So this is an orthonormal basis of vectors for a
simple four-dimensional column vectors.
This is not the only orthonormal basis.
You can find just in the same way as
I could choose these two vectors to form a
basis on the blackboard,
I could also choose these
two vectors to form a basis
on the blackboard.
They're supposed to be unit vectors.
So there's a
degree of ambiguity in the basis,
but you can check a given set of vectors and
check whether it's a basis or
not by calculating their inner products.
Yes?
Where?
Oh,
yeah,
okay,
that's right.
Yes,
yes,
no,
you're right.
Let's,
let's,
let's straighten that out.
I should have written before,
and I
should have written that this is equal
to the row vector 0 0 0 1.
Does that help?
Good.
Yeah,
no,
that's a good point.
Just for consistency,
I really should have written b1 as a ket vector,
b4 as a
bra vector,
and then taken the inner product of b1 with b4.
Good.
I was
jumping ahead a little too quickly.
All right,
this equation now,
these two
equations can be summarized by a single equation.
This is b i b j f d
j is not equal to i.
If it is equal to i,
then the answer is just 1.
So b i b j is
equal to 1 if i is equal to j,
it's 0 if i is not equal to j.
That's the
Kronecker delta symbol i j,
delta i j.
Delta i j is defined so that it's 1 when
i is equal to j and 0
when i is not equal to j.
That's the definition of the Kronecker delta,
and that defines a basis.
Now let
me show you how to take any vector.
Let's suppose we have d basis vectors.
We know
we don't need more than d vectors
in a d-dimensional vector space in order to
expand any vector.
That's the definition of the dimensionality of the vector
space,
that you don't need more than d vectors.
We have d vectors,
namely the d basis vectors.
Therefore,
it should be possible to take any vector,
let's call it v,
any vector,
and write it as a sum
over the basis vectors of coefficients,
and let's call those coefficients v
i times the i-th basis vector.
And this is just,
you
know,
v 1,
b 1,
plus v 2,
b 2,
and so forth,
etc.
Alright,
now let me take the inner product
of both sides of this with some particular
one of the b's.
I could call it b j,
but let me do it extremely specifically.
Let me
take the inner product of this with b 1,
b 2,
and b 3.
And let's call it b j,
and
see if it actually gets ever better.
bsb1 with the first basis vector.
b 1 with v.
What do we get?
Well,
we get a sum over i of the
inner product of b 1 with this expression.
expression,
but that's just vi,
b1,
bi.
Notice,
it's summed over i,
but I've chosen the first
basis vector on the left here,
so one of the indices is just 1,
I don't want to confuse
this with i,
let's draw it so that it looks like a 1.
Does that look like a 1?
I hope
so.
Okay,
now what is this thing?
It's summed on i,
but there's only one term in that sum.
That's because b1 is orthogonal to all
the bi's except for i equals 1.
Okay?
So there's
only one term,
and that term is when i is equal to 1.
When i is equal to 1,
the inner
product here is just the number 1.
So the result is i.
So the result is just v1.
What about the inner product of b2 with v?
Exactly the same argument
will tell you that the inner product
of b2 with v is the coefficient v2.
Now this is
kind of interesting.
I have now figured out what the v's are.
If I give you a vector v,
okay?
And I ask you to expand
it in terms of the basis vectors,
it's very easy to figure out
what the coefficients are.
The coefficients are just the
inner products of v with the
basis vectors.
So we can now write a
more general formula and put it together.
Let's
write a more general formula,
put it together.
Okay.
First of all,
we can say that,
let's call it bjv is vj.
Now I want you to imagine that
vj is the thing I was trying to figure out.
I was trying to figure out what expansion
coefficients I need here in
order to expand the vector v.
I want to write v in this form.
All right?
Well,
the answer is that the expansion
coefficients are just these inner products.
But now let's
rewrite this equation.
I can also write it,
I can also write the,
of course,
that v,
that
vi,
v is vi.
Doesn't matter whether I stick j or i there,
same formula.
And now let's
rewrite this formula here,
sticking in the v's that I've calculated.
So let's do that.
We have v is equal to a sum.
Now I'm going to start by writing bi here.
You asked me
earlier whether there's any significance to whether I
put the vi on this side or on
that side.
The answer was no.
So I'm going to choose to write it over here.
But now I'm
going to take what vi is.
Okay.
And I'm going to write the
inner product of bi with v.
So let me just substitute that
in.
Bi with v.
That's a kind of neat formula.
That formula will come up over and over again.
It's sort of easy to remember.
V is the sum of all
the basis vectors of the i-th basis
vector times biv.
And I choose to write it
in this form because later on,
when we get
to the point where we find out
what an outer product of two vectors is,
we'll discover
that this has some nice significance.
But this is a formula
for any vector if you know
it's in the product of the basis vectors.
Okay.
So that's a useful formula,
which we will draw on over and over again.
And I'm
going to write it over here.
But for the moment,
that's it about vector spaces.
We haven't discussed operators yet.
I don't know if we'll have time tonight.
I would like to get to operators.
I think we
will.
But let's just talk a little bit
now about the physical significance of vector
spaces.
In quantum mechanics,
in classical mechanics,
the space of states,
the phase space,
the
space or the collection of
possible configurations of a system,
form a set.
In the mathematical
sense of set theory,
the operations that you can do
with sets are the usual operations
that you can do — you can form the
intersection of two sets — that's the operation of and.
Now if you have a set,
if you have a set of some kind...
Hold it.
If you...
and you consider some subset,
and you consider another subset
then the things which are
in both subsets are the intersection
and the things which are in one set or
the other set are the union of the two sets
those are the basic operations or two
of the fundamental operations of set theory
intersection and union,
and they correspond to AND and OR
Quantum mechanics is very very different
the concepts of AND and OR are quite different
we're not going to talk about them tonight
but the difference derives from the
fact that the states of a system
are not points in a set,
they are vectors in a vector space
and the algebra of vectors is very
different than the algebra of Boolean algebra
Boolean algebra being the algebra of ordinary sets
of ordinary set theory
so what is the connection between
states and vectors in quantum mechanics?
well,
let's go back
to what we discussed last quarter
let's start with some discrete systems
the coin,
the coin was a good system
that was useful for us in formulating classical logic
the coin had two states
the coin on the table,
I don't have a coin
do I have a coin?
yeah
it's a penny
it's going to be heads or tails
it came up heads
and so heads or tails
the coin is a two-state system
the classical coin is described
by a system with two states,
heads and tails
and they form a set
that set is called the phase space
we discussed this extensively
last quarter
I'm not going to discuss it again
we could also think of this slightly differently
we could think of the coin as having an arrow,
a pointer embedded in it
and I don't want to call this,
I'm not going to call this a vector on purpose
I'm going to call it a pointer
just to distinguish it from the
vectors which describe vector spaces of states
we'll call it a pointer
it points in some direction
and here the pointer is pointing up
here the pointer is pointing down
and I could call these
two states either up and down
heads and tails
or I could even give them a different name
I could call this state plus
or even plus one and minus one
just giving them names now
we call these states plus one and minus one
in quantum mechanics
we take these two states
of the coin
but of course we don't
really need quantum mechanics for coins
it wouldn't do us very much good
but for some very very quantum mechanical variable
which could either for one reason
or another be up or down
I'm really thinking about the spin of an electron
but for the moment it's just a system
which can take on two values and only two values
either heads or tails
plus one,
minus one or up or down
okay
and we simply assign vectors to these two states
two basis vectors
two orthogonal vectors
one of them we can call heads
the other one we can call tails
or
we can call them
the vector plus one
and the vector minus one
now these are just names
this plus one doesn't mean
that this vector has length plus one
and it doesn't mean
that this vector has length minus one
they're just names
the vector plus one and the vector minus one
or if you like the vector heads and tails
well you could do this in classical physics too
you could
nothing to prevent you
from imagining
that you could identify some sort of vector
with the two configurations of heads and tails
but it wouldn't do you any good
there'd be no particular purpose in doing so
in particular
what sense would it make
to add the two vectors heads plus tails
sure you can call
you can call the configuration heads
by the label
if you like a ket vector
with an h stuck in it
and just call it that
you could call the down state
or the tail state t
but you would have no meaning whatever
to a combination like
oh I don't know
again complex numbers
alpha times heads
plus beta times tails
what on earth would that mean
in particular with alpha and beta being complex numbers
doesn't mean anything in classical physics
so this is something you would not entertain
adding the two vectors together
and therefore since you wouldn't entertain
the idea of adding them together
there's no point in calling it a vector space
instead you just call it a set
heads and tails
and you never think about combining them together
by the operation of addition
the operation of addition has no meaning
for a point and a set
of course you can form the union
of two points
but that's not adding the two points together
to form a third point so to speak
you don't add two points together
in a vector space to form a third point
but you do add two points together
to form a third vector
so there must be some kind of concept
of a state
of this two level system
of this two state system
which is the linear superposition of two of them
that's what's new in quantum mechanics
that this has the meaning
this has a meaning
and it has a meaning
of a particular state
of the heads tails system
which is different than either heads or tails
what way it's different
how it's different
is at the heart of quantum mechanics
this is going to take
us a little bit of time
we're probably not going to really get to it tonight
but that's the basic setup
that the states of a system are vectors
and not only that
that we can add them together
and make sense out of new states
which is for example
a linear combination of heads and tails
it's neither heads nor tails
but it's some number alpha h times heads
plus alpha t times tails
now let's
there's no reason to restrict
ourselves incidentally to two states
but before I go on to more states
six state system or a ten state system
let's just specify a little more carefully
the properties of the vectors heads and tails
or the properties of the vectors one and minus one
first of all
they are orthogonal to each other
now this is a postulate
the postulate is
that states of a system
which are clearly distinguishable
by a single experiment
and in this case the
experiment would simply be to look
is it heads or tails
one experiment
if by a simple experiment
you can uniquely distinguish
the two configurations
then the vectors that go along with those two configurations
are orthogonal
so orthogonal vectors
correspond
to configurations
for which there is an experiment
a clean simple experiment
that can tell you whether it's one or the other
that's the meaning of orthogonality
distinguishable in the sense that there's
an experiment that can distinguish them
good
that's number one
so we assume
that h and t are orthogonal to each other
that means that h and t
have zero in a product
another rule
which is now somewhat arbitrary
but we can impose it
we can also choose
the vectors h and t to be of unit length
so let's also choose h h
equals t t
equals one
in other words the two vectors
h and t form a basis
a basis identified with the
distinguishable states of a system
which can be distinguished by a clean experiment
we identify the different configurations that we can measure
with a basis of
in the vector space
nothing special about two vectors
another
simple system
would be the die
die as in dice
we throw a die
it comes up
with anything from one to six
one
two
one two three
this
corresponds
it's on the table
we identify this with the state
let's call it now
just call it three
this doesn't mean it's length
this doesn't mean the length of the vector is three
it just means the vector is called three
there are six of them
six distinct
one dot dot dot dot dot up to six
here
the state vector space was two dimensional
two basis vectors
here the state vector space is six dimensional
six orthogonal vectors
all mutually orthogonal
I'm not going to write that down
all mutually orthogonal and of unit length
in other words the six vectors corresponding
to the six distinct configurations of the die
distinguishable configurations
that you can tell the difference between
basically in a single experiment
just one experiment
you just look at it
and you see which faces up
that determines for you
which of the six
vectors describe the particular configuration
now
I haven't told you the physical
meaning of adding these vectors together
I just told you though
that it makes sense in quantum mechanics to
do something you would never do in classical mechanics
and that's add
these two configurations to find yet some new configuration
configuration which is different than either of these
h and t
that's what's new in quantum mechanics
that if you had a single coin
which whenever you measured it
was either heads or tails
there are additional possibilities
which are somehow mixtures
of heads and tails in a
way that doesn't happen in classical physics
the same thing is true here for the die
you can have
let's call these
let's give them coefficients again
this would be alpha one one
plus alpha two two
dot dot dot
up to alpha six six
this is some state
of the die
which doesn't have a classical analog
well what does it mean
we're going to eventually get
around to exactly what it means
but let me tell you some properties
of such a state
let's begin with the heads and tails
whenever I look at a coin
and I check whether it's heads or tails
I find it's either heads or tails
I don't find
I mean except with the extremely unlucky situation
or maybe lucky situation
where it's
I can't even get it to stand on
no way I can do it
it's either heads or tails
if I check whether it's heads or tails
it will be one or the other
so if I check it's one or the other
what kind of thing
is alpha h heads plus alpha tails tails
it is a state
and it's a state which if you
measure the heads or tailsness of it
will have a probability
of having heads and tails
and the probabilities for heads and tails
will be related to alpha h and alpha t
so this is some state
in which when we look at the penny
it has
a probability for being heads
and a probability for being tails
remember quantum mechanics
is probabilistic in a way that classical physics is not
so what is the probability for heads
let's call it p sub h
that's the probability for heads
it has to be positive
it has to be real
these alphas are arbitrary complex numbers
what can it be
it's just alpha h star alpha h
that's a postulate of quantum mechanics
and of course the success of
this postulate is an experimental fact
but it's a fact
it's a postulate of quantum mechanics
if we take a sort of axiomatic view of it
that the probability for heads in this case would be
alpha h star alpha h
which is a positive real number
and what about t
the probability for tails would
be alpha star t alpha t
well
that tells us one more constraint
about these vectors describing physical states
we do expect the probability for h
plus the probability for t
to add up to one
so we expect then that alpha h
ah
star alpha h
plus alpha t
star alpha t
is equal to one
let's give this vector a name
I don't know what to call it
let's just call it
anybody have a suggestion what I should call it
I don't know
hmm
b
p
why p
well this isn't the probability
this is some vector
here are the probabilities
I don't want to call a vector
by a name which stands for probability
let's just call it v for vector
coin
okay
confused coin
how about confused coin
cc
confused coin
coin doesn't know whether it's heads or tails
it's got some probability amplitude
these are called probability amplitudes
these are complex numbers
they can be positive negative or complex
imaginary whatever you like
and when you add these together you get a coin
a state of a coin
you don't get a coin you
get the state of a coin
in which somehow it doesn't know or it's
if you measure it
you will find with probability alpha h alpha h star
that it's heads and similarly for tails
alright
this object here is just the inner product
of the vector cc with itself
it's just alpha h star alpha
h plus alpha t star alpha t
so this is just
the inner product
of the vector with itself
the vector cc does not stand for cosmological constant
and it doesn't stand for
what is it that you do
when you send an email message
you carbon copy it I guess
it's not carbon copy it just stands for confused coin
alright
any state
any properly defined state
of the confused coin
should have unit length
should be normalized
that's another postulate of quantum mechanics
that the properly defined states of a system
are normalized
have unit length
in the sense that their inner product with themselves
is equal to one
that's the statement that all probabilities
should add up to one
likewise for the die
we have alpha one alpha one star
plus alpha two alpha two star
that that that
is equal to one
and if we call the state now
I guess we should call it cd
for confused die
confused die
then its inner product with itself
is also equal to one
so that's another postulate of quantum mechanics
the first postulate
is that states which are distinguishable
clearly physically different
because you can do a measurement to distinguish them
correspond to orthogonal vectors
second statement
is that
all of the
linear superpositions
which correspond to physically
sensible states
should have unit length
should themselves be
of unit length
the basis vectors are of unit length
but we should also only consider states
whose total normalization
is equal to one
those are postulates of quantum mechanics
yeah I lost you there
alpha
alpha h and alpha t
how did they become
you lost me or I lost you
well I don't know
so alpha h and alpha t
they became probabilities at one point
can you explain that a bit more
that is a postulate of quantum mechanics
that if you like
that that's the meaning of the alphas
but it's not the total meaning of alphas
there's more to the alphas than just probabilities
but
as I said
it's a postulate of quantum mechanics
that the states of a system form a vector space
if they form a vector space we can add them
we have to then interpret
we have to know what the meaning
what the physical meaning is
of a superposition of states like that
I'm not telling you the full meaning
I'm telling you now one feature
of such states
we will learn more about these
and we'll get familiar with the idea
but for the moment
one of the postulates is that
the probabilities are simply the squares
or the absolute values of these
of these probability amplitudes
not the absolute values
the square of the absolute values
of the probability amplitudes
it's only possible to justify
these things by showing you how they work
by showing you the ins and outs of it
and how they work
and how they lead to a consistent picture
it's best at this point to accept
make sure you know what I'm saying
the words I think are clear
that the probability
if this is the state of a confused coin
then
if somebody somehow created a coin
confused in this exact fashion
what does it mean for the probabilities
to be this incidentally
what it really means
is that you have a lot of these confused coins
all created the same way
let's be very specific now
we have a lot of coins
a million of them
and we have a lot of coin tossers
and they all toss the coin
or they all do the experiment
whatever that experiment is
it's not really tossing coins
it's something else that we're going to do
but we do some experiment
starting with all the coins
the same
let's say we take all the coins
and put them heads
and then we do something to that coin
whatever it is
we put it in a magnetic field
we turn the magnetic field
we do various things to it
but not just with one coin
but with a whole bunch of them
each one dealt with identically to the others
a zillion of them
however many we need
in order to be able to use the statistics
and probabilities
we have to be able to use the statistics
in a sensible way
then after having done this
we look at the coins
I look at the first one heads
I look at the second one tails
I look at the third one heads
tails,
heads,
heads
and so forth
from the frequency of heads and tails
I can experimentally determine the probability
for heads and tails
if I have equal number of heads and tails
the probability is a half
if three quarters of them are heads
and one quarter are tails
and I have enough of them
then I say the probability is three quarters heads
one quarter tails and so forth
the postulate is that the probability for heads and tails
is given by these coefficients here
that is it,
it's a postulate
you can't ask me why
you can't ask why a postulate is true
of course you can ask what the experiments
which led to this weird guess were
but we only have ten weeks
so we've already gone through two of them
I was just wondering
does that mean that the alpha h and alpha q
are equal to like one
over the square root of two
well that would be the case
that could be
well they can be complex numbers
but that would be
in the case of equal probabilities
yeah
it doesn't have to be one
over the square root of two
it has to be a number of length one
times one over the square root of two
but you've got the right idea
remember they can be complex numbers
and there are complex numbers
whose length is one
any number
whoops
any complex number
which lies on the unit circle
is a number whose length is one
alright,
z star z is equal to one
alright
so if I take
if I choose these numbers to be
unit numbers divided by the square root of two
then we would have the probabilities adding up to one
each probability being one half
yeah
so you,
yes,
you've got the right idea
ok
but do keep in mind that
in general these are complex numbers
alright
for the die
we would put a one over the
square root of six in front of it
to do the same thing
now what I haven't told you is that
is experiment
it's pretty obvious in classical physics
how you make a heads or a tails
you just flip the coin and slap it down
see the heads or tails
how do you make
how do you construct for a coin
one of these weird states which is half
heads and half tails
that I haven't told you how to do it experimentally
we're going to come back to that
we're not going to deal with coins of course
we're going to deal with electrons
but
for now
we want to get some formal ideas
we want to get to the quantum mechanics
as fast as possible
and to get to it as fast as possible
it's best to just tell you what the postulates are
and show you how they work
show you how they work
and then come back and say
how the hell did anybody figure this out
where did it come from
what were the experiments that led to it
one more time about the
the orthogonality of the allowable states
the orthogonality of those states
which correspond to
measurably different configurations
in a single measurement
let's be very clear about it
and this is a necessity
this is a
is it a necessity?
well you'd run into bad
things if you didn't do it
quantum mechanics would fall on its face very quickly
but let's do it
and then we can come back and ask
what would go wrong if we didn't do it
given the shortness of the time that we have available
I think the best way to do it
is to give you a bunch of postulates
show you how they work
and then come back and say what
would happen if we did something else
and
rather than to try to derive these ideas
in fact even if I had 30 weeks
I would probably do it the same way
well I actually think I'm finished
with the things in my notes
so um
we can
ah
no I'm not
no no I'm not
I'm not at all finished
with the things in my notes
but I don't know
it is
have I saturated you thoroughly?
no?
ok
go on a little bit
alright
the next subject
is the subject
the next subject,
mathematical subject
before we go on to its physical interpretation
is the concept of operators
operators are operations that you do on vectors
let me give you some examples from ordinary vector spaces
from you know the kind of
vectors that you draw on the blackboard
there are operators that you draw on the blackboard
there are operators and there are operations
operators are a special case of operations
or really strictly speaking one
should speak about linear operators
linear operators are a special case of
operations that you can do on vectors
ah
here's an operation that you can do on vectors
I just draw this to make some axes
take all of the vectors
incidentally when I speak of operations
you can do on a vector
I mean operations that you do on all
the vectors that you draw on the blackboard
so you can do on all the
vectors that you draw on the blackboard
alright
so here's an operation I could do
I could rotate all of
the vectors by the same angle
every vector in the vector space rotate by 90 degrees
that would mean that this
vector would go to this vector
I wish I had some more colors
well the other colors don't show up very well so
use wiggly lines
wiggly line this vector would go to this vector
and so forth
rotation by any angle
is an op- it's clearly an operation
that I can do on the vector space
it is also a linear operator
we'll define linear operators soon enough
let me give you another example
I could double I could keep
the direction of the vectors fixed
and double the length of every vector
that's an operation
it would take
every vector and simply double it
that's in fact that's just multiplying it by a number
so multiplying vectors by numbers
is also an operator
an operation and they're also linear operators
but we'll come to linear operators soon enough
take every vector and reflect it
reflect it about the x-axis
so take this vector and replace it by this vector
that's an operation that you
can do on the vector space
every operator,
sorry,
every vector goes to some unique new vector
that's also a linear operator
let me give you an example of
an operation which is not a linear operation
take a vector
and square its length
if its length is 2
replace it by a vector of length 4
if its length is 3,
replace it by a vector of length 9
that's not a linear operation
it's an operation,
but it's not a linear operation
so what does it mean,
what does the notion of a linear operator mean?
what does it entail?
ok,
so
two things,
and we've already used these things over and over
but let me spell it out
an operator is a linear operator
and I'll represent linear operators
by letters with little hats on top of them
that's a somewhat standard notation
often operators are represented by boldface
but I can't do boldface on the blackboard
so I'll use the little hat notation
an operator is indicated by
a hat on top of it
this is not a bra symbol turned on its side
or a ket symbol turned on its side
it's just a little hat on top
indicates operator,
linear operator
a linear operator has the property
that it
if it acts on any vector
it gives another vector
so it gives a kind of image vector
whenever the linear operation acts on it
if it acts
on a vector
take a vector which is alpha times a
remember,
vectors are things you can multiply by numbers
multiply the vector a by a number
and then apply the linear operator
well,
the answer
is equal to alpha
times the linear operator on a
so in other words it just says
that if you take twice a vector
and apply the linear operator
it just gives you twice
what the linear operator gives on the original vector
was that clear?
did I say that clearly?
I hope so
so that's one property of
linear operators
that if you multiply a vector by a number
and then operate with the linear operator
it just gives you the number times the linear
times the linear operator on a vector
on the original vector
number one
and number two
a linear operator
if it acts on the sum of two vectors
just gives you the sum
of the action on each of the vectors separately
so it gives you
l times a
plus l times a
times b
times being used in the sense to mean
operating on
let's just check that for some simple operations
if I take a vector
if my operation is
rotation
by 90 degrees
let that be the operation for the moment
is it a linear operator?
we want to check it
well,
the first question is
supposing I take a vector
and I multiply it by a number
let's say double it
do I just get twice
what I would get
if I rotated the vector
the original vector
so here's the original vector
here's
twice the original vector
the operation is rotation
it rotates every vector by 90 degrees
let's say
in particular
the result of the original vector
is the result of the original vector
of rotating twice a
is the same as twice
the result of rotating a
that's obvious
alright
so it satisfies the first rule
that if I rotate
alpha times a vector
I just get alpha times the rotated vector
what if I rotate the sum of two vectors
if I rotate the sum of two vectors
here's two vectors
an ordinary vectors
a and b
the sum of a and b
is just the resultant
like that
if I rotate a and b
the whole
parallelogram rotates
and a and b will rotate
but so will the sum of a and b rotate
and so the rotation of
the sum of a and b
is just the sum of
the rotation of a and b
and so it satisfies this rule here
you can check that
check that for yourself
multiplying a vector by the number two
again
is a linear operation
but squaring the length of a vector is not
check that out
you'll discover that that's not a linear operator
so there's the notion of linear operators
and here's its definition
linear operators are important
they don't correspond to states
they correspond to the quantities that you can measure
they're called observables
observables means the things that you can measure
you can measure the headsness or tailsness of the coin
so the headsness or tailsness of the coin
is represented by a linear operator
I think we have to finish now
we'll come back to this next time
and I'll explain to you how the
observables that you measure
are identified as linear operators in quantum mechanics
and then we can do some little examples
and
and work out some predictions
that would follow from this set of rules
the set of rules seems very abstract
but we're almost at the stage
where we can make predictions
about coins based on quantum mechanics
by using this set of postulates
we're fairly close to that by now
the preceding program is copyrighted by
Stanford University
please visit us at
stanford.edu