This program is brought to you by Stanford University.
Please visit us at stanford.edu.
Okay,
periodic,
periodic line can either mean
particle really moving on a circle,
or it could just be a rule
that you have a finite length of line.
And your rule is,
whenever the particle gets to this point over here,
it instantly reappears at the other end of the line.
Just a rule that you could wrap it in
a circle if you wanted to in your mind's eye,
but that doesn't necessarily mean that
the object is moving in a circle.
It's moving on what is called a periodic line.
So that motion is periodic.
If you disappear out this end,
you reappear on this end.
Under these circumstances,
the analog or the analog statement for quantum mechanics
is that the wave function,
psi of x,
should be periodic.
Psi of x,
let's call this distance L.
Psi of x should equal psi of x plus L.
That's the notion of a periodic wave function.
The infinite line,
where the line grows to infinity,
is the limit of a periodic
line where the length goes to infinity.
So you can study quantum mechanics or waves,
any kind of field theory,
as the limit of a field theory or
a Schrodinger equation or whatever it happens to be,
even just particle mechanics,
on a periodic line in the
limit that the line gets infinite.
For ordinary particle,
classical particle mechanics,
there's not much advantage in thinking
about the limit of a particle.
You can think about it periodically.
But in quantum mechanics,
it is very,
very useful to begin with a periodic line.
Now,
since psi of x has to be
equal to psi of x plus L,
that has,
as was pointed out a moment ago,
that has implications for the spectrum of momentum,
for the possible eigenvalues of momentum.
Remember,
the wave functions for a momentum eigenstate
are e to the i p x.
Incidentally,
this is not quite the ortho- p being-
oh,
this is not right,
is it?
I'm missing something.
h bar.
h bar in the denominator.
And we often call that
e to the i k x.
k is just momentum divided by h bar.
I think I'll use the k notation.
Or you can simply work in units
where Planck's constant is equal to 1,
and then k and p are the same thing.
Okay.
This is the wave function,
but it's not properly normalized.
Remember,
the rule for a normalized wave function
is that the integral of psi
star psi should be equal to 1.
That's basically the statement that the
total probability of finding the object someplace
should add up to 1.
If I take this wave
function with p as a parameter,
and I multiply it by its conjugate,
psi star psi,
would just be equal to 1.
And if I then do this integral,
then- oh,
I'm sorry,
you know what?
I want to go back one step.
I want to think of L
as equal to 2 pi r.
I want to imagine that it is on a circle.
This is just for notational convenience,
to think of it as on a circle.
Um,
and then this would not be true.
Psi star psi is 1,
but then the integral over x
from 0 to 2 pi r
would not be 1,
it would just be 2 pi r.
So what I would do to fix it
is I would divide the wave function here
by the square root of 2 pi r.
Then,
when I did the integral,
the integral of psi star psi
for each of these momentum eigenfunctions,
they would be normalized
so that the total probability would be equal to 1.
Everybody understand why I put square root there?
I put square root there because
when we multiply psi star psi,
the square root from here will combine-
well,
the square root from here will be squared,
and the integral will be 1 instead of,
uh,
instead of what I have there.
Okay,
that's- this is- I only mention this
because you're going to see
two pi's all over the place.
This is where they come from.
They're not very interesting,
uh,
but that is where they come from.
Now-
Or you could say that the definition of length
has a square root in it.
Nah,
okay,
however you-
well,
the definition of length doesn't have a square root.
The definition of the wave function has a square root.
No,
I mean,
the reason you chose the square root there
is that we're trying to get unit length.
Unit length for the vectors,
yeah,
for these vectors.
Yeah,
yeah,
not for this length.
Right,
that's right.
That's right.
Um,
once we have that,
we look at the individual wave functions,
these wave functions for given momentum,
and we require that they're periodic.
That says that k times 2 pi r,
that's the value-
of the exponent here,
when you've gone one full cycle around,
that must equal 2n pi.
2n pi.
In other words,
if the wave function over here-
let's say the wave function over here is 1,
then over here,
it will contain the factor e to the i k,
and then x will equal 2 pi r.
If the wave function is to be periodic,
then e to the i k
times 2 pi r must equal 1,
and the only way that that can happen
is if 2 pi r k is
equal to an integer multiple of 2 pi.
All right,
so that would just say that,
uh,
that the length r times k
must equal an integer.
Or,
that the eigenvalue k,
this is the eigenvalue of the momentum,
or strictly speaking,
it's the eigenvalue of the momentum times a-
uh,
divided by h bar,
the quantity k
is quantized in units of n over r.
All right,
now,
this means
that if I were to plot
on the horizontal axis here,
the spectrum of possible values of k,
I'm not making a graph,
I'm just gonna put down,
all the possible points k,
that,
uh,
they form a discrete collection
with a spacing which is 1 over r.
So,
there they are.
Those are the possible values of k,
starting at 0,
going off to negative infinity,
going off to positive infinity.
And the separation between them
is 1 over k.
Sorry,
1 over r.
So as r gets bigger and bigger,
the spacing between different values of k,
neighboring values of k,
gets smaller and smaller,
and eventually we can say
that when the r-axis gets infinitely big,
the spacing between neighboring values of k
shrinks to 0,
and we can say just about
every value of k is possible.
Or,
there's no value of k,
which isn't arbitrarily close to an allowable.
They get dense.
We might as well just say
every value of k becomes possible.
That's,
in that limit.
Now,
next step.
To go to the limit
in which the eigenvalues become very,
very dense,
oh,
before we do that,
let's just notice that
without proving it,
since we've already proved it,
since these wave functions are eigenvectors
of a Hermitian operator,
for different values of k,
they must be orthogonal.
Okay?
This is true
if we calculate the integral
from 0 to 2 pi r
of e to the i k x
times e to the minus i,
let's call it k prime x,
where k and k prime
are allowable values.
Then this integral is 1,
sorry,
we have to put a 1 over 2 pi in,
1 over 2 pi r in.
That's this normalization factor here.
1 over 2 pi r on the outside.
We do this integral.
It will be 1
if k is equal to k prime.
That's obvious.
If k is equal to k prime,
then this isn't here.
This product is 1,
and it's just the integral
from 0 to 2 pi r
divided by 2 pi r.
That's 1.
If k is not equal to k prime,
then the integral is 0.
Okay?
The integral is 0
because basically what you're doing,
these things are made out of sines and cosines.
Right?
This one is made out of functions
which oscillate like this.
which oscillate with a different period.
Okay?
And the product will be positive
some places
and negative other places.
Here the product is negative.
Here the product is positive.
If we take two different values of k
and look at it along the line,
we'll find that it cancels as much as it adds.
The result of that is
that this integral is always 0
for k not equal to k prime.
So,
there's an easy way to say it.
This is just equal to a Kronecker delta,
a thing which is 0 if
k is not equal to k prime
and 1 if k is equal to k prime.
Now,
k itself is not quite an integer.
k is related to an integer.
And so what we'd actually write is that this
is equal to delta of n and n prime
where n and n prime are the appropriate integers
going with k and k prime.
That's standard quantum mechanics.
Raising its head for us.
Orthonormal eigenfunctions
being the eigenfunctions of a Hermitian operator.
So that's good.
All of that is good.
Yes?
Is that a definition?
No,
this is not a definition.
This is a theorem.
Oh,
yeah.
Yeah.
The value of integrals is never,
well,
the value of integrals is a general rule
for well-defined functions.
This is something you calculate.
Okay,
but what I'm not clear with
is where does that come from?
Are you just trying to show
that the two wave functions are orthogonal?
You're asking me can I prove this?
No,
no,
no.
I'm asking where does it come from?
Because they are eigenvectors with different eigenvalues
of a Hermitian operator,
it implies that they're orthogonal.
Okay,
and that shows that...
Yeah,
yeah.
This is a...
Either we can think of this as a consequence
of the fact that they're...
eigenfunctions of a Hermitian operator,
or we can say this is confirmation of the...
of that fact.
Yeah?
They're sines and pro-sines that
are periodic over the same interval.
They're periodic over the same interval,
but they don't have the same...
If they have the same wavelength,
they're going to integrate as a zero.
If they do have the same wavelength?
That's right.
That's all.
Yeah,
that's all that's happening.
Right.
Right,
for example,
well,
yes,
that's right.
If they don't have the same wavelength,
they will cancel out as much as they add.
Okay,
so this is an example of the orthonormality,
the orthonormal character of the eigenfunctions
of a Hermitian operator.
In other words,
these functions,
thought of as vectors,
form a basis for the vector space.
The next step,
if we were trying to...
if we were trying to get to this continuum limit,
we want to replace sums by integrals
and Kronecker deltas by delta functions.
I'm not going to go into
that very much except to tell you
that to do so,
what we basically do
is we multiply up these...
each of these wave functions by a large number.
In other words,
instead of taking wave functions
which are in the standard sense normalized to one,
we multiply...
we multiply them by a big number.
How big a number?
We simply multiply them by the square root of r.
If we take each wave function of this type
and multiply it by the square root of r,
it's no longer a truly normalized wave function,
but now we'll just define it.
Psi p of x will,
instead of being this thing,
it'll be the same thing,
e to the i p x,
over the square root of pi,
square root of 2 pi,
2 pi,
without the r here.
That means these wave functions have been stretched out
by a factor of r.
This...
Sorry.
Stretched out by a factor of square root of r.
Now that's not going to change the fact
that if we take two different ones...
Where did I put it?
If we take two different ones,
that the integral will be zero.
That's not going to be affected by multiplying by r.
It'll be zero if k
is not equal to k prime.
That will still be true.
But what if k is equal to k prime?
Originally,
we had zero there.
I'm sorry.
Originally,
we had one there.
If k is equal to k prime,
we had one.
Now we're going to get something big.
If we get rid of the...
If we get...
If we stretch out the vectors by
a factor of square root of r,
then on the right-hand side,
we will get r.
If k is equal to k prime.
In other words,
we now have that the inner product
between these two functions as a function of...
Notice it is a function of k minus k prime.
If I combine these exponentials together,
it really just becomes k minus k prime x.
It's a function of k minus k prime.
It has the property...
It's zero if k is not equal to k prime,
but it has the property that it's very big,
namely equal to r.
We're imagining r getting very,
very large now
when k is equal to k prime.
So we've stretched it out to make the inner product
be a delta function instead of a Kronecker delta.
Once we do that,
we can then rewrite.
We can write...
I'll write the original equation,
which I haven't written down,
but I'll write it down now,
that the inner product between two eigenvectors,
instead of being equal to a Kronecker delta,
becomes a delta function,
delta of k minus k prime.
So here was the step
where we stretched out the vector
and made a delta function out of a Kronecker delta.
We multiplied each wave function
by the square root of r.
Notice that the wave functions still have
the square root of 2 pi in them.
All right.
That is where the Kronecker...
That's where the Kronecker delta
became equal to the delta function.
Once we do that,
we can freely pass to a notation
where sums are replaced by integrals,
where Kronecker deltas are replaced by delta functions,
and just comfortably go ahead,
more or less,
just blindly using delta functions.
Now,
I'm not going to say anything more about it
than that right now.
Yeah?
I'm not sure I was listening.
In that initial one you had,
didn't every square root of r somewhere in there?
No.
Not anymore.
It's r now.
What we had...
Let's go back.
What we had
is if I put r down here,
then it was equal to 1
if k is equal to k prime.
I simply multiplied it through
by the square root of r
and another square root of r
and got r here.
In other words,
an inner product which was 1
now becomes an inner product
which is very large
if k is not equal to k prime.
That happens to be a delta function,
a legitimate delta function,
is something that you can prove.
But I simply wanted to show you
at what stage,
at what point,
the stretching of the vector took place.
The stretching by the factor of square root of r.
Okay,
that's one
important observation.
Now,
what I want to do is
show you the connection
between momentum states
and position states,
the momentum basis
and the position basis.
But before I do,
I want to come to a very,
very simple theorem
which we've already studied,
but get around it a little more.
First of all,
we've discussed the inner product of two vectors,
a,
b,
and the inner product of two vectors
is a number.
There's another concept
which is the outer product of two vectors,
the outer product of two vectors,
and it's written this way.
b,
a.
This is the inner product of the ket vector b
with the bra vector a.
This is the outer product
of the ket vector b
with the bra vector a.
What the hell does this mean?
This is no longer a number.
This object is an operator.
It's a linear operator,
and the way that it works
is if you take this object,
think of it now as an object
in its own right,
just in order to indicate
that it's an object in its own right,
let's put a red bracket around it.
What you do with this object
is you multiply it by vectors.
In other words,
you act on it
with this being thought of as an operator.
Let's operate on the vector c.
What does this mean?
It means just about what the notation
might lead you to believe it means.
It means the inner product
of a with c,
the a which is adjacent to the c over here,
just write down the inner product
of a with c,
that's a number.
That is a number times the vector b.
So the result is a vector.
This is an operation on vectors
which give vectors times numbers.
Vectors times numbers are vectors.
The outer product of b with a
is legitimately a linear operator.
It's a dyad.
It's called a dyad,
and that's what it is.
Okay,
that's one observation,
an important observation.
Now,
another observation is the following.
If I have a basis of vectors,
I can expand any vector in it.
I can write that this is a sum
of coefficients v sub n.
No,
I'm sorry,
I did not mean to write this.
I want to write v as a vector
is a sum of a set of coefficients
times the nth basis vector.
That's what a basis is good for.
It's good for writing any vector
as a sum of the basis vectors.
What are these coefficients v sub n?
The coefficients v sub n
are equal to the inner products
of v with the basis vector n.
The coefficients themselves
are nothing but the inner product
of the vector that you're expanding
with the basis vectors themselves.
This is easy to prove.
I think I actually proved it in class
at one point.
So you can rewrite this
as the sum of,
now let's do it right,
let's put first n,
that's this n over here,
and then let's put v sub n,
which is n times v.
You can read this in two ways.
Both of them are correct.
The sum is,
of course,
sum over n,
all basis vectors.
Two ways that you can read this.
You can say,
first of all,
that this is just a sum of vectors
with coefficients.
The coefficients being these v sub n's.
But the other way that you can read it,
which is also correct,
is to say that we have a set of
vector,
sorry,
a set of operators,
these kind of outer product operators,
one for each basis vector.
You add,
what happens when you add operators?
You get operators.
So,
you can read this another way.
You can read this as saying
that there's a certain operator,
let's write it out,
a certain operator,
I'm going to call it i,
and it's equal to the sum over n
of the dyads n,
n.
That's what appears here.
And it has the property
that if you multiply it by any vector v,
you get v.
i times v is equal to v.
This operator,
which is composed out of
the basis of dyads,
is nothing but the identity operator.
The identity operator means the operator
which,
when it hits any vector,
gives back the same vector.
Call it the unit operator,
you can call it just plain one,
you can call it i,
you can call it a number of different things,
but whatever it is,
it's something that when you see it,
it just gives back the same vector to begin with.
That's a useful formula.
Let's write it out over here,
that the identity operator,
the thing which does nothing when it hits a vector,
just gives back the same vector,
is the sum over a basis of basis vectors,
of dyads.
An example of this
would be to take momentum eigenvectors.
But if the momenta form a continuum,
if we go to this limit
where the circle is very,
very big,
and when we replace sums by,
sorry,
sums by integrals,
and Kronecker deltas by delta functions,
this becomes i is equal to the integral over k,
of k with k.
At some point,
I'm almost certain
I'm going to lapse into calling k p,
and call it the momentum.
That's just setting h bar equal to one.
So if I do that,
either yell out or just swallow it
and say he set h bar equal to one again.
Yeah?
On that formula,
if i equals the sum to n,
would it be right to say that you could say
that would be,
instead of calling it n as the sub,
call it i and i and i,
basically?
I'm kind of confused by that notation,
because you've got two n's in there.
Yeah.
Three n's in there,
basically.
Well,
this sum just says sum over them.
That's just the summation index.
It's just all the vectors in that space?
Yes.
You sum over all the basis vectors.
All the basis vectors,
yeah.
Now,
there may be many bases,
many possible bases.
Many possible bases.
A basis is just a set of orthonormal vectors.
There may be more than one.
For example,
just an ordinary two-dimensional space,
a real two-dimensional space,
that's a basis.
That's a basis.
Those vectors.
It's the same for any one of them.
It's common with an uncountable basis
to just use a letter like alpha,
both as the index and
the way you're using n there.
For an uncountable basis?
Yeah,
you just write alpha as sum over alpha,
even though you can't really sum over it.
It's common to do so,
but in practice,
what it means if the basis vectors are labeled
by a continuous variable
is it means integral.
It means integral.
In practice,
to make it concrete,
one would write,
one would replace the sum by an integral,
and remember,
wherever there are inner products
between basis vectors,
they're not Kronecker deltas,
they're delta functions.
They're delta functions.
This is a useful fact.
And it is in fact at the heart
of Fourier's theorem about Fourier transforms.
So let's discuss Fourier's theorem
and its relationship with quantum mechanics,
state vectors describing particles
with definite positions,
with definite momenta,
and their various wave functions.
Let's see.
I have too many things in front of me here.
Ah,
here it is.
Okay.
Definition.
If psi is the state
of a particle on a line,
and x is an eigenfunction of position
with eigenvalue given by the label here,
then the wave function is by definition
the inner product of the state vector,
with the eigenvector of position.
This is called psi of x.
According to the postulates of quantum mechanics,
the product of this with its complex conjugate,
psi star psi is the probability
to find the particle at x,
or the probability density,
to be precise.
Okay?
Now,
let's apply this in particular
to a wave function of definite momentum.
Let's call it p.
Ah,
if I call it p,
I'm going to have to put an h-bar in.
Let's call it k.
This is a definite state vector
describing a particle with momentum k,
and I'm interested in its inner product
with a particle of position x.
It's the wave function of the particle
with momentum k.
It's the wave function of that state.
What is that?
That is just e to the i kx
over the square root of 2 pi.
I've left out the r in here,
because I'm going to use delta functions
instead of Kronecker deltas.
All I've done here is to use the wave function
that we've written down up here,
thrown away the square root of r in the denominator,
and written that that wave function,
psi of x,
is just e to the i kx.
So what I've discovered is that the inner product
of a momentum wave function,
a momentum state with a position state,
has this nice symmetric form.
Notice it's sort of symmetric between k and x.
e to the i kx over
the square root of 2 pi.
That's one observation.
Now let's take a more general state,
psi,
and I'm interested in what's the probability
that it has different momentum.
Here is the probability amplitude
for it to have different positions.
I multiply it by its complex form,
x conjugate,
to find the probability.
Now I want to know what's the probability
for finding different momenta,
if I were to measure the momentum
instead of the position.
Well,
that's related,
or is equal,
to the square of this quantity,
k,
of course,
being related to the momentum
by a factor of h bar,
which I will ignore.
The inner product of psi with k,
quantity squared,
multiply this by its conjugate,
call this here,
let's call it,
psi twiddle of k.
It's the thing that you square
to find the probability for different momenta.
I put the twiddle up here
to indicate that it's not just psi of x,
it's a wave function that depends on momentum,
not on position.
Its square is the probability
that the particle has different momenta,
if I were to measure the momentum
instead of the position.
Okay?
Let's calculate that.
Let's calculate that by using our trick.
Where is our trick?
Our trick is over here.
This is the trick we'll use.
What we're allowed to do
is we're allowed to substitute,
or not to substitute,
but insert
into any expression,
let's see,
which one do I want to put in there?
Uh...
Excuse me one minute.
Yeah.
x,
psi,
integral dx.
What I've done here,
this is not quite what I've used,
what I've used is i is also equal
to the integral dx of x,
x.
Both of these are bases,
the k basis and the x basis.
The momentum basis and the position basis.
The position vectors are all orthonormal,
or at least they're normalized with a delta function,
just like these k vectors here.
And so what I've done in here
is to insert unity
in the form of the sum of dyads,
summing over a basis.
Okay?
Well,
what is this object over here?
This is psi of x.
What is this object?
This is e to the ikx.
Let's see,
it's actually a complex conjugate of this.
Notice over here I have k on
the right and x on the left.
Here I have k on the left,
x on the right.
What's the relation between this and this?
Complex conjugate.
So I actually have to
put e to the minus ikx,
all divided by the square root of 2 pi.
1 over square root of 2 pi.
Integral e to the ikx,
psi of x dx.
That's equal to what?
That's equal to psi twiddle of k.
What's the bottom line?
The bottom line is if
I want to know the probability
for a given momentum,
I take the wave function as a function of position,
I multiply it by e to the minus ikx,
and I integrate.
That gives me a function of k.
And that function of k
is the thing that you square
to find the probability for different momentum.
Okay?
So...
That's the mathematical logic
connecting position and momenta.
This operation has a name.
Taking psi of x and multiplying
it by e to the minus ikx
and integrating dx is called the Fourier transform.
So this is the Fourier transform.
The momentum space wave function,
psi twiddle of k,
is the Fourier transform of
the position space wave function.
Okay?
You can go in the other direction.
You can do exactly the same thing
to relate
the position space wave function
to the momentum space wave function.
You go through exactly the same operation,
or almost exactly the same operation.
Let's just,
let's see if we can do it.
Let's see.
What we write is that psi of x,
I'm taking this pattern that we have here,
but interchanging x and k.
So psi of x is by definition x times psi.
That's its definition.
And now to calculate it,
I'll insert a complete set of momentum states.
x,
k,
psi,
integral,
dk.
Again,
I have now done exactly the same thing,
except I've expressed the identity operator,
r,
as an integral over k.
Well,
what's this?
This is nothing but psi twiddle of k.
This is psi twiddle of k.
And what is this?
Where is it?
Here it is right over here.
It's e to the ikx.
Integral dk.
Square root of 2 pi,
right?
That's psi of x.
So look,
we have a reciprocal relationship
between psi of k and psi of x.
On the one hand,
psi twiddle of k is gotten by integrating over x
of psi of x with e to the minus ikx.
On the other hand,
psi of x is gotten by integrating over k
of psi twiddle of k.
Let's put the two formulas down next to each other
and compare them.
Here.
Psi twiddle of k is equal to
the integral of e to the minus ikx
over square root of 2 pi times psi of x.
If somebody tells you the,
the position space wave function,
you can immediately read off
the momentum space wave function.
Okay?
From this formula.
On the other hand,
if somebody tells you the momentum space wave function,
you can read off the position space wave function.
e to the plus ikx over
the square root of 2 pi
psi twiddle of k.
The only asymmetry here is that one of
them has an e to the minus ikx
and the other has an e to the plus ikx.
So this little formula here,
this type of formula here,
is rather powerful.
And it encapsulates,
among other things,
the reciprocal relationship of Fourier transforms.
That...
Can k have negative values too?
Can what have negative values?
k.
Absolutely.
Momentum can be negative.
It just means that,
it just means the particle's going in a negative direction.
Question.
Is there a physical interpretation
of that symmetry between the two?
Well,
is there,
is there a physical interpretation?
Um...
It was not obvious from classical mechanics
that there should be any reciprocal relationship
between momentum and position,
at least not until you get to the point
where you have the Poisson bracket formulas,
where you begin to see that they are
symmetrically related to each other.
This is all very,
very closely related
to that story of Poisson brackets,
but we're not there yet.
But this is another example of the reciprocal relationship
of momentum and position.
Okay?
Good.
Um...
Here's something you can sort of guess.
In other words,
there are two representations of the same thing.
The representation,
we have a state psi.
We can represent that state psi
in terms of a wave function psi of x,
whose square is the probability,
when I use the word square,
I mean times its complex conjugate,
whose square is the probability
for different positions.
Okay?
But we can also use a psi twiddle of k,
which has the same information.
How do I know it has the same information?
Because you can go back and forth between them.
One simple vector is described in two distinct ways,
one in terms of a wave function of position
and the other in terms
of a wave function of momentum.
Now,
let me remind you now.
How does the position operator act on psi of x?
What does it do?
Multiplies by x.
This is an operator now.
It's not just coordinate x.
It multiplies by x and the psi of x.
Okay?
How about the momentum operator,
k?
Thought of as an operator.
What does it do to psi of x?
Minus i d by dx of psi of x.
Now,
this reciprocal relationship,
which I'm not going to prove,
but it's more or less clear
from the symmetry pattern between x and momentum here,
is,
first of all,
how do you think the momentum operator
acts on psi twiddle of k?
Well,
psi twiddle of k...
What does it do?
Multiplies by k.
K times psi twiddle of k.
So if we happen to have had the wave function
in the momentum basis,
called the momentum representation,
if we had the state vector expressed
in the momentum representation,
and we wanted to know how k acts,
it's easy.
We multiply by k.
How about x?
How does x act
when it acts on the wave function
psi twiddle of k?
What would you guess?
Plus or minus?
Plus.
It's this funny asymmetry
between plus and minus
in the Fourier transform formula.
It is plus...
i dpsi twiddle by dk.
All right.
These are,
first of all,
formulas about Fourier transforms,
among other things.
But there are also formulas
about quantum mechanics.
These formulas,
of course,
were well known
before quantum mechanics was ever invented
by people who did Fourier analysis.
So they were just reinvented
by quantum mechanics
for the purpose of studying particles
on a line,
for example.
Um...
For the...
Yeah?
Yes,
so you can't represent
the state vector with both of them.
You can only do one or the other.
Yes,
that's right.
The question was,
you don't represent the state,
either one or the other.
Let's say either one or the other.
You represent the state vector
as a psi of x
or a psi twiddle of k,
and most certainly not
a function of k and x.
Is that because of the Heisenberg uncertainty?
Right.
Or you could say it the other way.
The Heisenberg uncertainty relation
is the fact that the function of x is...
that the...
well,
this reciprocal relationship.
No vector is both an eigenvector of k
and an eigenvector of x.
All right?
So there is no state
which has a definite position
and a definite momentum.
And in fact,
it's as bad as it could be.
A state of definite momentum
has a completely uncertain position.
And by symmetry,
by now you can see there's a symmetry
between the two problems.
So if a state of definite momentum
is smeared all over the place in position,
then a state of definite position
has a completely uncertain momentum.
Okay?
That's the character of the position versus...
or the position-momentum correspondence,
if you like.
Can you remind me
what the physical interpretation
of conservation of phase-space volume
would be other than just a state restatement?
I can remind you
the conservation of phase-space volume
will become the unitarity
of operator...
of the...
time-development operator.
Well,
just within classical mechanics.
I mean,
like,
I guess...
Within classical mechanics,
the conservation of the phase-space volume
is the conservation of the space-space volume.
Right.
It doesn't have an interpretation physically
other than just the consequence
of the transformation you get.
Well,
you can kind of think of it
as the...
as a classical version
of the statement that
distinctions between states
are maintained with time.
That the phase-space volume doesn't shrink.
For example,
if you start with a phase-space volume
which looks like this in phase-space,
which has many,
many points in it,
it will not evolve to a single point,
for example.
All right?
If it did evolve from a single point,
that would mean that there was no way
to figure out where you came from.
So the conservation of the space-space volume
is roughly speaking
the statement that distinctions
between different states are maintained
and there's a more quantitative version of it
which is just conservation of phase-space volume.
In quantum mechanics,
it becomes the unitarity of the...
which we haven't gotten to yet.
We may or may not get to it tonight,
what unitarity means.
But unitary is the quantum mechanics
of the quantum mechanical analog of...
what do you call those transformations
in classical mechanics?
Canonical.
Great.
Which preserve phase-space volume.
Okay.
Can you get the derivatives?
I'm sorry.
The k-operators of the psi of x.
How did you get that?
Here?
The second...
This one?
Yeah.
Or that one too.
Well,
I just guessed it from this.
Yeah.
I'm sorry.
I had to get that one.
Oh.
That was the original starting point
for what momentum is.
Momentum was the object represented
by the linear operator minus i d by dx.
Remember,
we proved that minus i d by dx
was Hermitian.
Minus i d by dx
equals k-hat times psi of x.
That's the statement that...
well...
Thought of as an operator equation,
it's the definition of k-hat.
If we actually put a definite k here
and said that this was psi sub k,
psi sub k,
this would be the eigenvalue equation
that says that the momentum operator
acting on psi of k gives us k times...
gives us the eigenvalue times psi.
But let's just leave it this way for the moment.
All right.
So I went...
Let's...
Yeah.
I may have just confused you
and I didn't mean to.
I just guessed this one from this one.
But I also know that it's true.
And it's easy to work out,
quite easy to work out
from all the definitions.
Yes,
sir?
When we did that,
I said you remember you...
some ways that works in there.
Some ways?
Weasel works.
Weasel works?
That's a weasel word.
That may or may not have anything to do
with what we thought...
or what we think of as momentum,
but that's not what we call it.
No,
the point is,
thus far,
we haven't established a clear connection
between what we're quantum mechanically calling momentum
and what we classically call momentum.
Okay?
Let me tell you right now
what that connection is.
All right?
Without deriving it,
let me tell you what it is.
There are wave functions
for a problem involving a particle
moving in a potential well
or something like that.
There are wave functions
which hold themselves together pretty well.
As long as the potential is smooth
and not too crazy,
then the motion of a wave packet...
What is a wave packet?
I'll tell you what a wave packet means.
It first of all means
that the wave function
psi of x
is concentrated
in some region
with a nice smooth shape,
perhaps a shape that looks like a bell curve,
but it doesn't have to be exactly a bell curve.
So,
psi of x
looks like this.
But it also says
that the momentum space wave function
is also...
That's psi of x,
but here I'm just writing the magnitude of it.
I haven't tried to express the phase of it,
just the magnitude of it.
It is,
of course,
a complex thing,
and I haven't tried to indicate
how the complex part of it varies across here.
The magnitude of it varies like this.
It's also implicit
in the notion of a nice wave packet
that psi of k...
Can that be seen?
Psi of k...
Psi twiddle of k
is also
a nice
concentrated wave function of some sort.
Do you mean those to be a Gaussian?
A Gaussian would be an example,
but it doesn't have to be literally a Gaussian.
A Gaussian is a good example,
but it does not have to be literally a Gaussian.
Just a wave function which is concentrated at some position
and concentrated at some k,
but not infinitely narrow in x,
because if it's infinitely narrow in x,
it will be spread all over the place in k,
and vice versa.
All right.
Now,
if it is concentrated in k,
that means it looks more
or less like a plane wave,
like an e to the i k x,
right?
Right.
So that must mean that it looks like this,
or that the real and imaginary part of it
looks something like that.
It oscillates...
The real and imaginary part of it
oscillate almost as though it were a momentum wave function,
but with an envelope,
with an envelope
that's fairly concentrated in x.
Wave functions which look like this.
For example,
you just take e to the i k x
and multiply it by some function of x,
which looks like that.
This will be something which is concentrated in x
by virtue of this factor,
but it will also oscillate
pretty much like a plane wave
inside that lump.
Those are wave functions
that describe particles
not with very precise momentum and position,
but with fairly precise momentum and position.
Somewhat precise momentum,
not in violation of the uncertainty principle,
but more or less saturating the uncertainty principle,
meaning to say,
as certain as possible in both position and momentum.
Now,
those wave functions will move.
They will propagate the Schrodinger equation,
which is the equation which tells you
how these change with time,
will have these wave packets moving.
And they will move more or less,
or similar,
to the motion of a classical particle.
That's the theorem that will prove.
The theorem that will prove
when we finally get to it
is that the center of the wave packet in position
moves very much like the position of a classical particle.
In fact,
as long as the wave function maintains its shape function,
it moves like this.
It moves along like a classical particle.
And with time,
first of all,
the position will change with time,
but also the momentum will change with time.
That means that,
for example,
if the momentum increases,
that might mean that the wave
packet gets more and more oscillating,
or less and less oscillating.
Both the momentum and the position will change.
The wave packet,
if it's a nice problem,
will maintain its integrity,
with both a position moving in space
and a k moving in momentum space.
The theorem that will eventually prove
is that the centers of these wave packets
move like classical particles,
and the center of their momentum distribution
move with the same equation of
motion that the classical momentum evolves with.
That's the bridge to classical physics,
the motion of wave packets,
but we're not there yet.
So for now,
we just call these things position and momentum,
and accept on faith
that there's some connection between classical momentum,
classical position,
and quantum mechanical momentum and position.
Okay.
Let's take a five minute break.
if A and B are complex vectors,
that can be a complex number.
Where are we?
Up here?
Yeah.
So,
if A and B are complex vectors,
the inner product can be a complex number.
In general,
yes.
So I'm trying to get my head around,
what is the outer product of complex vectors?
A non-Hermitian operator in general.
Now,
we haven't discussed,
yes,
we have discussed.
Once you multiply it over there,
you've got AC,
and it's a,
it's a,
it's a ket.
Which?
Yeah,
yeah.
But you can ask,
what's the connection?
Operator times ket equals ket.
Operator times ket equals ket,
yes.
But the question is,
in what sense is this complex?
Okay,
Well,
it's complex in the sense that
it's not equal to A times B.
These are kind of complex conjugates of each other,
but strictly speaking,
the correct term,
which I haven't introduced yet,
is their Hermitian conjugates of each other,
we've,
we've discussed what a Hermitian operator is,
but we have not discussed what
the Hermitian conjugate of an operator is,
and we will eventually,
but if you happen to know what it means,
this operator and this operator
are Hermitian conjugates of each other,
which is the operative version of complex conjugate.
Any other question before we take a break?
Okay.
The thing that we have seen rather clearly,
is the notion of incompatible observables,
incompatible operators that don't
have the same eigenfunctions,
and therefore cannot be definite in the same state.
We're starting to get some idea about
how the logic of quantum mechanics works,
and that it works quite differently
than the logic of classical mechanics.
In classical mechanics,
you would simply specify a position and a momentum.
In quantum mechanics,
you can specify a position or a momentum,
or you can specify a more complicated object,
a wave function,
psi of x,
which contains probability information,
or you can specify the same state vector
in terms of a momentum space wave function,
which has information in it about the momentum.
But not both.
Not both at the same time,
it's one or the other.
I like to say that,
that quantum mechanics often replaces the
word and by the word or.
Classical physics,
you might say that a particle
has a position and a momentum.
In quantum mechanics,
you would say a particle
has a position or a momentum.
You work in one representation or the other,
and at no point do you
ever assign a notion of probability
to more than one variable,
if those variables are incompatible.
We'll come to examples of compatible variables,
but the particle on a line
is not a good example for that.
Now I want to come to
a system which is in many ways
much,
much simpler.
It's a system which has only two orthogonal states.
Now the last time I taught this course,
I did this exercise by
using the spin of an electron.
The spin of an electron is
like a heads or tails coin,
which if you measure it along some axis,
is either up or down,
and it's never in between.
On the other hand,
you can measure it along any axis,
so it gets a little complicated.
This time,
I want to do a different system,
which also has two orthogonal states.
You can think of it
as the spin of a photon,
if you like,
or better yet,
the polarization of a photon.
Light is polarized,
or light can be polarized.
Light is made of photons,
first of all,
so think of light as particles now.
And we're interested in the quantum mechanics
of those particles.
But don't completely forget the fact
that there's also a wave theory of light.
They've got to be made compatible somehow.
Let's just go to the wave
theory of light for a minute.
There's a notion of the polarization of light.
Light is an electromagnetic wave
of course,
and a typical wave describing a light wave
moving down this axis,
let's say with a certain wavelength,
would be a wave consisting of the electric field.
And in this case,
the electric field oscillates
in the vertical plane here,
positive to negative and so forth.
But it also has a magnetic field,
and the magnetic field is always perpendicular
to the electric field.
And so an ordinary electromagnetic wave,
let's see,
let's try to draw it.
This would be the electric field,
and there would be the magnetic field in the...
Let's see if we can draw it.
Electric field oscillates in the vertical plane,
and magnetic field oscillates
in the horizontal plane,
like that.
Of course,
you can rotate it.
They're not out of phase,
they're in phase.
I just drew...
No,
the reason this is lagging behind here
is because I projected it onto the x-axis.
Is that drawing clear?
No.
Sorry,
too many people are talking,
I can't hear.
That's what I'm afraid,
yeah.
Yeah,
okay.
The picture is clear.
My question was,
should they be out of phase?
No.
No,
okay.
no,
no.
Good.
No.
Now this is a plane polarized electric...
plane polarized light wave,
meaning that the electric field
oscillates in a plane.
Right?
Oscillates in a plane.
If this is called the z-axis,
and the other two axes are x and y,
and supposing I look at that wave
looking down along the axis,
we have an x and a y axis,
and in this case,
the electric field
is along one of the directions.
That electric field,
and a magnetic field perpendicular to it.
The definition of the polarization
of a light wave
is the direction of the electric field.
However,
we don't distinguish
whether the electric field is up
from whether it's down.
In other words,
we just say,
for example,
it's polarized in the y direction.
It's an oscillation up and down
in the y direction,
but just think of it as a wave
polarized along the y axis.
Or,
the wave can be polarized
along the x axis,
or it can be polarized along any axis,
the definition of the polarization
is the plane or the direction
of the electric field oscillations.
That's arbitrary,
you could have defined it
to be the magnetic field oscillations,
but that's how it's defined.
Now,
if you take a
long wavelength electromagnetic field,
radio waves,
or microwaves,
let's say,
and you run them past a grid,
a grid consisting of wires
in the vertical axis here,
the wave will come out
on the other side polarized.
It will come out polarized
along a particular axis.
Let's see,
does it get polarized
along the axis of the wires,
or does it get polarized along the direction
perpendicular to the wires,
do you know?
perpendicular to the wires.
The wires short the E field out.
The wires short out the E field.
Exactly.
The wires short out the E field
in the vertical direction,
but they allow the E field
in the horizontal direction to go through.
There's no current flowing
in the horizontal direction.
Here's the way to say it.
Supposing you just took a square
of conducting material,
and you shined light on it.
What happens to it?
It reflects.
It doesn't go through it at all.
Now,
supposing we take this grid of wires.
Oh,
how does it reflect?
What causes it to reflect?
What causes it to reflect
is currents that are generated
in the piece of metal here.
For example,
an electric field
comes in here,
starts,
charges moving,
the charge is moving,
make a reflected wave,
and the wave reflects off
because the original wave
starts some current oscillating
in the metallic conductor.
Now,
here,
the only direction
that the electric field can drive current
is in the vertical direction.
It's not possible to drive current
in the horizontal direction
because there are no wires
in the horizontal direction.
The result is that a vertically polarized
electric field,
a wave coming in
with vertically polarized electric field
will start a current going,
and will get reflected.
A wave with its electric field
in this direction,
it just behaves exactly as if
there was no grid there.
It cannot start any currents going,
and so it just goes right through.
So the field that goes through
to the other side is perpendicular
to the direction of the grid.
A grid like this is a polarizer.
At a microscopic level,
roughly speaking,
a polarizer
is just a grid of lines like this,
which transmits through it
one direction of polarization
and either reflects or absorbs
the other direction.
Sometimes it just absorbs
Sometimes it transmits it through.
So that's what a polarizer is.
Whatever wave falls on it,
only the component along the direction
of the axis of the polarizer
gets transmitted.
Okay?
The direction of the polarizer
happens to be perpendicular
to the direction of the current flow,
but nevertheless,
we speak about
the axis of the polarizer
as the direction of transmission
of the electromagnetic wave.
Now,
electromagnetic waves
are made out of photons.
Okay?
If we take a polarizer,
let's draw the polarizer this way.
This means that it transmits
through the vertical polarization.
When we send just a single photon
through there,
the single photon may or may not
pass through.
If it happens to be a photon
which is associated with
an electromagnetic wave
with vertical polarization,
it will pass right through,
come out the other side,
and what's more,
it will come out
the other side with the same polarization
that it started with.
On the other hand,
if it's a photon
which happens to have been associated
with a horizontal polarization,
then it won't go through.
It may get absorbed or it may get reflected,
but in that case,
nothing comes out.
Is the reflected photon polarized?
The reflected photon may be polarized,
yes.
It'll be polarized.
But I want to ignore the reflected photon
because it's not a photon.
It's not hard to imagine a polarizer
which actually absorbs the other polarization.
I want to just ignore the one that is reflected
or just let it be just dropped from the picture.
If it goes through,
I count it as a photon which has successfully
passed through the polarizer.
If it gets bounced back,
it's for my purposes lost.
Now this is a device for preparing,
the particular state of polarization
which we can call vertical polarization.
There are two states of possible polarization.
Now you're going to ask me,
what about polarizations at different angles?
We'll get to it in a moment.
But any given photon,
no matter what the direction of polarization
of the light wave that carried it,
in other words,
no matter how that photon is prepared,
it will either get transmitted
or reflected.
Either one or the other.
Even if that photon were polarized,
even if the original electric wave
were polarized along some other axis,
for example,
supposing the electric field
of the classical wave describing that photon
happened to look like this.
We let through photon by photon,
one photon at a time,
and we ask what happens to a photon.
You might think that,
a fraction of the photon goes through,
and a fraction of the photon gets reflected.
A fraction of the energy of the photon goes through,
and a fraction of the
energy of the photon gets reflected.
But no.
Photons are indivisible.
You can't break them up like that.
What happens is the photon either goes through
or it's reflected.
It may have a probability for going through
and getting reflected,
but it will do one or the other.
Discrete choice.
Nothing in between.
So there are only two possibilities.
The photon makes it through,
in which case it's called vertically polarized
when it gets out here,
or it doesn't get through,
in which case it must have been horizontally polarized.
Now,
next fact.
There's a kind of consistency.
If you manufacture a vertically polarized photon this way,
by sending it through the vertical polarizer,
and it happens to come out,
then it is definitely vertically polarized.
You can send it through another vertical polarizer,
and it will,
with probability one,
go through.
So you can think then of the polarizer
as both a measuring apparatus
and a preparer of states.
It prepares states.
In this case,
this polarizer prepared a vertical polarization.
But you can also use it to detect
what the polarization is.
For example,
having made it vertical here,
if I send it through the next polarizer,
if the next polarizer is vertical,
it will definitely get through,
confirming the fact that it was vertically polarized.
If,
on the other hand,
I happened to prepare the photon
with a horizontal polarization,
just by rotating the polarizer,
so that it comes out this way,
then it just gets blocked out.
So this polarizer can be thought of as an apparatus
which is measuring the direction
of polarization of the photon.
If it makes it through this polarizer,
then it has detected a vertical polarized photon.
If it doesn't make it through here,
it has detected a horizontally polarized photon.
We can prepare photons by sending them through polarizers,
and we can detect their polarization
by checking what happens at the next polarizer.
So the same apparatus can be thought of
as an apparatus for preparing a state
and measuring a property of the system.
As I said,
if we restrict ourselves to an apparatus here,
which measures polarization,
what's this doing?
This is measuring polarization in the xy plane.
It's either vertical,
or it's horizontal,
and this apparatus tells us
whether it's vertical or horizontal.
Let's start doing some quantum mechanics.
Let's try to make quantum mechanics out of this.
In other words,
let's try using the formalism
that we've concocted
to describe the polarization of the photon.
We're not going to worry
about the position of the photon.
We're going to take the polarization itself
as a system,
and not worry that much about where the photon is.
Alright.
There are two orthogonal states of polarization.
The two orthogonal states of polarization we could label,
first of all with a ket vector,
and we could label them this way.
This represents polarization along the x-axis.
We could also just call it
polarization along the x-axis.
And we could,
if we like,
associate with it
a column vector.
A column vector could be taken to be one,
zero.
This represents a,
this represents the vector polarized along the x-axis,
represented by a column vector with
a one here and a zero here.
The one indicates that it has probability amplitude one,
for being along the x-axis,
and zero probability for being
polarized along the other axis.
These are three different notations I could use
to describe the same thing.
Then I have,
of course,
the other possibility
that the photon is polarized in the other direction.
We could call that a photon polarized along the y-axis,
or we could call it the column vector .
x and y are distinguishable,
distinct,
measurable,
measurably different states of being of the photon.
They are completely distinct.
If I create a photon like this
and I send it through the next polarizer,
if the polarization is horizontal,
it will definitely go through.
If I create a photon like this,
it will definitely not go through.
So these are two completely distinguishable,
a single experiment can tell you which
of these two states a photon is in.
And therefore,
these must be orthogonal vectors.
x and y must correspond to orthogonal states.
That,
of course,
is consistent with this notation here.
Remember how we calculate the
inner product between the two vectors.
We multiply the first component times the complex conjugate
of the first component of the other one,
and so forth.
These are two orthogonal vectors.
So we can regard these as
basis vectors in a two-dimensional space.
The two dimensions correspond to the other.
They are corresponding to the
two mutually exclusive directions of polarization.
So this is equal to zero.
They're orthogonal.
On the other hand,
we can also choose the
vectors describing the two configurations
to be normalized.
We can choose them to be of unit length.
In other words,
we just invent or concoct a vector space,
a two-dimensional vector space
with mutually perpendicular directions,
x and y,
and unit vectors along those directions
to describe the two possibilities.
This is what quantum mechanics would tell us to do.
And these are then a basis vector.
These are then a pair of
basis vectors in a two-dimensional vector space.
This is a very simple system,
much simpler than the particle on a line.
That's of course because we're
ignoring the motion of the photon.
We're just dealing with the polarization of it.
Just two possibilities.
Question?
Yeah.
Is this thing to do with observables?
Before we talk about observables...
Yeah,
we haven't...
We're just about to do that now.
Okay,
so the question is,
you said that these states represent the polarization,
one way or another.
Is that an observable?
You can certainly observe it.
The question was,
is that,
is the polarization an observable?
You can observe it.
You can send the photon through a vertical polarizer,
and it will either go through or not go through,
and that will select out for
you whether the photon was vertically polarized
or horizontally polarized.
So yes,
it is an observable.
Okay,
but I thought we talked about states not being observable.
Okay.
No,
no.
The states are not observables.
The things you observe are the polarization,
whether it is or isn't horizontal.
The states represent the
possible configurations of the photon.
The observable is the polariz...
Now we're going to talk about the observable
that corresponds to the polarization.
Let's call...
Let's define an observable quantity
by the following rule.
That if the photon is horizontally polarized,
let's...
Yeah,
we're going to write capital...
This funny P here represents polarization,
and it's going to represent an operator.
It's our operator,
which will represent the polarization of the photon.
And it has the property by definition
that if the polarization is horizontal,
then P is equal to plus one,
and if the polarization is vertical,
it's equal to minus one.
That's a definition now.
I will simply assign the number plus one
to horizontal polarization
and minus one to vertical polarization.
That's the thing which becomes the observable.
It's either plus one or minus one.
It has a numerical value.
If the photon goes through the polarizer,
I assign plus one.
If it doesn't go through the polarizer,
depending on the direction of polarization.
But we'll define now a polarization...
This is the polarization operator.
For polarization in the xy plane.
I'm going to put a symbol there
which is intended to show the xy axes.
This is the polarization in the xy plane.
And it's equal to plus one for horizontal polarization,
minus one for vertical polarization.
That's the definition.
Just in...
If we have a bunch of photons going through,
and we see one go through,
let's assume the polarizer is
oriented along the horizontal direction.
Polarizer along the horizontal direction.
We send a bunch of photons through.
If a particular photon gets through,
we put it on notebook plus.
If a photon gets absorbed or reflected,
we put it on notebook minus.
That way we define a numerical quantity
which we can call the polarization.
So we can call it the xy plane.
But it's the polarization in the xy plane.
That's polarization in the xy plane.
And here's the way we define it as an operator.
It operates...
When it operates on a polarization along the x axis,
what does it give?
Plus one times x.
In other words,
x is an eigenvector of this polarization operator
with eigenvalue plus one.
What about polarization along the y axis?
Same operator,
acting on a different vector.
y.
y has eigenvalue minus one.
So this is equal to minus y.
That completely specifies the operator p
with this subscript xy polarization.
You know how it acts on x.
You know how it acts on y.
In fact,
you know how it acts on
any linear superposition of x and y.
You can even represent it as a matrix.
Let's represent it as a matrix.
If we represent the vector space as column vectors,
we can represent the polarization as a matrix.
Here's the matrix.
Here's the matrix representation of it.
It's very simple.
It's just the matrix one minus one.
Zero,
zero.
Let's check it.
The x polarization is represented by one,
zero.
What does this give?
One times one plus zero times zero.
One,
zero times one.
One times zero.
Zero.
So that says that this polarization
operator acting on the x polarization
gives back the x polarization.
That's just this equation.
And let's try the other one.
One,
zero,
one.
Minus one.
Zero,
one.
One times zero is zero.
Zero times one is zero.
Zero.
Zero times zero is zero.
Minus one times one is minus one.
And that's equal to minus one.
Minus the original vector,
zero,
one.
So in fact,
this polarization operator,
this operator here,
or this matrix,
represents as a matrix
representation of exactly this operator.
When it hits the x polarization vector,
it gives it back.
When it hits the y polarization vector,
it gives minus the same thing.
So this object,
capital P,
with a hat on top of it,
is the observable.
X's are the eigenvectors,
which are states of definite polarization.
The vectors here,
the two basis vectors,
are states of definite polarization.
And the observable polarization,
the observable,
the mathematical observable,
is represented by the operator P.
Any questions?
So that's simple.
But now you say,
wait a minute.
What happens if I orient my polarizer in another direction?
Nothing's to prevent me from
taking my polarizer and orienting it,
for example,
along the 45 degree axes.
There's a,
well,
okay,
here's a polarizer.
This is intended to be a piece of polarizer.
But the polarizer is oriented along the 45 degree axes.
Again,
we can send a photon through it.
What comes out the other end will be
a photon polarized along the 45 degree axes.
Obviously,
this must be a different
state than either one of these.
But here's the kind of question you could ask.
Let's draw it a little more,
a little better.
Here we have the photon,
the polarizer along the 45 degree axes like that.
Well,
it can't be both.
It can only be one of them.
Oriented along the diagonal direction like that.
And here's another polarizer here.
I'm using the first polarizer to prepare the photon.
So the photon goes in this direction.
It goes through,
comes out the other side.
Which way is it polarized?
Well,
it's polarized the way the
polarizer told it to be polarized.
Along the same direction as the polarizer over here.
What happens if the second
polarizer is along the same axis?
What happens to the photon?
It goes through.
What happens if the polarizer is oriented this way?
It either bounces back or gets absorbed.
But what happens if the polarizer is
polarized along one of the original directions?
Not this.
Let's take it to be along the x-axis.
This is the x-axis.
What happens if the second polarizer is along
the x-axis rather than the 45 degree axis?
Then what happens is the
photon either gets reflected or absorbed.
Nothing in between.
The point is,
even though
somehow this polarization is halfway
between the two possibilities here,
the photon has no choice.
It has no choices which are
halfway between being reflected and being transmitted.
It either gets reflected or transmitted with a probability.
With some probability.
The question now is,
what state and what would
you guess the probabilities to be
if this were at 45 degrees?
Half and half.
It's pretty obvious.
It's got to be a half and half.
So,
let's now take
Let's see how I represented this.
I had some notation for this.
Here it is.
Yeah.
So let's take the photon which
has gone through the 45 degree polarizer.
The polarizer now is this direction here.
The photon goes through it and it comes
out the other side with some definite state.
That state is neither x nor y but
has an equal probability for both of them.
Here's a guess and it turns
out to be the right guess.
I mean what's right and
what's wrong is determined by experiment.
So you do lots of experiments on photons and you find
out that the pattern that I'm describing is the correct pattern.
But what would you expect it to be?
Anyone want to make a guess what it would be?
It's not x.
It's not y.
On the other hand,
x and y are a complete basis.
There's nothing that can't be written
in terms of x and y.
x plus y seems a reasonable possibility.
The sum of the two vectors has equal amplitude
in both directions or equal coefficient in both directions.
It's not quite right because it's not normalized.
So we throw 1 over square
root of 2 in front of it.
Now it's normalized.
The sums of the squares of
the coefficients add up to 1.
1 over square root of 2 squared plus
1 over square root of 2 squared is 1.
This vector,
whatever it is,
has equal probability that when we
send it through the next polarizer,
which happens to be oriented along the x-axis,
it has probability 1 half going through.
If we send it through the polarizer along the y-axis,
it also has probability 1 half going through.
So this is a superposition of
the two original states with equal coefficients.
That's my guess.
If you like,
that's a guess for the photon
which is polarized halfway in between.
We can also write it another way.
Let's see.
This is photon polarized along the 45-axis.
It's this,
which we can also represent.
I'm using an equal sign,
but I should be using a sign that
says it can be represented by a column vector.
And the column vector would be 1 over root 2,
1 over root 2.
Okay?
Now,
these vectors are not...
Oh,
this is...
Okay,
this is one vector.
Now,
there's a second polarization.
The second polarization is orthogonal to
this and is in this direction.
What happens if I send
this polarization through this polarizer?
Supposing I create a photon with
this polarization in the minus 45-degree direction,
and I send it through the
polarizer in the plus 45-degree direction.
Right.
So we would expect,
then,
that the state vector describing
polarization along the minus 45-degree axis
would be orthogonal to the state vector
of a photon along the plus 45-degree axis.
So,
let's see if we can find a
vector which is orthogonal to this vector.
Well,
it's not very hard to find a
vector which is orthogonal to this vector.
It's just x over square root of
2 minus y over square root of 2,
represented by 1 over square root of
2 minus 1 over square root of 2.
Let's check that these are orthogonal.
First of all,
they're both normalized.
Both of them,
the sums of the squares of
the coefficients add up to 1.
No question of that.
Are they orthogonal to each other?
Yes.
To check whether they're orthogonal,
you take this times the complex conjugate of this.
Everything's real here,
so I can ignore the word complex conjugate.
This times this plus this times this.
All right.
That's 1 half minus...
Minus 1 half.
The inner product between them is 0.
So they're normalized.
They're orthogonal to each other.
These two vectors are also a basis.
This basis is just as good and has
just as much rights as the original basis.
It's just describing
polarizations in catty-corner directions.
Okay.
What is the probability
that...
if I create this polarization
and then send it through the vertical polarizer,
the Y polarization,
what's the probability that it goes through?
Well,
of course the answer is a half,
but let's do it by
using the rules of quantum mechanics.
I want to know the probability
that if I start
with 45 for the first time.
I want to know the probability that it goes through
45 degrees of polarization like that.
And then I send it through the vertical polarizer,
the Y polarizer.
This is the Y polarizer
that it goes through to the other side.
In other words,
what's the probability that this has Y polarization...
that it has Y polarization?
The answer,
as always,
is take the inner product
of the vector describing the photon
with the configuration that you're testing for.
What would that be?
That would be Y.
And then take the square of that.
That's the probability
that this cattywampus polarization over here
is polarized along the Y direction.
The inner product of this with this squared.
What is it?
Well,
it's easy to figure out.
Let's just do it.
Mechanically,
this guy over here
is X over square root of 2
plus Y over square root of 2.
That's this one.
And this one over here is just Y.
Well,
the inner product of Y with X is 0.
The inner product of Y with Y is 1.
So the answer is 1
over the square root of 2.
That's the thing before you square it.
This is the amplitude.
The amplitude gets squared to find the probability.
So the probability is
the square of this,
which is just the square of this,
which is one half.
All right.
Now I'm telling you something which is completely obvious,
that the probability is a half,
but I'm showing you how the formalism of quantum mechanics
carries out that intuition.
What about the probability that a
square root of 2 is 0?
Well,
the probability is that it's polarized along the X axis.
You do exactly the same thing.
Again,
the only contribution comes from XX here.
it's 1 over square root of 2 squared.
Again,
it's one half.
All right.
How about
the second diagonal polar,
I'll call this diagonal,
the second diagonal polarization,
pointing along the minus 45 degree axis.
For that,
I have to put minus here.
I'm now using the second vector
over here with a minus sign.
Sorry,
this is Y.
This is the probability that
this photon is in the Y direction.
All right.
Again,
now we get minus 1 over square root of 2.
But when we square minus
1 over square root of 2,
we again get a half.
I don't need to go through the last possibility.
The probabilities for both of these
in either the X or Y direction is a half.
So either photon's prepared this way or this way,
if sent through a vertical or horizontal polarizer,
have a probability of one half going through.
That's not too surprising.
I mean,
that certainly follows intuitively.
But it follows from the mathematical formulas
that we've written down.
Here's a new observable.
We've now concocted a new observable.
The new observable is not
the polarization in the XY plane,
but it's the polarization in the 45 degree plane.
For example,
we could define it to be plus for this polarization
and minus for this polariztion.
This is a kind of rotation of the polarization observable.
We can define a new observable.
This new observable,
we will say,
is plus 1 for this
and minus 1 for that.
Can we make a operator
for which this is an eigenstate
with eigenvalue plus 1
and this an eigenstate with eigenvalue minus 1?
Here's the polarization operator
for our...
for the XY plane.
Now we want to find the polarization operator
for the 45 degree directions.
Let's give that polarization operator a name.
Let's call it this.
There's a bit of arbitrariness.
Do we call this having
plus 1 and this minus 1?
Or do we call this one
having plus 1 and this minus 1?
But let's fix it.
For the rotated polarization operator,
let's say that this has polarization plus 1
and this one minus 1.
Then we want a operator which has the property
that it gives plus 1 times this
and the same operator should give minus 1
on this polarization.
This would define an observable
that's associated with polarization
in the 45 degree direction.
In other words,
it would be the polarization observable
for a polarizer oriented in this direction.
Can we find such an operator?
Sure.
The easiest way is to do it using matrices.
Let's find the matrix.
Let's see if we can
find a matrix which does that.
I'm just going to write it down.
I'm not going to bother finding it.
Easy enough to explore around
a little bit and find it.
This is given by the matrix.
The matrix which represents it is just .
Off diagonal,
like this.
Off the diagonal.
Let's check it.
Let's check that this polarization observable
multiplies this vector to give back the same vector
and multiplies this one to give minus it.
Let's go to another blackboard.
Let's see.
Where should we do this?
I guess just over here.
What this says is that the matrix
that's the conjectured form
for this polarization observable
multiplies this vector
but that's just 1 over square root of 2,
1 over square root of 2
to give,
let's see what it gives.
0 times this is 0.
1 times this is 1 over square root of 2.
1 over square root of 2.
Check that.
So first of all,
when it hits this vector,
it gives back the same one.
Let's see what happens when it hits the other vector.
The other polarization looks exactly the same
except it has a minus 1
over square root of 2 here.
So we write 1 over square root of
2 minus 1 over square root of 2.
Let's do this one a little more carefully.
0 times this element is 0.
1 times this element is 0.
1 times this element is minus
1 over square root of 2.
And then go to the second row.
1 times square root of 2 plus 0 times this
is just 1 over square root of 2.
Notice that this vector is minus this vector.
The vector we started with was 1 over square
root of 2 minus 1 over square root of 2.
The vector we wound up with was exactly the same
except with a minus sign in front of it.
This is minus the original vector.
So in fact,
this operator,
this matrix,
represents the operator that we're looking for
and represents the observable polarization,
the polarization observable for the xy plane.
Notice that there is no vector
which is simultaneously an
eigenvector of this polarization observable
and this polarization observable.
The eigenvectors of the vertical horizontal xy polarization
are just x and y here.
The eigenvectors of the 45 degree rotated polarization
are the linear combinations x
plus y and x minus y.
There are no common eigenvectors
and this means that
these two polarizations are incompatible.
You cannot measure both of them.
You cannot measure both of them simultaneously.
In other words,
there is no polarization experiment
which can tell you simultaneously
what the xy polarization is
and what the rotated polarization is.
There are experiments which can
tell you the xy polarization.
tell you the rotated polarization.
But there's no experiment which can tell you both
because there are no simultaneous eigenvectors of these two.
In other words,
they're sort of like position and momentum,
two incompatible quantities.
If you know one of them,
you can't know the other.
If you know the other,
you can't know the first.
So these are another example of incompatibility.
Next time we'll explore
more complicated states of polarization.
We haven't discussed what happens if
the polarization is along some arbitrary angle.
I did not intend this to look like 45 degrees.
If it does,
I think it doesn't.
But in case it does,
it was not intended to be at 45 degrees.
What happens if it's at 15 degrees
and a perpendicular one which is at
90 plus 15 would be 105 degrees?
How do we describe that?
What are the eigenvectors?
How do we describe it?
And what is the polarization observable that describes it?
The one thing you can be sure
of is that it will be incompatible
with the other two that I've already described.
So there's no compatibility
between the polarization observables
in any two different directions.
Oh,
that's not quite true.
Is there anything?
Well,
if you rotate by 90 degrees,
that's trivial.
That just changes x into y.
And of course,
it basically just multiplies the polarization by minus 1.
What had plus polarization becomes minus.
Never mind.
As long as we're talking
about distinctly different axes of polarization,
then there are no simultaneous eigenvectors,
as we'll see.
And so they're all a
mutually incompatible set of polarization observables.
That's what makes this interesting.
So far,
notice that everything we've written down
has no complex numbers in it.
Why is that?
Circularly polarized.
Yeah,
that's right.
We're discussing a subset of the possible
kinds of photons which are plane polarized.
If we put complex numbers in,
then we're studying circularly polarized,
left and right.
And we'll do that also.
So there's more polarization states than
just those which are plane polarized.
There are also polarization
states which are circularly polarized.
And we'll discuss that circularly polarized light next time.
Yeah?
The probability of a photon getting through
a polarizer seems to be an observable.
Yeah.
And yet,
you don't have an operator for it.
You just think it could probably get together and get...
Wait,
excuse me.
What I've been doing here
is the observables for polarization.
What are you saying?
I'd like to .
X has an operator in X position,
so the permission operator is not .
The probability is that the bottom gets
together without an permission operator between .
I'm missing your question.
It seems like the probability is an observable.
Probability is not an observable.
Probability,
you cannot measure for a particle.
You measure probability by measuring many,
many,
many particles.
But in a single experiment,
you cannot measure the probability.
So probability is not counted as an observable.
The polarization is an observable.
You send it through a polarizer.
It either gets reflected or it doesn't get reflected.
If you get reflected a single
experiment and you get a number,
that number goes into your list,
and it's an observable quantity for each experiment.
So I don't want to mix up language.
Probability is not an observable.
It's a polar...
What's that?
It seems like you end up with
a number and after you're done through...
I didn't mean to say you can't observe the probability.
I said a probability is not an observable.
That's a technical term,
observable.
It's a thing which you
can measure in a single experiment.
You cannot measure the probability in a single experiment.
All you'll get is a
plus one or a minus one
with no way to determine what
the probability is in a single experiment.
So observables are things that you measure
in a single experiment on the system,
and you get a definite answer.
There's no way to get
a definite answer for a probability
without doing the same experiment
over and over and over again
and accumulating lots of minus ones and plus ones.
So according to the official language that we use,
probability is not an observable.
The polarization is an observable.
That doesn't mean that we don't observe the probability,
but to do so we'd have
to do a lot of repeated experiments.
I think what it's trying
to say is something like this.
You have something in a particular state,
that has been prepared in it.
You have something...
One photon.
This p-half thing that you use,
that you're going to observe,
and then you have a
third thing which is sort of...
That's what the possible result you're considering is.
And then you get a probability by squaring that.
Whoa,
whoa,
wait a minute.
Let's use language correctly.
The things that you can get...
The things that you can get,
the answers you can get,
are the eigenvalues,
the possible answers you can get are the eigenvalues.
You don't square the eigenvalues to get probabilities.
I just mean that you take the state,
you hit it with the operator,
the observable,
and you form the inner product of that resulting ket
with the bra for the particular
result that you're considering the probability of.
You take the vector describing the system.
Okay.
You don't hit it with the observable.
You just take its inner product with the eigenvectors,
with two possible eigenvectors of the observable,
x or y.
And from these,
you get probabilities by squaring.
All right.
So the role of the observable is to tell you,
or the observable operator here,
is to tell you what the
possible values that you can get,
and which states have definite values.
When you know which states have definite values,
I might have begun,
I might have begun with
the operators rather than the states.
I might have said,
this is an observable.
This is an observable.
Here are its eigenvectors,
and its eigenvalues are plus one and minus one.
I'm talking about is right there.
Okay?
Mm-hmm.
Where you write x over here on the,
at the bra.
Here?
Over here on the bra.
Yeah.
Okay?
Mm-hmm.
It's really the complex conjugate of p plus of x
using the eigenvalue equation.
Sorry.
It's just the,
it's just the complex conjugate of the vector x.
Yeah.
It's also the complex conjugate of
the left side of the equal sign.
Yeah.
But,
yeah,
I could have it in this particular case.
So in that,
in that particular case,
you're also able to write it with
the p in the same inner product.
Yeah.
But you don't want to do that generally.
You don't want to do that generally.
Okay.
What you generally want to do
is take the inner product of
the vector with the eigenvector of p.
That's the general rule.
Take the vector in question that you prepared,
take its overlap or its inner product
with an eigenvector of the observable,
and square that to get probability.
Okay.
Is observable the same,
is that synonymous with Hermitian operator?
Or is there some situation?
All observables are Hermitian operators,
and all Hermitian operators are observables.
Okay.
Right.
I was noting that the,
that you didn't have to
choose numbers one and minus one.
You could have chosen one and minus one.
Right.
I could have chosen one and zero,
or I could have chosen,
right.
One and 59.
Absolutely.
So there's an ambiguity
in what the observer writes down in his notebook.
But having chosen his convention
to call one polarization one
and the other polarization seven,
you stick with it.
Had he done that,
the operator would have been,
let's see,
where is capital P?
Then we would have written this and seven over here.
And the matrix would have been one seven.
An interesting case would have been one zero.
No,
it's as interesting as the matrix.
The expectation value of that operator
would be the probability.
In fact,
it would be,
yes.
That's correct.
Okay.
So we can actually make a correct statement using,
all right,
good,
good.
All right,
so let me give you the precise statement
which you just gave a special example of.
Take this vector,
okay?
and let's construct out of this vector
not this observable,
but another operator,
namely the dyad made like this.
Okay?
You understand what this thing is?
This is a special case of the dyads
that we spoke about before.
Mm-hmm.
Now take the vector that we're interested in
and sandwich the dyad,
this operator.
Incidentally,
this operator
is represented by one zero zero zero,
just as you said.
Okay?
Sandwich the vector,
or use the,
the vector as the bread,
the salami as the,
as the dyad in between.
Make a sandwich like this,
and this of course is the probability
because it's the inner product of psi
with the eigenvector of the observable squared.
Okay?
There's another dyad we can make.
The other dyad we can make is this one.
This expression is the probability
to find X polarization.
to find Y polarization.
But neither of these two dyads
happens to be this.
What is this?
This happens to be
the difference of the two dyads.
But I didn't,
you asked the question,
so I gave you a fairly complete answer,
but it was not what
I had intended to talk about.
Does that answer your question?
No.
It answers it,
but you may not understand it.
No?
Yeah?
Yeah.
No,
I,
I was making a comment,
not a question.
I know,
but did you understand my reaction
to your comment?
Yeah.
Yeah,
okay,
good.
Good.
Okay.
Yeah,
your comment happens to be right,
but it's only more,
somewhat accidental.
Yeah,
no,
but your,
your comment is right.
Your comment is right.
This,
you could have defined the observable this way,
and then the expectation value of it
would be the probability.
Right.
But the,
but the output would be one or zero,
not the probability.
The output of the experiment would be one or zero.
That's right.
Right.
So I think,
to get to the initial comment,
it seems like the real observable is the exclusion
that the polarization is not perpendicular to
what is the pass-through,
as opposed to that it's,
that it's,
that the polarization is what it's been filtered through.
Right.
The only thing you know is
that it's not 90 degrees off
of what the polarization is supposed
to be passing through the polarizer.
Is that what you're getting at?
But if you,
if you,
if you polarize on the,
on the y-axis,
and pass through the polarizer,
you have a 50% chance
of being 45 degrees either way,
zero percent,
zero probability.
Right.
So the only thing you know is that
the polarizer is not perpendicular to that polarization.
So the observable really is the
exclusion of the perpendicular to the polarization.
There are,
there's more than one observable that we're talking about.
Which one are you talking about?
You're talking about this one?
You're talking about the x,
xy,
yeah.
This one?
Yeah.
Well,
this observable is the observable
that's associated with a polarizer
that's polarized to the polarizer.
It's the observable that's measured by sending the photon through
a polarizer that is either along the x-direction or the y-direction.
That's what it is.
Or if you like to be precise,
it's the observable that's recorded by an observer who
writes down plus one if it goes through that polarizer,
minus one if it doesn't go through that polarizer.
And that's what it is.
I don't know any other way to say it.
To be very precise about it,
the particular observable is identified with
a particular apparatus for making a measurement.
In this case,
the apparatus is a polarizer and the polarizer,
let's say,
in the vertical direction.
The observable that's associated with it can
be taken to be that thing over there.
Of course,
you could define it differently.
As somebody said,
you didn't have to be very precise about it.
You didn't have to define the eigenvalues
to be plus one and minus one.
I did that for convenience.
I could have defined them to be 15 and 42.
That would have made very
little difference to the discussion.
I chose to define them plus
one and minus one for symmetry reasons.
But be careful with language.
The language is that the observable
is identified with a particular apparatus
and it records or it
has to do with the values
of the thing that you
would write down in your notebook
after having let the system interact with the apparatus
and then look at the apparatus.
So it's a thing that
has to do with one experiment,
not a repeated bunch of experiments.
And it's the little thing you record in your notebook,
event by event.
Good.
Everybody happy?
Thank you.
The preceding program is copyrighted by Stanford University.
Please visit us at stanford.edu.