This program is brought to you by
Stanford on iTunes U at Stanford University.
Please visit us at itunes.stanford.edu.
They behave oddly.
I've showed you some.
Interference of light waves when they go
through slits and that sort of thing.
Uncertainty principles for particles and a photon is a
particle so it shares the uncertainty principle with other particles.
But perhaps the really simplest context,
the simplest system for studying the basic fundamental difference between
classical thinking and quantum thinking is the polarization of a photon.
If we forget everything else about the photon,
assume that it's going in a particular direction,
let's say down the z-axis,
with a very specific momentum,
then the only thing that's left to discuss about
the photon is the direction in which it's polarized.
That polarization degree of freedom forms a kind of
mini quantum system that has more insight in it,
I think,
than the other kind of quantum system.
So more insight can be
gained from it than I think,
thinking about almost any
other simple quantum mechanical system.
So I want to go through,
we started last time,
I want to continue,
but first I want to review a little bit.
First of all,
you can,
how should you think about the polarization of the photon?
Well,
the photon is going into the blackboard.
Alright,
so we need not worry about its direction of motion.
We need not worry about its momentum.
We need only worry about this little vector,
this sort of little flag
that the photon carries with it.
It moves into the blackboard.
Let's see,
that's a bad color,
isn't it?
It moves into the blackboard.
That's an even worse color.
I didn't bring my own this time.
I tell them every time to please leave me pens.
Ah.
The photon is going into the blackboard.
Good.
And we can think of the plane
perpendicular to the motion of the photon.
And in that plane,
there's a kind of little flag.
The little flag can point in
any direction in the xy plane.
The photon's moving in the z direction.
This is the xy plane,
x and y.
And in a certain sense,
to be specified,
and only to be correctly defined
when we think about it quantum mechanically,
the little flag can point in
any direction in the xy plane.
So photons carry little flags.
The flags are their polarization vector.
The polarization vector is perpendicular
to the motion of the photon.
But it's an odd little flag.
It has some very peculiar properties.
So let's first of all go through
some of the simple properties that it has.
And why it is so odd.
First of all,
you can send the photon through polarizers.
Now polarizers are really not terribly quantum mechanical,
necessarily.
As I mentioned,
I think,
the previous time,
if you send microwaves or radio waves through a grid,
a grid of wires like so,
the photons,
or better yet,
the radio waves or the microwaves that go through it,
will come out on the other side polarized.
And the reason,
the best way,
the easiest way to think about it,
is to think about it in the language of waves,
electric and magnetic fields.
The electric field can vibrate vertically and horizontally,
but it can only drive current in the vertical direction.
Now,
a mirror is a system such that
when an electromagnetic wave falls on it,
a conductor,
an electric conductor,
is such that current can flow due
to the electric field in any direction,
and the flow of that current produces its own wave,
and typically what it does
is it produces the reflected wave
that reflects back off the mirror,
and that is why mirrors reflect.
Because they produce currents in there,
and those currents produce the reflected wave.
Exactly how that works,
we don't have to worry about here,
but it also works in this grid.
The only difference is that the electric
current can only oscillate in this grid.
In the vertical direction.
And so as far as the vertical direction goes,
the grid is a mirror.
It reflects waves whose electric field is vertical.
As far as the horizontal direction goes,
the grid isn't there at all.
It cannot,
the electric wave cannot drive
currents in the horizontal direction,
so it's exactly as if there
was no grid there at all,
and the photon just goes straight through.
So the result is a grid like this
produces an electromagnetic wave which is polarized.
The official definition of the polarization is
it's the direction of the electric field,
and so a grid like this will produce a photon
or an electromagnetic wave polarized this way.
I'll represent that by just drawing
my polarizer as having an axis.
The axis of polarization,
not the axis of the grid lines,
but the axis that the electromagnetic wave
that goes through it becomes polarized in.
All right,
so we send through photons one at a time,
and the photons come through.
If they pass through a polarizer like this,
they come out polarized in the x direction.
Let's call that polarization,
let's just call it x,
and never mind that we're
doing quantum mechanics for the moment.
The photons just come through.
If we send it through a second polarizer to check,
to make a check that it really was polarized horizontally,
if the second polarizer is also polarized horizontally,
then the photon will again go through.
So we can think of the
polarizer as both a preparer of systems,
it prepares a photon with a particular polarization,
and it can also be thought of as a detector,
or better yet,
a measuring apparatus that measures the photon polarization.
In particular,
if the photon was horizontally polarized,
it will pass through the horizontal polarizer.
On the other hand,
if the photon was created vertically polarized,
I don't need to put arrows on these things,
it's good enough just to put a direction.
If the photon is created vertically polarized,
and the apparatus is horizontally polarized,
then the photon will not go through the apparatus.
It may get reflected,
or it may just get absorbed,
one or the other.
But whichever it does,
by monitoring whether the photon
goes through over here or not,
you have measured whether the
polarization is vertical or horizontal.
Now there's nothing terribly non-classical about this.
You can easily imagine a classical setup
where some kind of device,
which let through a vertical flag,
would block a horizontal flag,
and would admit a vertical flag,
and vice versa.
There's nothing particularly,
and this is entirely deterministic,
if you send the photon,
if the photon is vertically polarized,
it'll pass through.
If it's horizontally polarized,
it won't pass through.
End of story.
Nothing out of the ordinary there.
The place where the out of the ordinary happens
is when we add to
this picture the idea of symmetry.
Yes?
Lastly,
do you have photons?
No,
but you could imagine that there are
bullets which have little flags on them.
Bullets with little,
funny shaped bullets.
With flags on them like that.
And they go through.
If they're along the direction of some kind of slits,
they get blocked otherwise.
Nothing special.
So classical particles could easily do this kind of thing.
The place where you start to
get into trouble thinking classically is,
oh,
one other thing.
Notice that there are also
only two possibilities for the photon.
It either goes through or it
doesn't go through in this setup.
Now,
now comes the kicker.
The kicker has to do with symmetry.
The symmetry is the symmetry
of rotation of the xy plane.
If it's possible to hold your polarizer vertically,
and it's possible to hold it horizontally,
then the symmetry of physics,
which allows you to rotate things,
allows you to construct a
polarizer which points at any angle.
What happens to a photon which goes through that?
It comes out polarized at an angle.
Well,
you can imagine classical setups.
For example,
a kind of setup which would emit,
which would allow this particular
kind of bullet to go through.
The other kind of bullet,
which was polarized horizontally,
would not go through.
Any kind of device that I
try to think of like that,
I tend to find would also
block a bullet that was polarized
in some non-vertical or non-horizontal direction.
For example,
if the polarizer literally consisted of a bunch of,
a grid,
a grid like this,
which passed things which were vertical,
blocked things which are horizontal,
it would also block things which were not horizontal.
Here's where the kicker is.
The kicker is that these
non-vertically or non-horizontally polarized photons
may or may not go through this polarizer.
They may or may not go through with a probability.
What's more,
there is only two possibilities.
The photon doesn't get broken into pieces,
some piece of it going through,
some piece of it not going through.
There are only two possibilities.
And that's it.
It either goes through or it doesn't go through,
even though it has been polarized in some other direction.
That's where the peculiarities of quantum mechanics start.
That's where you begin to wonder,
is the photon really behaving like a particle,
like a sensible particle or not?
And it gets even weirder and more mysterious
when we start to set
up a theory of the probabilities
for the photons to pass through the respective polarizers.
That theory is of course quantum mechanics.
And it is really quite hard
to think of a classical setup
which would produce the
same kind of probability distributions
and how they depend on the orientation of the polarizers.
I don't think anybody has
ever successfully designed such a thing,
at least not in any great generality,
that would do the right thing to polarize photons.
By design,
I mean design a classical apparatus
which would do the right thing.
So there are only two possibilities.
The photon either appears to be polarized up
or appears to be polarized horizontally when you detect it.
When you detect it with a horizontal polarizer,
it either goes through or it doesn't go through.
So you would be likely to
say there's only two possible states
for the photon.
On the other hand,
there's more than two possible states.
There's a continuum of possible states for the photon.
You can polarize it in any direction.
And so we have a kind
of conflict between discreteness and continuity.
Continuous direction in which the photon can be polarized,
but when we monitor it and we detect it,
there are only two possible states,
one or the other.
And that's the mystery of quantum mechanics.
It's a conflict between symmetry on the one hand
and discreteness on the other hand.
Okay,
so we were beginning to
set up the theory of polarization.
As I said,
it is probably the simplest context
in which to study quantum mechanics.
It doesn't have the full
complexity of all of quantum mechanics,
but it's the simplest quantum mechanical system.
So let's now label the quantum
states of the polarization of a photon.
I will make this phrase shorter.
I will simply say the quantum states of a photon,
but I mean its polarization.
All right,
it can be polarized horizontally.
Incidentally,
there is no difference between being polarized horizontally
to the right or polarized horizontally to the left.
That's why I tend to
draw double arrows on the polarization.
There's no difference between being polarized to the right
or polarized to the left.
If you think about it for a moment,
an electromagnetic wave will oscillate up and down,
and so there's no sense in which you can say
the polarization is vertically up versus vertically down,
and the photon inherits that fact.
Polarization,
you can think of a polarization vector,
but it kind of has two ends.
There's no sense in which it points
to the right rather than to the left,
but there is a sense in
which it's pointing horizontal rather than vertical.
So in some way,
it's simpler than the spin one
half system you looked at before.
Well,
they're actually quite isomorphic to each other.
They're completely parallel,
completely identical mathematics,
and the reason for not doing it this time,
the spin,
is because I did it last time.
That's the main reason.
Some people find it a little easier to visualize
the polarization of a photon.
They're identical systems quantum mechanically,
and so we don't really need to distinguish that.
Well,
okay,
let's go on.
All right,
we're going to call that,
we're going to give that the name x.
That's the ket vector x.
It represents a photon polarized horizontally.
And another way that we can label it,
I'm going to take these arrows off.
I get awfully tired of drawing arrows,
and they serve no purpose.
However,
since there's no sense of direction along the arrow,
and I'll also label that one zero.
Another representation of the,
oh,
incidentally,
the vector space of states
is clearly two-dimensional,
since there are only two possibilities for the polarization.
Two possibilities for the polarization,
x or y,
and we'll label y zero one.
All right,
so several different representations
to label the states of the photon polarization.
Yes?
Is that totally arbitrary,
one and zero,
to be anything else,
or?
No,
it's not totally arbitrary.
We want these vectors to be normalized.
Sums of the squares of the
components should add up to one.
That's one of the rules about state vectors.
That corresponds to the total probability
for a state adding up to one.
We want them to be orthogonal to each other.
These two vectors are clearly orthogonal.
Multiply the top by the top,
plus the bottom by the bottom.
Incidentally,
in order to take the inner product,
you should complex conjugate one of them,
but the complex conjugate of the bottom one is itself.
So it's one times zero plus zero times one.
x,
y equals zero.
They're orthogonal.
They're normalized.
They form a basis.
Now,
it's not completely...
In some sense,
you've chosen your axes
so that those will be normal.
Yes,
I have.
Now,
I could have...
We will see that these vectors are somewhat ambiguous.
We're going to calculate the things which really count,
and when we calculate what really count,
namely probabilities,
we'll find out that we can't,
for example,
distinguish this vector and this vector.
The fact that there's something in the first place
and nothing in the second place is the important thing,
and the other important thing is that
the sums of the squares of them
add up to...
Sums of the squares of the
two components add up to one.
But this is a convenient basis of the vectors
which represent the two states.
Okay?
We also said that we could define an observable.
An observable means the thing that we measure
or that we record in our little book.
We send a lot of photons through.
If a photon goes through the apparatus,
we say plus one.
If it doesn't go through the apparatus,
we say minus one.
Now,
there,
there's absolutely nothing unique.
I could have said seven and twelve.
Anything I like,
just to distinguish the two possibilities,
one and minus one are a nice pair of numbers
that they're easy to remember,
and there's no particular significance
to choosing one and minus one.
It's easy to remember,
has a nice symmetry to it.
And so what we'll say is that the X polarization,
we'll say has polarization plus,
and the Y polarization has polarization minus.
Again,
what I mean by that is
we send a lot of photons
through an X polarizer.
If they pass through,
each time a photon passes through the X polarizer,
we write down a little plus in our notebook.
Each time it is reflected
or whatever else happens to it,
we write down a little minus,
and then we can take statistics,
we can define the observable quantity
in the way that I said,
and label it or associate it
with a quantum mechanical observable.
A quantum mechanical observable is an operator.
I'll put a little hat on it.
If I forget to put a hat on it,
as long as it's this big double P here,
it means an operator.
It's an operator whose eigenvectors are X and Y,
or this one and this one,
and it has eigenvalue plus one
for X and minus one for Y.
That's unique.
Abstractly,
we know how it acts on any vector,
because any vector can be
linearly expanded in X and Y,
but here's the state.
This is equal to X,
and P on Y is equal to minus Y.
The eigenvalues are plus one and minus one,
and I'm going to label this thing here
just to indicate that it's a polarizer,
that it represents polarization in the XY plane.
I'm going to put a little symbol here
that represents the fact that it
has to do with the XY plane,
as opposed to some rotated direction.
Okay.
So this is its definition.
It's an operator,
a linear operator.
Associated with every linear operator is a matrix.
The matrix associated with P
is the matrix one minus one,
as simple as it could be.
And it's obvious now that when
it acts on the vector X,
let's let it act on the vector X,
it acts on the vector Y.
The vector X is represented by one,
zero.
That matrix times that column vector,
one times one is one.
Zero times one and one
times zero minus one times zero,
zero.
So we see that the P observable,
when it acts on the X vector,
X polarization gives us back the X polarization vector,
but when it acts,
sorry,
when it acts on the Y polarization vector,
it gives minus the Y polarization vector.
So this is the unique operator
which represents the observable,
the observable polarization
in the X-Y plane.
Now in this case,
we knew what we wanted,
we constructed the vectors,
and then we made up an observable
and we concocted it just so we
would do what we wanted it to do.
In other cases,
and I'll give you an example of another case,
in other cases,
there might be reasons to focus on an observable,
on an operator,
and ask what its eigenvectors are
and what its eigenvalues are.
The example that I've already given you
was for example the momentum.
The momentum was described by an operator,
minus I d by dx.
I told you what the operator was,
and then we found its eigenvectors and its eigenvalues.
So sometimes it's more convenient,
not a question more convenient,
sometimes we know more about the vectors and the eigenvalues
than we do about the
mathematical structure of the observable,
and sometimes we know it the other way.
But either way,
observables have eigenvalues and eigenvectors.
The eigenvectors are the states
in which the observable has a definite value,
and that value is the eigenvalue.
So we're back to the basic foundations of the subject
and the postulates.
We have an example.
Now,
what if we polarize at 45 degrees?
What if we turn our polarizer through 45 degrees?
I know we did this before,
but let's do it again.
If we rotate our polarizer through 45 degrees,
then we encounter a new state of polarization.
It's neither x nor y.
It's intuitively obvious
that it has equal probability,
when the photon is prepared this way,
and then goes through the x or y polarizer,
it's intuitively obvious
that it will have equal probability
to go through either the x or the y polarizer,
since it's polarized at 45 degrees.
So,
it makes sense then
to identify this polarization,
which I'll label that way,
as 1 over the square root of 2,
that's just there to normalize it,
times x plus y.
Equal likelihood for the polarization
to be up or horizontal
if it goes through the polarizer
which detects x polarization.
We can also represent this in another way.
We can represent it as a column vector,
1 over square root of 2,
1 over square root of 2.
Equal coefficients in terms of x,
or in front of x and in front of y.
Alright,
what about the other orthogonal polarization?
The other orthogonal polarization,
I won't draw it in here,
but it points in the orthogonal direction,
that's equal to 1 over square root of 2,
and that can be taken to be,
now the one thing we know about it,
and about the only thing we really know about it,
is that it should be orthogonal to this vector.
Orthogonal to this vector.
Why orthogonal to it?
Because it represents a completely distinct,
different outcome of an experiment.
Namely,
the experiment of sending it through
the 45 degree polarizer.
Alright,
things which represent different outcomes,
different definite outcomes of some experiment,
should be orthogonal to each other.
Well,
a simple vector that's orthogonal to this
would be x minus 1.
So,
x minus 1,
not x minus,
x,
minus y,
or,
1 over root 2,
minus 1 over root 2.
Now,
it makes no difference whatever,
if you put the minus
sign in front of the x
with no minus sign in front of the y,
or vice versa.
We'll see,
it makes no difference.
All we need to do
is to choose a second vector
orthogonal to this one.
Let's check that it's orthogonal.
So,
the inner product between this vector and this vector
are the sums of the x components,
the product of the x components,
and the product of the y components.
So,
it's 1 over square root of 2
times 1 over square root of 2,
minus 1 over square root of 2
times 1 over square root of 2.
The inner product is 0.
Again,
I didn't have to worry about complex conjugating,
because everything is real.
So,
we can write down,
1 over square root of 2
times 1 over square root of 2,
equals 0.
They're also normalized.
The sums of the squares of
the coefficients add up to 1.
1 over root 2 squared,
plus 1 over root 2 squared is 1.
So,
the two vectors are another basis.
They're a different and separate basis of states,
but they're just as good as the original basis.
The original basis was the basis 1,
0 and 0,
1.
Here's the second basis.
These are also mutually orthogonal,
and also normalized.
Roughly speaking,
well,
you can see the point.
I don't need to belabor it.
What happens,
if we start with a polarizer,
polarized at 45 degrees like that,
we send the photon through it,
it comes out the other side,
and then we send it through a polarizer,
which is either vertical or horizontal.
Let's take the horizontal case.
Then the rule of quantum mechanics is,
well,
let's see what we have.
Let's begin.
What is the state of the photon
when it comes out of the first polarizer?
When it comes out of the first polarizer,
here it is.
It's this.
So,
when it comes out of the first polarizer,
the state of the photon is like that.
What is the probability
that if we measure
the observable associated with the
x-y polarization
that we get plus?
The answer is,
again,
this goes back to the basic
postulates.
We take the inner product
of the state
that we've constructed,
we take the inner product of that
with the eigenvector
of the observable of interest.
The observable of interest
is now this observable,
and its eigenvectors are x and y.
So,
we take the inner product,
for example,
of this with x,
and we square it.
That will give us the probability
that after having gone through
the first polarizer,
it also goes through the second polarizer.
That's the probability that after going
through the first polarizer,
it then goes through the second polarizer.
We could also draw this x
as just a horizontal line here.
What is this?
This is the inner product.
Let's write them down.
The bra vector here can be represented
as a row vector,
the ket vector is a column vector,
and the inner product between them
is just .
So,
we have 1 over root 2.
1 times 1 over root 2.
The probability is the square of that.
So,
I shouldn't have written equals here.
I should have taken this away.
This is true now.
And the probability is the square of this.
Equal 1 half.
Okay,
so that was intuitively clear
in the first place,
that the probability for the photon
to go through the second polarizer
would be 1 half,
since it was polarized at 45 degrees.
Likewise,
if we ask what's the probability
that it would pass through a vertical polarizer,
same answer,
slightly different reason.
To calculate that,
we would put y here.
But that's also equal 1 over square root of 2.
And so,
both cases we would get the probability being 1 half.
Again,
not surprising.
Can we construct an observable
which represents the photon polarization
not in the vertical and horizontal direction,
but in the 45 degree directions?
Let's see if we can do that.
Let's invent the polarization now.
And let's call it this.
Let's call it that way.
It has the property that when it acts on...
I wish I had names for these two vectors.
Anybody think of names for the two vectors?
The slanty vectors?
Hmm?
I want a name for both of them.
I mean,
for each of them.
Slash and backslash.
Good.
Okay.
So,
the observable associated with slash and backslash
I will define to be plus 1 on slash.
And I'll define it to be
minus 1 on backslash.
What's the observable?
Can we find it?
Yeah,
it's not hard.
I'll just tell you what
the answer is in a minute.
And then we'll check it.
The matrix that's associated with it is rather simple.
It's .
Let's check that that acts on slash to give backslash
and acts on backslash to give backslash.
Alright.
Slash is just 1 over
square root of 2 times .
Where is it?
The 1 over square root of 2 here doesn't...
Here it is.
Here's slash.
It's 1 over square root of 2 times .
If a thing is an eigenvector,
so is any multiple of it.
So we don't need to
keep the square root of 2
in checking whether it's an eigenvector.
We do need to keep the square root
of 2 if we want to normalize it.
But if all we want
to do is check for eigenvectorness,
we need not keep that square
root of 2 in the problem.
Alright.
So what does this give?
It gives 0 times 1 plus 1 times 1.
1 times 1 plus 0 times 1 is 1.
So that is in fact what the
observable is supposed to do on slash.
It gives backslash.
Let's now try it on backslash.
0,
1,
0 on 1 minus 1.
What does that give?
0 times 1 plus 1 times 1.
1 times minus 1.
That gives minus 1.
1 times 1 is 1.
Notice that the right hand
side is the negative of backslash.
So in fact,
the observable on backslash does give minus backslash.
This is equal to minus 1 minus 1.
Okay.
So what does that give?
1 minus 1 times 2 minus 1 –
Minus 1 plus 1 minus 2 minus 1
plus 2 plus 3 minus 1 times 1 –
But what you get is 0 times 1.
So how do you know that here a
turned into 1 so I may 20ご oldtopustome?
How wrong is it to
be positive in what I did?
2 made it to a positive?
2 made it to a negative.
You may ask
You can't ask what's observable anything
is observable if it's an observable,
but you can ask what is definite
Given a particular state let's say slash are there any
quantities which when you measure them will give you definite
deterministic answers
Well if you measure
the original
observable
You won't get definite answers you get a half a
probability one way a half a probability the other way
If you start with slash on the
other hand if you measure this observable
The polarization at the 45 degree angle
Then you will get definite answers for slash and backslash
This corresponds of course to sending slash and backslash
through the slashed or backslash polarizers
So it's not right to say that
That if you're given a state it determines what's
observable no it determines what's definite it determines what's predictable
about
measurements on that state
Another example is if you're given
a wave function any wave function
You can measure the position of the electron and the momentum
of the electron if you just take a random wave function
And the old wave function you'll have a
statistical probability for different momentum and different positions
Neither will be definite
But if you take a delta function,
which is a very particular state delta function of position
Then you measure the position it'll be definite
It'll be right where that delta function says
it should be if you take a plane wave
Cosine not a cosine or sine,
but an e to the ikx and you
measure the momentum then the momentum will be definite
so given a state it
restricts the class of things which are
deterministic
It's not the right word
What's the right word definite I suppose certain?
Okay,
so this is the object the mathematical representation of
the object which is definite for slash and backslash states
It happens that I defined it so that it's positive so
the eigenvalue is positive 1 for slash and negative 1 for
backslash and negative 1 for backslash
I could have defined it the other way then I
would have put a minus sign in front of it
But that's not important
Okay,
well
So far we have polarizers which are oriented
That way and polarizers which are oriented that way
We can of course orient the polarizers in any direction
in any direction in the xy plane
So let's discuss that possibility now
Arbitrary angle
Let's write.
Let's have a polarizer now
Which is polarized in the arbitrary
angle theta theta relative to the horizontal
Then there's another polarizer
Which is orthogonal to this
Which is polarized in the perpendicular?
direction
polarized this way
We don't need
to
Invent a new label for this this is just
the polarizer whose angle is theta plus pi over 2
Pi over 2 is 90 degrees if you take
theta and you add 90 degrees to it it becomes
perpendicular so we can label the two
states theta and theta plus pi over 2
They represent the two orthogonal combinations
the two
mutually exclusive combinations if
you send the photon through
Any photon which goes through a theta
polarizer will pass through a second theta polarizer
But it will get blocked by
a theta plus pi over 2 polarizer.
That's a mouthful
The two vectors the two eigenvectors that go with
it if you pass it through the theta polarizer
You get out the state theta
I'm going to tell you what it is
how it's related to to the other states
in a more or less obvious way and
This one will be called theta plus pi over 2
These two should be orthogonal to each other
But they're not likely to be
orthogonal to the previous states in fact
If this goes to a vertical polarizer
it won't get blocked or may get blocked,
but it may not get blocked
so
We don't expect this to be
orthogonal to the vertical polarization or the horizontal
polarization or for that matter the 45 degree polarization
It's not going but they
should be perpendicular to each other.
They should be orthogonal to each other
Okay,
so let me tell you what this is
Now the justification for this is ultimately experimental,
but it makes sense it makes intuitive sense
We're rotating the horizontal polarization by an angle
Theta we started with that polarization and the
horizontal and now we rotate it by angle theta
It shouldn't be too surprising
that the answer is cosine theta
times the X polarization plus sine theta
Times the Y polarization or
equivalently cosine theta sine theta
in fact cosine theta and sine theta
Simply the components of a vector
a unit vector along the theta direction
So that's not too surprising
How about this one?
This one had better be exactly the
same except wherever you see theta here.
You should stick in theta plus pi over 2
so this should be cosine of
Theta plus pi over 2,
but what's the cosine of theta plus pi over 2?
Well not quite
close
minus the sine minus the sine of theta
Cosine of theta plus pi over
2 is minus the sine of theta
Let's let's just check why that's so
All right
Here's the sine of theta
Here's the cosine of theta now
here's theta plus pi over 2
Okay notice that?
That the cosine of theta plus pi over 2 that's
the X projection here the cosine is the X projection
The cosine here is negative
But the sine is positive
So the cosine of theta plus pi
over 2 is minus the sine of theta
Sine minus sine theta
X
plus the sine of theta
plus pi over 2
times Y
But what's the sine of theta plus pi over 2?
That's cosine theta
Okay now we can represent this bottom case here by
minus sine cosine
so
I can do this with a
OK this one represents a photon polarized along theta and
this one represents a photon polarized in the orthogonal direction
Are these orthogonal basis vectors?
Well first of all
are they normalized to unity in other words
as the length of them equal to unity?
Well,
that's just cosine squared plus sine squared equals 1
Cosine squared plus sine squared equals 1 so
that's the cosine of theta plus pi over 2
So they're normalized,
both of them.
Sine squared plus cosine squared is equal to one.
Again,
no complex numbers in these vectors here,
so we don't have to worry about complex
conjugation.
Next,
are they orthogonal?
Let's check that.
Cosine theta times minus sine theta
plus sine theta times cosine theta.
Obviously they are orthogonal.
Cosine times minus sine plus sine
times cosine adds up to zero.
So,
yes,
they also happen to be orthogonal to each other.
Theta plus pi over two equals zero.
And we've got yet another basis.
We've got yet another basis of
vectors for our space of states.
It represents a physically different kind of experiment,
a similar kind of experiment,
but different in that the different.
The polarizers are now in an arbitrary direction,
theta.
Now we can ask the question,
supposing we construct one of these theta photons,
a photon
polarized along the theta axis,
what's the probability that if we send it through an
x polarizer that it will pass through?
So let's do that experiment.
I mean,
this is exactly the kind of question
that quantum mechanics is set up to answer.
We have our theta polarizer over here.
We send our photon.
I'm going to make a red photon this time.
We send our photon through.
Of course,
the photon may not go through.
The photon may have been polarized in some wrong direction.
But.
But if it gets through,
it is then a theta polarized photon.
It's now a theta polarized photon.
And we now send it through a second polarizer,
which I'm going to take to be an x polarizer.
What's the probability that it goes through?
Question mark.
Does it or doesn't it?
And if it does or doesn't,
what's the probability?
This is the kind of question now that classical mechanics,
who would make no sense in classical
mechanics,
and classical mechanics is deterministic.
It either goes through or it doesn't go through.
OK,
so let's figure it out.
All we have to do is
take the inner product between theta,
that's our starting vector
here in the middle,
and x.
The square of this is the probability.
OK,
so what is this?
This is,
we can work it out using
the column vectors and row vectors.
OK.
The x is the row vector 0,
1,
0,
excuse me.
And theta is the column vector cosine theta sine theta.
And that inner product is just cosine theta.
1 times cosine theta plus 0 times sine theta.
That inner product is just cosine of theta.
Incidentally,
notice that it doesn't matter whether you take.
Whether you take.
Take.
Either way,
x theta or theta x.
The reason is that although in general
these objects are complex and different than each
other,
they're complex conjugates of each other.
When you square them or
when multiplied by their complex conjugate,
it doesn't matter
which order you put them in.
OK,
but in this case especially where everything's real,
it certainly doesn't matter.
And then the probability,
the probability over here,
the question,
the probability question,
this is not the observable.
This is the probability.
This is the probability that if a photon
was polarized in the theta direction that it passes
through the x polarizer.
That probability is the square of this inner product.
In other words,
it's cosine squared theta.
Notice it's cosine squared theta,
not cosine of theta.
OK.
What's the probability that it
passes through the y polarizer?
Let's send it through the y polarizer.
Through the y polarizer,
that's going to be very similar
except we're going to put y here.
And that's 0,
1.
This gives us sine theta.
OK.
That's going to give us sine squared theta.
What's the total probability that
it will either pass through the,
well,
the total probability
if we add up the probabilities
that it's x polarized or y polarized,
it's either x polarized
or y polarized,
here's the probability that it's,
I'm sorry,
squared.
Squared.
It's either x polarized or y polarized.
With probability cosine squared
theta and sine squared theta,
the total probability
adds up to 1.
OK.
So here's another,
here's a slightly more intricate
example of a quantum mechanical
problem,
where we send something through at an
arbitrary angle and then measure its polarization
along the vertical or horizontal direction.
We can go further.
We could send it through a
polarizer in the 45 degree angle here.
We have enough information to figure out
the probabilities that it'll go through 45,
pi over 2,
the pi over 2 polarizer.
But why work that out?
Let's just send it through an arbitrary angle,
the first one,
and a second arbitrary angle,
the third one.
I'm going to call those angles,
I hate using primes,
so I'm going to call them alpha and beta.
Alpha and beta are also good Greek letters.
When it passes through the first polarizer,
it comes out alpha polarized.
And then we want to know what's the
probability it will pass through the beta polarizer.
Let's check that and see if
we can get a general formula,
which will serve for all possible,
polarizers.
What's the answer going to depend on?
Is it going to depend on alpha times beta,
alpha plus beta?
Alpha minus beta.
The relative,
the angular distance between them.
It better,
otherwise we're doing something wrong.
Right,
okay,
so let's check out.
Alright,
here's where I either shine or,
or don't shine.
Okay,
so let's take the alpha,
let's take the alpha,
let's take the inner product of
the alpha vector with the beta vector.
The alpha vector,
oh,
you know,
before we do so,
let me do a bit of review of trigonometry.
A review of some trigonometric formulas that we'll use.
Keep in mind what problem we want to solve.
Two polarizers at arbitrary angles,
but we need a bit of trigonometry.
So let me just write down
the trigonometric formulas that we need.
Cosine alpha plus beta equals,
anybody know?
Cosine alpha cosine beta minus
sine alpha sine beta.
Now let's,
while we're at it,
we're going to wind up also
wanting cosine of alpha minus beta.
And to get the cosine of alpha minus beta,
we just change the sine of beta in this formula.
Changing the sine of beta does nothing to cosine beta,
but it changes the sine of,
it changes the sine of sine.
It changes the sine of sine.
It changes the sine with a
g of sine without a g.
Got it?
Okay.
So that gives us cosine alpha cosine beta
plus sine alpha sine beta.
Notice we don't change sine alpha.
We haven't done anything to alpha.
We've only done something to beta.
We will also need
sine of alpha plus beta.
And that is equal to
sine alpha cosine beta
plus sine beta cosine alpha.
And while we're at it,
let's also do sine of alpha minus beta.
Again,
all I've done is change beta.
It doesn't change the cosine of beta,
but it does change the sine of beta.
So this becomes sine alpha cosine beta
minus sine beta.
So,
I've got sine beta cosine alpha.
A nice check we can do.
What if alpha equals beta?
If alpha equals beta,
we have cosine of zero.
Cosine of zero is what?
One.
Alright.
On the right-hand side,
we would have cosine of alpha squared,
alpha is equal to beta,
cosine of alpha squared
plus sine of alpha squared.
That's one.
Cosine squared plus sine squared.
So that works.
How about sine of alpha minus beta?
What should that be?
Sorry,
if alpha equals beta?
That should be zero.
So if alpha equals beta,
these two will cancel each other.
Okay,
one more.
Cosine of two alpha.
That's easy.
We just read it off from here.
That's cosine squared alpha
minus sine squared alpha.
And sine of two alpha,
we read from here.
That's just twice sine cosine.
Alright,
here's our trigonometric table of formulas.
And,
uh,
we'll use them.
Okay,
so we passed through the first polarizer.
It's the alpha polarizer.
And what comes out is the alpha ket alpha,
which is equal to cosine alpha,
let's just write it this way,
cosine alpha sine alpha.
Just using this formula,
replacing it with this formula.
And we're replacing theta by alpha.
So we passed through the alpha polarizer.
But now we're testing for beta polarization.
The beta ket is,
of course,
cosine beta sine beta.
Or I really want the,
uh,
I really want the bra vector.
So the bra vector is beta
is equal to the row,
row of cosine beta sine beta.
We just turn it and make
a row vector out of it.
Now what's the inner product?
The inner product of alpha and beta,
beta alpha,
is cosine alpha times cosine beta
plus sine alpha times sine beta.
And lo and behold,
I hope,
that's the top formula,
which is,
no,
it's the second one,
which is cosine of alpha minus beta.
Now that's,
of course,
not the probability.
That's the thing that we square to get the probability.
So the probability,
is just cosine squared of alpha minus beta.
How could you be absolutely
sure that this wasn't the probability,
even if you didn't know any quantum mechanics?
Yeah,
because it can be negative.
Right.
All right.
Here's our formula.
Indeed,
it only depends on the difference between the angles.
But let's look at it a little more carefully.
First of all,
what happens if beta is,
beta is very,
very close to alpha?
In fact,
what happens if beta is equal to alpha?
If beta is equal to alpha,
we get cosine squared of zero,
which is one.
So that simply says,
that if we polarize along the alpha direction,
and then we send it through a polarizer very,
very close to the alpha direction,
it has a very high probability of getting through.
Almost equal to one.
Cosine alpha minus beta is almost equal to one,
if alpha is close to beta.
And as beta is rotated away from alpha,
this gets smaller.
When they're 90 degrees apart from each other,
then the cosine of 90 degrees is zero,
and there's no probability to go through.
So the formula makes some sense.
Formula looks good.
But keep in mind,
we're doing something interesting.
Interesting and unusual.
There are only two possible outcomes
to the beta experiment over here.
There are only two possible things that can
come out of the alpha polarizer over here.
And yet,
we're finding answers,
but answers which are probabilistic.
Answers which are probabilistic,
and equal to the square of quantum mechanical amplitudes.
These inner products are called amplitudes,
they're squares of probabilities.
So,
all right,
let's see,
shall we take a,
let's take a few minutes break.
And what we haven't done yet,
is found the observable
for a general polarization.
Observable for general polarization,
we'll do next.
All right,
so two people asked me an interesting question,
and,
it sort of does point out one of the,
somewhat mildly,
I don't know,
it depends on who
I've known it for so long
that to me it's mildly freaky,
but here's the issue
supposing you send a photon through a polarizer,
which is
polarized,
let's say in the theta direction,
not horizontally,
definitely not horizontally
but in some arbitrary direction,
and then you're going to send it through a second
polarizer or third,
I'm going to call this the third polarizer up here,
far away,
and it's
polarized in the orthogonal direction theta plus pi over two
of course the first photon
may or may not get through,
but let's suppose
it gets through,
it's polarized in the theta direction
and it will not make it through
the theta plus pi over two polarizer,
but supposing we put in
between a polarizer,
let's say in the vertical direction,
now let's make
it the horizontal direction,
for no good reason other than
then does it get through or doesn't it get through
the answer is it gets through with a probability,
the probability
we can calculate,
let's calculate the probability
well let's work it out,
I don't know,
I haven't worked it out,
the first question
is what's the probability that
it gets through the horizontal polarizer
I think we have a formula
for the horizontal polarizer that corresponds
to beta equals zero,
and the answer was just cosine squared theta
the probability cosine squared theta that the photon
makes it through the first polarizer here,
cosine squared theta
but now
when it makes it through the first polarizer,
it is now polarizing
in the horizontal direction,
it is no longer polarized in the theta direction
if it makes it through,
it's polarized in the horizontal direction
so what's the probability that
it goes through the third polarizer
it is cosine squared of,
now we have to take
the angle over here minus the angle over here
that's zero minus pi plus theta over two
cosine of theta plus pi over two
which is what?
sine squared theta
I think I did that right
not added,
but multiplied
the probability that it goes through
the first one is cosine squared theta
and then if it does,
it's horizontally polarized
if it's horizontally polarized,
then the probability that it
goes through the second polarizer
is sine squared theta
which is the same as cosine
squared of theta plus pi over two
what's that?
well
at a certain moment,
you're polarizing
say it again now
at a certain moment,
you're polarizing
this is less than one
right,
there is less than one
so it passes through this polarizer
with a probability less than one
each time you cut down the probability
so the probability if you do
a lot of polarizers like this
of course will go down with the number of polarizers
but by putting this one in
you take a photon which
was polarized in the theta direction
and could not go through the second one
and now allow it
so this is one of the
whether you find this
anti-intuitive or not is
it gets an assist
correct
if you actually do that
you'll get,
based on the angle in between
you actually get a different color
if you start off with
it may be,
but I don't know why
it's not silent
I don't know why
I've seen it so high over there
maybe so,
I don't know why it's true though
seems like
well,
polarizers
you don't change the energy of the photon
no,
no
yeah,
well
but do keep in mind
that polarizers have different efficiencies
for different colors
so it might,
I would have to think about it
but
it's also used as a stress test for blocks
yeah,
I,
you,
that's true
I've seen them do things like that
so I don't know offhand
I would have to think about why that's true
but it probably has to do with the fact that
the efficiency for polarizations is frequency dependent
it's optical by the way
I think the high frequency
goes through the
are too high for a big one
perhaps,
let me think about it
I,
it's completely something I didn't even know
so,
so I need to,
I need to
I need to,
dwell on it a little bit
okay,
good
interesting fact if it's true
but this is kind of an interesting quantum mechanical fact
that,
um
it's an interference effect
it's a funny kind of interference effect
that something
you would have thought that by
whatever the probability to go
through the second polarizer was
you would have diminished it
by putting something in the way,
huh?
by putting something else in the way
which cuts down the probability
you would have thought that
you would diminish the probability
well,
as you can see,
it's not always true
so this is one of these interference phenomena
okay,
let's see if we can find the,
um
the observable
now we're not learning very much by
figuring out the observables in these cases
I just want to show you that they exist
they make sense,
they're eigenvalues
and eigenvectors are correct
uh,
are,
are correct
there are lots of other cases where
we know much more about the observables
than we do about anything else
and then we work in the opposite direction
but okay
we're interested now in the observable
representing polarization in the theta direction
in other words,
by definition
this one's a little bit thicker
p theta acting on theta
gives us plus theta
and p theta acting on theta plus pi over two
gives us minus theta plus pi over two
in other words,
both of these vectors
both of these polarization states
theta
theta plus pi over two
they're both eigenvectors of the observable polarization
but eigenvectors with opposite eigenvalue
let's see if we can,
I'm not going to see if we can find it
I'm going to write down the answer
and then show you that it works
uh,
it took me about fifteen,
well,
less than fifteen minutes
ten minutes to work it out
and all I did was solve
I simply wrote these as algebraic equations
and solved the algebraic equations
component-wise
it was not very illuminating
but it's mildly illuminating to see
the answer and then check it
so,
the answer is
where is the answer?
here it is
p theta
is equal to cosine
minus cosine
sine
but cosine and sine of what?
anybody want to guess?
two theta
that's in the upper left
here we have
twice cosine theta sine theta
do anybody mind if instead of
writing cosine theta and sine theta
I'm just going to write c and s
c and s for cosine and sine theta
there will be no confusion
since there's only one angle here
so,
this is c squared minus s squared
this is twice s c
this is twice
s c
and this is s squared minus c squared
and we want to apply this now to theta
what is theta?
theta is
c s
look up on the upper right corner
okay,
let's just work it out
so we have to multiply c
squared minus s squared by c
so,
in the upper place we have
c squared
c squared c minus s squared c
that's this times this
plus twice s c times s
what about in the bottom?
in the bottom we have twice s c times c
twice s c times c
twice s
alright,
leave it that way
twice s c times c
plus
s squared s
minus c squared s
plus s c times s squared c times s
don't ask me why I
wrote it in this clumsy way
I don't know why
we have twice s squared c over here
this is twice s squared c over here
but we have minus s squared c over here
so,
the plus two and the minus one
conspire to change this to a plus sign
to a plus sign
and we get rid of this
now we have c squared plus s squared times c
c is a common factor in both of them
so,
let's take c outside
and now what is c squared plus s squared?
one
so,
this is just c
that's good
because we want to get
remember what we're trying to get
that p theta on theta just gives us back theta
ok now let's look at the lower piece here
twice s c c
here's minus c c s
so the two again conspires with the minus sign
turns it into a plus sign
and now we have
s squared s plus c squared s
and that's just s.
So we check explicitly that
p theta on theta gives us
back theta and I'll leave it to you
to check that p theta on this guy here
gives minus itself back again so these two vectors,
where are they?
Cs and minus sc are the eigenvectors of the observable.
The observable is hermitian
how do you tell that it's hermitian?
Remember what hermitian means?
Hermitian means that if you reflect
about the diagonal and complex conjugate you
get back to the same
thing.
For real matrices,
we're going to talk more about hermitian,
but for real
matrices hermitian just means symmetric.
This is a hermitian matrix,
its eigenvectors
and eigenvalues satisfy certain requirements.
The eigenvectors are
orthogonal,
the eigenvalues are real.
This is the observable that goes with the
polarization along the angle theta.
What happens incidentally,
interesting
question,
supposing I'm
going to take this,
here's the observable for angle theta.
What is the observable for
minus theta?
What happens to minus theta,
to the observable minus theta?
That's not
really what I want to do is it?
I don't think that's what I actually want to do.
I'm going
to look at,
what I wanted to do was to look
at the observable for theta plus Pi over two.
For theta plus Pi over two.
What happens to observable for theta plus Pi over two?
Theta plus Pi is just an alternative.
THEN you write the fraction and you put in the
I want to take in there.
If thiscess g is 0,
I just subtract h1 over here.
I'll add
this time to the relativores to mu degrees j.
I Okay,
that's the observable I want to make.
What should happen to it?
If this is theta,
what's the cosine of theta of twice theta?
Okay.
Here's theta.
Here's theta plus pi over 2.
And where is twice that angle?
Minus cosine 2 theta.
Minus cosine 2 theta,
right?
So if we do that transformation,
if we rotate by 90 degrees,
this becomes minus cosine 2 theta.
This one will become plus cosine 2 theta.
And what about sine of
twice theta plus pi over 2?
Also just change the sine,
right?
So this becomes minus.
In other words,
what's happened,
by focusing on the observable rotated by 90 degrees,
it's just changed sine.
Well,
that makes a lot of sense,
because all it's done is interchange
the positive eigenvalue with the negative eigenvalue.
It's just interchanged the positive
eigenvalue with the negative eigenvalue.
The observable for theta has eigenvalues.
It's got eigenvalues,
plus 1 and minus 1 for the two states.
The observable for the rotated 90 degrees just
interchanges the plus sign and the minus sign.
That's all I wanted to say,
that it interchanges the plus sign and the minus sign.
So that also makes sense.
Okay,
we've left out of the story an important ingredient,
another kind of polarization.
That there is another kind of polarization must be so,
because we haven't introduced any imaginary numbers yet.
Remember,
quantum mechanics is all about complex numbers.
And there's nothing to prevent us from
introducing state vectors with complex numbers in them.
For example,
here's a state vector with a complex number in it,
1i.
Is that normalized?
No,
it's not normalized.
Remember what we have to do,
we have to multiply each one by its
complex conjugate and add them to find the normalization.
1 squared is 1,
i squared,
i times minus i is also 1.
We need a 1 over square root of 2 here.
This is a problem.
We need a perfectly good
normalized state vector in quantum mechanics.
We may not know what it is yet,
and in fact I'm eventually going
to tell you what it is,
but it has to be there.
It has to be some kind of new state vector.
It can also be written as 1 over square root
of 2 x plus i over square root of 2 y.
It's something that doesn't have an
obvious interpretation in terms of these angles.
Is there a vector which is orthogonal to it?
Of course there must be another
vector which is orthogonal to it.
The orthogonal one is 1 over square
root of 2 times 1 minus i.
Let's check that these two are orthogonal to each other.
Well,
1 times 1 is 1,
i times minus i is 1.
If I add them up,
I get 2.
That's no good.
No,
but something's wrong with that.
I forgot the complex conjugate.
If I want to see whether these two are orthogonal,
one of them has to be a bra vector.
Let's take this one to be a bra vector.
That means it corresponds to the row
vector 1 over square root of 2,
1 plus i.
Not 1 plus i,
but 1 and i.
Not minus i,
but i.
And that's because we have to
complex conjugate in the bra vectors.
All right,
let's take the inner product of this
with 1i with another square root of 2.
That'll just get rid of the square root
of 2 here and put a 1 half there.
But now we can see this is
1 times 1 plus i times i,
and that's 0.
So these two vectors are indeed orthogonal.
There must be some observable which distinguishes them.
I'm going to leave it to you as a
homework problem to find the observable with the following property.
I'll give it to you next time,
but I'm going to leave it,
assign it as a homework problem for fun.
I'm not going to collect it,
so.
And try out your...
This one I will call that.
And guess what they are?
They are circular polarization.
Light can also be circularly polarized.
Let me tell you what circularly polarized
light means from the wave point of view.
From the wave point of view,
it clearly means that there is
both x and y polarization mixed in.
x and y polarization are both mixed in here.
In fact,
if I were to calculate,
and I will in a moment,
if I were to calculate the probability
that it passes through an x polarizer,
it'll be 1 half.
A y polarizer,
it'll also be 1 half.
In fact,
we'll see that it passes through probability 1
half through any one of the theta polarizers.
But,
so it's got both x and y mixed into it.
As we can see.
What was I going to say about it?
Yeah.
So from the point of view of wave theory,
it must have the electric field is
both in the x and y direction.
In fact,
it has more or less,
it has equal probability for being
in the x and y direction.
The magnitude of 1 and the
magnitude of i is the same.
So it looks like,
somehow,
it's a state with,
let's think about now the electric field.
Electric field going into the blackboard.
It looks like it has an electric field in the
x direction and an electric field in the y direction.
You would think that adds up
to an electric field like that.
And that it ought to just be
a polarization in the 45 degree direction.
But that's not right.
That's not what a circularly polarized light ray is.
What a circularly polarized light ray,
let's think about a vertically polarized light wave.
That has an electric field,
which is something like,
for example,
cosine of z,
it's moving down the z axis,
minus ct.
This is a wave moving,
c is the speed of light.
This is a wave moving down the
z axis with the speed of light.
And this could be the y polarization.
This could be the y component of
an electromagnetic wave moving down the z axis.
The x component,
if I wrote that that was also
equal to cosine of z minus ct,
that would correspond to a plain
polarized light ray at 45 degrees.
In other words,
it would just say that the component of
the electric field in the 45 degree axis,
was cosine,
or square root of 2
times cosine of z plus ct,
minus ct.
But,
we put them out of phase.
We put them out of phase.
What that means,
now these are the electric fields,
no magnetic field,
I have not mixed in the magnetic field at all.
What this says is if we look,
here's the z axis down here.
Here's x.
The electric field might be
a cosine and look like this.
Whereas the other component of the electric field,
the y component is a sine.
So,
where the x component is maximum,
the y component is zero.
And so on.
I don't know if I can draw this.
I can never do this.
I can never get them out.
The thing to do is to draw
them in phase and then shift them.
Now,
take the red one and shift it by 90 degrees.
I can never do that.
90 degrees is halfway and
I'm not good at halfway things.
Just take the red one
and shift it by 90 degrees,
so that where the y component
of the electric field is maximum,
the x component is minimum.
If you stand at a point,
let's say the point z equals zero,
stand at the point z equals zero,
and look at the x and
y component of the electric field.
What does it do?
It rotates around in a circle.
These are the equations for a,
for an electric field,
here's the electric field.
It has an x component that has a y component.
When the x component is maximum,
the y component is minimum and vice versa.
This is an electric field,
which is just rotating around with a uniform angular motion.
That's called a circularly polarized wave.
It's a perfectly good wave.
It's just a wave whose x and y component
are out of phase with respect to each other.
It's another solution of Maxwell's equations.
Incidentally,
the magnetic fields are the same as the electric fields,
except rotated by 90 degrees.
So you could write something similar,
similar for the magnetic fields.
There are two possibilities.
Ey equals cosine,
Ex equals sine,
and Ey equals cosine,
Ex equals minus sine.
One of them rotates around in one direction,
the other one rotates around in the other direction.
Those are circularly polarized light waves.
And the individual photons of
a circularly polarized light wave
are called circularly polarized photons.
I've labeled them this way,
and this is the state vectors that describe them.
Left polarization and right polarization.
I might have left and right mixed up.
It's not very important for us right now.
What kind of device does that?
A circular polarizer.
How do you make a circular polarizer?
Anybody know?
A quarter wave plate.
Next time I'll describe how you make a circular polarizer.
A quarter wave plate is the right answer.
But it is what gets the
X and Y components out of phase.
But there are two new kinds of photons.
Of course,
they're not really independent kinds of photons.
They are new,
circularly polarized photons.
But what happens if I send a
circularly polarized photon through a theta polarizer?
Well,
to answer that,
in other words,
what's the probability that it goes through?
Again,
we take the inner product of the circular polarized photon.
Here it is.
With the theta polarized photon,
and we square it.
I won't square it yet.
I'll square it after we calculate it.
So let's see.
The circularly polarized photon has
1 over square root of 2
and I over square root of 2
for its ket vector.
And the theta polarized one has,
what is it,
cosine theta?
Sine theta?
Did I get that right?
Good.
Okay,
so what's the answer?
Let's see.
We get 1 over square root of 2.
The inner product then is
1 over root 2 cosine theta
plus I over square root of 2.
Sine theta.
That's the inner product,
or that's the amplitude,
the quantum mechanical amplitude.
Now we want to calculate the probability.
To calculate the probability,
we have to multiply this by its complex conjugate.
So let's do that up here.
This times its complex conjugate is cosine,
let's just write,
let's just call it c.
c over square root of 2.
Well,
1 over square root of 2 times c plus is.
And then another 1 over square root of 2 for...
We're multiplying this by its complex conjugate.
So another 1 over square root of 2 times
c minus is gives us 1 half c squared.
So that's c squared plus s squared.
I times minus I is plus.
So it's c squared plus s squared,
which is just 1 half.
In other words,
as you might have expected,
for a circularly polarized photon,
there's a probability 1 half that
it will go through any linearly polarized.
You cannot tell what direction
your polarizer is polarized in.
So you can't tell.
By the fact that the circular polarization
goes through with a probability of 1 half,
whatever the direction of the linear polarized polarizer is,
the circular polarized photon will
go through with probability 1 half.
You can also say the opposite is also true.
A linearly polarized photon has a probability
1 half to go through the circular,
go through the quarter wave plate,
which makes...
which makes circular polarization.
But we'll come to that next time.
Okay,
so this is the basic setup of circular polarization.
Of course,
once you realize that complex numbers are allowed,
then you can put in any complex numbers here.
Any pair of complex numbers will be allowed,
any pair such that the sums of
the squares come out to be 1.
And those define a wider class of polarizations,
which are elliptically polarized photons.
Elliptically polarized photons are circularly polarized
when one of these is real
and one of them is imaginary.
If both of them are almost real,
one of them is real and one
of them is close to being real,
then it's an elliptical polarization,
which is almost a plane polarized photon.
Well,
I think we'll do a little more with elliptical polarization.
I'll talk about elliptical polarized photons
next time if I get a chance.
But the...
And don't ask me how you make a polarizer
that polarizes elliptical photons.
Well,
actually,
you can ask me next time.
I will have an answer for you.
I just realized I know how to do it.
Good.
All right,
we're essentially finished
with the idea of polarization.
Photon polarization for the time being.
We may come back to it as an example.
But first of all,
one thing which is obvious
is we've defined a whole bunch...
Oh,
I have not defined for you,
I'll do it next time,
the observable that goes with circular polarization.
It's got some imaginary numbers in it.
We'll all know that by then.
You should know that.
Yeah,
oh,
that's right.
Was that the homework?
That's the homework,
yeah.
Good,
all right.
So that's the homework.
Find the observable that
goes with the circular polarization.
But you're going to find,
if you find them all,
that for any two different polarizations,
circular,
linear,
or anything else,
the polarization observables don't commute with each other.
That's more or less obvious
because they certainly don't ever have common eigenvectors.
The eigenvectors of this polarization
are 1,
0.
The eigenvectors of this polarization
are equal mixtures of one of the X and Y.
And the circular polarizations have I's in them.
They have no common
eigenvectors for different polarizations.
The implication of that is that the polarization observables
do not commute for different directions
or type of polarization.
The implication of that is,
for example,
that you cannot measure simultaneously the X polarization.
Can you measure simultaneously the
X polarization and the Y polarization?
Yes.
X and Y,
yes.
If the X polarization is plus,
then the Y polarization is certainly minus.
They're trivial.
They're simply related to each
other in such a simple way.
And in fact,
the X polarization and the Y polarization
are just negatives of each other.
How about the X polarization and the 45 polarization?
No.
Those you cannot measure simultaneously,
the X polarization and the 45 and the slash polarization.
You cannot simultaneously measure the X polarization
and the circular polarization
because the observables don't commute.
The observables for a theta,
and for theta plus pi over 2,
do commute.
They're just the negatives of each other.
That's what I showed you a few minutes ago,
that p theta is just equal to
minus p theta plus pi over 2.
That's just interchanging the
positive and negative eigenvalues.
A thing certainly commutes when it's negative.
So the polarization for theta,
and for theta plus pi over 2,
can be simultaneously measured.
In fact,
when you measure one,
you automatically know the other.
It's just the negative of it.
But none of these commute
if the angles are genuinely different.
So those are examples of incompatible variables.
And it just says that you can't have a polarizer
which polarizes both in the
X direction and the theta direction.
It's just something more or less obvious.
Okay,
I want to come to one
thing that we have not discussed,
the idea of expectation value,
which really should just be called average value.
Expectation value is a poor choice of terminology.
Let me explain why right now.
Supposing I have a wave function
for a particle that looks like this.
But it's what you want if you're a gambler.
Well,
I don't know.
In this case,
I don't think.
There's a wave function which is nice and symmetric.
It has a lump over
here and a lump over here.
This could be X,
X0 over here.
What's the average value of X?
Zero.
And let's suppose this has tails over here,
tails over here,
and actually goes right to zero here.
What's the least likely answer that you could get?
You'll never get the average.
So the last thing you expect is the expectation value.
It should not be called the expectation value.
Even worse,
Murray-Galman insists on calling it the expected value.
It is not the expected value.
It's the average value that we're defining,
that I'm going to define now.
So let me define for you the average value
by first writing down a mathematical expression for it
and then showing you that
it really is the average value.
Suppose you have some observable K,
any observable whatever,
Hermitian operator K.
And I have some state value.
It could be the position operator.
It could be the momentum operator.
It could be one of our polarization operators.
The only thing about it is that it's Hermitian,
and it corresponds to some observable.
It has a collection of eigenvectors and eigenvalues,
lambda n and n.
This is the observable.
Here are its eigenvalues.
Here are its eigenvectors.
K acting on the eigenvector
n gives lambda n times n.
That's the definition.
Now take any state whatever.
I'll call it psi.
Operate with K.
K is an operator.
It hits any vector and creates a new vector.
And then take its inner product with psi itself again.
In other words,
it's a sandwich
where the bread is the
bra vector and ket vector psi,
and the bologna in the middle is the observable K.
Hmm?
Star?
No.
No star.
K is a Hermitian thing.
Oh.
Yeah.
The bra means that it's complex conjugated.
It effectively means it's complex conjugated.
Whenever you see a bra,
it always implies complex conjugation.
Just another symbol for complex conjugation.
All right.
Let's calculate this.
Let's calculate it by inserting complete sets of states.
Remember that these n vectors
here are a complete orthonormal family,
a basis of vectors.
And let me just remind you of the basic rule
that if I make the
dyad nn and sum over n,
that's just equal to the identity operator
and can be stuck into any
expression for free without changing it.
Since n is a summation index,
I could also call it m.
It would still be the identity operator.
It doesn't matter what I call this.
It's a summation index.
Okay.
Let's put such a basis of vectors in here.
Psi k hat.
And now right over here,
nn psi summed over n.
I have not changed it.
This is equal.
This is equal to this.
But now what does k do when it hits n?
Lambda.
k on n equals lambda n on n.
So we can rewrite this as sum on n,
psi,
n,
lambda n.
What I've done is I've said that k,
when it hits n,
just multiplies it by the number lambda n.
Now n is still inside the sum.
Okay.
Let's erase this.
Everybody see what I did?
I stuck the complete basis n between k and psi.
Then I said that k,
when it hits n,
just multiplies by lambda n.
Now what is this psi in a product with n
times n in a product with psi?
This is,
psi n times its complex conjugate times lambda n.
And what is psi n times its complex conjugate?
It's a probability.
The inner product of a state vector
with a basis vector representing an observable k
is the probability
that the system has eigenvalue lambda n.
So what this is,
is it's the sum
on n
of the probability that if you were to measure k,
you would get the nth eigenvalue
times the nth eigenvalue.
For example,
if I plot lambda n this way,
these are the lambdas,
here's lambda 1,
lambda 2,
lambda 3,
lambda 4,
lambda 5,
and each one has a probability.
Here's the probabilities.
Just,
what do you get if you
add up all the probabilities times the eigenvalue?
You get the average,
the average
of lambda.
In other words,
it's the probability times the thing which you're measuring,
summed over all the,
is this obvious to everybody?
That if you sum over all the possible values
that you can get for a measurement,
you sum over all the possible
values you get for a measurement,
with the value for the measurement that you get,
times the probability that you get that value,
that is called the average.
The average of lambda,
or you could say
that it's the average of k,
of the observable k.
Better yet,
the quantum mechanical notation
is just k,
representing this thing over here.
This is the symbol that's often used
for the average of a quantity,
just bracketed between,
without particularly writing down the vector here.
It's just a notation,
represents the average.
And you can see that what it is,
is just a sandwich
of the observable evaluated between
the same,
between the bra vector and the ket vector
representing the state of the system.
This is why it's often useful
to actually have these observables.
If you're interested in calculating
the average value of a measurement,
then if you know the vector
that you've prepared,
in other words,
if you know what you've prepared,
psi,
and you know the observable,
you just sandwich it in this way.
Okay?
Let's do an example.
I'm tired,
so I'm going to do the very simplest example.
My observable is just going to be
1 minus 1,
0,
0.
This is the observable polarization
in the xy plane.
And now let's take something,
the vector theta.
In other words,
a linear polarization polarized
in the theta direction.
Okay?
What is the average value
of this observable?
Well,
we take theta,
we put p,
and we take theta again.
We make a sandwich.
Okay.
In terms of matrices,
that's 1,
0,
1.
The ket vector over here is
cosine theta,
sine theta.
And the bra vector
is just the row vector,
also cosine theta,
sine theta.
What do I get when I'm...
This is minus 1,
excuse me.
Okay,
just take 2 minutes
to work it out.
Multiplying the matrix
by the vector,
what does that do?
It just changes the sign
of the bottom entry.
So it just gives you
cosine theta,
sine theta,
times cosine theta,
minus sine theta.
That inner product is
cosine squared theta,
minus sine squared theta.
Which is also something else.
Cosine 2 theta.
All right,
so we found out
what the average
of this observable is.
It clearly lies between 1 and minus 1.
It could hardly be bigger than 1
or smaller than minus 1.
And depending on the direction
of polarization,
the average will just be
cosine of twice the angle.
You can check that out
and see if it makes any sense to you
by trying it out for some angles
and seeing if it makes sense.
But we could do the same thing
with any observable.
Any observable and any vector,
we could calculate the...
Not the probability,
but the average of the observable.
I will use the standard
terminology and call it
the expectation value,
but keep in mind that
that really is a misnomer.
It should be just the average value.
Good.
I think we're finished for tonight.
The preceding program
was brought to you by Stanford
on iTunes U,
and is copyrighted
by the Board of Trustees
of the Leland Stanford Junior University.
Please visit us at
itunes.stanford.edu.