Stanford University
Alright,
so we were in the midst of talking about symmetry.
Symmetries are operations that you can do
on a system which don't change the description,
which don't change the phenomena,
which don't change the energy levels,
which don't change the values of the energies of systems.
That's not ours,
I don't think.
In particular,
they don't change the values
of the energies of a system.
Examples that we talked about were translation.
If you take an atom with a given energy,
and you move it from one place to another,
the energy doesn't change.
Doesn't matter which atomic state you study,
it's not just true for the ground state,
it's true for every atomic state.
And so,
the Hamiltonian doesn't change when you move things.
That's a symmetry.
The Schrodinger equation doesn't change.
Same Schrodinger equation.
Same thing is true for rotating a system.
We're going to talk a lot tonight about rotating systems.
Another example is just interchanging two particles,
two identical particles.
You might call one electron,
electron one,
and the other electron,
electron two.
You might call them Harry and Fred.
Changing the names of the electrons,
interchanging electron one with electron two,
doesn't change the properties of an atom.
So that's also a symmetry.
We tend not to think of it as
a symmetry just because we're so used to it.
Identical particles are identical,
so it doesn't matter what you name them.
But it is a symmetry.
And there are other symmetries of physics.
For example,
if you have a crystal lattice,
a crystal lattice has a kind of translation symmetry.
It's not translation symmetry in space.
It is translation symmetry in space,
but a different kind of translation symmetry in space.
It's just translating everything by one lattice unit.
If we had a very,
very long,
almost infinite crystal,
then it's almost a perfect symmetry.
To translate from one atom to the,
you know,
to translate the whole system by one lattice spacing.
Of course,
there it's not exactly a symmetry
if the system is not infinite.
If the system is not infinite,
then there are boundaries to the crystal.
Well,
then you can't really translate it.
But if the crystal went
on and on and on forever,
then you could do two things.
You could imagine taking the crystal,
and moving the entire crystal a little bit.
This one goes to here,
this one goes to here,
this one goes to here.
That is a symmetry of a crystal.
That's true.
It's a symmetry of anything.
The ability to move it from one place to another.
But the crystal has a different symmetry,
which is just,
just,
translating from,
let's call this one,
two,
three,
four,
and let's suppose it goes on
and on and on forever and ever.
Just relabeling the crystal so that
this one is now called minus one,
this one is called,
no,
not one,
minus one,
zero,
one,
two,
three.
Imagine the crystal goes on and on.
That's also a symmetry.
Translation of crystals by the crystal,
by the crystal lattice spacing.
What else?
What other symmetries are there?
There are lots.
There are lots,
but,
some of them are more abstract than others.
The physically intuitive ones
tend to have to do with properties of space.
The homogeneity of space,
the fact that every point is like every other point,
is translation symmetry.
The isotropy of space,
the fact that every direction is like every other direction,
is rotational symmetry.
Now,
another concept
that is,
we'll see is related to symmetry,
not the same thing,
is called degeneracy.
Degeneracy and then specifically
degeneracy of energy levels.
Degeneracy of energy levels is simply the statement
an energy level of a system
is said to be degenerate
if there's more than one
state with the same energy level.
Then that energy level is called degenerate.
When does it happen,
for a random system with a generic Hamiltonian,
assuming that the spectrum of it is,
discrete spectrum,
some sort of discrete spectrum of energy levels,
it would be an accident,
it would be a rather odd accident,
that two levels would have exactly the same energy.
And when I say exactly,
I mean exactly the same energy.
They may have the same energy to
one part in 10 to the 15th,
but to say they have exactly the same energy,
what kind of coincidence would that take?
Well,
as we'll see,
it doesn't necessarily take a coincidence,
it takes a symmetry.
In fact,
those are the only cases
where we really believe that there are true degeneracies,
exact degeneracies of nature,
when there are symmetries.
Degeneracies sometimes,
no,
sometimes,
not degeneracy,
means symmetry,
the other way.
Symmetries sometimes imply degeneracy,
but not always.
And I'm gonna show you now,
I'm gonna begin with an example
in which you can see sort of intuitively
how symmetries and when symmetries imply degeneracy.
That incidentally is one of the main uses of symmetry
to analyze the energy,
the energy spectrums of systems,
and see that they have levels that exactly match.
That can be very important.
In atoms,
it's extremely important.
Let's start with rotation symmetry.
And I wanna think about a very simple system,
namely a particle moving on a circle.
It could be a particle moving on a circular wire.
I don't want it to get off the circle,
so it's a little particle,
which is kind of a bead moving on the circle.
And what is the symmetry?
The symmetry is rotational invariance.
How do we describe the location of the particle?
Well,
if we embed it in two-dimensional space,
then we could describe it by
an x and a y coordinate.
But as long as a
particle can't get off the circle,
if it's only moving in the angular space,
then it's a little bit excessive
to think about an x and a y coordinate.
We can just think of
a theta coordinate or an angle.
That particle has a wave function.
Here's the particle over here.
It has a wave function.
The wave function could be thought of
as a function of x and y,
but as I said,
that's excessive,
too many variables.
We can just think of it as psi of theta.
The wave function,
its square,
or it times its absolute,
excuse me,
it times its complex conjugate
defines the probability to find particle on the circle.
What does the operation of rotation do?
Let's say rotation,
counterclockwise,
rotation counterclockwise takes
psi to psi of theta minus epsilon,
where epsilon is the small angle of rotation.
I constantly get confused about whether
it's plus epsilon or minus epsilon.
I hope I have it right,
but if not,
don't worry about it.
It just means all of my signs will be wrong.
Okay.
So,
psi goes to psi of theta minus epsilon,
or another way to say the same thing
is that the change in psi,
epsilon,
of course,
is our small number,
which is so small that it's square or zero.
It's an infinitesimal number.
The change in psi
is equal to the derivative of psi
with respect to theta times epsilon.
I can rewrite that
as minus i epsilon
times minus i epsilon,
minus i derivative of psi
with respect to theta.
Now,
I've put those i's in there
because
I want you to remember,
well,
let's think about ordinary momentum.
Ordinary momentum
is
described by an operator which
is minus i d by dx.
Angular momentum
is simply,
basically the same as momentum,
except the coordinate is angle
instead of being linear position.
The operator minus i d by d theta,
and that's an operator,
it's a linear operator,
it's a Hermitian operator.
The i is there to make it Hermitian.
Without the i,
it would not be Hermitian.
Does one of those i's be positive?
Is one of the i's what?
Should be epsilon and then positive plus,
no?
Do I have a...
I think the epsilon is...
Minus i,
then minus i,
yeah,
I think it may be plus.
Let's see,
did I get it wrong?
No,
I actually had it right.
Minus...
I had it right,
this side was wrong.
Yeah,
okay.
It's correct now.
Okay,
but
minus i d by d theta
is a Hermitian operator,
you may be surprised
that there has to have
an i in front of it
for it to be Hermitian.
After all,
Hermitian is the analog among operators
as being real,
but I guarantee you
that i has to be there.
Go back in your notes
to the study of momentum,
and you'll find out
why that i has to be there.
And that's called the angular momentum.
That's usually denoted L.
And that's the angular momentum
of the angular momentum.
Y L?
Don't know Y L.
Y P for momentum?
Don't know Y P for momentum.
But L is the angular momentum.
And so,
we can write
that the change in psi
under the operation of infinitesimal rotation
is governed by
minus i
times the action
of the angular momentum operator
on psi.
That identifies,
according to the definitions
of last week,
that identifies L
as the generator of rotations.
If you can't remember
the precise definition,
let's just say
that this is the definition
of the generator
of a symmetry operation.
It's the generator
If the symmetry operation is such
that it has a version of it
for arbitrarily small parameter,
in this case angle,
then the definition of the generator
is just in terms of the small change
in the wave function
when you shift by an infinitesimal amount,
and that will just give you the generator.
You lost an epsilon.
Don't worry.
I did lose an epsilon.
I did lose an epsilon,
and this defines L,
and L is minus i d by d theta.
Okay.
And L is known as the angular momentum.
Now,
before I go on,
I want to put in some H bars.
I'll surely drop them again,
but just to remind you where they go.
The precise definition,
including H bars,
when we don't set H bar to one,
contains an H bar over here.
That's the same H bar that occurs
in the momentum,
P equals minus i H bar d by dx.
Same H bar,
and it's a little bit arbitrary
where we put it,
but putting it over here,
I guess we would say that
the change in psi is i
epsilon over H bar times L.
Now,
probably here and there,
just to remind you and to keep you awake,
I will put in H bars
now and then,
every so often,
randomly.
Okay.
What are the eigenvectors
of the angular momentum?
The eigenvectors of the ang-
and the eigenvalues.
The eigenvalues are the values
of the possible outcomes of experiments,
and the eigenvectors are the states
of the system which-
for which those outcomes are certain.
All right,
to answer that,
we write the equation L on psi,
that's the action of the angular momentum,
is equal to an eigenvalue,
I'm going to call that eigenvalue M.
It's standard.
M times psi.
Now,
if I were doing it,
I would have put little L here,
but somebody did this long in the past.
M happens to stand for magnetic quantum number,
but that's a historical,
and it's not a real number,
it's a real anachronism.
Nevertheless,
the eigenvalue of L,
and let's add a little more to this picture.
Let's put a z-axis in.
The z-axis comes out of the blackboard.
So we're talking about rotations
about the z-axis.
We could call this the z-component
of the angular momentum.
It is the z-component of the angular momentum.
For the moment,
I'm going to suppress that.
All right,
and M is the eigenvalue
of that angular momentum,
so strictly speaking,
it's the eigenvalue of the z-component
of angular momentum.
Does it matter which axis is z
and which axis is x?
So you rotate the home?
No,
it doesn't matter,
but it's convention.
Okay,
how do we find the eigenvectors?
In other words,
how do we find the wave functions
that correspond to eigenvectors?
And for that,
we just do the obvious thing.
We put in minus i h-bar d by d theta.
That's L acting on psi of theta
is equal to M psi of theta.
That's a standard type of equation.
The derivative of something
is proportional to that something else.
We could bring the i
h-bar over to the right-hand side,
and that tells us
that the eigenvector with eigenvalue M
is equal to m.
So that's the eigenvalue of M.
It is equal to e to the i M theta.
It's very similar to the case of ordinary momentum.
Oops!
What do I have missing here?
I'm missing the h-bar.
The h-bar would go downstairs here.
Because if you divide by h-bar,
you see the thing that
comes in is M over h-bar.
Now,
unlike the case of ordinary linear momentum,
there's another constraint.
You know the other constraint.
I'm sure that most of you know it,
but let's spell it out anyway.
The other constraint is that
when theta is equal to 2 pi,
the wave function should be exactly what it was
when theta was equal to 0.
Why?
Because going around by 2 pi
brings you back to the same point.
And so if there's a sensible wave function,
that sensible wave function
should be unchanged
if you go around the circle by 2 pi.
So that says that e
to the i M over h-bar
times 2 pi...
Well,
let's see.
First of all,
the wave function for theta equals 0
is just 1.
If I set theta equal to 0,
this is just 1.
If I go around by 2 pi,
the answer will be...
e to the i 2 pi M over h-bar.
And that also has to be equal to 1.
What's the constraint?
The constraint is that M over h-bar
has to be an integer.
In order to make sure that the wave function
comes back to itself,
that it's single-valued,
that it has a definite value at each point,
it's necessary
that the eigenvalues M
be integer multiples of Planck's constant.
So let's write that out.
M is equal to an integer...
No.
Yeah.
M is an integer times h-bar,
but the usual notation,
the usual definition,
is to set M equal to the integer.
Just call M the integer,
and then the angular momentum,
the eigenvalue of the angular momentum,
is an integer times h-bar.
That's the quantization of angular momentum
in units of h-bar.
Hereafter,
at least for the time being,
I will drop h-bar,
and we'll just say that the angular momentum
must be equal to an integer.
Angular momentum must be equal to an integer,
and that's a fundamental fact of quantum mechanics
that we've known since the time of Niels Bohr.
Okay,
now I have the following question for you.
Must it be the case...
Let's suppose there's some energy.
And let's suppose the energy
depends on the angular momentum.
Of course it does.
The energy...
The bigger the angular momentum,
the bigger the energy.
The particles whipping around
with a large angular momentum
that has more energy than a small angular momentum.
So we expect that the angular momentum...
that the energy will depend on the angular momentum.
But must it be the case
that the energy of a state with angular momentum m...
That's the eigenvalue.
Must it be the same
as the energy of a
state with angular momentum minus m?
What's the difference between m and minus m?
Well,
the only difference is that
positive angular momentum means the particle is moving.
The particle is going around the circle counterclockwise.
And negative angular momentum
means it's going around clockwise.
Take a vote.
How many people think that the energy must
be the same for m and minus m?
Of course.
I'll raise my hand too.
How many think it does
not have to be the same?
I will also raise my hand.
I have a question.
Yeah.
Just when you start out,
you said that theta goes beside theta minus epsilon.
Should I think that then
that implies we're looking at it
as going in a clockwise direction?
It's not telling you anything about
the direction of motion of the particle.
It's only telling you which
way you counted theta as positive.
It's just telling...
It's like telling you I've decided
that the positive x-axis points that way.
That tells me nothing about whether
I'm walking that way or I'm walking this way.
All right.
It does set the definition of what
you mean by positive and negative angular momentum.
But it does not tell you whether
the system has positive or negative angular momentum.
Okay.
Art,
you raised your hand the second time.
Do you know an example where...
I was just thinking that you
could have an asymmetrical field somewhere.
Okay.
All right.
Does anybody know an example of a field
which would lead to an asymmetry between positive
and negative angular momentum or angular velocity?
Magnetic field for electrons.
Yeah.
Magnetic field.
If there were a magnetic field,
that's exactly what magnetic fields do.
Magnetic field,
for example...
Magnetic field into the blackboard will
raise the energy a little bit.
Maybe I may have it backward.
Raise the energy a little bit of positive
angular momentum and lower the energy a little bit
of negative angular momentum.
And it will break the degeneracy.
It'll break the degeneracy between m and minus m.
That's the language.
If you didn't have the magnetic field,
the energy levels would be degenerate in pairs.
Angular momentum zero...
Oh,
angular momentum zero would not be degenerate.
There's only one of them.
But angular momentum plus one
and minus one would be degenerate.
Angular momentum two and minus two would be degenerate.
In the presence of the magnetic field,
that degeneracy is broken,
but that magnetic field
does not violate the energy levels.
It doesn't violate in any way rotational invariance.
The magnetic field is pointing into the blackboard.
It doesn't in any way violate
the invariance with respect to rotation.
And so we see that symmetry is itself not enough.
Not this symmetry.
Rotation symmetry by itself is not enough to
tell you that the energy levels are degenerate.
Why am I even talking about it?
Well,
you need to add...
If you add one more symmetry,
one more symmetry is enough to tell you
that the energy levels have to be degenerate.
And symmetry is very simple.
It's not a continuous symmetry.
It's a discrete symmetry.
It's simply the discrete symmetry of
reflection about one of the axes.
Reflection about an axis is basically mirror.
Reflection.
Imagine you had a horizontal mirror here,
and any system above the mirror
has a mirror image below the mirror.
And if there's mirror symmetry,
it's not called mirror symmetry,
it's called reflection symmetry.
I'm going to call it mirror symmetry and
use the notation m to describe that symmetry.
The reason is I don't want
to use r for mirror symmetry.
I'm going to use r for reflection because
I don't want you to confuse it with rotation.
So m,
big M.
Big M stands for reflection about a mirror.
And in particular,
we could imagine the mirror is oriented along the x-axis.
Of course,
a mirror is two-dimensional,
but in this situation,
along the x-z plane.
But we don't have to think about z.
We just have a mirror and the mirror image of...
I don't know if I can
draw the mirror image of that.
I don't think I can.
Did I get that right?
Maybe not.
I don't know.
The mirror image of...
This is this.
Okay.
If there is not mirror symmetry in a problem,
then a configuration like this...
Whatever it happens to be,
I don't know what it is.
It's a couple of building blocks or something.
The energy of this does not have to
be the same as the energy of that.
If there is no mirror symmetry in the system.
But if there is mirror symmetry,
it means that the description of this
and the description of this are indistinguishable.
And that they must have the same energy.
So let's add mirror symmetry to rotation
symmetry and see what we buy from it.
Well,
we will certainly find that the energy levels of...
The energy levels E of M must
be the same as E of minus M.
Why is that?
Let's think about in the upper half plane here.
Let's think of a circular motion moving counterclockwise.
What's the mirror image of that?
That's a circular motion moving clockwise.
So the mirror image of a particle moving with positive
angular momentum is a particle moving with negative angular momentum.
And if the world or our
system has such a mirror symmetry,
such a reflection symmetry,
then it means that the M energies of
the two states must be exactly the same.
There we have an example where rotation symmetry...
which tells you that the energy
levels depend on the angular momentum,
and that the angular momentum is conserved.
The added ingredient is the mirror symmetry,
which tells you that the
energy levels have to be degenerate.
So that's a case in which two symmetries combined
tells you that there have to be degenerate energy levels.
Yes?
If we...
If the position of the particle is...
is determined by the probability,
i.e.
by the square of the sine,
we look at the sine,
and think of the Moivre expression,
the cosine,
and we change M to minus M,
and you do the algebra,
at least.
It seems that...
But it seems that the sine goes
away and you're left with the same number.
So in a way,
replacing M with minus M algebraically will
show that it is the same probability,
meaning it's...
They're equal.
The energies are equal.
Is that not a good way to look at it?
It's just wrong.
Um...
A function of theta is not the
same as a function of minus theta.
For example...
Here's a function of theta.
The probability is concentrated over here.
Here's a corresponding function of minus theta.
The kind that's over here.
They're not the same thing.
Also,
e to the i theta is...
Or e to the i M theta is not
the same as e to the minus i M theta.
But the square of the...
Yes,
yes,
but we don't...
But that's...
Right.
But the square...
This is the equation for the eigenvectors of psi,
or the eigenvectors of angular momentum.
It involves psi.
It doesn't involve psi star psi.
Yeah.
ご視聴ありがとうございました
That's the whole point of quantum mechanics.
We have to work with wave functions,
not probabilities.
So is it the case that
mirror symmetry guarantees degeneracy in any situation?
No.
It doesn't.
It doesn't in itself.
What's necessary is to have two symmetries and one more
condition that the two symmetries don't commute with each other.
That the symmetry operations for the
two symmetries don't commute with each other.
I'm going to let you prove that,
that if symmetries don't commute with each other,
that it implies degeneracy.
It's not hard to prove,
but I'm going to show you how
it works in a couple of examples.
Okay.
Any two symmetries,
if they don't commute with each other.
So let's ask whether
rotation symmetry and reflection symmetry...
Incidentally,
the term mirror symmetry happens
to have another meaning in physics.
It's a very fancy term,
very mathematical term that applies
to certain manifolds in string theory.
Don't get confused by it.
It's a completely different concept.
I just use mirror to represent the reflection in space.
Yeah?
Does the mirror symmetry break the magnetic field?
Yes.
Very interesting.
Good.
Good point.
Yeah.
The mirror symmetry of a magnetic field,
the mirror inversion of a magnetic field,
is a magnetic field pointing in the other direction.
If you take a magnetic field pointing into the blackboard,
and you reflect the configuration about a plane like this,
what you get is a configuration with
the magnetic field coming out of the blackboard.
This is because magnetic field is an axial vector.
Okay.
You can see it another way.
Magnetic fields are made by currents.
Currents...
Let's not imagine...
Let's not imagine that the magnetic field is there.
Let's instead imagine that the magnetic field is
being made by a current going this way.
A current going around in a loop like this.
It could be going around a solenoid.
We could be talking about a solenoid
into the blackboard with the current going clockwise.
That creates a magnetic field going into the blackboard.
In the lower half plane,
the mirror image of that
is a solenoid in which the
current is going in the opposite direction.
And because the current is going in the opposite direction,
it makes a magnetic field pointing out of the blackboard.
So yes,
the mirror inversion of a magnetic
field is not the same magnetic field.
So I think you foresaw that
that had to be the case if...
Yeah.
Okay.
Alright,
let's ask.
Let's ask the mathematical.
Let's go through the mathematics now
of showing that reflection...
mirror reflection does not commute with rotation.
And we'll do that by
showing that the generator of rotation
doesn't commute with the action of the reflection operator.
We need to figure out what the reflection operator does.
Okay.
The reflection operator,
we'll call m for mirror,
it takes any wave function
and replaces it...
I shouldn't write arrow,
I should write equals.
And replaces it by wave function of minus theta.
Reflection about the horizontal axis
just takes theta to minus theta.
So any wave function,
when you reflect it,
goes to psi of minus theta.
Okay.
In particular,
if you apply it to...
Well,
alright,
we'll do it in a minute.
Now let's consider the commutator
of the mirror symmetry transformation
with the angular momentum.
The angular momentum is just
a version of a rotation operator
for very small rotation.
Let's consider the commutator.
Okay.
What the commutator is telling us about
is what happens if we do
the two operations in opposite order.
A rotation about an axis and a reflection
versus a reflection and a rotation about the same axis.
Are they the same operations?
Rotating about an axis and then reflecting,
is that the same as reflecting and then rotating?
Okay,
the answer is obviously no.
Well,
if it's not obvious to you,
think about it.
But we'll work it out by doing it.
We'll work it out by doing the mathematical commutator
and seeing what we get.
Let's look at the commutator of M with L.
We know what L does.
Here it is.
It differentiates with respect to theta.
What does M do?
It reflects theta.
So we can figure out what the commutator does.
We can figure out what it does
when it acts on a wave function.
I'm going to act on a particular wave function.
I'm going to act on the wave function
e to the i m theta.
A eigenvector of the angular momentum.
I'm leaving h-bar out of it.
We don't need it.
And don't confuse big M with little m.
Little m and big M have
nothing to do with each other.
This stands for mirror.
This stands for magnetic quantum number.
Okay,
let's see if we can work it out.
Let's first do M L
times e to the i m theta.
What does L do when it
hits e to the i m theta?
It brings an M down.
Right.
It just brings an M down.
So this gives us
M times little m
e to the i m theta.
And what does capital M do
when it hits e to the i m theta?
It just changes the sign of theta.
Incidentally,
once this is just a number,
it doesn't matter which order
big M and little m appear.
And so this is just equal
to little m times e
to the minus i m theta.
The big M just reflected theta.
Okay,
let's do it in the opposite order.
L times e to the i m theta.
So this is equal to M
e to the i m theta.
Now in the opposite order,
first M acts.
And that gives us L.
When M acts,
it changes the sign of theta
and gives us e to the minus i m theta.
But what happens when L hits
e to the minus i m theta?
Anybody got a good idea?
It brings down a minus M.
By reflecting,
we've changed the sign of the angular momentum.
So the angular momentum operator
gives us the minus of what it gave before.
It gives us minus M
e to the minus i m theta.
So the answer is that M and L,
angular momentum and the reflection operator,
don't commute with each other.
That's the key to whether or not
symmetries...
whether or not symmetries
create degeneracies of energy levels.
We've seen in this case
that two symmetries,
rotational symmetry together with reflection symmetry,
tell us that there are degeneracies of the energy levels.
That M and minus M
have to have the same energy.
That's a pattern.
It's also a theorem,
but we'll...
I don't think we'll do the theorem right now.
Does this mean that any Heisenberg pair
generates degeneracies?
A Heisenberg pair like x and p?
Well,
the problem is that x and p are not conserved.
Right.
And they're not symmetries in themselves.
In the case of a particle
not having a magnetic field,
then angular momentum,
rotation,
and reflection
are both symmetries.
They both commute with a Hamiltonian.
They both are conserved.
x and p are typically and generally not conserved.
If they were,
then the answer would be yes.
Then the answer would be yes.
Yeah.
Okay.
We're going to study an example in some detail tonight.
I think we'll get through it.
Oh,
let's...
Well,
let's just write down
just some formal observations of what I mean.
Supposing you have two symmetries.
Now,
what does it mean to have a symmetry?
Let's call the two symmetries A and B.
The A and B stand for operators.
Operators that act on the state vectors.
They could stand for infinitesimal generators,
or they could stand for
the full operation of the symmetry.
A and B.
Let's say they refer to the generators.
Let's take the case of where there are small versions
of the transformations.
Then,
to say they're symmetries means
that both of them commute with a Hamiltonian.
It does not in itself
say that A commutes with B.
In general,
here's an example where they didn't.
Commutator of A with B may be non-zero,
and there are two possibilities.
Both possibilities will lead to degeneracy,
but let's think of two possibilities.
In one possibility,
the commutator of A and B
may be A itself,
it may be B itself,
or it may be some
linear combination of A and B.
That does not lead to a new symmetry.
It doesn't lead to a new operator.
It just leads to a
linear combination of the old ones.
But let's suppose that it
leads to a genuinely new operator
that cannot be written as a linear commutator.
It's a linear combination of A and B.
Let's call it C.
Okay,
first theorem.
It's not a theorem.
It's hardly a theorem.
C also commutes with H.
How do I know?
Let's put an I in here.
Why am I putting an I in there?
The commutator of two Hermitian operators
is not Hermitian.
It's anti-Hermitian.
The commutator of X and P is I.
If you want a Hermitian operator,
you have to put an I here.
So let's suppose that C is
the commutator of A and B
except with an extra I.
Then C is a Hermitian operator.
And let me show you why it's conserved.
It's conserved for a trivial reason.
Let's think about the commutator of C with H.
That's ABH minus H.
AB is equal to C,
apart from the factor of I.
So the commutator of C with H
is proportional to ABH minus HAB.
But now all we have to do is say,
look,
we know that B commutes with H.
That's an assumption.
That means that we can
move B to the other side.
Once we've moved B to the other side,
we know that A commutes with H.
That's also an assumption.
So we can move A to the other side.
And that,
of course,
is equal to 0.
So if A and B both commute with the Hamiltonian,
then the commutator of A and B
also commute with the Hamiltonian.
In fact,
the product A and B commute with the Hamiltonian.
But the reason we don't
consider the commutator is because...
Sorry.
The product of A and B commute with the Hamiltonian.
Certainly the commutator does.
Okay?
I'm not so interested in the product
because it's not generally Hermitian.
It's the commutator which is Hermitian.
So there's an example
where given two symmetries,
if they don't commute,
you generate a third symmetry.
And it might be an independent one.
It might be a new thing.
Once you have A and B and C,
you can play the game again.
Commute C with A and B.
See what you get.
You may get something that just reproduces
or that's just a linear combination
of the three that you started with.
Or you may get something new.
You may get D.
You keep doing this and doing this and doing this
until you don't get something new.
You might never end.
You might get an infinite number
of different symmetries.
That's rare and that's unusual and it's bizarre.
Or it will close eventually
and you'll have some finite number of symmetries
which are all independent of each other
and which form a kind of closed system
when you commute them,
when you commute the generators.
Question?
Yeah.
Just to make sure I understand your argument,
what you showed was that
if you have A and B
that commute with H,
then the product A and B commutes with A.
It does.
And then since the commutator of A and B
is just A and B minus B A,
then you'll get the full commutation.
Yeah.
Right.
So eventually,
if you have a few symmetries,
you can start commuting them and commuting them
among themselves,
being guaranteed that what you get
is another symmetry,
which may be just a trivial superposition
of the original ones or it may be something new.
If it's something new,
good.
Put it into your list and commute some more.
Eventually,
you'll either run out of them
or you won't,
but I'm particularly interested in the situations
where you run out.
And then you'll have what is called a commutator algebra.
The commutator algebra includes
the commutators of all the symmetries
and it includes the commutation relations
with the Hamiltonian,
which just say zero.
When you're in that situation,
whenever that happens,
you have a great deal of power over the system
to be able to say a lot about the nature
of the energy levels and the degeneracies among them.
Okay,
so that's the general...
Oh,
what is such a structure called?
The collection of symmetry operations.
A group.
This is a symmetry group.
Why do we care that these two things are degenerate?
Why do we care that it's degenerate or not?
It would certainly be important if,
for example,
we wanted to know if from one state
you could emit a photon and
then go down to the other state.
Can't do it if the energies are the same.
We want to classify the energy levels of systems.
Why?
Because we're spectroscopists
and we want to study the spectroscopy of atoms.
Oh,
we're spectroscopists and we want to study
the way hadrons,
excited states of hadrons emit pions
or whatever.
Same rules.
So the commutator...
The elements of...
So each of these commutators would
be an element of this symmetry group?
Well,
these things themselves,
these I imagined were generators.
The generators form an algebra,
a commutator algebra,
a Lie algebra.
The symmetries themselves,
which are built up from the generators
by applying small transformations repeatedly,
those are the group elements.
But we're going to mainly work with the generators.
The generators have a lot of power.
The algebra of them.
The C generators,
it's not a combination?
Yeah.
They're all generators.
Right.
They're all...
Now you can have a situation
where you may have many symmetries,
but they commute with each other.
That can happen.
Then you don't get anything terribly interesting.
You just have separate symmetries
that commute with each other.
Symmetries of that kind are called abelian.
Abelian means everything commutes with everything else.
When there are non-zero
commutators between symmetry generators,
it's called non-abelian.
Is there any fundamental definition of a generator again?
A generator of a symmetry is
if you take the symmetry operations,
unitary symmetry operations,
and you consider the case of a
symmetry operation very close to the identity.
In the case of rotations,
it means a rotation by a very small angle.
And you write it in the form 1,
I can never remember,
I think it's minus i g times epsilon,
then g is called the generator.
Okay?
You can build up,
if you know the generator,
that allows you to make a small rotation.
If you keep doing small
rotations repeatedly about a given axis,
you'll eventually build up a whole rotation,
I mean a finite rotation.
So the generators contain basically all
the interesting information about the group.
Well,
almost.
Is there any fundamental difference between
ab and then c or d?
No.
We could have started with b
and c and then with a.
Yeah.
Well,
maybe yes,
maybe no.
You might take b and c,
and you might not get a.
You might get d.
You might.
Or you might get a plus b.
If you got a plus b,
then it wouldn't be anything new.
You might get a plus b plus c back again,
and it still wouldn't be anything new.
But if you got something new,
d,
which was not among your previous list,
then you have a genuinely new symmetry.
Question?
Yeah.
Could you please repeat what
you said about what's an algebra?
That's not a question.
That's a Dirac story.
What did you ask me?
No,
what did you tell me?
What did you request of me?
You said something was an algebra,
and first of all,
I want to know what is the algebra,
and what is the momentum?
The algebra is the collection of things.
It's a collection of generators.
You can add them.
They are still generators.
You can subtract them.
You can even multiply them by ordinary numbers,
and you can commute them.
So commuting is a product in that algebra?
That's correct.
Commuting is a product in that algebra.
An algebra is a thing,
is a collection of elements that you can add,
you can multiply by numbers,
and you can multiply.
Sorry.
And you can multiply by each other.
In this algebra,
multiplication is commutation.
That's correct.
Okay,
so we'd like an example.
Not only would we like an example,
we would like the preeminent,
most important example,
and that is angular momentum
and rotation about different axes.
As an example of what I'm talking about here,
we can consider rotation about the x-axis.
Which way is the x-axis?
That way,
I guess.
Rotation about the x-axis.
Rotation about the y-axis.
And if you think about it,
and you probably know this,
I can never do this.
I'm not going to try it.
But,
you know,
if you do rotate about the x-axis,
then rotate about the y-axis by the right amount,
what you get is a rotation about the z-axis.
What's more,
if you rotate a little bit about the x-axis,
and then a little bit about the y-axis,
no,
a little bit about the x-axis,
and then a little bit about the y-axis,
it's not the same as rotating
a little bit about the y-axis first,
and then about the x-axis.
They don't commute with each other.
We're going to show that.
We're going to show that
by studying the commutation relations
of the angular momentum.
You look puzzled.
I'm puzzled because I know
that that's true for finite rotations,
but I thought somehow that infinitesimal rotations...
Infinitesimal?
Okay.
They don't commute to second order in the small numbers.
Yeah.
That's enough.
But remember,
these generators have the small
numbers factored out of them,
and they don't commute.
They really don't commute.
Okay,
we're going to work out an example in detail.
We'll do it right now.
The example is the three components of angular momentum.
The three components of angular momentum
are the three rotations about any axis form a group,
but for our purposes now,
we're not concentrating on groups.
The angular momentum generators form a Lie algebra,
a commutator algebra.
That simply means that the commutators
of components of the angular momentum
give you other components of the angular momentum,
and we'll work that out.
But first,
let's talk a little bit about...
classical angular momentum for a minute,
just to understand the corresponding classical concept.
Okay,
we can do this.
let's imagine a planetary orbit.
For my purpose now,
it can be a circular orbit.
It's orbiting about an axis,
and it has an angular momentum,
which is perpendicular to the orbit.
That could be LZ.
It has a certain energy,
E.
at a classical level,
is that energy level degenerate?
The meaning of that is,
is there another orbit with exactly the same energy?
Of course,
there are many other orbits with exactly the same energy,
but in particular,
there's some that you can easily compute.
Some of them can easily prove have the same energy,
because of rotational invariance.
All you have to do
is rotate this about an axis.
Let's rotate it about the y-axis.
Take this configuration,
rotate it about the y-axis.
It's a new configuration,
and the angular momentum has changed.
Oops.
Yeah,
I guess that's okay.
I guess,
what did I do?
I don't like my picture.
My picture,
this is in the wrong place.
It should be coming from here.
There's LZ.
And now there's a change in L.
It's picked up an x component.
Yes,
in fact,
it's picked up an x component.
And so because of rotation about the y-axis,
rotation about the y-axis has not only
given us another configuration with the same energy,
but it's given us a configuration
with a shift of the angular momentum,
and in particular,
a shift of the x component of the angular momentum.
Classically,
that's an indication that quantum mechanically,
the components of angular momentum don't commute.
A rotation by one,
a rotation of a component of
an angular momentum about a different axis
changes the angular momentum about the third axis.
That has a great deal to
do with the commutation relations of rotations,
but we'll work it out in detail.
So here's an example.
Classical physics,
just at the classical level,
the combination of rotation and variance,
rotation and variance,
the combination of the different
rotation and variances about different axes,
tells us unequivocally that there
must be degeneracy of the orbits,
that there must be orbits with the same energy,
with rotated angular momentum.
That's the basic idea classically.
So let's go through it quantum mechanically.
The first thing we have to do
is understand the angular momentum generators better.
So let's come back to the angular momentum generators
and their form.
Previously I just said minus i d by d theta.
But let's work them out,
not assuming that a particle is moving on a circle,
but that a particle could be moving in three dimensions.
In fact,
it doesn't even really have to be a particle,
but let it be a particle.
A particle moving in three dimensions.
First,
before we do three dimensions,
let's do two dimensions.
Particle moving in the xy plane,
not restricted to a circle.
And let's ask,
what's the generator of rotation now?
It's not i d,
well,
it may be i d by d theta,
but we can represent it
in terms of the xy coordinates.
Alright,
so here's the position of the particle,
let's say.
Let's suppose we rotate the configuration.
Rotating the configuration,
whatever it happens to be,
means whatever the particle is,
or whatever the wave function of it is,
shifted.
So if the particle was at point xy,
it moves to a new point.
What's the new point?
The new point is given,
if the old point was given by xy,
then the new point is shifted by
an amount delta x and delta y.
I'm assuming that the angle is small,
and let's call the angle epsilon.
Let's call the angle epsilon.
Then,
what is delta x and delta y?
I'll leave it to you to
prove this is a very simple exercise,
it's just simple geometry.
For a small epsilon,
can anybody tell me what delta x is?
It's of course proportional to epsilon.
Minus y.
Yeah.
If y is positive,
and you rotate,
the change in x is negative.
So,
it's got to be minus,
and it's proportional to y.
What about delta y?
That's epsilon times x.
Okay,
now let's consider a wave function,
psi of x and y.
What is the change in the wave function
if you reconfigure the system by rotation?
It's equal to the derivative
of psi with respect to x,
times the change in x,
plus the derivative of psi with respect to y,
times the change in y,
if I shift the wave function.
But delta x is minus epsilon times y.
Minus epsilon times y.
And this is plus epsilon times x.
That's the change in the wave function,
and of course,
this must be,
by definition,
I guess it's L sub z,
times psi.
So,
oh,
i epsilon,
i epsilon times L z.
Now it's much too late in the evening
for me to follow the signs,
so I won't.
I'll leave the signs for you to figure out yourself.
But,
it has this form.
But what is the psi by dx in quantum mechanics?
i times px.
So this is another factor of i,
and this is
y times px.
Did it matter which order I put down
y and px here?
Do they commute?
Yeah,
y commutes with px.
x doesn't commute with px.
y doesn't commute with py,
but x commutes with py.
What about this one?
This one is
plus i
times xpy.
All times...
Alright,
apart from the sign,
which I said I wouldn't
try to track in any detail,
it's quite clear
what the correspondence between the z component
of the angular momentum,
the generator of rotations,
and the coordinates and momenta of the particle are.
Lz
is to be identified with
xpy minus ypx,
and now I do have...
this is the right sign.
I lost track of the sign,
but this is the correct sign.
Have you seen that before?
That's the component of r cross p.
The standard three-dimensional angular momentum.
r cross p.
So now we see a
new interpretation of r cross p.
Not just the mechanical angular momentum
from classical physics,
but it now has the role of the thing
which generates small rotations
by acting on the wave function.
Okay.
What about the other components of angular momentum?
You can read them off just by cycling,
by cycling through the xyz.
x goes to y,
y goes to z,
z goes to x.
Alright,
so going through it.
z goes to x,
x goes to y,
y goes to z,
minus zpy.
And lxxyz.
pypzpx minus xpy.
These,
of course,
you could confirm
by doing,
by imagining rotations
about the other axes,
but just by,
you know,
just by the parallel reasoning,
this is what you would get.
Questions?
Oh,
you're right,
pz.
I have two different notations for z,
don't I?
Yeah.
Wait a minute.
Which one,
which one?
Ly,
good,
thank you.
Ly,
good,
good.
Okay.
These are the,
these are,
are they symmetries?
Well,
they're symmetries
if the system is rotationally invariant.
Why?
Well,
because rotating a system
shouldn't change the Hamiltonian.
So we expect,
we fully expect
that if we have a system
with rotational invariance,
then these should commute with the Hamiltonian.
And typically they do,
they do.
In fact,
they always do if the system has invariance.
What kind of systems have rotational invariance?
Well,
a very particular system
is a particle moving in a central force field.
A particle moving in a central force field
will have rotational invariance,
and therefore for that kind of system,
the commutator of Lx with h equals zero,
and in fact all three of them.
L sub i,
one,
two,
and three,
or x,
y,
and z,
they all commute with the Hamiltonian
and they're all conserved.
And this is just good old angular momentum conservation
except in the quantum guise.
Next question.
Do they commute with each other?
Suppose all we had was Lx and Ly.
That's all we knew about.
Lx and Ly.
Why we only knew about Lx and Ly?
I don't know.
Our mothers only told us about x and y.
Would we discover Lz?
That Lz is another symmetry.
Well,
our mothers only told us about x and y,
but they also told us about commuting
the generators of Lie groups.
So,
mom tells us,
look,
commute Lx and Ly
and see what you get.
Let's commute Lx and Ly
and see what we get.
Okay,
well,
what do we need to do?
We need to know the commutation relations
between x,
y,
and z on the one hand
and px,
py,
and pz on the other hand.
The rule,
I'll write it over here,
any x with y or z or anything like that
is always equal to zero.
x with itself is equal to zero.
x with y,
x with z is equal to zero.
They commute.
Ps commute with each other.
px,
py,
and pz all commute with each other.
Which things don't commute?
The things that don't commute
are x with px,
and that's equal to i,
strictly,
i times h-bar.
Same with y.
y with py is i,
and z with pz is i.
I won't write it down.
How about x with py?
That commutes.
Multiplication by x
and differentiation with respect to y
commute with each other.
And you can check that.
Okay,
so let's calculate the commutator
of Lx with Ly.
That's the commutator of ypz
minus zpy,
comma,
comma for commutator,
zpx minus xpz.
Now,
I'm not going to go through the rules
for commutators.
If you remember them,
you don't,
but I'll just,
but it's by inspection.
You can more or less see what to do.
Who in this side doesn't commute
with who on this side?
It's a commutator of this thing with this thing.
What on this side doesn't commute
with something on this side?
Well,
y commutes with z,
y commutes with px,
and so forth,
but pz does not commute with z.
So there's two things which don't commute.
And,
let's see over here,
z doesn't commute with pz.
With pz.
Those are the only combinations,
if we were to expand this out,
the only combinations which don't commute
are pz,
did I get it right,
with z,
and z,
did I get that right?
Zpx minus x,
no,
what have I written here?
pxpd.
What am I doing?
I'm commuting lx,
that looks right,
ypz minus zpy,
with ly,
which is zpx minus xpz.
Yeah,
that's right.
okay?
Okay.
Alright,
from this term over here,
you get a commutator of pz with z.
What's the commutator of pz with z?
Minus i.
So there's a minus i,
and that gets rid of pz and z,
and you're left over with y times,
no,
y,
sorry,
you're left over,
that gets rid of z with pz,
and that leaves over y and px.
From this with this,
you get y times px.
Does it matter which order
you write down y and px?
No.
Okay,
so there's minus i,
y times px,
and then there's the other one,
which is
commutator of z with pz is again,
i,
and now we get
plus i,
xpy,
I believe.
Yeah,
x times py.
Where is it?
Ah,
x times py from here.
Which is our friend
i times lz.
So this is an example of commuting
generators and discovering new generators.
Not a big surprise,
but nevertheless,
we see it before our eyes.
And so now we can write down
the general list of commutation relations.
Notice that by commuting to angular momentum,
we got a third one.
There's only three.
There's no way we're going
to get more than three generators
out of this sequence of commutations.
And so the Lie algebra is just going to be
the Lie algebra of the three components
of the angular momentum.
Let's write it down.
This one says that
Lx with Ly
equals ilz.
And then the trick is always the same,
just cycle.
LL equals il.
L....
comma
xyz
YZx
xy
Those are our basic
commutation relations of angular momentum.
If you
continue commuting,
you won't get anything new.
So we've discovered the genuine Lie algebra.
Yeah?
When you generate an LC,
don't you have to prove that
it's not a linear combination of
LX and LZ?
Well,
you want to prove that
LZ is not a linear combination.
I suppose we do.
But yeah,
I think we can prove that.
Let's see,
what can we do?
Let me not answer that right now.
It gets me off track.
It should be...
Let's come back to it.
It should be very easy.
I don't want to get my head...
Confused.
Of course,
the Z component of the angular momentum
is not likely to be a linear combination
of X and Y components.
But yes,
you're right.
You're right.
We do have the obligation
of showing that LZ is not...
You know what?
I think we can probably show that LZ,
from these commutation relations,
I believe we
could show that LZ does not commute
with any linear combination of LX and LZ.
So,
we have the obligation of showing that LZ
is not a linear combination of LX and LY.
If LZ was a linear combination of LX and LY,
it would commute with that linear combination.
I think we can prove it.
But...
So,
you could say it's orthogonal?
What does that mean?
LZ is orthogonal?
What does it mean?
Well,
there's no linear combination of LX and LY.
What does it mean that the LX and...
Yes,
they are components.
They are perpendicular components
of some three-dimensional components.
vector r cross p.
But I don't want to use that.
I think the right thing to do is
exactly as this gentleman said,
is to directly prove algebraically that LZ is
not a linear combination of the others.
I think we can prove that,
but yeah.
What's that?
A Lie algebra is an algebra
where the rule for multiplication is
commutation.
Okay,
that's what it means.
But don't worry about the name.
The name is just,
it's a collection of objects whose commutation
relations close.
A collection of objects,
when you keep commuting them,
you don't
get new ones.
That's called a Lie algebra.
And it's just a name.
Lie,
of course,
was
a mathematical name.
A mathematician.
I don't know,
was algebra a mathematician?
It might have been,
I don't
know.
Al-Jabeer.
Yeah,
I think he was.
What's that?
Algebra is an Arabic word.
I think it's an Arabic word,
yeah.
I don't think so.
I think it was.
I have a feeling his name was just Al-Jabeer,
but I'm not sure.
I remember
reading that,
but maybe I don't remember reading it.
Okay,
so where are we?
We have this nice
collection of algebraic relations,
including three more,
but I'll just write them as one
more.
The commutator of any component of L with the Hamiltonian.
Okay.
The commutator of any component of L
with the Hamiltonian is equal to zero.
Which means that the three
components of angular momentum are conserved.
Okay,
what can we do with that?
Well,
a lot.
Okay.
This is a good time to remember what we learned about the
harmonic oscillator by having a lot of time to think about it.
Okay.
So,
we had a similar kind of algebraic structure.
The similar kind of algebraic structure that we
had were the commutation relations of creation operators,
annihilation operators,
and the number operator.
We had closed commutation relations of a very similar kind,
not exactly the same kind,
but closed commutation relations,
and they were quite powerful.
We deduced the entire spectrum of
the harmonic oscillator by the number operator.
We did it from
constructing creation and annihilation operators.
It was much easier than solving any Schrodinger equation.
We're going to do the same thing here.
We're going to construct
creation and annihilation operators,
but the creation and annihilation operators
are not going to change the energy.
What they're going to change is
the z component of angular momentum.
Now,
why do I pick the z component of angular momentum?
That's arbitrary.
Remember,
in quantum mechanics,
if you want to actually work with things,
you usually have to pick a basis.
You usually have to pick a preferred set of operators,
which you regard as defining a basis.
Often it doesn't matter.
There's the x basis or the x representation.
Not a basis,
a representation.
Okay.
In quantum mechanics of a particle,
there's the position representation,
there's the momentum representation.
In studying spins,
we have the sigma z representation and
the sigma x representation and so forth.
It really doesn't matter for the purposes
of the invariant physics which basis you use,
but it's common to pick one and
work with it and keep with it.
We're going to do the same thing here.
We're going to pick out
the z component of angular momentum.
We're going to pick out the z
component of angular momentum to focus on.
There's nothing special about it.
We could have picked the x
and we could have picked the y,
but it's useful to pick the z component.
No more useful than x and y,
but let's do it.
Okay.
So we're going to work with the
z component of angular momentum and its eigenvectors.
We're going to work with the z
component of angular momentum and its eigenvectors.
And see what we can
find out about the entire spectrum.
Okay.
Lz has eigenvectors.
It's a Hermitian operator.
How many it has,
I don't know.
We'll find out as we go along.
And let's call the eigenvalue of Lz little m.
It's the same eigenvalue or the same
notation that I used in two dimensions.
In two dimensions where there was
only the z component of angular momentum,
I called the eigenvalues m,
and I'll continue to do that.
Again,
it's a historical notation.
It had to do with putting atoms in magnetic fields.
You put an atom in a
magnetic field and you study its spectroscopy.
And arbitrarily,
the z direction was chosen for
the direction of the magnetic field,
and the angular momentum about the z
axis was called the magnetic quantum number.
But for our purposes now,
m is just an eigenvalue of Lz.
This is the equation that says that the eigenvector
m is an eigenvector of Lz with eigenvalue little m.
Sort of redundant notation.
I've used the same notation
for the eigenvector and the eigenvalue.
And here's where mathematicians go crazy,
because they don't like you to
use the same notation for two things.
But we'll do it anyway.
Okay,
so that's the...
and what we want to find out
is what are the possible values of m.
The possible values of m
will be a little bit different.
They're exactly the same as the
possible eigenvalues of Lx and Ly,
because there's nothing special about Lz.
But nevertheless,
let's see what we can find out.
Now,
in the case of the harmonic oscillator,
we figured stuff out by
inventing creation and annihilation operators,
or operators which raised and lowered the energy.
We're now going to invent
operators which raise and lower m.
They raise and lower the magnetic quantum number.
And how do you do it?
You do it in a way
very similar to the harmonic oscillator.
Question.
Yeah.
When you refer to...
we did the harmonic oscillator,
you talked about the classical harmonic oscillator?
We did.
Or the...
The quantum harmonic oscillator.
Okay,
we never did that.
We didn't.
We didn't do that?
Not in the class,
not in the book.
Not in the last class,
but it's in the book.
Oh.
And there is a video that covers it.
Ooh.
Somewhere back in history.
Ooh,
we didn't...
we never did the harmonic oscillator.
Okay.
In that case,
we'll come back to the harmonic oscillator,
and instead of telling you how
much this is like the harmonic oscillator,
I will tell you how much
the harmonic oscillator is like angular momentum.
Good.
This is self-contained.
It doesn't require us to know about...
I thought that was one of your...
I thought that was one
of your main motivations for this...
for this second course,
because
you said,
gee,
we didn't get to cover the harmonic oscillator.
I had forgotten.
Well,
it's in our book,
but...
There is a...
I'll send the link out to the video.
Good.
Thank you.
The book will open.
It's up.
Yeah,
on the email.
Right.
You'll find out.
Okay,
do not worry about the harmonic oscillator now.
It's much more complicated than this.
Okay.
Thank you.
So,
we've picked out,
LZ is a little bit special.
Not physically,
but mathematically for our purposes.
And,
let's invent operators LX plus ILY,
and also LX minus ILY.
And,
call them L plus and L minus.
Now,
what I want to figure out
is the commutation relation of the...
of L plus and L minus with Lz.
For the moment,
I don't really care too much about the
commutator of L plus with L minus.
I'll tell you now it's Lz,
but that's not so important.
What I want is the commutation
relations of L plus with L minus.
So how do we get them?
Well,
we're going to get them from
the last two of these equations.
Let's rewrite them.
Let's see,
how did I write them?
Lx with Lz,
that's this one over here.
I've changed the order of x and z.
So that's minus Ily.
Do I have that right?
Yeah.
That's this one over here.
And since I changed the order of x and z,
that changes the sign.
Then there's the other one,
commutator of Ly with Lz.
And that is,
or Ily with Lz.
We have to do a little bit of work.
Here's Ly with Lz.
Multiply it by I,
and we get minus Lx.
And now we're just going to
add and subtract these two equations.
Adding and subtracting them will
give us the commutation relations
between L plus and L minus on the one hand,
and Lz.
Do you have minus or what now?
Minus Lx,
yeah.
Okay,
we add them and subtract them.
If we add them,
we get L plus commuted with Lz.
And if we subtract them,
we get L minus.
We do the summation on this side also.
And here's what we get.
I'll just write it out.
We don't need to belabor it.
The commutator of L plus
with Lz is minus L plus.
And the commutator of L
minus with Lz is L minus.
Not minus L minus,
but plus L minus.
L minus.
Those are the two basic
commutation relations that follow from these.
Now I understand this is very abstract.
How did anybody know to do this?
Well,
I did.
I'm not even sure who did it.
It's probably Dirac.
Dirac had a weird mind.
He liked to commute.
I can't tell you exactly why he did this,
but once you do it,
you say,
wow,
okay,
that's very clever.
So this is just another
way of writing the Lie algebra.
It's probably true that commutator of
L plus with L minus is Lz.
Or maybe twice Lz.
You can work that out.
But we won't use it.
Okay.
Now what I'm going to prove
is the following very interesting little theorem.
Supposing we have an eigenvector.
The eigenvector of M,
of Lz.
Supposing we have one.
We found one somehow.
Now I'm going to show you how
to find another one with a different eigenvalue.
Okay.
We're going to do it
by applying one of these equations.
Which one are we going to do?
L plus.
Let's do L plus.
We're going to take this equation for L plus
and multiply it by the eigenvector.
L plus L minus.
Sorry,
L plus Lz.
Minus Lz L plus.
That's the commutator.
Acting on the vector M is equal to
minus L plus acting on the vector M.
Okay.
So what do we know?
Let's take this first term here.
Well,
okay.
Let's take this first term here on the left.
What does Lz do when it hits M?
Multiplies by M.
That's because M is an eigenvector of Lz.
So the first term becomes M.
M times L plus M.
I'm going to take L plus and M and
I'm going to put them in a red circle.
Because I want you to
think of it as a unit.
Now,
let's add this over to the left side here.
We're going to take this term
and move it to the right.
And we're going to take this
one and move it to the left.
So let's take this one and
move it over to the left.
That will give us plus L plus M.
That's also exactly the same thing
that appears in the red circle.
So what do we get?
We get M plus 1 times
the object in the red circle.
Let's just draw a red circle there.
That's the left hand side with
this term transposed to the left.
Now let's transpose the other term to the right.
That's equal to Lz times L plus M.
But L plus M is again
exactly the thing in the red circle.
The thing in the red circle is the same thing.
There's a certain ket vector.
So what does this say?
This says that there's another eigenvector of Lz.
This equation is an eigenvector equation for Lz.
Lz acting on the red eigenvector gives
us M plus 1 times the red eigenvector.
What does this mean?
It means we've discovered another eigenvector
of Lz with eigenvalue M plus 1.
We can call the thing in the red bracket here,
we can just call it the eigenvector M plus 1.
We found a trick for taking any eigenvector of Lz
and promoting it,
lifting it up one unit,
and increasing the eigenvalue by one unit.
What about if we did
the same thing with L minus?
If we did the same thing with L minus,
we would again discover another
eigenvector with one lower unit.
So we've used a simple algebra of commutators
to generate a spectrum,
a spectrum of values of Lz.
And what's more,
they're separated by,
an integer,
they're separated by integers.
So we've discovered the following fact,
that if we plot on the vertical axis here,
the possible values,
the values of M,
or Lz,
Lz,
the possible values of Lz,
if we find one at some value of M,
oh,
let's first of all,
let's,
um,
let's put some,
let's lay some integers down.
minus 1,
minus 2,
minus 3.
Let's suppose we found an eigenvector,
or an eigenvalue of M.
Nothing yet has told us it must be an integer.
So it could be anywhere.
It could be over here.
It could be at 3 quarters,
or it could be at 7 eighths,
or it could be pi quarters,
or it could be a half.
It could be anywheres.
Not over here.
Let's put it over here.
Then...
Just one question.
Look,
it was,
the way it was defined,
it had to be an integer.
Going all the way back.
In fact,
we're going to find it has to be...
Yeah.
You're right.
Except,
not quite.
What I mean is,
I thought you already said that.
Yeah.
We could go back to what I said earlier,
and use that.
I don't want to,
because,
I want to show you another argument for it.
Now,
the other argument will not prove it's an integer.
It'll prove something a little bit looser.
And the looser fact is,
in fact,
the correct fact.
But we'll see.
Alright,
so the first thing is,
we know that there's got
to be another one above it.
One unit above it.
And another one,
one unit below it.
Now,
there's one exception to this statement,
that when we apply L plus,
we will necessarily get a
new eigenvector with one unit up.
What's the other alternative possibility?
Zero.
That you get zero.
That you get just plain zero.
No vector at all.
So this could terminate.
Conceivably,
it could terminate.
I wish I had a green pen.
I don't.
It could terminate somewheres.
Let's say it terminates here.
And,
by the same logic,
it could terminate from below.
If L minus killed the vector.
So,
we will generate a family
which may or may not also terminate somewheres.
Now,
the first thing which is true,
is if it terminates,
then there's a relationship about where
it terminates from above and below.
And the reason is very simple.
M is the eigenvalue of Lz.
Remember we have rotation invariance.
Supposing I use my rotation invariance
to completely rotate by 180 degrees.
If I rotate by 180 degrees,
then Lz becomes minus Lz.
If there's really rotational symmetry,
then it must mean the spectrum,
the possible eigenvalues of Lz must be the same
as the eigenvalues of minus Lz.
It's just looking at the same system,
except standing on your head.
And if there's rotation invariance,
you should get exactly the same spectrum.
So,
from that,
you can conclude that this red dot
and this red dot have to be symmetrically placed.
There's only two possibilities.
If the red dots are symmetrically placed,
and these are separated by integers,
then there's only two possibilities.
The first possibility is that the red dot
is at an integer.
Let's call this,
this is the integer M.
And 0,
down here.
Symmetrically placed about the origin,
and separated by integers.
That would be one possible spectrum.
If it terminates.
There's another possibility,
and the other possibility that still is consistent
with a symmetric spectrum
and separation by integers,
and that's the half integer option.
The half integer option is 0 again.
1,
2,
whatever.
Whatever.
Start here.
Shift by an integer.
Let's see,
here's 0.
And it's also symmetrically placed about the origin.
In this spectrum over here,
if it's physically reasonable,
the values of the angular momentum,
the z component of the angular momentum,
are half integers.
Half integer,
3 halves,
5 halves,
minus a half,
minus 3 halves,
minus 5 halves,
ending somewheres.
Or the other possibility is integer spectrum.
Now,
you mentioned before
that I've already spoken about
how we sort of proved that the spectrum is integer,
and I did.
Somebody mentioned.
And that's correct.
That is correct for orbital angular momentum.
Orbital angular momentum means r cross p.
It means wave functions of particles
that depend on position.
And how do we prove that?
Remember how we proved it?
Oh,
we proved it by saying the wave function
has to be single-valued when you go around,
when you go all the ways around.
Okay.
So,
on the face of it,
it would seem that this is the only physical possibility.
In fact,
this possibility here is also real,
and it corresponds to spin angular momentum.
But for the time being,
let's just get rid of it.
We'll come back to it.
All right,
there's a maximum.
Given a state of the mass,
a state like this,
we can generate a few more.
It may or may not terminate,
but let's assume it terminates.
We found a multiplet of states.
A multiplet of states
which are in some way related to each other
and which have to have the same energy.
Why do they have to have the same energy?
Let's prove they have the same energy.
And then we'll quit.
That'll be enough for tonight.
Let's prove one more thing.
They have to have the same energy.
Let's suppose that we found a state M,
and it has an energy equal to E.
So,
let's say that we found a state M,
times M.
It's an eigenvector of the energy.
It has L sub Z equal to M,
and it has energy E.
Now,
let's go to M plus 1.
M plus 1
is L plus times M.
That's M plus 1.
And let's ask what its energy is.
So what do we do?
We apply the Hamiltonian to it.
And see what we get.
Okay.
But,
the Hamiltonian commutes,
it's assumed that the Hamiltonian commutes
with all the components of the angular momentum.
So that means we can write
that this is the same as
L plus H times M.
But H times M is just E times M.
Okay.
What does this equation say?
It says H on M plus 1,
that's L plus on M,
is equal to E times M plus 1.
We can do the same thing with M minus 1.
That tells us that if we find an eigenvector
of the Z component of angular momentum,
which happens also to be an eigenvector,
an eigenvector of energy,
then by raising and lowering,
until we run out of possibilities,
until we run out of,
until we hit the endpoints,
we create states of exactly the same energy.
This is the idea of degeneracy following from symmetry
when symmetries don't commute with each other.
This is what we talked about in the beginning.
When symmetries don't commute with each other,
the L's in this case,
it tells us that there are degeneracies.
And the degeneracies are states of equal energy.
And in this case,
the states of equal energy are just found
by going up and down this ladder in this way.
But these just states go to the different axes?
Like the Z axis is equivalent to the Y axis?
Yeah.
Yeah,
they're very closely related
to the idea of tangent.
I mean,
they're very closely related to the idea of tangent.
and then we're taking these states and rotating it.
Yes.
For example,
you could ask the question,
what are the eigenvectors of L sub X?
The eigenvectors of L sub X
are not individual ones of these,
but linear combinations of them.
Right.
Linear combinations of these are eigenvectors of Lx and Ly,
and so in that
sense what we're finding here
is essentially the eigenvectors rotated,
the
rotated versions of the...
yeah.
And that's kind of obvious because when you
apply an L,
you're generating a rotation.
Yeah.
So this is the quantum analog
of saying that if you take an
orbit and rotate it about an axis,
you'll find a
new orbit with a different angular momentum,
but with the same energy.
Different angle...
different z component of the angular momentum.
It's exactly
what's going on here.
Rotating the configuration is creating states of
different z component...
different z component of the angular momentum,
but
with a different angular momentum.
So we're going to be able
to do the same thing here.
Rotating the configuration is creating states of
exactly the same energy.
That's what's happening.
Yeah.
By applying the other
rotation operators...
now it's convenient to use this particular combinations L
plus and L minus just because Dirac
figured out how to do it this way.
This
is the the trick of using raising and lowering operators,
and this occurs all
the time in quantum mechanics.
Whenever you find an algebra like this which
closes on the commutation,
that's a signal that you should be looking for
creation or raising and lowering operators
and using the algebra to sort
out the spectrum of the system,
the spectrum of eigenvalues.
Can you apply the operator L plus to the maximum?
That'll give zero.
By definition.
That's the definition of the top level.
There may not be a top.
You may just go up and
up and up and up and up.
What's the definition,
please?
I had a question.
How do you define you reach the top?
What happens?
L plus gives zero.
And you're minus zero at the bottom.
Right.
Now this can all be made concrete by
specific wave functions that will show that this happens.
I didn't want to write
down complicated angular wave functions.
One possibility is you never run out of anything.
That would correspond to
basically infinite angular momentum states.
States of infinite angular,
infinite capacity,
but typically real angular momentum states
of atoms and so forth in somewheres.
We'll work out more about angular momentum,
a little more,
and then we'll apply it to atoms
and understand a little bit about atomic spectrum.
A little bit about the spectrum of the hydrogen atom.
But this is where the degeneracies,
or some of the degeneracies,
well it's where all of the exact
degeneracies of the hydrogen atom come from.
All of the equality of a...
And these states are the orbital,
or the various orbital quantum numbers of...
Of the hydrogen atom.
There's more,
there's more,
but...
Okay.
For more,
please visit us at stanford.edu.