Stanford University.
This goes back to particle physics.
It's a bit off the subject of the class,
but
there's evidence that the neutrinos
have mass and that they mix.
Mm-hm.
In the particle physics class,
we didn't address mixing.
And I wanted to ask if the neutrinos,
if they have mass,
must they have all the same mass?
No,
they don't have all the same mass.
So then the question would be how
on earth can you mix and conserve energy?
Well,
okay,
what it really means is that the mass is energy,
right?
Okay,
the eigenstates of energy are linear superpositions
of the eigenstates of something else.
That something else is called the type of neutrino.
So the eigenstates of energy don't mix.
The eigenstates of energy do not mix with each other.
And it's just that the
eigenstates themselves are mixtures of different,
different states.
There are many,
many examples like this in quantum physics.
Mechanics.
A simple example is if you
have a potential which looks like this.
This is the phenomenon of mixing in a particular context.
Supposing you have a particle that moves
in a potential that looks like this.
All right,
so the particle can be on this side.
And let's suppose for the sake
of argument that the barrier in between
the two minima is pretty large.
Large enough that that's to a good approximation,
we might want to say that the
particle is either trapped on this side or
trapped on this side,
okay?
And can't get through.
Now,
of course,
quantum mechanically,
there's a little bit of
possibility of leaking through the barrier.
It's called tunneling.
But supposing we ignore that.
The barrier.
That's what I begin with.
Then we could just take the left hand side here.
Treat it as though the right hand
side didn't exist as though there was an
infinite barrier preventing the particle from going through.
You could think of this as a brick wall.
This is a brick wall.
And ordinary particles don't go
through brick walls very easily.
So it's a good approximation just
to pretend this is infinitely high.
And in that case you would ask,
what is the ground state?
What is the ground state wave function
and ground state energy of the system?
And you might say,
well,
okay,
let's just forget the fact
that this part is over here.
The ground state looks like that.
It's some wave function.
It has no nodes,
no zeros,
as smooth as possible,
and it has some energy,
E.
But wait a minute.
If this potential is exactly symmetric,
then there must be another ground state on this side.
Another ground state on that side,
which has exactly the same energy.
Same energy,
same profile,
except it's on the other side of the barrier,
and in every way is identical.
These are two distinct states which
apparently have exactly the same energy,
but they don't.
They don't.
And the reason is that these wave
functions are not exactly eigenstates of the earth.
They're not exactly the same energy.
Now here's what we know.
We know that for a potential like this,
the eigenstates of energy are either symmetric
or anti-symmetric functions.
This is a theorem about quantum mechanics.
It's a theorem about differential equations.
If the potential is symmetric,
then the wave functions,
which are the energy eigenstates,
are either symmetric or anti-symmetric.
What does anti-symmetric mean?
It means that the wave
functions are either symmetric or anti-symmetric.
It means that when you cross
over the dividing barrier between here,
it goes from positive
to negative.
Okay,
so let's see if we can
understand better what's really going on.
Each one of these wave functions to
begin with is neither symmetric nor anti-symmetric.
There's one over here,
and there's another one over here,
and it's neither symmetric.
This doesn't look very symmetric.
Symmetric means that it is invariant with
respect to the energy of the earth.
It's not a reflection about the origin here.
Symmetric would mean that if you reflect it,
it stays the same.
Well,
this is certainly not symmetric.
If you reflect it,
you get a wave function over here.
So this is neither symmetric nor anti-symmetric.
Neither is the other one.
But you can make symmetric and anti-symmetric combinations.
For example,
if I take a wave function,
which looks very much almost identical,
and I take
a wave function exactly like that,
gets very small in between where the potential energy
is very large,
can't get into there,
or it can,
but only a tiny little bit,
and then
continue it symmetrically on the other side,
that doesn't look very symmetric,
I apologize.
But it's supposed to be symmetric.
Then this wave function would have a slightly
lower energy than either a wave function restricted
to this side or to this side.
You can lower the energy.
Now how much would lower the energy?
A tiny,
tiny amount,
an exponentially small amount.
But the energy of the symmetric wave function
would be slightly less than the energy of
either one of these.
That's the first state.
The ground state,
the true ground state,
the true energy eigenstate is this combination
here.
The next excited state looks like this.
It looks almost exactly the same.
Oh,
incidentally,
remember that the sine of the
wave function is immaterial to anything.
If you have a wave function
and it's an eigenstate of some operator,
if you change the sine of
the wave function,
it's still an eigenvector of the same quantity.
The sine of the wave function doesn't contain anything.
It doesn't contain any real information.
So what is the first excited state?
The theorem is that the first
excited state always has one node.
Given the symmetry of the problem and so forth,
the only node,
everybody know what a node is?
It means a place where the wave function is zero.
If it's antisymmetric,
it surely has a node.
It can't be antisymmetric and not have a node.
And if...what does I mean?
the wave function look like?
It looks like almost exactly the same thing on
this side,
likewise on this side except that it's negative,
like that.
So over the
region where the wave function is appreciable,
it looks exactly the same on
this side,
and on the right-hand side it
looks exactly the same except that it
that's negative.
This energy is ever so slightly
larger than the energy of just
one of these waves if it
were constrained to live on one side.
So what
happens is originally before we took
into account the fact that the barrier
is not infinitely high,
before we took that into account we basically had
infinite waves.
two energy levels,
let's draw energy here,
the one on the left
and the one on the right,
and they were at exactly the same energy,
but not quite,
of course.
Now we took into account
the fact that the wave functions can
leak through the barrier a little bit.
That's just the fact that it
doesn't quite go to zero here,
it's almost zero,
very close to zero,
but not quite.
The effect of that is to
split these two energies a little bit.
It splits the two energies,
but gives you wave functions which are not
like the original one-sided wave functions.
The one-sided wave functions,
which would have been
what you would have if you
really had an infinite barrier in between,
get mixed.
They get mixed from left-sided and right-sided
to left-sided plus right-sided
and left-sided minus right-sided.
Basically that's what's going on.
You have two states,
the left side and the right side.
Neither one is exactly an energy eigenstate,
and the real energy eigenstates are
mixtures of the two of them.
The mixtures of the two of them,
with slightly different energy,
are the ones that are not right.
What's the consequence of the fact
that the wave functions are these mixtures?
It's neither left nor right,
but one over the square root of two left
plus one over the square root of two right,
and one over the square root of two left
minus one over the square root of two right.
Those are the two eigenstates of the energy.
Okay.
So.
Now,
let's try to find out
what would happen if we started,
if we put an electron,
an electron,
a particle,
if we put an electron on the right hand,
on the left hand side.
We start with an electron on the left hand side.
What happens?
How does it evolve?
So we can work this out.
Let's say we have two wave functions.
One of them is psi left plus psi right.
And this is an eigenstate
of energy with slightly less energy.
Let's say the energy of this is E1.
E1 is ever so slightly less than the
energy if you couldn't get through the barrier.
And then you have,
that's the,
that's,
uh...
Let's call it E1 minus epsilon.
In other words,
when the two wave functions mix,
the energy is lowered for the symmetric state.
And for the anti-symmetric state,
there should be a square root of two here.
And then we have psi left minus
psi right over square root of two.
And that has an energy E1 plus epsilon.
It gets shifted up by one.
It gets shifted up a little bit.
Okay?
Now,
each one of these is an eigenstate of the energy.
That means that if you
were to follow its time dependence,
it would...
If you were to follow its time dependence,
if you were to solve the Schrodinger,
the time-dependent Schrodinger equation,
what would be the time dependence of this one?
E to the i.
E1 minus epsilon t,
right?
Okay.
Now,
what about this one?
This one has E to
the i E1 plus epsilon t.
Okay,
now let's start with psi left.
Well,
let's call this...
Let's give this a name.
Let's call this psi plus,
and let's call this psi minus.
Psi plus and psi minus.
But now I'm interested not
in psi plus plus psi minus.
I know exactly what happens to either of those.
But I'm interested in what happens
if I start with pure psi left.
Somebody just plopped a particle
into the left-hand well here.
How does it evolve?
So that means that at time t equals 0,
we start with just psi left.
At t equals 0,
But psi left is equal...
This is at time t equals 0,
so we can set the t is equal to 0.
That's equal to psi plus plus psi minus
over square root of 2.
We get that just by adding these two.
The psi rights cancel,
and if we're careful about it,
we'll find there's a 1
over square root of 2 there.
So that's the initial state...
Sorry,
psi minus.
Psi plus plus psi minus over
square root of 2 is psi left.
So this is the initial state.
But how does it evolve?
What happens to it with time?
With time,
each one of these picks up its own phase.
So after a time t,
the wave function is no longer just psi left.
Let's write it down what it is.
It's psi plus times e to
the i e1 minus epsilon t.
That's what happens to psi 1.
Or psi plus,
excuse me.
That's what happens to psi 2.
That's what happens to psi plus.
And what happens to psi minus?
That's plus psi minus e to the minus i e1.
I guess it's plus...
No,
it's e to the plus i e1 plus epsilon t.
Did I get the sine of the exponent right?
I did not.
It should be minus.
It doesn't matter.
It doesn't make any difference.
Just leave it.
Okay.
So first of all,
we can factor out an overall factor.
e to the i e1 t.
That factors out from both of them.
And then we get psi plus
e to the minus i epsilon t
plus psi minus e to the plus i epsilon t.
Or a square root of 2.
Okay,
what happens to this with time?
With time,
these phases are different.
Notice that one of them goes as
e to the minus i epsilon t.
The other goes as e
to the plus i epsilon t.
What's going to happen?
We started out only with psi left.
We wrote it in terms
of psi plus and psi minus.
And now we let it evolve with time.
After an appropriate amount of time,
the sine of these two
will be opposite to each other.
How long does that take?
How long does it take?
These are two different complex numbers.
How long...
And think about it this way.
They're points on the complex plane,
on the unit circle.
One of them is slowly
drifting up on the unit circle,
e to the plus i epsilon t.
The other one is drifting down.
It takes a certain amount of time
before the first one is up on the top
and the second one is down on the bottom.
Shall we figure out how long that takes?
Let's figure out how long that takes.
We want to know how long does it take
for this to become equal to minus that.
So let's just write it down.
e to the minus i epsilon t
equals minus e to the plus i epsilon t.
Let's just multiply by...
What does it say?
This says that e to the 2i epsilon t
equals minus 1.
I just multiply both sides by
e to the plus i epsilon t.
I get e to the 2i epsilon t here,
and on the left side I get 1,
but there's a minus sign.
Okay,
how long does it take
before this thing is equal to minus 1?
Well,
minus 1 is e to the i pi,
right?
e to the i pi.
So the time must be
twice epsilon t equals pi.
At twice...
twice epsilon t equals pi,
then we're in this situation
where the two phases here have opposite sign.
By the time that happens,
this wave function has become proportional
to the wave function with a minus sign here.
All right,
there is an e to the
2i epsilon t on the outside,
but that's not interesting.
What was originally a plus sign
evolves into a minus sign
because the two phases are not...
because the energies are slightly different,
the two phases are getting out of phase,
and after a while they become opposite.
Well,
when psi plus...
when it becomes psi plus minus psi minus,
we go back to here.
Psi plus minus psi minus
is psi right.
Let's look at this.
Take the difference psi plus minus psi right...
minus psi minus.
The psi lefts cancel,
and we get just the psi right term.
So that means after this amount of time,
which,
if epsilon is small,
can be a very long time.
If epsilon is small,
then this time is very small.
But after that amount of time,
if you were to look,
the particle would be on the other side.
It would have materialized on the other side,
gone through the barrier,
and materialized on the other side.
That's what this says.
Okay,
so the phenomenon of mixing
goes together with the phenomenon of oscillations.
This will go on and on and on
after when...
Okay,
so...
In another corresponding interval,
it'll swing back,
swing back and forth and back and forth
and oscillate.
So it looks like you're getting oscillations
between one wave function and the other.
That's correct,
you are.
Well,
between the two sides.
It's not violating energy.
The energy eigenstates are
doing what they're supposed to do.
Each one evolves separately.
But if you start with a thing
which is not an energy eigenstate,
it will also do what non-energy eigenstates
are supposed to do.
It will evolve.
And it will evolve back and forth
from one to the other.
Neutrinos behave like that.
The analog of the left wave function
is the neutrino which is made...
It's not made on the left.
It's made by the decay of...
decay involving an electron.
Decay of a particle that involves an electron
and it's called the electron neutrino.
The same precise kind of decay,
if it decayed into,
instead of an electron,
a mu particle,
it would make a...
a mu neutrino.
The real eigenstate of the energy,
of mass,
is kind of a linear...
is a linear combination of the electron
and the muon neutrino,
which is entirely analogous
to the two states,
psi plus and psi minus.
But when an electron...
when a neutrino is made,
it's made either in a decay
involving an electron
or in a decay involving a muon.
If it's made in a decay involving an electron,
it's like plunking the particle
into the left well here.
If it's made in a decay that involves the muon,
it's like plunking the state
into the right well.
But if you wait a while,
it'll just go back and forth between them.
Now that's interesting,
because an electron,
which is created...
sorry,
a neutrino,
which is of the electron type,
can undergo processes
other kinds of processes,
not just these decays,
scattering processes,
in which it produces an electron.
It will not produce a muon.
An electron neutrino will not produce a muon,
and a muon neutrino will not produce an electron.
So here's the experiment.
You start with an electron neutrino.
You wait a while,
half a period like this again,
and it becomes a muon neutrino.
And once it's become a muon neutrino,
you let it interact with something
and see if it produces an electron or a muon.
Okay?
So if you create this electron...
sorry,
this muon...
this neutrino
as an electron neutrino,
and then you just let it go a little bit.
You know,
you don't let it go very far,
very long.
Well,
if it was produced here,
it sort of stays here.
So after a little bit,
you do your experiment,
and you discover the electron,
neutrino only makes electrons,
only interacts in such a way as to make electrons.
The muon neutrino only interacts in ways
such as to make a muon.
But if you have a long baseline
so that the neutrino can go a long ways,
long enough that it undergoes one of these oscillations,
an electron neutrino made somewheres,
if you go down a line far enough,
you'll discover it can make muons.
Likewise,
the muon neutrino.
And in an oscillating way,
if you have a very long baseline,
you would discover that there are oscillations
of the neutrino from one type to the other.
Question.
What determines the size of epsilon?
Oh,
well,
all sorts of details,
such as the mass of the particle,
the height of the potential,
the width of the barrier,
it's extremely sensitive,
exponentially sensitive to,
to the parameters of the barrier.
Has this been observed?
Hmm.
Absolutely.
Both in neutrinos and in tunneling things like this.
How is that connected at all to neutrino mass?
The neutrino masses are the energy levels.
Now,
they start out with very,
very small energies
to begin with,
but then the mixing between them splits the energies
a little bit.
So,
they start out with small energies,
but then even on top of that,
there's a little bit of splitting.
And,
uh,
yeah.
So the prevailing wisdom is that neutrinos have mass?
Oh,
absolutely.
Not wisdom,
it's an experimental fact.
Yeah.
If this were,
say,
an ammonia molecule,
that barrier would be represented
as switching through the plane.
What does that barrier represent when you have a...
Well,
okay,
the,
um...
I can't...
What's an ammonia?
Is that a tetrahedron?
What's...
It's a tetrahedron?
Yeah.
Yeah,
okay.
that's binding to the anaphylact.
Uh,
well,
the only reason I say tetrahedron is because
a tetrahedron is an obvious
one to have a tunneling process.
Tetrahedron has,
um,
four atoms.
One,
two,
three.
What is ammonia?
NH3-1.
What is it?
NH4.
NH4?
Four?
You're telling me it has five atoms?
NH3.
So it has three H atoms.
I assume that's what NH3 means.
I'm not a very good chemist.
And then it has a noogie or whatever it's called.
So there's a triangle,
and then up above the triangle is the tetrahedral nitrogen.
Nitrogen?
Must be nitrogen.
Yeah,
right,
right.
Okay.
Now,
the,
uh,
the molecular bonds are such that this,
that this,
I'm going to call it a neutrino.
Please help me.
It's not a neutrino.
It's nitrogen.
This nitrogen likes to sit a certain
height above the base of the triangle there,
meaning to say its energy
is lowest when it's up here.
But of course,
there's another thing.
There's another state which is symmetric where the,
um,
nitrogen is down below here.
And the point is you can tunnel from
one to the other in exactly the same way.
So tunneling from one to the other
is basically the nitrogen tunneling through the,
through the plane of the hydrogen or something like that.
Um.
The question was,
you can see physically what it,
what the barrier is in ammonia,
but what physically is the barrier between it and nitrogen?
that's,
uh,
there's no barrier.
There's just a,
um,
no,
no.
It's more than an analogy.
Um,
the,
uh,
um,
there's coupling in the Hamiltonian,
which for whatever reason,
nobody knows why,
but there's coupling in the Hamiltonian.
Hamiltonian,
which takes an electron neutrino to
a muon neutrino and vice versa.
Uh,
in this case,
there's no,
there's a,
there's a coupling and the coupling
is due to the tunneling process.
This is basically the same mathematics,
but,
um,
I'll tell you where else you've seen this.
Well,
you've seen the same thing.
And it's also a good example.
The mathematics is the same.
Um.
If you take a,
a,
yeah,
take a spin.
Just a spin.
We've done spins,
uh,
little,
you know,
magnetic spin,
electron.
Without any magnetic field,
the two states,
let's call them up and down,
have the same energy.
Up and down have the,
uh,
the same energy.
Has energy E.
And down has energy E.
The energy would be just mc squared for the electron,
let's say.
Alright,
now you put a little magnetic field on.
Let's say the magnetic field is pointing upwards.
A weak magnetic field.
What happens to the energy of these two?
These are little magnets,
if you like.
They're little magnets.
Magnets either up or down.
And depending on the direction of the magnetic field,
the up magnet will have a
slightly different energy than the down magnet.
Takes some work to,
uh,
to turn the,
the thing over.
So the up electron and the
down electron will have slightly different energy.
Okay.
Um.
The up electron and the down electron,
oh,
no,
let's do something else.
Okay.
Yeah.
Let's put,
let's,
little different.
Let's actually make the,
um,
the magnetic field along the x-axis.
Let's put the,
um,
the magnetic field along the x-axis.
Then what are the eigenstates of energy for the system?
Are they up and down?
They're what we called left and right.
Remember when we studied spins?
They're what we called the electron
pointing along the x-axis or the anti-x-axis.
But the electron pointing along the x-axis is just
a linear combination of the electron being up or down.
Same exact kind of combination.
Let's call it left.
I love this.
I like the red.
Is this,
is this visible?
Yeah,
yeah.
Okay.
Left is equal to one over
square root of two up plus down.
Likewise,
right is of the same sort of thing,
the other equation there.
Now,
when I put a little bit of magnetic field on,
the result is energy eigenstates which are left and right,
but with slightly different energy.
Why is the energy slightly different?
Well,
because there's a little bit of a difference.
Depending on which way the electron is oriented,
it's either oriented along the magnetic
field or opposite to the magnetic field.
So,
we have the same situation where there's
a slight splitting of the energy levels.
What's the result if we
were to start the electron up?
Let's suppose we start the electron up.
Somebody gave us an up electron.
And said,
here,
do with it what you want.
But it's in this very weak magnetic field.
What happens to it?
Do you remember?
It precesses.
So,
after a certain half period,
it becomes a down.
After another half period,
it becomes an up.
Same exact phenomena.
The energy eigenstates are mixtures of up and down.
And because of that,
there are up-down oscillations.
If there was some reason why an electron
liked to be made in a certain way,
and it was not an
experiment pointing along the up direction,
then if you waited a little while,
it would be along the down direction.
So,
it's the same phenomena.
But it doesn't require any tunneling.
It's just a term in the
Hamiltonian which mixes the up and down,
in this case the magnetic field.
What happens to the tau?
Oh,
it also gets mixed in there.
It also gets mixed in.
So,
it's the analog of having three states
which all get mixed with each other.
It's a little more complicated because spin comes into it.
But this is the basic phenomenon.
You know,
if you...
You're probably quite capable of understanding it now.
You know enough to read
a paper or two on it.
I have a quick question.
So,
in this case,
when you mentioned that it precesses,
if we look at it a tiny
time after we put the magnetic field,
we still find it in the up position?
It's a tiny probability of
it being in the down position.
Will it ever be towards us?
Yeah,
it will.
yeah,
It will precess around here.
Going from up to down.
So,
it will not have just up or down.
It could be in and out.
It will never...
If you start it up,
it will not get along the x-axis.
It will stay perpendicular to the x-axis.
So,
it's a continuous on this theta angle.
Yeah,
it's quite continuous.
These phases just evolve continuously.
Right.
But,
of course,
if you look at it,
depending on what you're measuring,
let's say you're measuring up or down,
you'll either find up or down.
You won't find anything in between.
But the interesting thing is if you
make the electron in an up way
and you wait exactly a half period like this,
you'll find it definitely down.
So,
if there's something that a down electron
can do that an up electron can't do,
and let's say something that an up electron
can do and a down electron can't do,
you can do an experiment in which you create
the up electron by doing one kind of interaction
and then at a later time ask
whether it's behaving like the down electron.
And,
of course,
this is easy to do.
Much harder to do for neutrinos.
You said it will never point
to the left or point up,
down,
or in or out.
Well,
yeah.
Is that why you specified a weak point?
Weak field?
No,
no,
no.
It's got nothing to do
with the weakness of the field.
The only reason I say a weak field is
because I don't want it to process very rapidly.
If I want it to
be anything like the neutrino situation,
where the oscillations are very slow,
I will want to make a weak field.
The magnitude of the field only
determines the period of the oscillation.
The analog of the field itself
is the strength of the mixing
between the different kinds of neutrinos.
And that's simply,
and as far as we know now,
it's just a parameter.
It's a parameter in our theory and we
don't know with any confidence where it came from.
It's a very small parameter.
The electron masses are tiny to begin with,
and the splittings between them are obviously
no bigger than the masses of the electron.
The bigger the mass of the neutrino itself.
And so they're tiny numbers,
and what their origin is is uncertain.
What is true is that in
the standard model of elementary particle physics,
there is no room for that parameter.
That parameter is mathematically forbidden
in the absolutely standard theory of particle physics.
Meaning the standard model.
So,
where it comes from is
some violation of the standard model,
but it's very small,
so it could be a very remote phenomena,
remote in energy,
remote in distance scales,
and so forth.
And it probably is.
Okay,
quick question.
Yeah.
Is the only reason that
people think the neutrino has mass
because it just,
it does change?
The oscillation.
Is that the only reason?
Mm-hmm.
Other than theoretical,
yeah.
Right.
Because of the relativity,
the time dilation couldn't change if it was...
That's right.
If it was truly massless,
it couldn't change.
Time dilation is right.
Yeah.
You could do experiments where you detect
whether it's in or out of the ground.
Well,
it's up and down.
You can do any experiment you want.
But the...
If...
Yeah,
you...
Right.
The polarization of the electron,
in other words,
the direction of the spin,
doesn't tell you what value you would measure,
except that if it's known to be up
and you measure upness or downness,
you get up.
It does not tell you if you measure
the x component whether you get plus or minus,
and it doesn't tell you whether if you multiply,
you measure the y component.
So the idea is to put it in
a known configuration where if you measured the upness-downness,
you would get up and then wait a half
period until it's pointing down and then measure it again,
and you will definitely get down.
That's the experiment.
And after a quarter period,
you'll definitely get towards your...
Yeah.
If you waited a half period
to do the experiment with the neutrino,
do we get 50% probability
of it acting like a neutrino?
Mu neutrino 50% like an electron,
correct?
That would be a quarter period.
Quarter period.
Yeah.
Um,
it's...
I don't...
The answer's no,
but for reasons that are somewhat incidental,
it is a little more complicated.
The complications of spin get into it,
and the oscillations are not
exactly symmetrical about the two,
but that's a refinement.
The basic physics is this.
So,
um,
yeah.
Since the neutrino masses vary,
and say you were looking at a
neutrino coming from the sun to us,
to preserve or conserve the momentum,
is the velocity changing as it oscillates?
Yeah,
the velocity...
Um...
Yeah.
Let's see,
the velocity must change,
yeah.
Yeah.
The momentum stays the same.
Right.
And if the mass is undergoing oscillations,
Uh,
right.
Incidentally,
this is believed to be the reason
why there was a deficit of solar neutrinos.
For many years,
there was a deficit of solar neutrinos
where not enough solar neutrinos were seen on Earth
to account for the,
um,
for the expected number of neutrino interactions
taking place in the sun.
And,
of course,
the reason was that by the time
the neutrinos get here,
half of them are unavailable to interact with electrons.
Or half of them or something.
They've become muons or whatever.
Muon neutrinos.
Or some other species.
All right.
Well,
since we're talking about,
um,
these kinds of things,
uh,
I did read in the article that somebody sent
through the email that the electrons,
the electron is a sphere.
And I was a little bit surprised to read that.
I didn't,
I didn't think the electron is a sphere,
and I still don't think the electron is a sphere,
even after reading the venerable,
um,
Scientific American.
So I thought I might,
uh,
since,
has,
have people read that article?
Oh,
only one person read it?
Oh.
Hm?
Yeah,
it came in my mail.
I assumed it came through the,
uh,
did it,
did somebody send it?
Maybe they sent it just to you.
Maybe.
Maybe it didn't come from any of you.
Maybe it came from,
uh,
No,
it didn't come from Scientific American.
Maybe they just did this question to change character.
Okay,
so there's an article in the Scientific American,
just for fun,
let's,
uh,
I don't,
I thought we'd take a little bit of a break,
at least for part of the hour tonight,
and talk about,
um,
real physical phenomena.
Not that,
uh,
quantum field theory is not a real physical phenomenon,
but,
you know,
we've been concentrating on the formal mathematics of it.
Is the electron a sphere?
What would it mean for
the electron to be a sphere?
What does it mean for anything to be a sphere,
a particle or an atom or whatever else?
Uh,
and what is it that was or wasn't measured
that,
according to the author of
the Scientific American little blurb there,
indicates that the electron is a sphere?
And what does that say about,
uh,
physics?
Well,
first of all,
what was measured is the
electric dipole moment of the electron.
Okay,
now we'll come to what that means in a moment,
but,
uh,
I think you all know
what an electric dipole moment is,
right?
If you have a little bit of plus
charge and a little bit of minus charge,
and they're separated by distance d,
then the dipole moment is just
the charge times the distance between them,
and it represents a
sort of off-centered charge distribution.
The center of the dumbbell,
let's think of it as a dumbbell,
the center of the dumbbell is
at the center of the dumbbell,
and an electric dipole would indicate
that there was an imbalance on
the two ends of the dipole
of the electric charge distribution.
That's what an electric dipole means.
For a thing not to
have an electric dipole does not,
first of all,
does not say it's a sphere,
um,
a charge distribution can have many,
many different multipole moments,
many,
many different shape parameters.
Okay?
What kind of shape,
corresponds to having a dipole?
A situation,
exactly what I said,
where there's an imbalance of charge on
one side relative to the other side,
relative to some,
uh,
to some center.
What other kinds of charge distributions are there?
Well,
you could have a charge
distribution shaped like an oblate spheroid,
or a,
uh,
or any kind of,
any kind of ellipsoid,
symmetric ellipsoid,
non-symmetric ellipsoid,
any kind of ellipsoid of that type,
would not have any,
a dipole moment.
Now,
why not?
Because the ellipsoid
is symmetric about every axis pass,
about every plane passing through the center.
If the charge was uniformly distributed on the ellipsoid,
there would be as much on
the top as on the bottom,
the left as on the right,
and there would be no dipole moment.
What would you say about it?
Would you say it was a sphere?
No.
You would say it has a quadrupole moment.
A quadrupole moment is the shape of a squashed sphere,
an ellipsoid.
It could also not even have a quadrupole moment,
it could have an octupole moment,
that's a little bit different kind of thing.
Uh,
an octupole moment would be free of dipole moment,
it would be free of quadrupole moment,
but it's not a sphere.
So,
in measuring the fact that,
uh,
the fact that an object
doesn't have an electric dipole moment
is not the evidence of
any kind that it's a sphere,
it's just an evidence that it
doesn't have an electric dipole moment,
nothing more than that.
But when you start to think about it,
in quantum mechanics there's something funny
about the notion of spherical symmetry and things like that.
Let's suppose we had this dumbbell.
But it's a quantum mechanical dumbbell.
There are quantum mechanical dumbbells.
Some of my,
uh,
some of my,
um,
colleagues are...
I didn't say that.
There's a quantum mechanical dumbbell.
It's a molecule of some kind,
a molecule with a bond that's more or less fixed
with two atoms,
okay,
two atoms on either side.
Um,
let's take the ground stat...
Now,
that doesn't look like a sphere.
It doesn't look anything like a sphere,
right?
In fact,
uh,
let's not worry about where
its charge is for a moment.
Um,
yeah,
we could put some charge.
Let's put some charge over here,
plus,
and charge over here,
minus.
Okay,
now let's take the ground state of that molecule.
There are two particles orbiting each other.
How do you describe a state of the molecule?
You describe the state of
the molecule by its angular momentum.
Angular momentum about the center.
All of the states of this molecule...
Well,
of course,
there are also vibrations,
but let's ignore the,
you know,
radial vibrations.
But let's only talk about the rotational states.
The rotational states are characterized by angular momentum.
In general,
if the molecule is a boson,
that means it has an
even number of fermions in it.
If it's a boson,
if the molecule has integer spin,
then the ground state will have what spin?
What angular momentum?
Zero.
Sure,
the lowest energy will be
when the angular momentum is zero.
But in quantum mechanics,
angular momentum is the generator of rotations.
What it says for a system to have angular momentum
zero is that its wave function is completely symmetric
with respect to all rotations.
Angular momentum zero states are all rotationally symmetric.
So quite independently of what
the charge distribution might look like,
the quantum mechanical state is rotationally symmetric.
Now,
you could say,
well,
that just means it's a dumbbell,
all right,
but it's just a dumbbell in a superposition of states.
So,
you could say,
well,
that's just a
which is,
um,
symmetrized so that the probability distribution
for the electric charge
is completely rotationally symmetric.
Does that have a dipole moment or doesn't it?
You call that having a dipole moment,
let's take a snapshot of it.
Let's not worry about quantum superpositions
and all that sort of stuff.
Let's take,
just take a quick snapshot of it.
Look,
even what I'm saying here would even be true
for the kind of dumbbell that
you would get in the gym.
If you really got it
down to the absolute ground state,
which you can never do,
of course,
the energy levels are so closely spaced,
but if you got it
down to the absolute ground state
in infinitely empty space,
that the wave function of that
dumbbell would be completely rotationally symmetric.
So,
now comes a question.
Do you,
are you willing to call that a sphere,
a spherical charge distribution,
or is it just a lopsided charge distribution
with a probability distribution or a wave function,
uh,
which has symmetrized it?
Okay,
the answer is ambiguous.
The answer is ambiguous depending on
the kind of experiment that you do.
If you took a sudden quick snapshot of it,
you would discover that it
has a lopsided charge distribution.
Right?
But you could ask,
how fast does the camera have to be
in order to detect that
it wasn't smeared over the sphere?
How fast,
what is the time resolution that's necessary?
And the answer is,
it's not too hard to figure out.
Let's suppose you took a quick snapshot of,
this is a measurement,
a snapshot means a measurement,
and basically the snapshot is measuring the angle
of the,
um,
of the molecule or the,
or the dumbbell.
You take a quick snapshot and you measure the angle.
Well,
if you measure the angle,
a measurement of something leaves the system
in an eigenstate of that something.
When you measure something,
you kick it into an eigenstate
of the thing you measured.
So,
it may have started in an eigenstate of angular momentum,
you measure it,
and all of a sudden it's in a state
of definite orientation.
Is a state of definite orientation,
does it have a definite angular momentum?
The analogous question would be,
for a particle which has a definite position,
does it have a definite momentum?
The answer is,
of course,
no.
That's the uncertainty principle.
And the same is true with angular momentum and angle.
If you measure the thing and
you kick it into a state
of a definite orientation,
you must have a definite angular momentum.
You must have given a kick to its angular momentum.
Same kind of Heisenberg story.
If you measure the position,
you give it a knock
and you influence its momentum.
If you measure the orientation of the molecule,
you affect its angular momentum.
But what if the spectrum of energy levels is such
that the first angular momentum excitation
is just more energy than you have available
in your photons that are doing the measuring?
What if the energy to the first excited rotational state
is gigantic for some reason?
Then your apparatus simply cannot resolve the orientation.
So it becomes a question,
given your apparatus,
what is the excitable?
How much energy does it take
to excite the first angular momentum state?
Now,
for a basketball or a dumbbell,
a real dumbbell,
the energy separation between the first state
and the second state is incredibly small.
You can figure it out yourself.
There's moment of inertia.
There's quantization of angular momentum.
You can figure it out.
But the separation of energy levels is incredibly small.
So it's not surprising that with an ordinary light,
you can measure the orientation of the dumbbell.
It doesn't take very much energy
to kick the dumbbell into a state of definite orientation.
But for a molecule,
the energy levels are somewhat spread.
The smaller the molecule,
if we go from molecules,
for example,
to mesons,
mesons are also dumbbells.
They've got two quarks.
They're also dumbbells.
The energy that it would take
to kick a meson into its first excited rotational state
is hundreds of millions of...
Yeah,
hundreds of millions of electron volts,
maybe a billion electron volts.
That's huge by comparison with any optical photon
that you would try to do an experiment with.
So,
if this were a meson,
you simply could not,
with ordinary experiments,
resolve the fact that it's lopsided
or that it's not a sphere.
All you would do is measure over and over again
the fact that on the average it's spherical,
that on the average,
the ground state wave function is spherical.
And you keep measuring it
and measuring it and measuring it,
and you're not going to
find out it's not a sphere
until you probe it with your own eyes.
But you can look at things which have enough energy
to be able to kick
it into a state like this.
So the question of whether a
thing is a sphere or not
is a little bit confusing.
The molecule is composed of two things
with a bridge between them like this.
It doesn't look like a sphere,
but on the other hand,
the quantum mechanical wave function sphericalizes it.
Okay.
Ordinary particles,
if they are bosons in their ground states,
typically have zero angular momentum,
look as spherical as it's possible to be
if they are bosons.
But if they're fermions,
then they have half spin.
They can't have angular momentum zero.
If they don't have angular momentum zero,
it means they're not rotationally symmetric.
This has nothing to do
with how the charge is distributed.
It's just a fact that
half spin particles have an axis.
They have a spin axis.
You can measure their spin along an axis.
They're definitely not spherical.
They definitely have a spin axis.
So,
quite independently of any measurement
that's done about electric dipole moments,
the electron is not a sphere.
The electron has a spin.
Or it's not spherically symmetric.
It has an axis.
The axis is the spin axis.
You have the spin axis.
And about that spin axis,
you can imagine a little current.
There's a little electric current
that goes around the spin axis.
This is a little model for
the magnetic moment of the electron.
You can think of it as having a spin axis,
carrying charge around,
forming a current.
And that current makes it a little electromagnet.
Okay,
so it has a magnetic moment.
Definitely not spherical.
And that should be the end of the story
about whether an electron is a sphere or not.
But what did they measure?
Okay,
so once you know
that the electron has an orientation like that,
and the orientation can be defined
by the direction of its magnetic moment,
then you can ask,
relative to that direction,
is there a charge imbalance?
Is there more charge on the,
let's call this the north,
and let's call this the south.
It's a little magnet.
It's also got electric charge.
You can ask what the electric charge distribution
is if the electron is
put into a definite spin state.
For example,
up.
Well,
I didn't draw up.
I did some other one here.
So we could ask,
is there a little bit of excess
positive charge at the north pole
and negative charge at the south pole?
Of course,
the overall electron is not neutral.
It's negatively charged.
But on top of that,
is there a displacement
of the center of charge relative to the axis,
along the axis of the north-south orientation of the magnet?
So what we're talking about is a correlation,
a correlation between the electric charge displacement
and the magnetic direction.
That's the thing that would be called
the electric dipole moment of the electron.
If you orient the magnetic properties of the electron,
the magnetic dipole,
or just the spin along some axis,
then is there an electric dipole moment along that axis?
And that's a good question.
That means something.
That's measurable.
Okay.
Any questions about that?
Are you interested?
I mean,
I'll go on a little more about what the experiment...
Yeah.
So wouldn't that violate charge quantization?
No.
Why charge quantization?
I guess I think of it in terms of
you either have a fixed charge or you don't.
There's no freedom to spread the charge about.
If the charge were just a
little bit displaced toward the north pole,
it would have a dipole moment.
That's all it would take.
Just displace it a little bit.
Whether you smear it or not,
all it would take is a little displacement.
And so aren't electric dipole moments forbidden
by quantum field theory?
No.
If they were,
nobody would be looking for them.
They are forbidden by certain symmetries.
Okay?
So let's talk about the symmetries which forbid...
which would forbid electric dipole moment.
Okay.
The first symmetry that would forbid electric dipole moment
is reflection symmetry.
Reflection in a plane.
Now,
let us suppose for a moment
that the world and the laws of physics
were really reflection invariant.
In other words,
every mirror image
is a possible solution of the equations of a system.
And let's suppose there's only one electron.
Well,
if the mirror image of an electron
has to be another possible solution of the theory,
okay,
and if there's only one electron,
meaning to say one species of electron,
then the mirror image must be exactly the same
as the original electron itself.
There's only one electron,
and it must be its own mirror image.
Okay.
So now let's talk about this thing here.
Let's think about it.
Let's put a mirror over here.
Can you see where the mirror is?
Okay.
We could also think about it.
Yeah,
let's think about the blackboard as the mirror.
And let's look into the blackboard.
The traditional way of drawing a magnetic field
into the blackboard
is to put some tail feathers sticking out.
So that's the tail end of the...
And that means that the
current is going around this way.
And we're asking,
is there an in-out
image of the blackboard?
Okay,то
is a maligghand thing.
But
here we have a very efficient type
of magnetic field.
And
the first right represented is
this blackboard.
And
we're going to put the color,
North Pole.
You think it's here,
don't you?
The mirror image is here again.
Okay,
why is that?
It's because the real thing
that's going on that gives the
North Pole—this is an electromagnet—the real
physical phenomena that's going on
is not oriented along here.
It's the current
going around in the loop.
The current going around in the loop here is the
real thing which is creating the magnetic field.
The real phenomenon of
magnetism is associated with loop-like currents.
Now,
let's suppose we have a
loop-like positive current going around this way.
What's the mirror image of it?
It's a loop-like current going
around in exactly the same way.
So the mirror image
up here has a loop going around the same way.
The same way this does,
and therefore the mirror image
of a magnet is a magnet
pointing in the same direction.
Okay,
now let's also suppose that there was some
charge imbalance,
and let's suppose that the charge imbalance of this electron
over here was displaced up
toward the head of the arrow.
Where would that be?
Where would the charge displacement of this one be?
Now just think mirror image.
Don't think about north-south,
think mirror image.
I have a
thing with a charge displaced toward the mirror.
What's the mirror image going to be?
Toward the mirror.
So the charge displacement is going to be down here.
But now we have an electron
which is different than this one.
Its north-south is correlated in a
different way with its electric dipole moment.
This one has an electric dipole moment that's along...
that's matched in the same direction as the magnetic moment.
This one has an electric
dipole moment in the opposite direction.
If all electrons are the same,
in other words,
if there's only one kind of electron
and if mirror symmetry is a good symmetry,
if it's a good symmetry,
and if it's a mirror symmetry,
then it's a good symmetry.
If the world is really symmetric,
in other words,
if everything which exists its mirror
image can also exist,
but there's only one electron
and there's only one conclusion,
this charge cannot be displaced from the center.
It must be at the center so
that the mirror images have the same property.
That's the only way that the electron charge
can be distributed if you have mirror image
symmetry,
parity symmetry,
it's called,
reflection symmetry,
all the same thing.
In other words,
if the world is such that
the laws of physics don't distinguish between
left hand and right hand.
Okay,
now the laws of physics do
distinguish between left hand and right hand.
We know,
for example,
there are left hand and right hand.
There are neutrinos,
there are only right handed anti-neutrinos.
Left and right are not the same,
they're correlated with,
and reflection symmetry is not a good
symmetry of physics.
So that sounds like it opens up
the possibility of an electron dipole moment.
It sounds like once you admit that the
world is not symmetric with respect to reflection
symmetry,
then there's no reason why the...
The electron may not have a dipole moment.
However,
there's another symmetry which works in a very similar way,
which is a much more
accurate symmetry.
Reflection symmetry in particle physics is bad.
It's not even approximately right in the weak interactions.
It's broken as bad as it could be.
There's another symmetry and it's time reversal.
It's simply the same as the statement
that if you take a movie of a...
Okay.
...thing and you run it backward,
that that's another solution of the theory.
Now that may or may not be a symmetry.
It may or may not be,
but let's suppose that it is.
Let's suppose that reversing the film is a symmetry.
First question is,
what happens to the...
Now we're not reflecting in a mirror,
we're just reflecting in time.
So let's put another...
Another electron over here.
What happens under time reversal
to the north-south magnetic moment?
Switch.
Switches.
Why?
Because if a positive current is going around
this way and you run the film backward,
the
positive current is going the other way.
What happens to the position of the electric
charge along here if you run it backward?
Nothing.
Running it backward doesn't move the electric charge.
So when you time reverse it,
the north pole gets down here,
the south pole gets up here,
but the electric charge,
if it were displaced,
would be displaced toward the south pole here
and toward the north pole here.
And so again,
you would find out that if time symmetry,
time reversal symmetry were a good symmetry,
you could not have the electron having a dipole moment.
If there was only one electron and it
looks exactly the same as its time reversal,
then the charge has to be right at the
center because the time reversal interchanges north and south.
In other words,
it just turns this thing over,
but it doesn't move the charge.
Yeah.
So like...
Currents and charges have to be...
Reverse?
Have to be what?
Are reversed by time reversing?
No.
Currents are,
not charges.
Charges are reversed by C.
Doesn't nonrelativistic quantum mechanics already not
time reversible because the operator is antiunitary?
Yes,
but it's time reversible because it's antiunitary.
It's time reversible.
Wouldn't all of this whole discussion be based
upon the fact that electrons have a volume,
it's not a point particle?
No,
no.
We're just asking whether...
Okay.
You don't have to...
If you want to know whether
it has an electric dipole moment,
what's the experiment you do?
We now have...
Okay.
We put the electron into a magnetic field.
And...
No,
we don't put the electron in a magnetic field.
We want to know whether the
electron has an electric dipole moment.
How do we find out if
it has a magnetic dipole moment?
You put it in a magnetic field and you see
whether the two orientations of the electron have different energy.
Okay.
You do the same thing with an electric field.
You put the electron in an electric field and you see if the two
orientations of the spin of the electron have different energy because of the electric field.
I mean,
that's a very easy way to do it,
except that's much too hard experimentally.
It's trickier than that.
But that's the basic experiment.
Okay.
So,
time reversal would be enough to tell you
that the electron can't have a dipole moment.
Okay.
But is time reversal a real symmetry of nature?
The answer is no.
Again,
in particle physics,
we know that time reversal is not a good symmetry.
There are processes,
even in the standard model,
which violate time reversal symmetry.
But the magnitude of the effects are very,
very,
very tiny.
The magnitudes of the effect...
We understand where time reversal is.
Time reversal asymmetry comes from the standard model.
You can then do a calculation in the
standard model of the allowable value of the electron
dipole moment.
And it's far too small to be experimentally detected.
So,
it's never been experimentally detected.
And if the standard model is right,
I don't know if it'll ever be detected,
but it'd be
very hard to detect.
They didn't detect it.
They detected no dipole moment.
That's good for the standard model.
The only thing is that most
people don't believe in the standard model.
They think that the standard model
has to be corrected by additional particles,
by supersymmetry,
by new interactions,
by new corrupting influences,
which potentially could break the time reversal
symmetry much worse.
So,
the fact that the electron
is discovered from non-dipole moment,
which is a very,
very
important factor in the electron's life,
is not an indication that it's a sphere.
It's an indication it doesn't
have an electric dipole moment.
And it makes it that much harder
to introduce things that change the standard model.
The standard model at the
moment describes everything we know.
This was an experiment to
try to find the dipole moment.
It was to try to detect an
effect that the standard model would not have,
could not have.
Basically,
it's unallowed.
It's allowed,
but it's at such a level,
at a computable level,
which is much too small.
So,
the result is that this experiment makes it
even harder to believe in this or that
modification of the standard model.
What was the context of the experiment?
Was it a material body or a material object?
Was it a high energy physics experiment?
No,
no,
no.
It's a tabletop experiment involving
electrons and magnetic fields and...
With solid objects.
Yeah.
Electrons and magnetic fields.
I don't know exactly what the experiment is.
I mean,
ordinarily,
you take an electron and you put it
in a field and you let it process
around the field,
but for many,
many processions...
Is it more near the
sensitivity to compare with the number?
No.
But it had enough sensitivity.
It had enough sensitivity to compare with
the modifications of the standard model that
people would like to see.
Right.
So,
it's kind of interesting.
I always love reading the commentary that
people write in and how confused they can
be about what...
Yeah,
somebody wrote in saying,
well,
this really proves that the standard model is garbage.
And we should give it up.
Well,
exactly the opposite.
It's...
Anyway,
I don't know how I got on that.
So,
does that result...
Hmm?
Does that result constrained in an
interesting way which modifications are potentially viable?
I don't know.
You know,
I haven't followed that kind of thing in great detail.
Somebody like Savas Damopoulos,
who wrote a book called The
Paraclassical Model,
could probably tell you,
well,
that cuts the parameter space down
by 72.1%.
And...
But,
you know,
any experiment which insists on
giving results which are consistent with
the standard model to high precision make
it that much harder to modify it.
So...
Right.
I just got a quick question.
Is time reversal symmetry and
conservation of information somewhat related,
or...?
No,
time reversal symmetry...
You always have in physics a symmetry called CPT.
That's the combination of time reversal,
change the charges,
change the sign of the charge,
and reflect in a mirror.
All three of those simultaneously is a symmetry.
Always.
Has to be.
And that's enough to ensure that...
In fact,
you don't even need that
to ensure that information is conserved.
No.
You can...
There are systems,
very familiar systems,
which are not time reversal invariant,
just
an electron in a magnetic field.
An electron in a magnetic field goes in circular orbits,
and those circular orbits go one way
or the other,
depending on the sign of the magnetic field.
So if you stick in a definite magnetic field,
the mathematical structure of the theory
is not time reversal invariant,
but it's a perfectly good quantum mechanical system.
So just a particle in a magnetic field,
the mathematical structure of the Schrodinger equation
is not time reversal invariant.
If you knew what the magnetic field was,
and somebody showed you a movie of the Olympic
Games,
and you saw the electron moving,
you could tell instantly whether it was a movie
or an anti-movie,
meaning to say that it
was going backward rather than forward.
But,
of course,
that's only because you didn't time reverse everything.
What did that experiment...
The experiment I just described,
electron in a magnetic field,
and it goes in one direction.
What did I fail to not time reverse?
The magnetic field.
If I was really doing the full-blown time reversal symmetry,
I would also have to change
the sign of a magnetic field.
Yeah.
Okay,
I'm sorry,
I don't know how I got on all of that.
It was not my intention to...
I'm just rambling.
It's called old age.
Let's stop for a few minutes,
and then we'll get back
to second quantization and all that
stuff.
Mostly I wanted a rest
from doing mathematics on the blackboard.
Okay,
we were doing second quantization,
and I thought I would...
I thought I would...
I thought I would tell you a few
things about it that I haven't mentioned so far,
in no
particular order,
but some of the physical consequences of it.
The first...
First thing is,
somebody asked me whether the field operators and so forth,
how they're
connected with Fourier transforms,
so I thought I would tell
you to begin with exactly what
the connection with Fourier transforms is.
It's very simple.
If you remember,
in ordinary quantum mechanics,
you have wave functions,
and the squares of
the wave functions are probabilities
to find particles at different places.
You can Fourier transform the wave function,
and the Fourier transform is the wave function
in the momentum basis.
So while...
So I have a particle,
psi of x...
This is not the field operator,
this is little psi.
Little psi is the wave function for a single particle.
Psi of x is the wave function,
and psi star of psi is the probability.
Probability of what?
Probability to find the particle at position x.
P of x.
Probability of x.
Now,
supposing I want to work in the momentum basis,
the momentum basis tells me what the
amplitude for the momentum to have a certain value,
and if I square it,
it gives me the
probability to have a certain momentum.
So that's a thing that's called...
I think we probably called it psi...
Um...
Did we call it psi twiddle?
We did.
Psi twiddle of p.
The twiddle is just to make another symbol.
Psi twiddle of p,
where p is the momentum,
that's a thing which when you square it,
is
the probability,
but not the probability for the
particle to have a certain position,
but
the probability to have momentum p.
This p and this p are different.
One is probability,
one is momentum.
Okay,
what's the connection between psi of
x and psi twiddle of p?
They're Fourier conjugates of each other,
or Fourier transforms of each other.
So let's write that down.
Let's come over here.
Psi twiddle of p is
equal to the integral over x...
e to the minus i px.
That's the Fourier transform.
It's a function of p,
not x,
because x has been integrated over.
And the marvelous thing is that
you can go back and forth.
If you know what psi p is,
then you can reconstruct what psi of x is.
And so psi of x is equal to
the integral dp over square root of 2 pi.
Psi twiddle of p.
Only difference,
e to the plus i px.
And that's Fourier's theorem.
That's Fourier's theorem relating
functions and their Fourier transforms.
Now it has a physical significance,
and the physical significance is in terms of
probabilities or wave functions for momentum and position.
Okay.
Now,
let's go now to second quantization theory,
where we have not a wave function for a particle,
but a field operation.
So let's go back to the field operator.
Creation and annihilation operators...
I'm not going to prove a lot of stuff tonight.
I'm going to tell you facts,
but they're facts which are pretty darn reasonable,
and you can reconstruct them from what we said.
Okay,
so let's go back to
the definition of the field operator.
Now it's a field operator,
capital Psi of x.
And it was originally here.
Now,
let's look at the definition of the field operator.
So we can write a sum over
all the energy eigenvectors of a system,
of creation operators.
This one would be,
let's see,
this is the annihilation operator.
Let's call it Psi minus.
A minus of i times Psi i of x,
where this Psi i of x over here
is just the ordinary wave function of a particle
with state I.
Okay,
we went through that a couple of times.
Now what if we were dealing with the case
of a free particle on an infinite axis,
or infinite whatever the dimensionality of space is,
a free particle whose energy eigenstates are what?
Just a particle moving in empty space.
What are the energy eigenstates of a free particle?
Well,
you can begin by asking what's
the Hamiltonian,
and the Hamiltonian is p squared over 2m.
So the eigenstates of energy are likely
to be eigenstates of momentum.
If you know the momentum,
then you know the energy.
What are the
eigenstates,
or what are the wave
functions of the eigenstates of momentum?
They're e to the i p x.
Okay,
so if we were to go
to the case of a free particle,
the psi i's of x would be
e to the i p x.
Well,
this i is different than this i.
This i is the square
root of minus 1 over here.
This i is an integer.
What happened to the integer here?
Where's the integer labeling the momentum eigenstates?
There is no integer.
All there is is the momentum.
The momentum states are labeled by momentum.
Momentum is not an integer.
It's a continuous variable that goes from
minus infinity to the i p x.
delta of x is the sum of there and
it's e to the number of re'th's of i's.
independence x.
vérith's is delta of x.
reaction time is b plus times h,
plus of b x plus Mana
precip 보니까.
But now the new solution
comes out as subtraction from infinity.
This'll just say pas Jonas proof to
be P times..
So this,
when minus infinity is proved,
this normalization,
is going to result in
of momentum p.
This object here removes a particle of
momentum p in the same way that
A minus removes a particle in the state I.
So if you have a state with lots of particles
in it,
and there are among other things particles of momentum p,
if you act with A minus,
it
removes one particle of momentum p.
What if there is no particle of momentum p there?
What does it do?
It just annihilates the state in
the same way that annihilation operators
or lowering operators annihilate
states with nothing in them.
So that's psi of x,
the field
operator.
And for good measure,
it's a matter of definition,
we put a square root of 2 pi
there.
Just to make it look like
um
I like this equation here.
So it looks awfully much like
A minus of p in the mathematical
connection here is playing the same
role as psi twiddle of p here.
Okay.
All we've done is replace sums by integrals
with i
i by the momentum of the particle,
and we now
have the notion of a,
um,
of an annihilation operator for a particle of momentum p.
Now
remember what psi of x did itself?
Not what,
not what these creation operators here did,
but what did psi of x do when it
acts on a,
um.
When it acts on a,
um on the vacuum for example?
Sorry.Oh.
I want the creation piece.
It's I plus.
Same thing,
except A plus here.
With E to the minus I PX.
My knee is going.
Okay,
so what does Psi plus do?
It creates a particle.
It's got a bunch of creation operators in it.
And what kind of particle does it create?
A particle at position X.
That's what Psi plus of X is.
What do you think that A plus of P does?
It creates a particle with momentum P.
So it's clear that Psi plus and Psi minus...
You can invert this equation.
You can,
for example,
write that A minus of P
is equal to integral
dx
field operator Psi of X
times E to the minus I PX
again over square root of pi to pi.
In other words,
you can do the same manipulation
as you do with Fourier's theorem.
You can prove it.
You can prove one thing follows from the other.
And what it says is
that there's a mathematical correspondence
or similarity between wave functions
in position and momentum space
and creation and annihilation
operators for particles at positions
or particles with given momentum.
The A minus of P
is essentially the Fourier is analogous.
I could have done that.
I could have called this here A of P.
I could have called this A of P.
Just redefine instead of Psi twiddle.
And then these formulas would look very similar.
They would look identical.
But all this is saying is that
the relationship between creation and annihilation operators
for positions and momentums,
creating a particle at a given position,
that's done with Psi of X.
Creating a particle...
Is this right?
Yeah.
Let's do the creation part.
Plus,
I think it's this way.
The creation operators for particles
of given position and given momentum
are Fourier conjugates of each other.
So that's one fact about second quantization.
And keep in mind,
these are not wave functions now.
These are operators that operate
to create and remove particles.
Psi is the field operator
for a particular kind of function.
So if you have a particular kind of particle,
if there are several different
kinds of particles in the system,
then you have to have
several different kinds of field operators.
There's a field operator for each kind of particle.
Okay,
so that's one fact.
That's one fact.
Second fact,
and I'm going to quote some facts now without proof,
but they're all things that
you can prove from the definitions.
And they're straightforward.
Okay,
let's come back to the,
let's use the A plus Is
instead of momentum states.
Here's something that we wrote down
for creation and annihilation operators.
I.
Do you remember what the commutator
of A plus I was?
What A plus with A minus is?
Delta Ij.
What about A minus with A minus?
For any i and j?
Zero.
What about A plus with A plus?
These are the only commutators
which are non-zero.
Well,
I could ask a different question.
I could ask instead,
what are the
commutators of size of x
at different positions?
Instead of asking
what are the commutation relations
between the creation operators
and annihilation operators
in the basis i and j,
I could ask what is
the commutator of the creation operator
for a particle at point x
with the annihilation operator
at point y?
You're right.
That's right.
But how would you prove it?
You would prove it by simply sticking in
the definition
of the size
in terms of the creation and annihilation operators
and then using
the commutation relations of the creation
and annihilation operators.
And what you would find
is exactly what was just said.
It's just delta of x minus y.
In other words,
they commute
when the points are not
the same,
and they don't
commute,
and they're a very big
non-commutator.
Remember,
a delta function has the property that it's
infinite when x is equal to y.
So,
the commutators
of size,
psi plus and psi minus,
have this delta function in them.
What about psi plus with psi plus?
That's just made out of creation operators
and all creation operators commute.
Likewise for
psi minus.
So the only things which don't commute
are psi plus with psi minus.
Now,
we could
we've mentioned
several times,
I think,
that the
size,
because they're complex,
because they're not Hermitian,
they're not
observables.
This is true,
but it's
not a very interesting point,
because
the sum of psi plus
with psi minus is an observable,
and the differences times
i are observables.
So,
let's,
this is
not a particularly interesting
fact.
Uh,
yeah?
I'm just curious,
what does that mean when x equals y?
It means that it's very large.
Everywhere?
No,
yeah,
for any x,
whenever x is equal to y,
it's large.
No,
no,
suppose you put in
Oh,
okay,
I see.
Yeah,
okay.
Now,
let's ignore the fact that
for the moment that these are
not observables.
The real and imaginary parts
are observables,
and
what's true is the commutator of
the real part with the imaginary
part is also a delta function
like this.
The point is the delta function,
and
it's not so interesting
that these things are not Hermitian.
You can always make them Hermitian by adding
real and imaginary parts.
Okay,
so what does this say?
What is the consequence of two
things not commuting?
You know any examples of
operators which don't commute?
X and P,
right?
X and P are the
standard examples of operators
that don't commute.
X and P,
the commutator is I h-bar.
How about
sigma,
you know,
the
x component of a spin and the
y component of a spin?
They don't commute either.
The commutator is the z component of a spin.
What's the physical
significance of not commuting
as far as doing measurements
is concerned?
You can't
do simultaneous
measurements of the same thing.
Or another way of saying it is the measurement
of one of them gives a
kick to the other one.
Trying to measure with precision
the position of a particle
necessarily gives it a hard
kick and
destroys the
measurement of the momentum
or makes the measurement of the momentum
very uncertain.
Measuring a momentum
very precisely spreads the position
all over the place.
But let's just say
that it introduces mutual
uncertainty.
Mutual
uncertainty of the kind,
the Heisenberg
kind,
where measuring one
thing interferes with the measurement
of another thing.
Alright,
now this is a very interesting
fact here.
Let's
forget for the moment
the delta function when x is equal to
y.
Let's talk about when
x does not equal y.
When x does not equal y,
it says that these things commute.
This is very,
very plausible.
It says that the measurement of a field
over here does not interfere
with the measurement of a field over here.
If I measure the
electric field,
this could be
the electromagnetic field.
It's a little bit different and we're going to
come to it,
but if we get time.
But it's a field.
What this says is measuring
the field at one place does not interfere
with measuring the field at another place.
You can measure a
field over here and here simultaneously
and there's no mutual
uncertainty in them.
No.
When you get right on top of each other,
then
measuring the
real and imaginary parts
you can replace
this here commutator by
the real part
and the imaginary part.
Do not commute.
Measuring the real part
and the imaginary part,
these two observables,
you cannot
measure them simultaneously
at the same point.
And
they interfere with each other.
Trying to measure one gives an enormous
wallop to the other one.
And that's
of course interesting.
It's telling us something
important.
But the more
important thing right now
is that you don't have any
interference in measurements if they're
at different places.
And of course
that's very logical.
I mean
that makes sense.
Particularly,
we're not doing
relativity theory now.
We're not doing relativity theory,
but imagine that we were.
The same
basic principle is true in relativity
theory.
Supposing
it were true that making
a measurement over here
interfered with and did something
over here at the same instant of
time to the possibility
of making a measurement at a
distant point.
Supposing
this commutator were not zero.
In fact,
let's suppose the commutator
were big for some reason.
That the commutator of a field
over here and here were big.
What that would
say is trying to measure the field over here
gives the field a kick over here.
Makes it impossible to
measure it because it gives it a kick over here.
Well,
I think that would violate
your sense of
causality or your sense of
mentality that
Einstein tells us
that signals should not
propagate faster than the speed of light.
Somebody over here trying to
measure the field and finding
that he can't do it because it's not commuting
with something over here
violates some notion
of independence
of measurements at different places.
In particular,
if we take two places
in times which are such that
light could not go from one to the other,
they're space-like separated from each other,
then we would
be in a very confusing situation
where measuring a thing over here
and a thing over here wouldn't commute,
would interfere with each other,
and that seems
to violate the spirit of
information
or perturbations
or signals
or
effects
do not propagate faster
than the speed of light.
And that's true.
Isn't that what EPR experiments already
show?
That what?
That the effect of a measurement over
here has a
consequence for a measurement over there.
Oh boy.
No.
What?
The most
fundamental thing about
entanglement is it does not tell you
that making a measurement over here
has an influence over here.
Well,
I didn't say influence,
I said
correlation.
Yeah,
I know,
but we're talking
about influence.
We're talking about making a measurement over here
giving a sudden kick to something over here.
That's exactly what doesn't
happen where,
because
of entanglement.
Measuring
something over here does not give a thing
a kick over here because of entanglement.
It can only give a kick over here
and the reason why
is because things at one place commute
with things at another place.
That's exactly the reason
why entanglement
doesn't
send influence as fast as the speed
of light because all the degrees
of freedom at one point commute
with the degrees of freedom of someplace
else and that means they behave
independently.
Correlation is different than
influence.
So what this says,
this is good,
this says that there's no violation
of your
naive ideas,
or maybe they're not so
naive,
but your straightforward ideas
about the independence
of measurements
at different points of space.
Now,
of course,
we're not doing
relativity,
but nevertheless
it's still a true thing here.
We're going to come next time to
fermions.
Fermions are fields
or fermions are particles
which do not satisfy
any of this.
In fact,
they satisfy a different
algebra with anti-commutators.
We're going to work that out
and why it's true,
but
the one thing it says,
and anti-commutators don't have
to do with independent of
measurements.
It's the commutators.
Commutators tell you that things are
independent and measurements are independent.
Fermions,
the fields,
anti-commute at different
points.
They don't commute.
If they don't commute,
that means you can't
measure them simultaneously at two different
points,
no matter how far away.
A measurement of a
fermion field at one place
gives a sudden kick
to its complex conjugate
arbitrarily far away.
That sounds
crazy.
Or,
fermion
fields are not observables.
There's no way that you can construct
what it's telling you,
really.
There's no way that you can construct it
as a device to measure a fermion field.
Why?
Because that device would have to be spread
all over space and be extremely
non-local.
That's what we're going to take up next time.
Fermion operators
are the operators which create and
annihilate electrons.
Boson operators
are the operators which create and annihilate
photons.
So we'll come next time
to the fermion version
of second quantization.
Okay.
And do that.
Okay,
good.
I'm thankful that nobody forced
me into doing any mathematics tonight.
Well,
we did a little bit.
For more,
please visit
us at stanford.edu.