Stanford University
We were waist deep into the Dirac land, the Dirac Sea.
Well, we didn't get to the Dirac Sea yet.
But before we continue with the three-dimensional,
before I'll do a little review of the Dirac equation that we studied,
and then we'll go into the three-dimensional version,
three-space, one-time dimension, it's a real world Dirac equation.
But before we do, let's go back and review, not review,
generalize what we said about second quantization, the field theory,
the fields governing multiple particle systems.
We made them out of creation and annihilation operators.
What's the difference between fermions and bosons in that respect?
And the difference is simple, not so intuitive, but rather straightforward.
If you have two bosons, you can put them into the same state, number one.
And, no, no problem.
Okay.
So, I'm putting them into the same state.
And what's more, the creation and annihilation operators all commute with each other.
Nothing particularly odd about things which commute with each other.
There is something very odd about things which anticommute with each other.
So, let's talk about anticommutation.
Supposing we have two particles, and we want to say that when we interchange them,
that the wave function or the state vector should change sign.
So, let's think about what that would mean for these operators that we're constructing.
A particle at x and another particle at y.
Particle one now stands for which slot?
This is slot one.
This is slot two.
This stands for particle one.
This stands for particle two.
X stands for the position of particle one.
Y stands for the position of particle two.
Neither x nor y refers to the x and y coordinates.
X and y are each, if you like, three-dimensional positions or one-dimensional positions, depending on the context.
That's a state with two particles, one at x and one at y.
For both, the state vector is the same.
It's the same.
For bosons, this is exactly the same thing as putting particle one at position y and particle two at position x.
They're equal to each other.
So, in particular, that would tell you, how do you make a particle at x and particle y?
You take psi of x times psi of y.
A creation.
This should be creation operators.
A creation operator for a particle at x, a particle at y, and you hammer on the vacuum.
You let them act on the vacuum, and that creates particle at x and y.
Supposing I want to interchange particle x and, or the two particles.
That's just interchanging x and y.
That would be, sorry, dagger at y.
Psi dagger at x.
Also vacuum.
Good.
Now, why is this true?
It's true because the psi's commute with each other.
You can interchange them.
This and this are related very simply by interchanging the two operators here.
And if they commute, that just says that psi dagger at x is a vacuum.
That just says that psi dagger of x times psi dagger of y is the same as psi dagger of y times psi dagger of x.
And so it's guaranteed that with the objects and the theories that we've been making up till now,
that they satisfy this kind of Bose statistics, this kind of Boson rules.
Now, for fermions, the rule is exactly the same, but with a minus sign.
Remember that the state vector of a system is the same as the state vector of a system.
Remember that the state vector of a system, the real physical observable state vector of a system,
doesn't care about the sign here.
But in keeping track of the formulas, it's important to know that for fermions,
if you interchange the two particles, you get a minus sign.
That must mean that for fermions, if psi here is representing fermions,
that this is the top equation here.
The top formula is minus the bottom formula.
And the mathematics that goes with this is just a statement that for fermions,
the fields anti-commute.
So let's write out what that means.
It means psi dagger of x times psi dagger of y equals minus this over here.
But let's shift it to the left-hand side and write that plus.
Plus psi dagger of y, psi dagger of x equals zero.
This object, if you take two operators, and you take their product,
and instead of subtracting in the opposite order, you add in the opposite order,
that's called the anti-commutator.
And it's written, instead of a square bracket, instead of a square commutator,
usually written with a curly bracket,
psi dagger of x, psi dagger of y equals zero.
In general, when you go from fermions to both,
you just take every commutation relation and replace it by an anti-commutation relation.
And that's how you go from fermions to bosons.
Now that has, let's see, is there anything else?
Yeah.
First of all, it's quite clear that you can't have two particles in the same state.
For example, supposing you wanted to put two particles at the same point.
You want to put two particles at the same point.
That corresponds to...
Let's get rid of this over here.
That corresponds to acting with creation operators at the same point.
But, this equation over here, or let's say this one over here,
that tells us that psi dagger of x,
psi dagger of x,
times psi of x,
plus psi dagger of x,
times psi dagger of x,
that's the anti-commutator of psi dagger of x with itself.
I've just replaced y by x,
and the statement here is that that should be equal to zero.
Well, this operator and this operator are exactly the same.
This is just twice psi dagger of x times psi dagger of x equals zero.
And if something is equal to...
If twice something is equal to zero,
the thing itself is equal to zero.
So, trying to put two particles into the same state always gives you zero.
Anti-commutators take...
Anti-commutators give you fermions, which cannot go in the same state.
There's an interesting peculiarity here.
For bosons...
For bosons, there's a clear mathematical distinction
between creation operators and annihilation operators.
Um...
Even if you didn't know what...
what the devil these things stood for,
when you write out the commutation,
we don't... we have no idea what these things stand for.
We just know that there's this algebraic structure
that some kind of creation...
some sort of object...
Let's not put daggers on for now.
It doesn't matter. Daggers or no daggers.
Some sort of objects...
Commute.
These things commute.
No. I'm sorry.
I wanted to take...
Side dagger equals one.
Here we are.
This way.
Equals one.
That's a harmonic oscillator.
Or it could just be a creation and annihilation operator for a boson.
Okay?
Could you mistake which one is the boson operator...
which one is the creation operator
and which one is the annihilation operator?
Well, if you try to switch them,
if you try to replace A by A dagger,
and A dagger by A,
this is very definitely not equal to one.
In fact, what is it equal to?
Minus one, right?
Combinator.
Commutator.
If you switch the two things,
the commutator changes.
This is minus one.
And you could always tell,
even if I didn't label these as A and A dagger,
if I just labeled them as A and B
and asked you which one is the creation operator
and which one is the annihilation operator,
what you do is you look at the commutators,
and if the commutator is plus one,
then the first one here is the creation operator
and the second one is the annihilation operator.
There's no way to make a mistake.
So...
And in fact,
creation operators and annihilation operators
are fundamentally different.
Here's the stack of all possible states.
N equals zero.
N equals one.
N equals two.
Creation operators, just mathematically,
creation operators do not annihilate any state.
They just take you up the ladder.
And since the ladder never ends,
a creation operator
never runs out.
And that runs into the problem
that an annihilation operator does
if it annihilates too many times.
Annihilation operators,
when they get down to the bottom,
they give zero.
Another way to say it
is that this spectrum of N
going from zero to infinity
is not the same if you turn it upside down.
You can go up to infinity,
but you can't go down past zero.
Okay, what about fermions?
Well, now you look at the fermion operators.
They also have creation and annihilation operators.
The difference, though,
is that you have anti-commutation relations
for fermions.
You also have creation operators.
You can create a fermion
plus one.
Anti-commutators are the same
if you interchange.
Why?
Because this is a a dagger
plus a dagger a.
It doesn't matter
which order they're in.
So just from the mathematical structure,
from the algebra,
there's no difference between creation operators.
It's true, they do different things,
but just looking at the algebra of them,
you can't tell the creation operators
from the annihilation operators.
And another way of seeing it,
is just to look at the possible
possible
occupation numbers
of a fermion.
Let's say it's a fermion with only one state.
Fermion is in the ground state
of the hydrogen atom.
Okay, what can you have?
The answer is you either have no particle
or you have one particle.
You can't have any more than one,
and you can't have any fewer than one.
And you can't have any fewer than zero.
What does the creation operator do?
It takes you from zero to one.
But what does it do when it hits one?
Nuh-uh, no state there.
Annihilates the state, right, zero.
On the other hand,
the annihilation operator takes you down.
If there's a particle there, sure enough,
it can take you down,
but if there's no particle there,
end of story, you annihilate the state.
So there's a complete difference.
So there's a complete symmetry
between being empty and being filled
and replace creation operators
by annihilation operators.
Now, that doesn't mean they're physically the same.
It just means the algebra and the mathematics,
the symbols, you can't tell one from the other.
Yes, question?
I had a question back when you were saying
if you try to have two fermions in the same place,
you'd have side dagger, side dagger, x equals zero.
Why is that?
Why is that a contradiction or why is that not?
It's not a contradiction.
It just gives zero.
It doesn't give a state.
A state, a zero state is nothing.
So, but that, I'm just curious,
that's, so that's, that operator's squared, essentially, right?
Side dagger is squared, yeah.
Yeah.
If side, if you have an operator squared,
does that mean the operator is zero?
No, it means the operator's squared is zero.
No, no.
Look, here's a creation operator.
The creation operator squared,
there's nothing up here for it to give.
So it gives zero.
If you take the creation, for fermion,
for fermion, if you take the creation operator squared,
it's zero, there's nobody here.
If you take the annihilation operator squared, it's zero.
On the other hand, for bosons,
there is not this symmetry of filled and empty.
It's filled.
It's the symmetry of filled and empty,
two possible states and only two possible states
and no, um, for a single state of a fermion.
All right, that's going to play a role.
We'll get back to it.
What it says is that in some sense,
just pure mathematical sense,
you can interchange creation and annihilation operators.
Now, you may not want to do that
because they have physical significance,
but just as a, as a symbol,
but just as the algebraic structure of them,
you can interchange them.
Okay, let's come back now to the Dirac equation,
the wonderful Dirac equation,
and let's pursue it.
Various things we want to understand.
We already figured out how to deal with the fact
that the simplest Dirac equation that we wrote down
doesn't have the possibility of having a mass.
Let's just go back through it.
The simplest thing was just to write an equation
which was d by dt of psi,
let's put an i there,
i psi equals minus i d by dx psi.
This was for the case of one dimension.
Now, this psi here is some,
this is the wave,
is a, is let's say a wave function for a single particle.
For the moment, we're just doing single particles,
one particle.
This would be the Schrodinger equation for,
this would be the Hamiltonian over here.
This would be the Hamiltonian acting on psi
is equal to the momentum acting on psi.
And we will recognize this as just a theory
in which the energy of a particle
is equal to its momentum.
Okay.
Energy equal momentum is a relativistic massless particle.
For mass, you want p squared,
sorry, e squared equals p squared plus m squared.
All right, so this was a failure
as a theory of one-dimensional electrons
because one-dimensional electrons moving on a wire
or something have a mass.
Okay, we figured out what to do with that.
We introduce a second species of electrons,
which this, these were right-moving electrons.
These were waves which moved strictly to the right.
The time derivative is minus their space derivative.
That means they move to the right.
So wave packets just propagate off
with constant velocity, speed of light.
Okay.
What you want to do is you want to invent another species
which propagates to the left.
So we could call this one psi one.
And we invent another one,
h psi two, a completely different particle,
equals minus p psi two,
a particle whose energy is minus the momentum.
And this just interchanges plus momentum in that direction,
right, with minus momentum in that direction.
And so this particle clearly propagates to the left.
Then we combined these two equations
by taking psi one and psi two
and making a column vector out of them.
Quantum mechanically, this means the particle
can either be of one type or the second type.
So there's a new degree of freedom we discovered.
The new degree, or we were inventing,
a new degree of freedom,
which is above and beyond the momentum of the particle.
It's, it's handedness.
Does it move to the right or does it move to the left?
Incidentally, this particle can have negative energy
or positive energy,
because p can be positive or negative.
But in either case, it goes to the right.
This one can have positive energy or negative energy.
In either case, it goes to the left.
Okay.
Then we, then, uh, we invented a matrix.
The matrix was alpha.
Alpha, oops, that's gamma.
Lie down, alpha.
Get on your side and be alpha.
And this says that psi one
is an eigenvector of alpha with eigenvalue plus one,
and psi two is an eigenvector of alpha with minus one.
And now we can combine these two equations.
And just write that h psi,
this is supposed to be a, a simple psi,
h psi is equal to alpha times p psi.
What does this mean?
This means that if alpha is plus one, h is p.
If alpha is minus one, h is minus p.
So we have both of them in the same structure here.
At the cost of doubling the number of components of the field.
Okay.
That didn't get us any, that didn't get us a mass,
but at least got us things going in both directions.
Then we did one more trick.
We invented a, another matrix that's called beta.
And that one looks like this, one, one.
Now the fact that these happen to be Pauli matrices
is somewhat incidental at this point.
They're just matrices for the moment.
And instead of writing h is equal to alpha p,
h is equal to alpha p, that's that equation down there,
plus p or minus p, depending on the sign of alpha,
we added another term, beta times m.
Okay, now here's some things about alpha and beta.
Alpha squared and beta squared are one.
And alpha beta plus beta alpha equals zero.
You can check that.
Just check that if you multiply them in one order,
you get one thing.
If you multiply them in the other order,
you get the other thing, and they cancel.
You might say that alpha and beta anticommute, and it's true,
but don't confuse that with the anticommutation of the fields.
Okay.
So alpha and beta anticommute, they each square to one.
Now consider h squared.
That's the square of the energy.
That's the operator that governs the square of the energy.
Well, that's going to have one term, which is alpha squared p squared,
another term, which is beta squared m squared,
and then yet another term, which is alpha beta plus beta alpha p times m.
But we were lucky.
Alpha beta times beta alpha is identically equal to zero,
and so the only terms that are there are p squared plus m squared,
which is exactly what we want for a relativistic particle with mass.
Okay.
So we manage by combining a left-moving and a right-moving
and then coupling the left-moving and the right-moving
through this matrix beta.
The matrix beta does couple them together.
We end up with a particle with a mass.
It's in this sense that a mass term is a mass term in the Hamiltonian
is something which sort of switches you from left-moving to right-moving.
Well, it doesn't really do that.
It just gives the particle a mass,
but you can picture it as causing transitions between left and right,
moving to the left and moving to the right.
And if you can have transitions between left and right,
you might start to think, well,
maybe it even makes sense to think of a particle at rest.
Pss, pss, pss, pss, pss, pss, pss.
Sort of at rest.
At rest, good.
You can have a massive particle at rest.
You can't have a massless particle.
What are you doing?
I'm filming you.
Oh, okay.
I have a question.
Is there more to the physical interpretation of having both types of particles?
It is what it is.
I...
Is there more to it?
We'll get there.
Yeah, there is more to it,
but at this point, that's what the...
That's all there is, yeah.
Sometimes things are just abstract.
Sometimes that's all there is to it.
All right, so then comes the question,
how do we do this in three dimensions?
Three dimensions instead of one dimension.
Three dimensions of space.
Okay, so let's go back.
Let's start with what will turn out to be the case which is massless.
Will turn out to be a case which can't have a mass.
Here's what we're going to do.
We have three dimensions of space.
It wouldn't make sense to have only one alpha.
We can have px.
We can have py.
And we can have pz.
This looks like it wants to be some sort of product
of a degree of freedom with p,
but p is a vector.
What do we get to make...
What do we get to multiply by vectors
to make things which are invariant?
Other vectors.
We take dot products of vectors.
So here's what Dirac thought to himself.
He thought this alpha here must be a vector
if we're going to multiply it by p
and make something which is rotationally invariant.
That means it must have three components.
It must have three components.
So he said, let's try the equation h equals alpha dot p.
This means alpha sub x px plus alpha sub y py plus alpha sub z pz.
Okay.
What do the alphas have to do to make this sensible?
For the moment, we're not going to try to make a mass.
We're going to make a massless equation.
So what is the right formula for our massless particle?
It's energy versus momentum.
The answer is energy squared equals momentum squared,
but that means energy squared equals px squared plus py squared plus pz squared.
That's what we want to get.
h squared equals px squared plus py squared plus py squared.
What happens if we square this thing over here?
Well, we'll get terms which are alpha x squared times px squared.
That's okay.
That just means we want alpha x squared to equal 1.
Likewise with alpha y.
Alpha z squared equals 1.
But now we want to make sure the cross terms aren't there.
So we're going to have to make a massless equation.
When we multiply out the cross terms, we get px times py,
and it will multiply alpha x alpha y plus alpha y alpha x.
That's what will happen.
So we had better have that alpha x alpha y plus alpha y alpha x equals 0.
And likewise for the other combinations.
Same with x and z, same with y and z.
So Dirac says, can I find three matrices which each one squared is 1
and which mutually anticommute?
And the answer to that is easy.
Pauli matrices.
The three Pauli matrices do exactly that.
So if we say alpha x is equal to sigma x,
the Pauli matrix equals 1 1 0 0.
Alpha y equals sigma y equals what?
Minus 1, sorry, minus i i 0 0.
And finally, the last one is alpha z equals sigma z.
And that's the easy one to remember, 1 minus 1.
And we got it.
In other words, our Hamiltonian h is equal to sigma dot p.
You can think of this as a particle whose,
well, it's a particle that has a spin, that's the sigma,
and a particle that has a momentum,
and the energy is proportional to the dot product
or the component of spin along the direction of motion.
Okay?
Good.
So it's a massless particle,
but it has the odd behavior that its spin is always,
well, let's go back.
Okay.
Sigma dot p.
Its energy is proportional to the component of its spin
along the momentum direction.
Now, the component of a spin is always plus or minus 1.
So it sounds like there are two cases here.
One case where the spin is literally along the momentum,
pointing along the momentum,
and the other case in which the spin is opposite to the momentum.
In one case, the energy is positive.
If sigma is in the same direction as the momentum,
sigma dot p is positive.
If they're oppositely aligned, that's negative.
So again, we have the situation, massless particle,
okay, a massless particle with positive and negative energy states,
and instead of saying that the particle can just move along the x-axis
or along the y-axis, sorry, along the x-axis positively,
along the x-axis positively,
this one is stuck in a different kind of way.
It's stuck in that its momentum or its energy is sigma dot p.
In other words, if its energy is positive in particular,
if it's a positive energy particle,
then its spin is always locked to be in the same direction as the momentum.
So I've heard said that the spin drops out of the Dirac equation, so to speak.
It does?
Well, I mean, I've heard that said, but that's wrong.
I was going to say this seems to be we're introducing it.
Well, it certainly doesn't drop out of the Dirac equation.
Where does it come from?
What do you mean, where does it come from?
I mean, we just introduce it because we know the electron has a magnetic moment.
Well, yeah.
That's not why Dirac introduced it.
Dirac introduced it because he wanted to write a Hamiltonian equation.
I think you missed reading it.
It falls out.
It comes in as a result of.
Oh, oh, falls out means that it just plopped into your lap.
No, I mean it the way Mike said.
Which?
That it comes as a result of.
Yeah, it comes as a result of.
Plops into your lap for free.
Right, I thought you meant it falls out that it doesn't appear in the equation.
No, no.
It just drops.
Ah, okay.
Good.
A couple different numbers.
Right.
Yeah, well, okay.
Look, Dirac's logic, which was not necessarily unimpeachable, was that he wanted to write
an equation where the Hamiltonian would be written in terms of the momentum without having
some insane square root.
This is the best he could do.
He said, I'll write H equals alpha dot P because I want it to be linear in the momentum, but
then he said, what the hell is alpha?
It can't just be a bunch of numbers.
And by requiring that H squared equals P squared, he found the Dirac matrices or these alpha
matrices.
He found the Pauli matrices.
So he said, oh, oh, I think I've discovered why this spin.
And in fact, he was right.
He said, well, I don't know.
I don't know.
Well, I don't know.
He found the Pauli matrices.
So he said, oh, oh, I think I've discovered why this spin.
And in fact, he was right in a sense.
He was not right that every particle on Earth has to have a spin.
But he was right that the particles that are described by the Dirac equation have a spin.
And that meant fermions.
OK, so, so far we haven't said what this has to do with whether they're fermions or bosons.
And we'll come to that.
OK.
still we have h squared equals p squared and we don't have a mass. h squared equals
p squared is the massless particle. What do we have to do? So you might think well
what we have to do is put another beta m here. Let's try that. What are we going to
require when we square h? We're going to get the usual sigma squared p squared
which is just p squared. We're going to get, assuming that beta, assuming the
square of beta is one again, let's assume beta squared is one again, then we'll get
an m squared term we'll get h squared equals p squared plus m squared
plus a cross term. And the cross term will involve things like
this.
So we have an m squared term, which is the massless particle, and then we're going to
let's say Px, M, I take the x component of this,
and I multiply it by sigma x beta plus beta sigma x.
In other words, we want this to be, of course, zero.
We don't want that there.
So we want whatever beta is to anti-commute with all the Pauli matrices.
That would be great, except that there is no matrix
which anti-commutes with all the Pauli matrices.
When you start looking at 2x2 matrices,
you discover that there are three mutually anti-commuting ones and no more.
So we give up.
Or we say, why does it have to be 2x2 matrices?
Maybe what we have to do is introduce another binary degree of freedom,
another two-value degree of freedom.
So if there is this two-value degree of freedom,
and another one, we would be talking about 4x4 matrices.
Each particle would have a four-component thing associated with it,
some new degree of freedom.
You could look for 10x10, you could look for 100x100.
Turns out, you could look for 3x3.
Mm-mm, there are none.
No 3x3 matrices which have the anti-commutation relations
of the four necessary matrices here.
The first case where you discover that there are
four mutually anti-commuting matrices is the 4x4 case.
Now, the fact that it's 4x4 has nothing to do with the fact
that spacetime is four-dimensional.
It's just a mathematical fact about anti-commuting matrices.
And I'll show you what they are.
You can work them out yourself and see that they all anti-commute.
Oh, incidentally, there are many, many different versions, or very,
very many different versions of these matrices.
There are many, many different versions of these matrices.
There are many, many different representations of the Dirac matrices.
I'll write down what that means in a minute.
You pick one and you stick with it.
They're all equivalent.
They're all absolutely equivalent in the physics.
Roughly speaking, the relationship between the different representations,
nobody would mind very much if I called the x direction the y direction,
the y direction the z direction, the z direction the x direction.
So if I called sigma y,
I would call sigma y.
So if I just permuted them in some way,
it would be just as good.
Same is true of the alpha and beta,
of the Dirac matrices.
There are many, many different representations.
We just have to pick one and stick with it.
Alright, so what are the rules?
Once Dirac realized,
I don't know what Dirac realized and what he didn't realize,
but once, in my imagination,
he realized that he had to go over four by four matrices,
he stopped calling these things sigma.
And he started calling these things sigma.
And called them alpha.
Same alpha as up there,
except they're not two by two matrices.
He called them alpha.
Now the fact is, I think he wrote this down before he even thought about the one-dimensional case.
And now what we need is we need
four mutually anti-commuting matrices.
Alpha squared equals one.
Alpha x squared equals one.
Alpha y squared equals one.
Alpha z squared equals one.
We better also have beta squared equals one.
But then we also have to have
alpha x alpha y plus alpha y alpha x
alpha y alpha x
equals zero.
That's to make sure that when we square this,
there's no term with px times py.
There's no term with px times py.
Similar things to this.
But finally,
for all of the alphas,
all three alphas,
we have to have, I'll just call it alpha x
times beta
plus beta alpha x
also equals zero.
Same for y and same for z.
Alright, and as I said,
such matrices exist,
four by four matrices.
Could we call beta alpha t?
You could,
but it's not really.
It's,
it's,
no,
they don't form a four vector.
I'll tell you what forms a four vector.
I'll tell you in a minute.
Once we get there,
once we write the Dirac equation,
I'll tell you.
So,
we have a four vector
and we have a four vector
and we have a four vector.
Okay, here are the matrices.
Once you know them,
you can forget them because really all that counts
is these properties here.
You can work just with the abstract algebra.
I think you essentially
never need the actual form of the matrices.
But, nevertheless,
you just want to make sure there are such matrices.
Here's a particular representation.
This is not the one that Dirac used.
This one is called the
Pauli representation of the Dirac matrices.
It's not the Pauli,
but it's the Dirac representation.
Alright, here it is.
Alpha,
the three of them,
alpha x, alpha y, and alpha z.
I'll explain this notation in a minute.
These are four by four matrices,
but they consist of blocks.
Two by two blocks.
In each block,
there's a two by two matrix.
In here, you put sigma,
which means in a minute.
Here you put minus sigma.
And here you put zero, and here you put zero.
So, for example,
if I was interested in alpha x,
that would be the matrix
sigma x up here
minus sigma x down here
zero, zero.
And what would that look like?
It would be, again,
divided into blocks.
In this block,
put sigma x,
which is one, one, zero, zero.
In this block down here,
put zero minus one,
minus one, zero.
All others, zero.
Same thing
for alpha y
and alpha z.
And you can check,
you can very quickly check that these
anti-commute with each other.
They anti-commute with each other
as a consequence of the fact that the
sigmas, the Pauli matrices themselves
anti-commute with each other.
And so the second you start writing down
the products of them, you realize
you're just working with the Pauli matrices
in some very simple way.
They anti-commute with each other,
and so this kind of thing is satisfied.
The only thing we have to figure out
is what beta is,
and beta is chosen in this representation
to just be zero, one, one, zero.
But each of these are
two by two blocks.
So what does this mean?
This means
in the upper left hand block here
you put zero, zero, zero, zero, zero.
Likewise down here.
And what does one over here mean?
It means the unit matrix.
One, one, zero, zero.
That's beta.
I am not going to work out the anti-commutator
if there's nothing to it
other than just multiplying it.
So we have the anti-commutator
multiplying matrices.
The anti-commutators are zero
of the alphas with beta.
And so we actually have a Hamiltonian
whose square is p squared plus m squared.
The relativistic law
of connection between energy and momentum.
It sounds good.
And it is good.
Yeah?
For the nexus particle
you had to make it work
on another degree of freedom
and that was the activity of the
spin.
Actually it wasn't in the one dimensional case.
Yeah, it's not spin.
You can't have spin in one dimension
really.
It was a spin-like thing, but it wasn't really spin.
Spin requires three dimensions
to spin around, you know, genuine spin.
When you added a mesh
you had to have another degree of freedom.
How is that physically manifested
in some other kind of thing?
If so, what is it?
It is.
It's connected with something called
helicity.
When we looked at the original equation
with sigma here
we found out that if the particle
has positive energy
that means that sigma has to be
aligned with the momentum here.
So there's only one kind of particle
with its momentum
and spin along the same axis.
What we did in effect here
was to put in a new form
of the momentum
and spin along the same axis.
We created another species
whose energy is
the spin
minus the spin times the momentum.
So we created another species
doubled everything up
and the other species has
what is called the opposite chirality.
Chirality meaning
the relationship between spin and momentum.
If spin is
along the direction of momentum
that's called right-handed
like your right hand, your thumb, and your spin.
Opposite is left-handed.
When we only took the
2x2 matrices we were stuck
with particles with only one-handedness.
We put the other one in
we put the other handedness in.
That gave us two kinds of particles
one which goes this way
and then we coupled them
together by putting this
off-diagonal thing here
which mixes
the left guys and the right guys
The result was
a massive particle.
This is the sense in which
mass for a Dirac particle
is a transition
or a coupling between the
left-handed spinning particles
and the right-handed spinning particles.
No, they have very good chirality
they don't have anything
which flips the chirality.
Yeah.
The massless particles of chirality is conserved.
Did anybody understand what I said?
For massless particles
the chirality is conserved.
It stays right-handed
or it stays left-handed
but the mass term
causes transitions between them.
It's a term that's
called the
massless term
and it's a term
that's called
the massless term
because it's a term
in the Hamiltonian
which takes one to the other.
How do I know that?
Because it's off-diagonal.
It takes the upper block to the lower block
and mixes them.
Okay.
Are these built into quaternions?
No, no.
The alpha matrices are not
The sigma matrices
are quaternions.
Yeah.
Alright, so since you asked me
about quaternions, I'll just spend
a moment with them.
Quaternions are a way of doing vector algebra.
They're connected with the sigma matrices.
Let's go back a step.
Let's take complex numbers.
Every complex number
is a plus ib, right?
a squared and b squared
are, oh, right.
Every
Hermitian 2x2
matrix.
Every Hermitian 2x2 matrix
can be written as a
ordnance
as a thing proportional to the unit
2x2 matrix
plus i
times, uh,
is there an i?
No i.
I think I
misspoke.
I think I want to put an i there.
Not Hermitian.
Forget Hermitian.
Sigma
dot
some other
some vector
I don't know.
Q, a vector.
Everything can be written as a linear combination
of, and these things are called
the 2x2 matrices
representing
things like this are called quaternions
but, um, it's not
going to play any role in what we're doing.
So
the spin is associated with angular momentum.
Yeah.
So is there an energy term
associated with that?
No, nothing other than this.
Now the alpha here is not actually
spin yet.
We're going to ask what the alpha means physically.
What is, uh,
what is alpha? Alpha,
each alpha, each component,
here's something true, each component
of alpha,
uh,
the three of them,
each component, um,
well, it's a matrix,
it has eigenvalues, and the eigenvalues
are plus one and minus one,
but it has two plus one eigenvalues
and two minus one eigenvalues,
because it's a four by four matrix.
And the question is
what physical quantity is it
representing? They don't commute with each other,
incidentally, so you can't measure
the different components of alpha
simultaneously, they don't commute.
But you can measure a component.
What is the physical meaning
of that component? And the physical meaning is very bizarre.
It's the velocity.
It's the velocity of the particle.
The alphas are
the velocity, which means
to say that the expectation value
of alpha in any state
is the velocity
of the particle. How do you see
that? Okay.
What you have to remember is you have to go back
to the
formulas for the time
derivatives of the expectation
values of operators.
I'll just remind you, if I have
some operator, let's just call it L,
a Hermitian operator, and I'm
interested in its expectation
value, I won't bother writing in states
here, I'll just, some states there, some
state, the expectation
value of L has a value,
and if the state changes
with time, the expectation
value of L also changes with
time. Do you remember the formula for this?
It's related
to the commutator
of the Hamiltonian with L.
Now for the life of me, I can
never remember, is it plus i or
minus i?
I don't know, and I'm not going to figure
it out. It's not hard to figure out,
but I'm not going to bother. We're just
going to write i.
We can always write i, it doesn't matter.
You can write plus i or minus i, but
then the question is whether
it's commutator of H with L
or L with H.
And I don't remember.
But we're not going to care, because
it's not important.
The time derivative, and you take the
expectation value of this.
The expectation value, the time derivative
of the expectation value of L,
you can just think of that as the average
time derivative
of L is equal
to i times the
commutator of H with L. In fact, you can even
erase
these brackets
here, and just
write it formally,
the formal equation that L dot is S.
Okay.
Let's take our Dirac
particle, and
let's consider x dot.
x is the x coordinate of the particle.
And let's
consider, using this formula,
let's try to figure out what the
velocity operator is.
What's the operator which, when you measure it,
gives you the velocity?
Okay, so this shouldn't be too hard.
It's i times the
commutator of
H, which is what? Alpha dot
P plus beta M.
That's H
commuting
with x.
...
Well, M is just a number.
The alphas and betas,
they commute with x.
They're in a different,
they're in a
different space.
They're not in the x space,
they're in this 2 by 2,
4 by 4 space.
So, beta and alpha
commute with x. What's the only thing
in here which doesn't commute with x?
P.
Which component of P?
P sub x.
So, when you
work out the commutator,
this is not here.
Alpha commutes with x, so that means
you can take it outside,
and you just have commutator with P with x,
which is what?
Minus i, minus i H bar.
Okay.
So this is equal to minus i times i
is plus 1 is equal to alpha.
Alpha sub x.
So alpha,
this crazy,
this crazy funny theory,
the, um,
the velocity of the particle
is not proportional to its momentum.
It's given by alpha.
So if you want to know what the velocity
of the particle is, you measure alpha.
Now,
it's weird.
Can it be plus or minus some large...
It can only be plus or minus 1 in any direction.
Right.
On the other hand,
alpha itself is not conserved.
If you...
Oh, that's an interesting question.
Alpha itself is not conserved.
Why not?
Let's see if alpha x is conserved.
For that, we have to take the commutator
of
alpha x,
of H with alpha x.
Let's take the commutator of H with alpha x.
That would be the time derivative
of alpha x.
And the problem is
that H has in it alpha y.
Alpha y doesn't commute
with alpha x.
It also has alpha z in it,
which doesn't commute with alpha x.
So the answer is that the commutator
of alpha x with the Hamiltonian is not 0,
which means that the particle
accelerates.
It does a crazy wobbly motion
which is called Zitterbewegung.
Zitterbewegung means something, I don't know,
some German word meaning
drunken...
drunken Scandinavian,
it means.
What?
Redundancy.
Right.
But of course,
what is also true
is if you look at the
time average of the velocity,
the thing is going this way and this way
and this way, but the time average
is exactly what you expect it to be,
namely the momentum divided by the mass,
at least if it's moving slowly.
But alpha, but the main point is
alpha is not the spin.
It's the velocity.
It's a vector quantity,
and spin is an axial vector quantity.
It's a pseudo vector.
So I'll tell you what the spin is.
It's very easy.
Let's see, where is alpha?
No.
Here's alpha.
Notice it has this
minus sigma down there.
The real spin is just this.
It's a different operator.
It's a different operator,
very closely related,
but it's the spin.
It's the legitimate, genuine
spin of the particle.
So Dirac discovered
a multiplicity of different states
of the electron,
one of them had to do with
the chirality,
which way the spin was,
or which way the alpha
was oriented relative to the momentum.
The other had to do with
the actual spin of the electron.
Alright, so...
So the Zitterberg wave gun
means a free electron
in every space will vibrate back and forth
with new external forces.
Doesn't that violate
something?
No.
What about Newton's laws?
No, no, no.
Newton's law says the time derivative
of the momentum is zero.
It doesn't say the time derivative
of the velocity is zero.
It says time derivative of the momentum is zero.
In most situations,
ordinarily,
momentum and velocity are related to each other.
Here, the velocity of this particle
is not the momentum.
Weird.
Isn't velocity C?
No, not when there's a mass.
Alright.
Um...
In relativity,
could you think of it as the mass varying
the velocity?
No, no.
In fact, I mean, it's true that in some technical mathematical sense,
alpha is the velocity,
but it's also true that
it itself is not conserved,
and so it's going around like crazy
in some complicated fashion,
and there is a time average of the velocity itself.
You can take the time average
of the velocity
over a little bit of time,
and that is the momentum.
That is P over m
for slow electrons.
For slow electrons,
you know, it's going around like crazy,
doing crazy things,
but as it's doing crazy things,
it's moving along with a smooth velocity,
smooth component of the velocity,
which is the momentum.
And that you can prove.
We won't do that now, but...
Could there be a measurement,
like, one instant going one way?
Yeah.
Yes, the answer is yes.
Right.
Okay, now we come
to the last thing for tonight.
Well, yeah, probably.
We come to this
strange fact that the
Dirac electron
can have both
positive energy and negative energy.
Now, for this purpose,
we don't even need to think about
the full-blown three-dimensional
Dirac equation.
It's enough just to study
the one-dimensional right-moving
electron.
Just take that case. We'll come back to the
three-dimensional case, but
all of the interesting ideas
are already there
just for
the one-dimensional case,
and even the one-dimensional case
without the alpha matrices,
just a pure right-moving massless
electron. That already has
negative energy.
If the particle has positive,
let's go back. What was the formula
for its energy?
The formula for its energy was just
H equals P.
That's the right, I think that's the right
moving electron, yeah.
Not even an alpha.
That was our simplest version
of the Dirac equation, if you like.
It was massless. It only went to
the right.
But it has both positive and negative energies.
And the reason it has negative
energies is because P can be negative.
There's no restriction here that P
can't be negative.
So we have to figure out what does this mean,
negative energies.
Negative energies are very dangerous.
The ground state, the vacuum
of the world, is
not necessarily the state with no
particles in it. It's trying to be
the state of lowest energy.
When you take everything out,
when you take all the energy, when you suck out
all the energy from the vacuum,
or from space,
what's left is the vacuum.
And clearly the vacuum had better be the lowest
energy, otherwise you could lower
the energy past the vacuum, and that's
a little bit crazy.
And even worse, you could lower the energy
indefinitely
until you have some sort of monstrous
thing with enormously
negative energy. What does that mean?
The vacuum,
the vacuum is supposed to be empty space.
There's not supposed to be anything that
you can remove from it anymore.
No way to lower its energy.
So what's going on here?
Well, Dirac said, let's take
the definition of the vacuum
to be the state of lowest energy.
What about these negative
energy particles? You can put negative energy
particles in, if they have negative energy,
they lower the energy.
So you can lower the energy past zero
just by flooding this thing
with many, many negative energy
particles.
Dirac very cleverly said, wait a minute,
I know that these particles are
fermions,
what is the lowest energy state
going to be? The lowest energy state
is going to be if I fill it up
maximally with every
possible negative energy particle.
Every negative energy particle gives you negative
energy, and if you
fill it up
with every negative energy particle, that's
as negative as it can get. Well, wait a minute now.
Why can't you put
two negative energy
particles in the same state?
Because they're fermions.
So once you've filled
up, see if they were bosons
you'd have trouble. No matter how many
of them you put in, you could always put in more.
So
if you had bosons
which were
negative energy, there really
would be no bottom. You could just keep putting
them in and putting them in and putting them in
and lower
the energy of anything. But
Dirac said, wait a minute, if these are fermions,
truly fermions, you can only put one into
a state. If you fill
all the possible negative energy states,
then your vacuum is stable
because you can't put another
negative energy particle in.
No room, so to speak.
So what Dirac said was
the vacuum, if it's to be the lowest
energy state, must be
the state in which every
negative energy
state is occupied.
And then you can't
put any more in.
This was an
intuitive way to describe some
mathematics, which I'll tell you in a moment
what the mathematics is.
But it's correct.
Modern physicists will tell you
they don't like that description because
it sounds a little
the vacuum is the vacuum,
it's not full of stuff. But
take it, let's follow Dirac's
reasoning because it was very effective.
He said, okay, let's
fill up all the negative energy states
and call that the vacuum.
Then what kind of things
can this system describe?
Well,
we could come along
here, we'll draw a picture
to describe this thing.
Let's label, of course,
the momentum is continuous,
it's a continuous variable,
but let's just suppose for a moment
that we discretized it.
Then,
here's the energies.
Here are all
the negative energy levels.
Lots of them.
E.
And what Dirac said is,
fill these all up.
Put a particle in every one
so it becomes a
monolithic
thing which you can't put any more
particles into.
And that way,
you stabilize the vacuum against
more negative energy particles.
But what do you have left now?
So he said, okay, you can certainly
put a positive energy particle into this.
There's your positive energy electron.
But you can
do something else.
You can remove
a negative energy electron from here
and put it over here.
Take out a negative
energy electron from
what has become
called the Dirac C.
The Dirac C, this incredible
collection of electrons which fill the vacuum.
Remove it,
and you have a hole.
You have a missing
negative energy electron,
but
you have an extra,
let's get rid of this one up here,
you have an extra positive energy electron.
You've made a hole
in the negative energy C
and created an extra positive
What is this thing over here?
This thing is something. It's a missing
If electrons have negative
charge, and you
plunk one out of the vacuum,
you'll be left with a little bit of a hole.
And the hole will have positive charge.
What about its energy?
What will be the energy of this hole here?
Hmm?
Yeah.
It will be exactly the same as the electron.
It won't be negative.
Removing a negative energy
puts in a positive energy.
increases the energy.
So,
by removing a particle from here,
you put
an extra particle here,
but you've also created a negative energy hole,
sorry,
a positive energy hole
in the negative energy C.
And that's called a positron.
That's called a positron.
Uh,
historically,
Dirac did not know at first
that he was talking about a thing which was
identical to the electron,
except for the sign of its charge.
Why does it have opposite charge?
Well, when you fill,
because it's a missing
negative energy electron.
A missing negative energy
is the same as a positive energy.
So, Dirac said,
this solves his problem.
He now has a stable vacuum.
There are no negative energy particles.
There are only positive energy electrons
and positive energy positrons.
Uh,
or positive energy
holes.
And this
then solves the problem.
And it does.
It does solve the problem.
Yeah?
This picture suggests there will always be
equal numbers of electrons.
Not necessarily.
You could start with some excess electrons
or you could start with some holes
and there would be no electrons.
Not necessarily.
Um, if you interpret it by saying
you started somehow just with a vacuum,
yeah,
then it's kind of true.
But there's no reason to start with only the vacuum.
You could start with some excess of one kind or the other.
But, um,
let's think about something else for a moment.
Uh,
Okay, so we start
with, let's start with a vacuum.
We start with a vacuum
which means all the negative energy states filled up.
And then a photon comes along.
Now,
think about a photon coming and hitting an atom.
It finds an electron and kicks
the electron upstairs, right?
It kicks it up to, uh, to higher energy.
Same thing will happen here.
A photon
comes along,
whacks an electron.
There's no electrons
up here, but this thing is full of electrons.
Full of negative energy.
It hits it
and takes one of the electrons from here
and puts it upstairs.
Increases its energy.
It can't decrease its energy because they're all filled.
All it can do is put it into the upstairs here
and leave a hole.
Okay, so what's happened?
What's happened is a photon has come along
and turned itself into a negative energy,
sorry, a posit, negative charge electron,
a positron,
and an electron.
We, as a matter of convention,
we always draw the electron lines
with arrows in them that point up
and positrons with arrows that point down.
That's just a convention.
Uh,
but it's kind of a nice convention
because it's a convention
that we can use to determine
how much energy is in the atom.
It's a nice convention.
Positrons point down, electrons point up,
and just remember that whenever you slice this
at a moment of time,
every particle that you slice
with an up-going arrow
is a negative charge
because it's an electron
and every, um,
particle that you cross
that has a down-going arrow
has a, uh,
a positive charge.
So,
this is, uh,
the Dirac theory of electrons.
Let's talk about the field operators
describing them.
The field operators are built
exactly the same way
as the boson field operators.
Psi,
it's built as an integral
over the momentum,
dp,
creation and annihilation operators
for particles of given momentum
that are not in the same direction
as the field operators.
Let's take, uh,
this one here.
That's, uh,
A minus,
the annihilation operator for a particle of momentum,
p, times e to the,
I guess it's minus ipx
if I'm not mistaken.
Yeah,
annihilation has e to the minus ipx.
Or is it e to the plus ipx?
Doesn't matter.
Okay,
that's the way we built field operators
creation operators and annihilation operators
times, um,
times this sort of thing here.
But now, these are fermion
creation and annihilation operators.
They anti-commute with each other.
Okay,
well, what do we integrate
p over? We integrate p
from minus infinity to plus infinity,
but that means that there are negative
energy particles in here because
negative energy corresponds to minus momentum,
negative momentum.
Right, there are negative energy
electrons in this formula here,
but let's divide it up into
two pieces. An integral from
zero to infinity,
dp,
annihilation operator for a positive
momentum or a positive energy
electron, e to the minus
ipx,
and another term from
minus infinity to zero,
dp,
creation
operator now for a,
oh, did I write, I meant annihilation operator.
My mistake.
Annihilation operator
here.
Same thing as here.
Annihilation operator for a
negative momentum particle.
Now,
Dirac said, wait a minute, actually
I'm not sure who said it. He said,
when you're dealing with fermions, the
mathematics does not distinguish
creation operators from
annihilation operators.
You can in the mathematics
say that every annihilation operator
is a creation operator, and that's because they
aren't that commute. Mathematics
just doesn't distinguish them. So,
instead of calling this an
annihilation operator
for a negative energy particle,
let's just relabel it and
call it a
creation operator
for a positron.
What does it do? Remember what it did.
It annihilated a negative energy
electron. In other words, it created
a positron. So let's just
call this annihilation operator of a
negative energy particle, let's call
it a creation operator for a positron.
And
he labeled them B's. B's,
I don't know why B's, but A's and B's,
electrons, positrons,
and I think
if you work it out and do the
little bit of
juggling, you'll get from zero to infinity
again, but
you'll get e to the, I think you get e to the plus
i p x, yeah, you do, I think.
So Dirac
said, you can think of the field
operator as a sum of two terms,
one with annihilation operators
for electrons, and the other with
creation operators for positrons.
I'll give you one example
of the kind of thing this does for you.
The field operator has two kinds of
things. So let's take
a process
where an electron comes along,
emits another electron,
and a photon.
This would be an annihilation operator,
an annihilation operator for an
electron, that's an A minus,
and a
creation operator for another electron,
that's an A plus,
and a photon operator,
let's call the photon operator
A.
Okay.
You might suspect that where this comes from,
and you'd be right, is a term in
the Hamiltonian which would be
psi dagger of x
times
psi of x
times A.
An annihilation operator,
a creation operator,
and a photon operator.
But now if you put in the fact
that the operators here have two pieces,
one with
creation operators of one kind of particle
and the other annihilation, and the
annihilation operator is the other kind of particle,
what you find out is that the same
operator has contributions in it
which is not an electron
being an electron and becoming a
photon, but in fact
for example, an electron
annihilating a positron.
Electron,
positron, photon.
If you look around for all the
creation and annihilation operators in here,
you find that it contains
combinations, the same operator,
the same operator which
took an electron to an electron and a photon
takes an electron and a positron
and makes a photon.
So one simple complex
of field operators describes
many, many processes.
There's even another one.
An electron and a positron
can be created and
a photon at the same time
just by using all the various
varieties of
creation and annihilation operators
that would happen in here.
This was the start, sort of, of Feynman diagrams.
Of course it was Feynman who figured out
how to evaluate them and make real sense
out of them, but Dirac
had quite a bit of the structure
down.
And that brings us, I think,
to the end for tonight.
So, yeah.
Can you say
how do modern physicists think about
this as opposed to using the Dirac C?
Oh, no,
very easy. They just
say forget the Dirac C,
just replace
creation operators for
negative energy by
annihilation operators for positive energy.
Just do that flip in the
formulas. And when you do that,
then it becomes completely symmetric
in the electrons and positrons.
You discover
right away that it's a complete symmetry
so you could think of the
vacuum as being
filled with negative energy
positrons and the holes
being electrons.
Okay, one last thing
is that this
same pattern
turns up in solid state physics.
If you have
a crystal
or anything else for that matter
with lots of electrons in it
and you want to know what the lowest energy
state is, you just put
all, however many electrons
you have, you put them into
the lowest available states.
Right? You just
if the ground state is not occupied
you put an electron in there.
Of course they're all positive.
But you keep putting electrons in
until you fill it up to some level.
What level? However many electrons you have.
You fill it up.
So then you have a ground state.
And the ground state is full of electrons.
The net charge of course
is zero because there are protons
there also canceling the charge.
So you have a C.
It's called the Fermi C.
What Fermi had to do with it I'm not sure.
Now you can take an
electron out of the C
and kick it upstairs to
a higher energy state.
That leaves a hole. Sure enough it leaves a hole.
Those are called in solid state physics
they're called holes.
But they can also be thought of as
positive charged particles.
So in solid state physics
you have exactly the same thing.
You have electrons
which have energy up above
the Fermi level, up above this filled C.
And you also have
positive charges
which are really just
really this time, just really the missing electrons
in the
and of course the positrons
not the positrons, the holes
also have positive energy
because they correspond to
a missing energy
at a lower energy level.
Well they do have
positive energy.
So the same pattern
is very well known in solid state physics
but Dirac did this first.
I always had thought that Dirac
patterned this on what happens to electrons
in a crystal
until I realized that he did this
long before anybody had thought about electrons
in crystals.
So, yeah.
I was just wondering if the
Klein-Gordon equation
for bosons, does it have a
problem with cascading
to the lowest? No. No.
No.
No it doesn't.
We don't have time to go through it but
Where does spin for bosons come from?
What's that?
Spin for bosons, the spin one
for bosons.
Where do they come from?
Not from this.
Yeah.
I was trying to
when you, in the Dirac equation
when they became Fermi,
what was it that pulled it in
that it had to be
fermions in order to solve
this negative energy problem.
Without
having fermions
you could just keep filling up more
and more and more negative energy
particles and the vacuum would just
be unstable.
You take an atom
the atom can decay
but let's take the ground state of the atom
why can't the ground state of the atom
decay by producing a photon?
Well, because there's
no energy level of the electron
below that. It's got to produce
a positive energy photon because there are
only positive energy photons.
So that means an electron
in the lowest energy
it can't decay any further because
it's down at the bottom. But suppose there was a whole
bunch of negative energy states of the electron
then no matter how
many of them you filled up, you could
always add another one to the negative
energy states and have
the atom decay
by having the electron sink down
even lower.
What prevents that? What prevents
that is the electrons are already
there, but it can only
prevent it if they're fermions.
It's not a Dirac equation.
It's a Klein-Gordon equation
which is different and does
not have the form H is equal
to a linear function of P.
It's a more complicated
right. So you can look up now
the Klein-Gordon equation for
bosons, we just don't have time
for it now. But I think you're
probably in a good position to
follow it. And it's a very
different structure. A very
different structure. It doesn't
have Dirac matrices, doesn't
...
negative energy positron.
But there's a difference and
they're not quite the same.
Which applies to me,
a degree of freedom, another degree
of freedom, which would be charge?
Yeah.
Well,
it's not really a degree of freedom.
Every electron has a negative
charge. Every positron has a
positive charge.
But,
yeah.
Okay.
One way of thinking about it,
it's sort of semi-correct,
but one way of thinking about it is
these 4x4 matrices, there are
two binary
things going on.
One binary thing is a spin,
and the other binary thing is whether it's an
electron or a positron. Now that's not
quite right, but it's
a reasonable
counting of how many different states
you have.
One more question.
Will the infinite Dirac
be causing an infinite cosmological constant?
There you go.
Yeah.
Right.
And,
right.
You can either think of it
as the energy in the Dirac's
spin,
or the energy in the
Cosmic's spin.
And,
you can either think of it
as the energy in the
Dirac's spin,
or the energy in the
Cosmic's spin.
And,
you can either think of it
as the zero point oscillation
of the field.
Photons you don't usually think of
as filling up the Dirac's spin,
but they also contribute
vacuum energy.
Half h bar omega for every
oscillating
mode of the electromagnetic field,
and that's also infinite.
and for bosons in general, a curious fact is that for photons, the vacuum energy is positive.
For fermions, it's always negative. So you could imagine canceling them,
but unfortunately, they don't really cancel because the electron has a mass,
the photon doesn't have a mass, and you're always left over with some huge amount of vacuum energy.
So you're right. That's right, but keep in mind the only time that the zero point of energy comes into anything
is when that energy is gravitating. For all other purposes, the zero point of energy can just be subtracted off
and neglected because it doesn't come into any energy differences.
It's only when you say, wait a minute, energy gravitates that you have to worry about it.
Okay, yeah, one more.
Can you say more about how mass relates to left and right moving?
It's just a term in the Hamiltonian which switches from one to the other.
That's all I can say.
You can like, if you like, to try to picture it, you can try to picture it,
but it's not a big deal.
It's always, these pictures are always defective.
So I won't say any more.
If I had more to say, I would have said it.
Right.
Okay.
For more, please visit us at stanford.edu.