Stanford University
So let's talk about supersymmetry. Supersymmetry
has to do with fermions and bosons.
Now, and the relationship between
them, symmetry is between them.
So actually before we talk about supersymmetry,
we should talk again about fermions and bosons.
I want to tell you some
odd and peculiar facts about fermions first.
No, before we even talk about
fermions, let's talk about rotations in space.
Now, we always say that a rotation by 2 pi
is equivalent to no rotation at all, but it's not true.
It's not true. Let me assure you
that if I take my hand like this,
and I rotate it like this,
and I rotate my wrist by 2
pi, it is not like doing nothing.
But then I tell you if I rotate it by
4 pi, which I will do for you in a minute,
if I rotate it by 4
pi, it's equivalent to doing nothing.
So you want to see me
rotate by 4 pi, don't you?
You're going to say, I can't
do it. Oh, yes, I can.
We started this way, palm up, rotate
by 2 pi, it starts to hurt.
Palm up, and I come back to nothing.
This is a topological theorem about rotations in space.
It's a topological theorem, and let me tell
you, let me explain the topological theorem to you.
I've proved it. I've proved it.
I don't need to prove it mathematically.
I've proved it by hand waving.
I've proved it by hand waving. Exactly right.
But let me tell you what the theorem actually says.
Here's the theorem. Take a box.
The box has walls. In that box,
put a basketball or some sort of object,
and connect that basketball to the walls by
strings, any number of strings, it doesn't matter.
Just connect them by strings. Connect
it to the front wall, back wall.
Now, I tell you, and I think you'll believe me, that
if I take this ball and rotate it by 2 pi,
I'm going to get a hell of a tangle.
The strings are going to get all tangled up.
And the question is, can I untangle
them by looping them over the ball,
by without rotating the ball further,
rotate it around by 2 pi,
can I get rid of the tangle
and bring it back to this configuration?
Anybody know the answer?
Rotated by 2 pi.
No, no, no, you're not allowed to rotate the box.
The box is fixed.
So this is a theorem about
rotations of the ball keeping spatial infinity,
the box really represents spatial
infinity, keeping the spatial infinity fixed.
You're not allowed to rotate the box.
So, question. Can I or
can I not undo that rotation?
Rotate by another 2 pi.
Not yet.
Suppose we do not.
We simply rotate by 2 pi and we ask,
can we undo it by moving around the strings,
taking them over the ball,
doing whatever we have to do.
The strings are flexible, they're
even stretchable, but they're unbreakable.
And they're connected both to the ball and the boundary.
Mathematically, it's the same operation
as trying to undo this.
The theorem is,
it says that a rotation by
4 pi, that you can undo it.
So, the answer is for any rotation
by an even number of 2 pi's,
you can undo it by moving the strings around and,
you know, taking them over the ball and so forth.
And it's a topological theorem about the equivalence between
a rotation by 2 pi and no rotation at all.
They're not equivalent, really.
A rotation by 2 pi is
not equivalent topologically to no rotation,
but a rotation by 4 pi is.
This is kind of unintuitive, but it's true.
Okay.
Let's now come to the
properties of wave functions of particles.
And now I'm thinking simply about their spin.
Imagine nailing down the position of the particle,
and the only thing that's important now is,
the spin of the particle.
And the spin of a particle
is described by a quantum state.
Let's call it S for spin.
I'm either thinking about fermions or bosons.
In the case of fermions, the spin is half integer.
In the case of bosons, it's integer.
Now the question is, what happens
to the state of a particle
if you rotate the particle by 2 pi?
Now you can imagine for an
electron actually doing this in the laboratory,
how would you actually rotate the
spin of an electron by 2 pi?
Anybody know a good way to rotate the...
You can grab it with your hand and rotate it,
but that doesn't work so well.
Magnetic field.
You put it in a strong...
Two ways you could do it.
You can put it into a strong magnetic field,
and then rotate the magnetic
field around until it comes back.
You can actually do something else.
If the spin happens to lie in the vertical direction,
you can put a magnetic field in and
just have it process by itself around there.
You don't have to rotate the magnetic field.
Either way will do.
You can rotate the spin of a charged particle
simply by grabbing it with
a magnetic field and rotating it.
What happens to the state of a spin particle
when you do rotate it by 2 pi?
Well, usually we say it has to be
it has to come back to itself.
After all, rotation by 2 pi is nothing at all.
But we found out that rotation by 2 pi
does... can do something.
So we might suspect then
that if we rotate the spin
of a particle by 2 pi,
it gets... something happens to it.
The simplest thing that could happen to it
is it could just get multiplied by a number.
So if I multiply by a number
instead of some other more complicated operator,
well, that's a little complicated.
Why? Because we really, we secretly believe
that no experiment will detect the rotation by 2 pi.
And if we multiply the wave function of a particle,
for example, by a phase or by a minus 1,
that won't change any physics.
We really secretly believe nothing experimental
will be detected by rotating by 2 pi.
One possibility is it gets multiplied by 1.
Another possibility is it gets multiplied by a phase.
But here's what we do know.
If we rotate by 4 pi,
if we rotate by 2 pi,
and that gives us some sort of phase,
at e to the i theta,
then rotating again by 2 pi,
we'll just square this.
And now we know that rotating by 4 pi
is equivalent to doing nothing at all.
Okay?
So if we rotate by 4 pi,
we'll just square this.
And now we know that rotating by 4 pi
is equivalent to doing nothing at all.
So we can say that the mathematical argument
says that xi squared must equal 1,
and there's only two possibilities,
xi is equal to plus 1 or minus 1.
So we could have either possibility
when you rotate a particle by 2 pi
just at spin,
you either multiply it by plus 1,
or you multiply it by 2 pi.
And that's the answer.
An interesting question is,
can you ever imagine,
just as a side issue,
is there ever any experimental
observable consequence
of the fact,
the potential fact,
that the wave function of a particle
might change sign
when you rotate the particle.
And it was generally confirmed
that the magnetic field
was considered to be a totally
unphysical operation,
you could never detect it.
In other words,
here would be the experiment.
You take a whole family of electrons
all prepared identically.
You take half of them
and you stick them into a magnetic field,
and you rotate the magnetic field by 2 pi.
You take the other half
and you do nothing with them.
At the end of the day,
is there any experimental difference between them?
No, you cannot tell the difference
which ones got rotated.
But you can do something else,
and I'll tell you what it is.
You can do a two-slit experiment.
Just to tell you the meaning
of this odd mathematical fact,
you can do a two-slit experiment
in which you take electrons,
let's start with a single electron,
not multiple electrons,
or one by one.
We take electrons one by one
and we send them through.
It either goes through the upper slit
or the lower slit.
We don't know which.
We're not allowed to look,
because if we look,
we will destroy the interference pattern over here.
Some interference pattern over here.
But now what we're going to do,
without looking at whether the electron is here or here,
we're going to place a magnetic field over here,
a B field over here.
We'll also do the same thing over here.
And we'll imagine
that the electron is here,
and the electron gets temporarily trapped
in this region by whatever.
Temporarily trapped
and then re-emitted.
If we do absolutely nothing
to these B fields,
we'll still get some interference pattern here.
Either the electron goes up through here
and gets stuck in the B field
and then gets re-emitted,
B field is not very interesting,
or same thing over here.
But now we do the following.
We do the two-slit experiment
and while the electron
is trapped in one of these two,
we rotate one of them and not the other.
We rotate one of them
and not the other.
Then the wave function here
may or may not get multiplied
by a minus sign,
but let's suppose it does.
The wave function in here does not get multiplied
by a minus sign.
It either gets multiplied
by a minus sign or a plus sign.
If it gets multiplied by a plus sign,
no detection.
If it gets multiplied by a minus sign,
and this one, the wave function coming out of here
does not get, what does
that do to the interference pattern?
It shifts it.
It shifts it up half a wavelength.
It shifts maxima to minima.
So yes, you can detect
this odd sign change,
but only by splitting a beam of electrons
and then rotating half the beam
and not the other half beam.
So it is an experimental,
it's a very interesting experiment.
It's a real phenomenon.
But if you were to take the whole experiment
and rotate all of it,
both magnetic fields simultaneously,
then you detect nothing.
Okay?
Alright.
It's very similar in mathematical structure
to the story
that if you rotate the ball
without rotating the box,
you can detect the fact
that you've rotated it by 2 pi.
If you're allowed to rotate
the whole thing,
ball and box, of course you can't.
So it's a similar kind of thing.
If you rotate it by 4 pi...
Yeah, exactly.
If you rotate the magnetic field
by 4 pi,
the effect goes away.
Right.
And this incident has been done
in the laboratory.
It was an experiment that was suggested
by Aharonov and myself in 1967.
It was actually done.
That's what you said.
Yeah, okay, so for...
Okay, so now you could...
You could do experiments with electrons,
you could do experiments with
charged ions of various kinds,
and you could see which ones
fall into the category
of getting a minus one
and which ones don't.
The ones that don't have a minus one
are the ones where the interference pattern
does not shift.
The ones that do get a minus sign
are the ones where the interference pattern
does shift.
The answer is all fermions
get the minus sign,
all bosons do not get the minus sign.
That's an...
First of all,
it would be an experimental fact
if you really did the experiment.
It's also deeply embedded in the structure
of the mathematics
of quantum field theory
and quantum mechanics.
All right, so that's an interesting distinction
between fermions and bosons.
Yeah?
How does the analogy with the springs work?
Uh...
The analogy with the springs...
Um...
Well,
roughly speaking,
bosons behave as if they weren't
connected by strings to the wall.
Fermions have some memory
of having been rotated by two pi,
so they have a sort of connection
to things which remembers
whether they rotated by two pi.
This is just a method
that's been used
to find out
the mathematical way to see
the topology,
the topological fact that rotation by two pi
is not so innocent
whereas rotation by four pi is.
But once you know that,
I think we forget about this.
Are they in the same quantum state?
Which?
Once that rotated two pi
and one that isn't rotated?
Yeah, well, no.
In this experiment,
yeah, the quantum state of this one
is localized over here.
So what's the idea?
The idea is you create
one way or another a superposition
of states in which the electron
is here or it's here.
Not two electrons.
An electron which is either over here,
so a wave function which consists of two bulges,
probability a half
of the electron to be over here,
probability a half of the electron
to be over here.
Now, both of these electrons now,
after you've...
Not both of the electrons, one electron
but if the electron is here,
we're actually putting it inside a box.
Put it inside a box.
So we create an electron over here.
We split the beam,
which means we create a superposition
of states where it might be here
or it might be here
with probability a half.
And then we rotate this box.
Put a magnetic field in it.
We rotate it.
We don't ask whether there's
an electron in it or not.
Whether or not there is an electron in it,
we rotate the box.
Now, to start with,
the wave function was a sum of two terms.
Psi one,
which is the wave function in here,
and psi two,
which is the wave function here.
Psi one plus psi two
was the full wave function.
Now we rotate
the right-hand box
without...
If we rotate both boxes for the electron,
electron being a fermion,
then the whole wave function changes sign.
If the whole wave function
changes sign,
remember all physical quantities
are proportional to the wave function
times its own complex conjugate,
and the minus sign will cancel out.
But now supposing we rotate
one box relative to the other.
Then what happens
is after the...
after the rotation,
this wave function has changed sign,
this one has not.
Let me give you a consequence of that.
If these two wave functions
were identical,
about reflection,
about the center here,
that would say that after the rotation,
the wave function must vanish
at the center here.
If psi one and psi two
have exactly the same shape,
and let's even suppose...
Yeah, alright.
After we bring them back together again.
By symmetry, the wave function will vanish
at the center here
if the wave function is odd.
If the wave function is even,
then after we bring them back together again,
it doesn't have to vanish at the center.
So an interesting consequence of this
is if this one is a fermion
and we rotate by two pi
and then bring the wave functions back together again,
we will never find the electron at the center.
That's an example
of an interference phenomena.
But,
the point is that there is a difference
between psi one minus psi two
and psi one plus psi two.
And that difference
can be experimentally detected.
Is it the case that
if you don't do a full rotation,
that basically the amount of rotation
is half as much for a boson
or twice as much
or something like that?
Well,
there is something like that,
but that's not...
Yeah, there is...
Would you say that you could tell
the loophole with the electron wet proof?
If you look for the electron
in such a way that you can tell afterwards
which one it was in,
then the interference pattern is destroyed.
What happens if instead of a screen
you test...
Let's say you put it all right,
all the spins are all in one direction
and at the screen you test
the resulting spin.
Will that destroy the interference pattern?
All the spins are in one direction.
Okay,
they are all in the same direction.
Oh, I see.
They still stay in the same direction,
just get a minus sign.
That's right.
Is it true that if you only
if you didn't turn it to pi,
to turn it just pi...
Oh, then it's certainly detectable
to change the direction of the spin.
Then the interference pattern
would be destroyed.
Right, the interference pattern
would be completely destroyed.
Basically, as you tune it,
you can tune it to get an interference pattern.
That's right.
If you rotate that spin,
you tend to destroy...
Rotate the spin by anything
whether it's 2 pi or 4 pi,
you'll lose some of the interference pattern.
If you actually rotate it by 180 degrees,
you completely destroy the interference pattern.
Right, that's correct.
You can't interfere an up spin with a down spin.
You can only interfere things
which are otherwise the same.
Yeah.
Good, all right.
Good, so we now have some bits of information
about fermions.
They change sign on the rotation.
They don't.
Now, let's come to yet another question.
Let's come to a question about Feynman diagrams.
The kind of Feynman diagrams
I have in mind now
are very, very simple.
They have no external lines at all.
They're just Feynman diagrams
in the vacuum.
Empty space.
And they consist of nothing more than
a single closed loop.
A single closed loop.
It could be an electron
or it could be a photon, for example.
It could be a fermion
or it could be a boson.
And this Feynman diagram,
among other things,
controls,
it's first of all,
among other things,
the amplitude that you start with nothing
and you get nothing.
So it's part of the value of the function.
So it's part of the vacuum structure.
The diagram has a value.
That value is a contribution
to the vacuum energy.
Let's not try to understand
precisely why that's so.
But just like the diagram
which is attached to the particle here
shifts the energy of the particle,
a diagram like this
in free-floating space
would shift the energy of a vacuum.
The question is,
how do you know
how much energy is in the vacuum?
The question is,
does it shift it up or down?
And we're going to find out
that the answer is different
for bosons and fermions.
So, let's think about
the sign,
just the sign
of a diagram which looks like this
for fermions or bosons.
Now amazingly,
without doing any work at all,
we can prove
the desired result,
which I will show you now.
No work at all.
Very little.
Here's the way we do it.
Let's start
with the boson case.
Well, let's start,
we can take both cases simultaneously.
And let's begin
with two loops.
In other words,
there are, what is a loop?
A loop is a pair of particles
in the subsequent annihilation of it.
Or you can just think of it
as a particle going around
in a closed loop in space-time.
You can either think of it
as a particle going around
in a closed loop in space-time,
or more physically,
less colorfully,
it's a production of a pair of particles,
a particle-antiparticle pair,
and then the annihilation.
Okay, here there are
two loops.
One loop is a positive sign
of the diagram associated
with just one loop.
It can either be positive or negative.
What about
two separate loops like this?
The Feynman diagram consisting
of two separate loops is just the product
of the Feynman diagrams for each loop
separately.
If there's a plus sign
for one loop,
then there will be a plus sign for two loops.
What about if there's a minus sign
for one loop?
There'll still be a plus sign for two loops.
So the answer for two loops
like this, disconnected loops
like this, is always positive.
Whether or not
the sign for one loop is negative.
Now, let's
do the following.
Let's assume
that our particles are fermions.
Let's break this over here
and look at it
right in the middle
at t equals zero.
While these two things are here,
let's put them
close enough together
that they almost overlap.
What happens
to the amplitude
for a system
if you interchange
two bosons?
If you take the two bosons
and exchange them?
Plus sign.
The wave function for bosons
is always symmetric,
which means if you interchange them,
plus sign.
What happens if you take two fermions
and interchange them?
Minus sign.
That's the property of fermions and bosons.
For fermions, the wave functions are anti-symmetric,
and so if you interchange the two fermions,
you get a minus sign.
For bosons, it's a plus sign.
So, we can compare two things.
And the first thing,
we take these and we don't interchange them.
That's just two loops.
And the second thing,
before closing it up,
we interchange them.
We just interchange which one is which.
What happens
if they're fermions?
If they're fermions, we get a minus sign.
If they're bosons,
we get a plus sign from here.
We've managed
to go from two loops
to one loop,
this is one loop now.
This is just one loop.
It's one loop.
We went from two loops
to one loop just by
interchanging two particles.
Two loops necessarily
has a plus sign.
If the loops involve
fermions,
then there's a sign change
when we interchange the two particles.
So a single loop like this
for fermions necessarily has
a minus sign associated with it.
A single loop for bosons
has a plus sign
in the amplitude.
The consequences of this are profound.
What it says is that
the contribution
to the vacuum energy
of a loop
of fermions
is negative.
The contribution of a loop of bosons
is positive.
That's very interesting.
We have this very strange
puzzle about the vacuum energy
that we talked about last time.
The vacuum energy, whatever it is
in nature, is very, very small.
We call it dark energy.
It's extremely small.
The amount of it in this room
is extremely negligible.
And
the naive calculation
in quantum field theory
would give an answer 123 orders
of magnitude larger.
It is at least
at minimum interesting
that the quantum field theory answer
can either be positive or negative
and that it's negative for fermions
and positive for bosons.
The answer depends on all kinds of details
about the particle. It depends on the mass
of the particle and other things.
It depends on its charge. It
depends on all sorts of things.
But at least we've encountered
a way to be able
to get both plus signs and minus signs.
The fact that they cancel out
to 123 decimal places
is bizarre, but at least
we have the possibility
of canceling contributions.
Bosons,
all things being equal,
will give equal means
the same mass, the same charge.
All things being equal,
a boson and a fermion
will give
the same contribution to the vacuum energy
except one with a plus sign
and one with a minus sign.
Now,
that does not explain
why the vacuum energy is zero.
But it does perhaps
create a thought in your head.
Perhaps there is
a lot of cancellation between fermions
and bosons.
What it would take to have an exact cancellation
would be,
we're going to discuss this,
you would necessarily have to have for every boson
a fermion
with exactly the same mass.
These diagrams do depend on the mass
of the particle.
We don't have to know the details
of how they depend on the mass of the particle.
But,
if for every boson
we have a fermion
with exactly the same mass
and the same properties
in every other respect,
then we could imagine
or we could conceive
that the theory might exactly
cancel out
the vacuum energy.
That's one of the things
that supersymmetric theories can do.
I will tell you later what a supersymmetric theory is.
I haven't told you yet.
But that's one of the things
that supersymmetric theories can do.
They can cancel out precisely
the contribution
to the vacuum energy.
Now, we know in nature,
we know with absolute certainty
that
there is not
for every particle
an image or reflection
particle for every boson.
There is not a fermion with the same mass
and for every
and vice versa.
We know that.
But we know
that there is not
a particle in nature
with the same electric charge
as the electron
but which has the opposite
which is a boson instead of a fermion.
We would know if there were.
We would know with certainty.
And the way we would know
is because in collisions, for example,
electron
positrons come in
and an electron
is a positron.
What happens to an electron at E-E plus?
What do they make when they collide?
A virtual photon.
Now,
if there was a
partner, let's call it a partner,
to the electron, which was a
boson with exactly the same charge,
then it could be produced
let's draw this dotted line,
then it could be produced from the virtual
photon
with exactly the same probability
as the electron.
And we know this doesn't happen.
Just go in a laboratory,
scatter an electron and a positron,
and what comes out is an electron and a positron.
Not a
a boson
with the same
mass and charge.
So we know that in fact in nature
there is not this symmetry
or this reflection symmetry
it's not a reflection in space,
but reflection of boson into fermion.
We know that that's not true.
But still it's interesting to come to the conclusion
that we have to contemplate the fact
that if we had a theory
which was sufficiently symmetric
we'll discuss what we mean by
sufficiently symmetric soon
but if it was sufficiently symmetric
between bosons and fermions
we would at least have a chance
of canceling out all this vacuum energy.
We would at least have a chance.
So it's a thought.
A thought to keep in mind.
Another thought to keep in mind.
Can it help us at all
with
the self energy
of bosons?
Here we have
these Feynman diagrams
which
give rise to
quadratic divergences
in the mass of
a boson.
Even if the mass of the boson
even if the bare mass of the boson
was initially zero
in other words the bare mass
these diagrams would create huge masses
for the bosons.
That's a problem.
That's a problem for all the reasons I said.
We'd like to get rid of that problem.
We would like to create a theory
in which bosons
don't get this huge amount of mass
from renormalization
or from whatever we want to call it.
We already have a theory
in which fermions don't get
these huge amounts of masses.
Remember we discussed a few minutes ago
that for fermions
because of this left-right
switch
fermions
in many situations
the self energy
of a fermion
will not be infinite.
For example if you start with a fermion
with no mass at all
it will not get this big mass.
Now supposing for some reason
your theory was concocted
in such a way
that even after all this
renormalization takes place
even after all the worst looking Feynman
diagrams you can imagine
there was enough symmetry
enough structure in the theory
that made certain
that the fermions and the bosons
traveled in pairs
and always had exactly
the same mass, the partners.
Then because
the fermions don't
get any mass
if they didn't start with any
it must also be true of the bosons.
Why?
Well, I'm not saying that we
can make such a theory
on the face of it, it seems
like we can't make such a theory
because obviously the bosons
do get big masses from self interaction
and the fermions don't.
But, here's what you can imagine
as an example
take the various Feynman diagrams
which contribute
to the self energy of the boson
you might have
a Feynman diagram
as an illustration
which looks like this
but you might have another Feynman diagram
these are all bosons
where what runs around in the center here
is a fermion
boson going around the loop
fermion going around the loop
fermions and bosons
always have opposite signs
for these loops
so one can think then
one can imagine
that if there was enough symmetry
and if every stage
of that symmetry was correctly preserved
in detail
the cancellation
of the self energies
of the bosons
might also be exact
ah
this cancellation of the
self energy for the fermions
that's exact
if it starts zero, it ends zero
if there was
such a symmetry between fermions
and bosons which was rigidly enforced
by the mathematics of the theory
of the fermion
then we might imagine
that there are theories
where the bosons do not
get these huge
self energies
that in itself is not good enough
we know that there is
not an exact
mass equivalence
between fermions and bosons
but it's a start
let's take a little break
let's take a break for a few minutes
so to zeroth order
the hypothesis is
not that there is
when I say to zeroth order
I don't mean in the mathematical sense
I mean in
some rough approximation
to what the story is
that
for every particle in nature
there is a partner
of the opposite
somethingness
the opposite of the other
the opposite
fermi-boson-ness
bosonosity, I don't know what the right word is
you know what I mean, for every fermion in nature
like the electron
there is another particle
which is a boson with integer spin
with the same
no, with the same charge
yes, with the same charge
same electric charge and so forth
now I would say
with the same mass, but we know that's not true
ok
so not with the same
mass
and for every boson there is a fermion
for every fermion there is a boson
this would entail basically doubling
the spectrum of all of the
element of particles
how about the fact
that they don't have exactly the same
mass
in fact their masses are going to be quite different
well if the masses
were equal
we would discover that all of this
bad junk cancels out
exactly
if the masses are almost but not quite equal
we still might have a lot of cancellation
perhaps not a complete cancellation
but an approximate cancellation
if the masses were not exactly equal
we don't care for example
that there might be
some self energy
for these bosons
we just don't want it to be huge
so a diagram like this
and a diagram like that
is a good example
of the fact that
a diagram like this and a diagram like that
will not exactly cancel
unless the masses running around
in the loop here are exactly the same
but if they're not exactly the same
but close
we might expect a good deal of cancellation
approximate cancellation
enough cancellation
to keep from getting this explosively large
answer
and in fact we will talk about supersymmetry
supersymmetry is nothing but
well
it is in fact much more
among other things
it is this idea
that every particle has a partner
of the opposite statistics
is the right word
statistics means fermion-ness or boson-ness
that's what supersymmetry is
it's a symmetry
which relates fermions to bosons
in such a way
that every boson has its fermionic partner
its fermionic superpartner
they come in superpartner pairs
and
with
precise
mass equivalents of the particles
partners
we would have precise cancellation
of this kind of thing
of the vacuum energy and so forth
with almost
degeneracy
degeneracy means equality of masses
we can have approximate
cancellation
that's the working hypothesis
that the things which control
and keep
these phenomena from running away
and being enormously large
is cancellation
between fermions
and bosons
now we are going to
say more about it
and perhaps even do a little
bit of the mathematics of it
it's extremely abstract
as I said
that doesn't mean difficult
it just means abstract
but
that's the
zeroth order idea
every particle comes equipped
with a superpartner
those superpartners have never been
discovered in the laboratory
not one of them
not a single one of them
has ever been discovered in the laboratory
the implication is
they must be a good deal heavier
I showed you
how you might detect the superpartner
of the electron
you collide a pair of electrons
you create a virtual photon
and then you create
the particles which are the partners of the electrons
the fact that they have never been discovered
means
that no experiment
has ever had enough energy
to create these particles
these particles must be quite massive
how massive?
basically at the edge of detectability
beyond the edge of detectability
that means
hundreds of gev
hundreds of times the mass of the proton
now is this
really as far fetched as
that sounds very far fetched
that we just by accident
all the particles
all the partners happen to be
too heavy to be seen
you know that really sounds
like really
not good
practice
well it's not really that bad
because when you look at these supersymmetric theories
what you discover
is that some of the particles
have the natural
not natural tendency
the property
the natural property
that the only way that they can get mass
is from the Higgs phenomenon
others can have mass
without the Higgs phenomenon
it turns out
in these theories just mathematically
that exactly half the particles
some of them fermions
some of them bosons
necessarily owe their mass to the Higgs phenomenon
which is another way of saying
they must be massless
there is spontaneous symmetry breaking
of the electroweak of the Higgs boson phenomena
and the other half
are allowed to have mass without that
so it's almost
natural to say that half the particles
might be a good deal more massive
than the other half
it is
for most of us
it's a little bit of a stretch
the supersymmetry idea
it's just a little bit too
lucky
that we just haven't seen
the entirety of it yet
on the other hand
there is some rationale
for why the particles that we've seen
happen to be the ones
which have low enough mass to be seen
and why the ones we haven't seen
could conceivably have higher mass
so we have to wait and find out
but that's kind of what LHC
was designed
to find out
originally it was designed
to detect the Higgs boson
but
by now
I think it's generally conceded
well the Higgs boson is going to be there
generally conceded
and it turns out to be the hardest thing
to discover in the list of things
that you might want to discover
the much easier thing
and in a sense more profound
and much more
um
interesting
from the point of view that
we don't know if it's there or not
but it's going to be studied
so what's going to be studied is collisions
at high enough energy
to produce these superpartners
if the superpartners are low enough mass
to be detected
now first question
how do we know that they're not
way off at enormous mass
what would happen
through this cancellation
if half of the particles
were at enormously large mass
how massive
I don't know
the Planck mass or something
then the cancellation
would be extremely bad
and it would be just as bad
as not having these heavy particles
at all or practically as bad
and
instead of having
infinite self energies
you would have self energies which were
as big as the Planck mass
so if you want
this supersymmetry
to play the role of somehow
protecting you against
enormously large self energy corrections
the mass difference
between the bosons and the fermions
cannot be too big
in fact a couple of hundred
GeV beyond that
the cancellation
would be too poor
to have a decent explanation
of why the self energy of the Higgs boson
was not too big
too big for experimental reasons
so
if
the role of supersymmetry
is to keep
the Higgs boson
from getting much much too much mass
then the difference
between the masses of the particles
and their superpartners cannot be all that big
it has to be
roughly speaking within
the experimental range of the LHC
that's the logic
of what's going on
superpartners
and their symmetry to protect
having the Higgs boson
dragged up to enormously high energy
and everything else with it
that's the role of the superpartners
the masses of the particles in the superpartners
are known not to be
equal
but how different can they be
and still do the job
that they were intended to do
and the answer is
not too far from experimental
detectability
yeah question
let's start over here
what you were saying is that
in the aggregate
I hope the terminology is correct
the statistics of the fermions
and the bosons
on a universal scale must roughly
even out or there would be
different
measures of vacuum energy
is that correct
that is different than saying
vacuum energy is not really our problem
I just illustrated vacuum energy
as one thing that supersymmetry can do
we're really more interested
in the self energy
of the bosons
of the Higgs bosons
what does it mean in the aggregate
a whole bunch of
yeah they all have to be
close to the
the mass splittings
between the particles
and the superpartners
cannot be too big
but that's different than saying
every fermion and boson
need to have some relationship
the aggregate in other words
no no oh oh oh
I know what you're asking
right one possibility
is that in aggregate
they cancel
that would not require
an exact matching
between fermions and bosons
it would just require the sum of all fermions
to approximately cancel against
the sum of all bosons
that's deemed to be
an accidental cancellation
as
uncomfortable and as
surprising and
fine tuned
as the original problem was
you could say well at least the fermions
give you the opportunity to have
some negative signs and that's true
they at least give you the opportunity
but if it was just a question of an
in aggregate cancellation
then you would say well this was
an extraordinary exceptionally lucky accident
but if you can build theories
if you can build theories
where this cancellation is more
natural
if you can build theories with a higher
at the moment the way I stated it
it's not very natural
so the question is is there a mathematical framework
that contains these kind of symmetries
between fermions and bosons
which also can explain the fact
that they're not exactly equal in mass
in a natural way
and in which these
in which the symmetry between them
by natural
nobody knows
exactly what natural means
it's sort of mathematical consequence
of some reasonable postulates
that these things approximately
cancel each other
that would be much much more
satisfactory than just saying
the whole bunch of them
accidentally cancel against the whole bunch
of the other ones
one more time
that's true if you assume reductionism
if you don't assume reductionism
it may be very natural
that in aggregate they cancel out
I don't know what that really means
I know what you mean
I think that just means
we don't really understand
or know what's natural
and what's not natural
this is true
there's no question that we're
groping around for answers to these things
one hypothesis is
the mathematics of supersymmetry
and spontaneously broken supersymmetry
we haven't discussed that
but there's a notion of spontaneously broken supersymmetry
which
is a very important
we'll create mass differences
for particles
the mathematics of that conceivably
could be something which would
not conceivably, I mean we know
theories where it really will do the job
the only question is
is it the right theory
and is it the only theory which will do that
and
at the moment yes
but that doesn't mean it will stay that way
I seem to recall that before
the top and bottom quarks
were directly detected
I think it was at SLAC
the measurements of the
yields of different particles got accurate enough
that it was
likely that there were three families
well it was the tau
the tau lepton that was discovered
yes
that was the third of the leptons
well
what I think I recall
is that the Feynman diagrams
of all these different virtual particles
that can be
excited and annihilated
and the sum
of all that gives a
measure of what I'm going to call the yield
is the accuracy of the
particle physics now getting to the
point where you can see anything
ok good good that's a good question
here let me phrase the question a little bit
differently
good
that is a very very good question let's come back
to this electron positron story
and superpartners as an illustration
I said there wasn't enough
energy or at least it had better
be that the superpartners
are heavy enough that current
experiments have not had enough energy
to create them
but you might expect you might
ask are there some possibly indirect
evidences the kind of indirect
evidence might be something like this
here's a Feynman diagram
with a
here's electron
positron collide
create
I don't know how to draw the
superpartners let's just draw the superpartners
with dotted lines
but there really isn't enough
energy to create the
superpartners so they have to annihilate
again and that means we just
think of this as a
virtual process
which violates energy conservation
a little bit for a short time
now you might ask well
doesn't this diagram modify
slightly what the other
electron positron
process is like
and can't you detect that difference
so it becomes a question of high
precision
what's called high precision electro
weak or high precision
phenomenology
of the particle
physics where you don't actually
look for the particles but you look
in very high precision experiments
that are already done
you look for evidence
of this kind of thing
well what I can tell you is
to some extent
the answer is that these high
precision experiments do constrain
things and they really are
pushing you to the edge of the parameter
space
in other words it's getting a little
dicey as to whether
you can really fit supersymmetric
particles
into the theory it's still
by no means
ruled out by no means ruled
out by these high precision electro weak
experiments but it's a very good
question
I think the answer
is if we would have
an electron positron
collider
with
at you know
oh I don't know energy of maybe
I'm not sure about
my numbers here but a few times larger
than slack
we might be able to do very high precision
experiments and rule out
supersymmetry on the basis of high precision
experiments we don't
have so why an electron positron
collider incidentally why is that better
for high precision and the answer
is electrons and positrons
what do you collide
at the large hadron collider
hadrons
protons basically
protons are a mess
they consist of several quarks and what you're
really trying to do is collide quarks together
and
it's a mess
it's a much more messy thing than
two elementary particles colliding
together like an electron and positron
so an electron positron collider
is a much better machine for
high precision if we had
such a machine now at
oh I don't know
1 gev or something like that
we could probably do business with a high precision
end of it but we don't
what we have you know like Donald Rumsfeld
said we go with the machine that we have
and
laughter
you know it's the things that we
don't know if we don't know it
right knowns
known knowns and the unknown knowns
laughter
if the probability of the
process
electron positron annihilating
and then creating two super particles
is a little bit different from
the other way
wouldn't it make sense
the other way being what
two super particles colliding and creating
well we have to get the super
particles before we can do the experiment
that's what I'm getting to if there was a universe
where you had a lot of super particles
they would go down wouldn't they
yeah
because it wants to be in a lower
energy state yeah
these super particles are not expected to be
stable they're expected to be rather
unstable they will decay
to known things fairly
quickly so the likelihood
that there's remnant
super partners of the electron
floating around in space
not likely they will have decayed
long ago
so I think the answer
is that
there's good reason to believe that there are no
freely floating around
you'd have to make them somehow
how do you make them by having
enough energy to make them to overcome
their mass
and that's what we're trying to do
I thought the super partners
were one of the candidates for the dark matter
oh
so that seems
at odds with what you just said
it is
possible that one
super partner might
be stable
the reason one because
they have to decay to something
alright
in many theories they have to decay
to something which is still a super partner
you can't get rid of all super partners
so yes but those super partners
might and very likely would be
electrically neutral the reason
is because any kind of electric charge
is likely to make them even
heavier so it's quite likely
that whatever
the stable super partner
is called the lightest super partner
the LSP the lightest super partner
the lightest super partner very likely
is electrically uncharged
that doesn't mean it's undetectable
you would detect it in the laboratory
but it wouldn't be this thing
here
the lightest super partner may well be stable
it may well be
the dark energy
but most likely there would only be one
of them which would be stable
so all the remnant particles in the universe
that were super partners would just
decay to that one
and that one if it were not electrically
charged would not be so easy to detect
but you would
but in principle yes
you would detect it
How do you know that
it's not the coupling constant that's keeping you
from seeing these things
maybe they have a different coupling constant
no no no one of the
things which is very very important
ok so that's an interesting question
um
let's draw some diagrams let's take
two
Feynman diagrams
I'll do it for the vacuum energy
but we could also do it in principle
for
oh no let's do it
yeah let's do it for the vacuum energy
here's two Feynman diagrams
one of them
involving
the electron going in a loop
and the other involving
the super partner of the electron
going in a loop they will have opposite sign
and they will cancel each other
if they're well matched
ok if they're well matched
if they're matched enough in mass
now let's draw another Feynman diagram
in which a photon goes here
and a photon goes here
will they match and
will they cancel each other yes
they will still cancel each other but
only if the electric charge of the electron
and the electric charge of the super partner
are equal
otherwise there will be a discrepancy
between these two
numerical discrepancy between them
which would lead again to
a big divergent answer
so it's important in these arguments
that you follow
through at every level
and make sure that the cancellation takes place
and that typically requires
the electric charge of the partners
to be the same as
the electric charge of the particles
so yeah
um
what is the partner of the photon
with what it's got mass
the real partner of the photon has mass
now how
hmm
this is what I'm telling you
we do not have a
collection of particles which have the same
mass as the known particles
we don't so supersymmetry
is not a precise thing
at best it's an approximation
it's an approximation
in which in the exact supersymmetric
theory if it existed
the super partner of the photon
would be massless
it's not
these particles have names incidentally
typically if you have a
if an ordinary particle is a boson
then the super partner is an eno
for example
the photon partner would be a fotino
the w boson
its partner would be a wino
or a we-no
the z particle
would be a zeno I suppose
and um
for the super partners of the bosons
they're typically scalar particles
and so you put an
s in front of their name
so that leads to disgusting names
like the selectron
which is you know not nice
the super partners have
peculiar names
uh
the gravitino would be a
fermionic version of the graviton
uh
what are the names
what are the peculiar names are there
there's a hexeno which would be a fermionic
version of the higgs particle
enos are always fermions
uh
except when they're
ordinary fermions then they're not enos
they're just electrons quarks
what would you
expect the bosonic partner
of a boson to be
a squark
yeah
so there are squarks and enos
of all kinds
and none have ever been detected yet
I think they're going to be detected
my guess is that this is going to work
but I don't know we'll find out
I'm just guessing
let's talk about one last thing before we go home
now
how is the spin
of the ordinary particle
related to the super particles
okay
the
super particles
if the ordinary
particles are bosons
then the super particles are always fermions
so if the
ordinary particle is a
boson then typically the super
partner is a half spin
and that's true whether it be a
whether the original particle is a scalar
or a gauge boson
the partner is a half spin
particle
if the ordinary particle is a half spin
particle then typically the partner
of it is a
scalar particle which means no spin
but it's always this interplay
they always differ by half a unit
of spin
so if the ordinary particle is half spin
the usual the super
partner would be spin zero
if the ordinary particle is spin zero
like the Higgs boson
then the corresponding fermion
would be a half spin
so they always differ by a half unit
yeah
would these new scalar particles be
subject to
which would what
if they were new scalar super partners
would they be subject
to spontaneous symmetry breaking
in principle the answer
could be yes
in fact that would be a very bad idea
yeah
so that must not happen
uh
right so
let me repeat the question
the question is if there are all these additional scalar
particles around that means scalar
fields and scalar fields are things
which we've seen can have the spontaneous symmetry
breaking phenomena
could we tolerate having an
additional some other spontaneous
symmetry break down no we couldn't
that would be a bad thing to happen
so that
that would not be good
so the fermion then would be
the super partner of the Higgs
the Higgsino
yeah would that have any special properties
well I suppose
it has all kinds of special properties
but nothing I mean you know to an
experimental particle physicist I'm sure we could
conjure up all sorts of special properties
but nothing
hmm
well
remember the fourth power
is simply another way of talking about a Feynman
diagram where two particles come in and two particles
go out so there will be
matching interactions one of the
things that has to match are the
interactions of the particles which we haven't talked about
at all yet
so there will be matching
phenomena to take the place of the
five fourth terms yeah but it won't
be exactly what you think but
related yeah
the
theorem about the rotations
does it hold
in higher or lower dimensions
basically
wait say that again
the theorem that says that the rotation
two pi rotations
oh you're asking whether there are higher
and lower dimensional versions of it
yeah there are
uh
the answer is yes
there are
it's an odd even
dimension business peculiar
discrepancy between
odd and even dimensions whether there
is or is not
an analog to that
there can be
analogs to it
because it seems easily in two dimensions
it wouldn't happen right in two dimensions
in two dimensions it doesn't happen
right
uh in two dimensions
there are things which are in between
fermions and bosons
they're called anyons
any meaning any value of the spin
so in two dimensions
two spatial dimensions
there's uh there's a generalization
to any spin
called anyons
and they happen in condensed matter physics
uh excitations in certain
condensed matter systems
have basically arbitrary spin
um
but this is not for us to
to discuss now
uh
okay i was going to talk about one more thing
um
just about
whether we
what would the world be like
if it were exactly supersymmetric
interesting question supposing it was
exactly supersymmetric
how different would the world be
how different would we be
how different would biology be
how different would chemistry be
and the answer is very different
so let me just show you
why it is not
possible certainly we
don't live in a supersymmetric world
supersymmetric meaning exact
degeneracy exact
equivalence between the masses of the particles
and the superpartners we do not live in
such a world could we live in such
a world would such a world
be one in which
ordinary chemistry
would exist for example
biology anything else that we are familiar
with
i think not
and let me show you what would happen to chemistry
among other things
atoms of course
have electrons
if there was a superpartner
to the electron
it would be a boson right
it would be a boson
it would have exactly the same
mass and charge of the electron
if we lived in such a supersymmetric world
there would also be
a partner to the photon
we would call it the photino
and because the photon is massless
the photino would also have to be
exactly massless
so let me show you
what would happen to an atom
not a
hydrogen or a helium atom but let's
start with some atom
with three electrons
or four electrons or five electrons
in a hydrogen atom of course
the
single electron moving in it
moves in the lowest orbit in the lowest borer orbit
in helium
we have two electrons
also both moving
in the lowest borer orbit
so both hydrogen and helium
the electrons all move
in the lowest orbit
in the stable form of these elements
let's go next to lithium
lithium has an extra electron
and the extra electron
is in the next orbit out
because of the
what's the principle which says that the lithium atom
can't have three electrons in the same orbit
Pauli exclusion principle
Pauli exclusion principle is more than enough to
make a electron move in the same orbit
it's most definitely associated with the fact
that the electrons are fermions
now
what would happen to this outer electron
remember the outer electron
has more energy
than the inner electrons
it wants to go down to the
lowest level but it can't get in there
because it's being blocked
by the other ones and it just doesn't want
to allow another electron
in there by the Pauli exclusion principle
how could the
how would it incidentally how
would it get down to the lowest level
it would get down to the
lowest level by emitting a photon
which would carry off some energy
and the electron drop down
to the lower level
but it's blocked it can't happen
now
imagine there was also a photino
which was also massless
what could happen to this electron
not what would happen
sorry the electron
moving around
would emit a photino
not a photon a massless photino
of exactly the same
properties or similar properties
to a photon and then what would it become
a selectron
it has to change this is a fermion
here's a fermion
and a fermion gets projected out
what has to be left over
a boson
right if a fermion
comes in and emits a fermion
it has to become a boson
but what would that boson be
it would be the super partner
of the electron which is called
the selectron
now the selectron is a boson
it has no trouble getting into the lowest orbit
so it drops down to the lowest orbit
and you would not have a lithium atom
you would have a
slithium atom
or something
where
but the main thing is
that the electron would be replaced
by something that drops down to the lowest
borer orbit
now think about a big atom
chemistry what does chemistry do to
the physics of the valence electrons
valence electrons
what would happen to the valence electrons
in a big atom
they would all
just drop down
by the same mechanism they would all
drop down to the lowest energy orbit
and
all crowd in on the lowest
energy orbit to the extent
that they can get in there
they would not be blocked by
Fermi statistics and so they would
all sit in the lowest energy they could
get into
and so what kind of thing
would you have at the center here
at the center you would have a
bosa condensation of
selectrons
rather than an atom with valence electrons
you would have an entirely different thing
now I don't know what the world would be like
I just know whatever it would be like
it would not have conventional chemistry
it would have nothing like conventional chemistry
whether
you can
use such atoms as
tinker toys to create molecules
and so forth I rather doubt
they're all going to be crowded in
at the
small distances near the nucleus
I rather doubt that there's
anything resembling ordinary
chemistry of molecules and so forth
but I don't think anybody's ever worked this out
incidentally what the world would be like
in such a super symmetric but it would not
resemble our world
so the selectron would limit
would emit a
a fotino
the electron would emit
if there was an electron
if there was in other
words if we started with something
that looked awfully much like a
lithium atom
it would very quickly become a slithium atom
with a fotino traveling out
wouldn't there be a coupling constant
associated with that
yeah but yes yes
so it could be hard to do
it could be what
yeah but we know what that coupling constant is
it's the electric charge
so we know it's not hard to compute
what would be
the lifetime of a lithium atom
if the electron could drop down
it would be short
it would be just a
microsecond or something
so one can calculate
and these would not be terribly small numbers
they would not be terrible
so no you're not going to
get away from it that way
so it's an interesting fact
that
why isn't the world super symmetric
I don't know
but I know that
at least I couldn't be here if it were
so it's
so let's assume that
if there are super symmetric particles
then the symmetry is
reasonably badly broken
and so we have a big mass separation
well okay
now the question is what's big and what's small
what are we comparing with
now if we compare with the mass of the proton
it's big
if we compare with the unification scale
or the Planck scale
it's terribly tiny
so the question is
what do we think the
reason for this broken symmetry is
in other words how come we're here
well one possible answer is
if the symmetry weren't broken we
wouldn't be here to ask it
right
I think that's the best answer we have
are they clear
yeah they're clear
on the other hand it's not very hard to break
these symmetries
it's not very mathematically terribly hard to break them
it's rather generic
but not that generic
there certainly are completely super symmetric theories
they're the ones we understand best incidentally
the mathematical theories
I'm not because of these
weak interaction issues
just as a mathematical fact
the quantum field theories
that are best understood
are the super symmetric ones
they have so much special structure to them
that they often can be almost exactly solved
much more is known about them
than the others
they have all sorts of fabulous
and fascinating theories
that have a very special
structure to them
yeah
okay
next week
more on supersymmetry
we'll have supersymmetry until you're sick of it
for more please visit us at
stanford.edu