Stanford University.
First we start with symmetries and I'll
remind you of a few things about
symmetries because supersymmetry, if
nothing else, is a symmetry.
Symmetries always relate things.
And what they do is they relate things
which are related by being transformed in some way.
A particular symmetry is left-right symmetry. My
left hand and my right hand are symmetric
and if the world and I
and everything about me has left-right symmetry,
then my right hand and my left hand are symmetric.
And my left hand and my right hand are symmetric.
And my left hand weighs exactly the same thing as my
left hand, would be exactly as strong as my left hand,
and would be in every
respect identical to my left hand.
And in that sense, symmetries relate objects,
objects which may be different but symmetric.
In particular, those objects that are related
by a symmetry generally have the same mass.
So let's talk about symmetries.
So let's talk a little
bit about the mathematics of symmetries.
We've already talked about some symmetries, in
particular things like rotation symmetry in space,
and now I'm thinking about continuous symmetries.
Whether supersymmetry is a continuous symmetry or
not is a question which has no answer.
It has no answer because it doesn't fall into the
category, really, of things where the question actually makes sense.
But let's just review a little bit about...
symmetries.
Symmetries are operations on a system which are
described quantum mechanically by, first of all, operations,
but operations are described by operators.
Operators on state vectors.
We start with a state vector.
Whatever it happens to be, I don't care what kind
of system it is, it's described by a state vector.
And we apply some symmetries.
Symmetry operation.
The most well-known symmetry operation that
I can think of is rotation.
Actually, I can think of an
even simpler one, just translation of space.
Then the operation would simply move
an object from one place to another.
But let's take the case of rotation
as a more representative example for the moment.
What's the mathematical symbol
to represent a transformation?
A unitary operator.
A unitary matrix or unitary operator.
This unitary operator here
could represent rotation in space.
You would have to indicate what the axis was,
and you would have to indicate what the angle was.
But once you did so,
there would be a unitary operator.
That unitary operator acts on any state to give a
new one, which is a rotated version of the same thing.
So, that's the first one.
But it operates on states, not on space.
It's not rotating states.
It's the operation of rotating an object.
It acts on objects.
It acts on states, but states mean collections of objects.
And this is the operation which rotates everything.
It just rotates everything in space.
So, it takes whatever the state is.
I'll give an example.
The state might consist of the mathematical representation of
a particle over here and a particle over here.
Alright?
So, this is a state which represents two
particles, one over here and one over here.
A rotation about an axis.
A rotation, incidentally, always takes place about an axis.
Let's say about this axis.
It will simply give you a new state in which this
particle has been rotated to here and this one to here.
And so, it's a new
state with a particle over here.
And so, it's a new state with a
particle over here and a particle over here.
But isn't the state vector
an element of a Hilbert space?
Yes.
So, that's an infinite dimensional vector.
It is.
And are we rotating the Hilbert
space or are we rotating three-dimensional?
Both.
It's the rotation in Hilbert space
that represents the rotation in space.
It's like a next step up.
Yeah.
Right.
That's right.
Both.
So, it's a new state.
Right.
But this is the rotation that
we do on the Hilbert space.
Now, it's not strictly a rotation.
It's a unitary transformation, which
is similar to a rotation.
So, it's both a transformation of the Hilbert space
and it represents the act of rotation in space.
Okay.
All right.
Now, as I said, U represents a
rotation about an axis, about a particle.
Right.
So, it's a rotation about
an axis, about a certain angle.
There's particular transformations, which are
especially interesting to us, that the
infinite test...
Oh, well, before that, let's talk about,
very briefly, about the properties that a
symmetry operation has to satisfy.
The most important is that it has to be unitary.
Unitary means...
Let's see.
It's unitary.
That it's Hermitian conjugate is its own inverse.
This is the unique property, which
says that state vectors maintain their length.
It's actually just probability, conservation of
probability that this vector should have
the same length in the Hilbert space, the
same norm in the Hilbert space as the original
for every vector.
That's the condition that U be unitary.
It's why it's called unitary.
called unitary. Well, it's called unitary. All
right, now there's a special family of
these which are very small rotations, rotations by
very small angles. Now every place I say
rotation, you could substitute other interesting
group operations, but let's stick for the
moment with just ordinary rotations. The
infinitely small rotations, infinitely small means by
an infinitely small angle, a rotation by no
angle at all, in other words, no rotation,
that's not represented by u equals zero.
U equals zero is not unitary. It's represented
by u equals 1. So an infinitely small rotation
is just u equals 1. Well, supposing you want
to rotate a little bit, not quite 1.
then you have to add something,
and if the angle is very small,
let's say the angle is
epsilon, epsilon is a small number,
then you have to add epsilon times something,
and in order to make it unitary, you
have to add i times a Hermitian operator.
Call it L.
L remembers the angle of rotation is epsilon,
but L has to be
indexed by a direction of space.
So this could be rotation about the x-axis, for example.
It could be rotation about the y-axis,
or it could be rotation about the z-axis.
Or it could be rotation about some other axis.
Or a sum, perhaps, x, y, and z?
Well, if you sum them, you wind
up getting a rotation about some axis,
which, yeah, intermediate axis, that's right.
So there's three basic...
There's three basic ones out of which
you can build all the small rotations.
An arbitrary axis is just a linear
combination of rotation about x, y, and z.
All right, that's the...
And it's easy to check that if
L is Hermitian, then U is unitary,
at least to the leading order in epsilon.
We're going to study things to
orders, to lowest orders in epsilon.
Now, one of the most important things about a group...
a group of symmetries is the commutator algebra.
It's a mathematical concept, the
commutator algebra of the generators.
These are called the generators.
The small...
These are called the infinitesimal generators, the Ls,
and they satisfy a commutator algebra.
I'll tell you first what a commutator algebra is,
and then I'll show you
how it's connected to these transformations.
First of all,
mathematically, what is a commutator algebra?
It's basically you take the independent generators,
in this case, rotation about
the x, y, and z axis.
You call them Lx, Ly, and Lz,
or better yet, just L sub i.
And a commutator algebra is
just a closed set of relations
that if you commute any one of the
Ls with any other one of the Ls,
you get back something proportional to an L again.
There are some constants that appear here.
Alright?
So, for example, let me write down
exactly what you would have for Lx, Ly.
You would have Lz here, but that's not quite right.
What am I missing?
I.
And then cycle it through.
Ly, Lz equals I Lx, and so
forth, but you can summarize them all
by writing I epsilon Ijk Lk Ly Lj.
This just says epsilon Ijk is
just a symbol which is zero
if any of the two of
them are the same, Ij and k,
and it's either plus one or minus one,
depending on whether this is an even
or odd permutation of one, two, and three.
Alright, and all it says is Lx,
Ly, commutator Lx with Ly
is I Lz, and so forth.
Now, what's the meaning, what's the, what's the meaning,
the geometric meaning of these commutator algebras?
What are they saying, and why is
it important that the generators close under commutation?
The right word is they close under commutation,
which means the commutator of any
two of them is another one.
This is called a commutator algebra.
Why is this important?
So what it really has to
do with is the following operation.
You take, you take a rotation represented by a U.
Now you take another rotation about
some other axis by some other angle.
Let's start it out, U, and
then you multiply it by V.
What is that?
That corresponds to a rotation about an
axis followed by another rotation about another axis.
Then you undo the first one.
So what, so far what we've done is rotate, rotate, then rotate back along the,
the original axis by minus the angle that we originally rotated, and then undo V.
Does that give back no rotation at all?
Does it give back no rotation?
No.
The answer is no.
If you rotate about an axis
and then rotate about another axis,
and then undo the first
one, and undo the second one,
it is not the original configuration.
It is not equal to the identity.
It is itself a small, another rotation.
Just, most of you have seen
a demonstration of this sort of thing.
What happens if you rotate a thing about the X
axis, then rotate about the Y, I can't do this.
But you rotate about the X axis, rotate about the
Y axis, now I've forgotten which the X axis is.
And do it again and come back.
You'll come back to some other configuration.
Consider an airplane and roll pitch and yaw.
What's that?
That makes it easy.
That's true.
I hope that was the idea of
an airplane where I can sense the commutator.
Right.
All right.
Let's check what you get.
In other words, what you get on
the right-hand side is some other rotation.
I won't give it a name.
It's another U.
But let's see what happens if
we do it for small rotations.
Let's check, in fact, exactly
what happens for small rotations.
And let's take the case of a rotation about
X, a rotation about Y, reverse the rotation about X,
and then reverse the one about Y,
but each one of them being small rotations.
And let's see what we get.
You know, I think that there's something that
you know so well that you haven't mentioned.
But when you did the U dagger U equals Y,
that could also be written as U dagger equals U inverse.
It does.
And so when you see something like you
just wrote up there, you're doing inverses of daggers.
Good.
So let me rewrite it
then the way you would like.
We started with U.
Then we did V.
And then we undid U.
I wrote U dagger.
You would like me to write U inverse.
I just like people to be aware of that.
Right.
I know you do.
So do I.
That's the same operation.
Same operation.
And incidentally, if we were just rotating about a
given axis, let's say one axis, the X axis,
we're never going to go from X to Y.
What would happen?
Rotation by X, rotation by another X, then
undo the first one, then undo the second one.
What did we come back to?
No rotation at all.
Okay?
So if we do everything in
one plane, we don't get anything interesting.
It's if we do it in
two planes that we get something.
The only thing you can do with that is you can put one of the
Vs, the second Vs on the other side, and if U inverse Vs, U equals V.
You can do lots of things.
Let's see what happens.
We start with U.
That's 1 plus I epsilon LX.
That's rotation about an angle of epsilon.
Then we're going to rotate about the Y
axis, and I'm going to use a different angle.
I'm going to call the angle delta now.
1 plus I delta LY.
Then we're going to undo the first one.
That's 1 minus I epsilon LX.
Incidentally, for small rotations, the infinitesimal, the
inverse operator is just 1 minus I.
1 minus I epsilon instead of 1 plus.
And then finally, we undo the last one.
1 minus I delta LY.
And let's see if we can
figure out what we're going to get.
There's a lot of terms
when you multiply these all out.
And some of them will get better.
Some of them will get mixed up with others.
Some of them will be order 1.
In fact, they'll only be 1, which is order 1.
It's 1 times 1 times 1 times 1.
The next thing will be order delta.
Let's see what's there to order delta.
Just delta by itself.
Well, there's going to be I delta of
Y times the rest of the 1s, right?
So there'll be a minus I delta
of Y times 1 times 1 times 1.
But then there'll be plus I delta Y.
So there'll be 1 times 1 times 1 times 1.
So they'll cancel.
Same thing of the I epsilon X.
There'll be 1 times minus I
epsilon X times 1 times 1.
But then there'll be the
opposite from this one over here.
So the things to order delta and
the things to order epsilon will cancel.
Nothing left of them.
There are things of order delta squared.
And things of order epsilon squared.
I don't want to keep track of them.
You can keep track of them another day.
What I want to keep track of
is the things of order epsilon times delta.
The things which are sensitive to the
fact that I rotated about two different axes.
One of them, the epsilon kept track
of the rotation about the X axis.
The delta kept track of
the thing about the Y axis.
So let's see what's there, what
remains there to order delta times epsilon.
Here we're going to have delta times epsilon
will always involve L Y times L X.
How many of them are there altogether?
How many delta times epsilons are there?
There's one over here.
And...
What have I missed?
I have missed this times this, right?
This one times this one?
Third term times the fourth term.
Ah, third term times the fourth term.
Yeah, third term times the fourth term.
First term times the fourth term.
You got that?
Yes, we got it.
We have the first term times the fourth term?
First term times the fourth term.
It's getting too complicated.
I need to clean it up.
Alright.
Ah, there are two terms and two terms.
That's the point.
Yeah.
Right.
Good, good.
Thank you.
Here's a delta times an epsilon with a
sign which is L Y times L X, right?
Right.
L Y times L X times minus I
times minus I I think is minus one, right?
Okay.
And then there is L
Y times L X over here.
And that comes in with what sign?
With the opposite sign.
I don't like that.
Okay.
Let's see what happens.
So that cancels this?
Does it?
Same sign or opposite sign?
Help me, help me.
Same sign.
It's the same order.
No, because I I is a minus, right?
Yeah.
So, minus I minus times minus is plus
and wait, wait, sorry, minus times minus is plus
over here and then we also have
L Y times L X over here.
The minus times the minus is a
plus times the I and a I.
Right.
So it's times two.
So it's a minus.
Yeah.
So it's minus two.
Minus two, right?
Yeah.
So it's minus two.
And now we have, that's L Y times X.
Now we have L X times L Y.
L X to the left, L Y to the right.
What do we have for that?
I hope it's twice plus two.
There are two terms with minus
sign, two terms with plus sign.
The terms with minus sign are L Y times L X
and the term with plus sign are L X times L Y,
I hope.
So let me just check it.
L Y times L X is minus times minus and L
Y and L Y times L X is plus times plus.
Those have the same sign.
Yeah.
All right.
Then there's L Y, then there's L X
times L Y and that has the opposite sign.
So there are two L Y L
Xs and two L X L Ys.
If L X and L
Y commuted, then this would cancel.
Okay.
Then this would cancel.
But the fact that these rotations don't
cancel, the fact that a rotation, another rotation,
followed by them back again, don't cancel, are
an indication that this should not be zero.
In other words, the commutator. . .
The commutator between L X and L Y is
the thing which keeps track of the fact that rotations
in different orders don't cancel out.
That's what the commutator really is.
The commutator is the non-cancellation
of operations which don't cancel.
That's what this is indicating here.
So what does this tell you?
This tells you. . . .
This is the commutator.
This is twice the commutator
of L X with L Y.
Twice the commutator of L X with L Y.
That's what's left here.
Plus one.
There's also the one.
Dr. Michael S. You know, I think that
we're off by a factor of two, because
there are really three terms with L Y L
X and one term with L X L Y.
Oh, no, no.
Dr. Michael S. That's what I get.
Dr. Michael S. Yeah.
Yeah, I think that's right.
That's what I thought.
So what is it? Just one times?
Yeah, that seems right.
There are three with one sign.
No.
Three with one order.
And one with the other order.
Remind me.
Yeah, three with L, Y, L, X.
It's because all the L, Y's are
on the left of all the L, X's.
So if you go to the L, Y,
you have two L, X's to the right.
If you go to the L,
if you're looking for...
I've done this at home a number of times
just to make sure I was ready for you today.
There's only one way to get L, X, L, Y,
and that's the middle one.
Ah.
L, X, L, Y. Right.
So that's this one.
And then there are three others.
This L, Y has two L, X's to the right.
That L, Y only has
one L, X to the right.
Do you get this?
Yeah.
Okay. Good enough.
Good enough.
I'm blind by now.
I can't do it.
Anyway, this is what you get.
You get something proportional to the commutator here.
So in other words,
the net answer,
there was an epsilon times delta.
Epsilon times delta.
No two.
All right.
L, X times L, Y,
or the commutator of L, X times L, Y,
this becomes one plus I, epsilon, delta, L, Z.
In other words,
this combination of rotations about X, Y,
then back again along X,
then back again along Y,
give you a small rotation by an angle,
epsilon times delta about the Z axis.
All right.
This is what the commutators tell you.
So whenever you have a group of transformations,
a particular continuous group of transformations,
the whole structure of the group is contained
in these infinitesimal generators,
and especially in their commutator algebra.
The commutator algebra is sort
of the group multiplication table,
but in the form of these infinitesimal generators.
All right.
That's a...
If you switch the U dagger and B dagger,
then it will equal the identity, correct?
Yeah, if you switch the middle.
Yeah.
So does this get more complicated
if you have four instead of three?
You have X, Y, and then...
Yeah.
And then there's Z, which is the third.
If you go to four, now it has to be...
It does get more complicated,
but it does get more complicated,
but if you know the commutator algebra here,
you can, in principle, figure out
how to compound together many, many little transformations.
This was just one example.
You can obviously build up any transformation
out of lots of little ones.
So if you know how the little ones combine,
that's very much knowing the properties of the group,
knowing the...
Knowing the algebra,
the whole structure of the group,
and how the parce Keith sана.
We're focused on that.
Right?
But also,
you have to consider,
for example,
know the vibration if you want to view
a lag from a random Pedrigan.
You do that.
It takes something.
You type it in the text.
You print it,
and it goes to a different duration
rather than four,
rather than two,
or you put it in the end.
OK.
So the Hebrew component
is this one,
n,
before you you know,
do a couple more things,
and the birth of
and the fact that English is so foreign is really,
and the fact that the year 8 and 9
is laminated.
Which is incredibly?
And one way,
Incidentally, in the case of rotations, L
is of course just the angular momentum.
I picked it just, there are
other transformations of space besides rotations, incidentally.
There's translations in space.
Let me fill out the rest
of the group of transformations of space.
These are the rotations, and they're
rotations, for example, about the origin.
The other things you can
do with space is to translate.
Translations are generated, again, by their
unitary transformations, but what are the
infinitesimal generators for
translation, for spatial translation?
The momentum.
That's what momentum is.
A translation, let's say about the x-axis,
where you push everything along the x-axis
by an infinitesimal amount.
That's, again, of the form
1 plus i times a parameter.
The parameter now would correspond to the
distance that you push things, the distance
that you translate.
Again, let's call it epsilon.
It's not an angle now.
It's a distance times the x component of momentum.
This would be a translation along the x-axis,
translation along the y-axis, 1 plus i epsilon
py, and so forth.
This would be the group of translations.
This would be the group of rotations.
What about commutators between rotations and translations?
Would you expect them to commute or not?
I think so.
How about commutation, first
of all, among just translations?
You translate something this way, then you
translate it this way, then you translate
it back this way, and then
you translate it back this way.
That's the commutation.
You translate it this way, translation along
x, y, invert the x, and then back.
What do you get?
The same thing.
Well, when you translate something or when
you rotate something, you first have to apply
a force to move it.
We're not talking about literally moving things.
We're talking about just imaginary transformations.
No force here.
All I'm saying is that you have to do it.
Then you have to undo what you did before.
You have to do it.
You have to do what you
did to make it do it.
You've got actually four actions involved.
You have to start it and stop it, and then
you have to start it and stop it again to
undo it.
These are not actual motions of a system.
They're just asking, what would the state of
a world be like if you displaced everything?
They're not saying, displace it.
They're saying, what would the state
be if you did displace it?
A little bit of a difference.
It's a bit of a dramatic thing.
It's mathematics, not physics.
Yeah.
Just a mathematical description of a displaced thing.
If you displace along an axis, and then
you displace along another axis, and then you
displace back along the first axis, and then
you displace back along the second axis, you
come back to the same place.
That's a property of Euclidean space.
What does that tell you about commutators of momenta?
Zero.
Commutators of momenta are zero.
Okay?
Now, let's try to see what would happen
if we take a point, first translate it.
We translate by one unit in this direction.
Now, rotate by an angle.
Okay.
So we rotate by an angle,
let's say by an angle theta.
All right?
So we rotate from here up to,
let's say, over here by this angle theta.
That's the angle theta.
And then we translate back, translate along the
same axis back, and then undo the rotation.
Where do we come to?
Do we come back to the same point?
No.
We come back to about over here someplace.
So it's clear that translations and rotations don't commute.
Translations and rotations don't commute.
And if you work it out,
it's not hard to work out.
You do little translations, little infinitesimal translations,
and you can work out what the
commutation relations are between the
rotation generators and the translation generators.
I'll tell you what they are.
They're just a commutator of LX.
Well, let's just do it in two dimensions.
LI with PJ is I epsilon IJK PK.
That's it.
But this is not important.
This is not important.
What's important is the idea that everything
is kept track of by these commutation relations.
All right.
That's the first thing about groups.
Groups are really commutator algebras
in disguise or vice versa.
Next thing about groups in quantum mechanics.
First of all, they're symmetries, but they tell
you something about the energies of different configurations.
Naively, it's clear.
Naively, it's clear what they say.
They say that if you perform one of
these symmetry operations and you really have a symmetry,
it should not change the energy of a system.
If you have an object, whatever that object is, and
it has a certain energy, and you just rotate it,
it shouldn't change its energy.
Or if you just translate
it, it shouldn't change its energy.
So if you have a legitimate symmetry,
then the conclusion should be,
that when you perform a symmetry operation,
the energy of a state shouldn't change.
Let's see what that says.
See mathematically if we can see what that says.
What the requirement is.
Okay, so let's suppose we have some state, any state,
and it happens to have energy E.
Let's say it has energy E.
It's an eigenvector of the energy.
It has a definite energy, let's call it E.
And now let's apply a small transformation to it.
Let's call it U.
Let's take U.
U is, it doesn't have to be
small, just a transformation of the appropriate kind,
translation, rotation, iso-spin transformation, anything that
corresponds to the symmetry of the system.
And now ask what the
energy of the resulting state is.
We find the energy of the resulting state,
well let's first of all say what this means.
What this means, that it's a state of given energy,
means that it's an eigenvector of the Hamiltonian,
with eigenvalue E.
Right? That's the definition in quantum mechanics
of saying a thing has a definite energy.
That the Hamiltonian acts on it
to just give the eigenvalue back.
It's an eigenvector of energy E.
Okay, now let's ask about this state.
If the original state was an eigenvector of the energy,
and we have a symmetry,
then the resulting state must also
be an eigenvector of the energy, right?
So that must say that
the Hamiltonian on this state
must be equal to the energy times the same state,
U E.
Okay?
But this is also equal
to H U E.
What did I just do?
I just said
that the energy times U times E
can be replaced by,
put the Hamiltonian over here,
why?
Because H on E just gives E times E.
Alright, so now I just subtract.
H U minus U H
on E
equals zero.
That's what the conclusion is
if a symmetry operation doesn't change the energy.
はい
So what was the first
relation that you had up there?
H or U times...
Okay, let's go through it again.
Let me go through it again.
This is tricky.
We start by saying we
have an eigenvector of the energy.
H on E equals E on E.
This says that E, the eigenvector E,
is an eigenvector of the Hamiltonian with energy E.
Okay, step number one.
All right.
Now, I assert that U times
E has exactly the same energy.
Why?
Because U is a symmetry.
It rotates or it does
something that's just really a coordinate.
It translates, it rotates.
It doesn't do anything important to the system.
This must have the same energy,
and so this must also
be an eigenvector of the Hamiltonian.
Let's write that.
H, U, E must equal E, U, E.
Okay, let's just...
Let me draw.
E is just a number,
except if it's in a vector, then it's a vector.
All right?
H times this vector here must
equal E times the same vector.
Okay?
That's the statement,
that U times E is
also an eigenvector of the energy.
Okay.
Now, E is just a number, as Michael said,
so it can be brought inside here.
It doesn't matter which side of U it's on.
It's just a number.
U times E. Fair enough?
I didn't do anything.
I just interchanged the numerical
number E with the operator U.
But now, E times the vector
E is H times the vector E.
So I can say that this is U, H, E.
Equals this one over here.
And now I come to the marvelous conclusion by
transposing that H times U minus U times E,
and then I get the same thing.
Okay?
Okay.
U times H acting on E is equal
to zero for an eigenvector of energy E.
But this has to be true not
for one particular eigenvector of the energy,
but for all eigenvectors of the energy.
For any eigenvector of the energy, this must be true.
If the energy eigenstates are a complete basis of states,
then it follows mathematically that H times U
minus U times H must itself be zero.
If something is true, if
something gives zero on every vector,
or every eigenvector of a particular operator,
then that thing must be zero.
So the conclusion is, if you have a symmetry,
it means that the symmetry
operations commute with the Hamiltonian.
All right?
So that's the signal, or
that's the conclusion, not the conclusion,
that's the criteria for whether a set
of transformations like U are symmetries or not.
They must commute with the Hamiltonian.
All right?
So here is every symmetry, whatever it is,
commutes with the Hamiltonian,
and that's equivalent to,
and that's equivalent to saying that the symmetry operations
do not change the energy of a state.
All right, so as an example,
as an example, the, um,
the, take a, take a state of a spin,
pointing in a certain direction,
rotate it,
what happens to the energy of it?
The answer is nothing.
Why not?
Because rotation is a symmetry.
Put the spin in a magnetic field.
What happens if you rotate
the spin in a magnetic field?
It will change its energy.
But the reason, of course, is because
you're not really doing a symmetry operation.
You're rotating one thing relative to
a thing which you're not rotating.
What would happen if you did a true symmetry operation?
That would mean rotate the spin
and also rotate the magnetic field.
That would not change the energy.
Okay?
Uh, same thing, for example,
you have a particle,
uh, let's say an electron.
Here's an electron in the field of a proton.
What happens if you translate the electron?
Does it, does the energy
of the electron stay the same?
Of course not.
The electron, you have to do
work to move it against the proton.
So you say, oh, translation of
the electron is not a symmetry.
No, translation of an electron
by itself is not a symmetry,
but translation of the whole thing is a symmetry.
Alright, so, um, translation being a symmetry,
rotation being a symmetry says that
those operations commute with the Hamiltonian.
Now, if every U commutes with the Hamiltonian,
let's come back to the generators.
That says that the generators commute with the Hamiltonian.
If every operator of the form 1
plus I epsilon L commutes with the Hamiltonian,
1 commutes with everything.
The commutator of 1 with anything is 0.
I and epsilon don't matter here.
It says that all of the components of
the generators of a symmetry commute with the Hamiltonian.
What else can you say
that commuting with the Hamiltonian means?
If you go back to your quantum mechanics,
Yeah.
The time derivative of the thing
which commutes with the Hamiltonian is 0.
So, one says that symmetries imply conservation laws,
or conservation laws imply
symmetries, it's not important which.
Alright, so this is, this is, I've
simply repeated everything that we've talked about before
about symmetries, but mostly to remind you of that.
Momentum conservation, angular momentum conservation,
all associated with symmetries.
And of course there are plenty of other symmetries around.
Now,
So it looks like the external
field has to have that symmetry.
Either the external field has the symmetry,
or you have to rotate the external field.
Right, right.
Okay.
But important thing is that
rotation does not change the energy.
Or not just rotation, but
symmetry operations don't change the energy.
That's the reason that the different components,
let's say we have,
uh,
electrons in orbit around a,
in a particular orbit around a nucleus.
Okay, so the orbits are
characterized by a total angular momentum
and the z component of angular momentum.
The different z components of angular
momentum can be rotated into each other.
They get mixed up with each other under rotation.
The total angular momentum, L,
doesn't change under rotation.
It's the total magnitude of the angular momentum.
But the various z components of the angular momentum,
do rotate into each other.
And the symmetry under rotation tells you
that all the different states of an atom
at a given L,
but for different M.
Everybody know what M is for an atom?
M is the magnetic quantum number.
It really corresponds to the
z component of angular momentum.
The different components, z components,
have the same energy.
As a consequence of rotational symmetry.
All right.
All of the symmetries that we've discussed up to now,
have one characteristic in common.
When they act on bosons,
they give back bosons.
When they act on fermions,
they give back fermions.
What happens to a boson,
what happens to an electron if you rotate it?
It stays an electron.
It doesn't turn into a photon.
So,
the electron is a photon.
It's a particle.
Quarks have symmetries under the color transformations.
Remember the color transformations?
Mixes up the three colors of quark.
Takes a quark into a quark.
It doesn't take a quark into a gluon.
A gluon is a boson.
A quark is a fermion.
In fact,
all of the symmetries we talked about up till now,
don't change the spin of a particle.
It would take scalar particles,
scalar particles to scalar particles,
half spin particles to half spin particles.
Generally speaking,
the symmetries we've talked about
don't do anything to the spin,
don't do anything to the type of particle,
don't do anything to the charge of a particle.
Keep the charge of a particle unchanged.
And especially don't do anything
to the mass of a particle.
In some way,
the symmetries tell you that
there are equalities between masses of different states.
For example,
they do tell you that the
various z components of angular momentum
all have the same energy.
Because you can rotate one into the other.
Z components of angular momentum in an atom.
As long as the atom is
not in an external magnetic field.
Or electric field.
Supersymmetry is a new kind of symmetry.
It's a really crazy kind of symmetry.
Which,
when it acts,
it takes a fermion into a boson,
or a boson into a fermion.
Just like rotations
tell you that there have to be these multiplets
with different z components of angular momentum.
That if there's a z component of angular momentum
which is plus a half,
then rotation symmetry tells you there has
to be one of minus a half
with the same energy.
If there's a spin up with one unit,
then it's enough to tell you
there has to be a spin down with one unit.
But if you look carefully at the mathematics,
you'll also find out that there has
to be one of zero in between.
All of exactly the same energy.
That's what the symmetry does for you.
As I said,
supersymmetry is a very strange new construction
which, when it acts,
takes a fermion to a boson.
The mathematics of it is very weird.
Very strange.
Very non-classical.
Extremely non-classical.
And absolutely impossible to visualize in any sense.
So I will tell you a
little bit about the mathematics of it.
Why is it important, incidentally?
It's important because if you have a theory
that enjoys the symmetry,
that has this supersymmetry,
then there will always be for every fermion
a boson, a super symmetry.
And every fermion has exactly the same mass.
And every boson a fermion of exactly the same mass.
That's exactly the situation that we were looking for
where bosons and fermions might
be able to exactly cancel out
the infinities or large, large
renormalization effects
that we discussed for a couple of times already.
This is very, very hard to motivate.
This is hard to motivate.
Because it is so completely unintuitive.
Very unintuitive.
These are symmetries, as I said,
which take fermions into bosons.
The generators of them are called Q.
There's a Q.
There are two.
There are several generators called Q.
We'll just call them Q for the moment.
And they take a boson into a fermion.
Something totally new.
These Q's...
Let's see.
I'm trying to figure out how to say this right.
Okay.
How can we make an operator
which takes a fermion into a boson
or a boson into a fermion?
Let's think about that for a moment.
Q is an operator which can
take a fermion into a boson
and a boson into a fermion.
What kind of operator could do that?
Well, it's very easy, actually.
Operator on the spin.
Just operate on the spin.
In charge.
Well, it has to...
What does it have to do?
If you have a boson,
it has to remove the boson
and put back a fermion.
Right?
If there's a fermion there,
it has to remove the fermion
and put back a boson.
I'll construct for you a Q
that does exactly that.
We have creation and annihilation operators
for fermions and bosons, right?
All right.
Let's...
What do we want?
Q, which takes a boson to a fermion,
it has to annihilate a boson.
So let's put an annihilation operator...
Let's see.
I always forget.
Is A a creation?
A is a...
A dagger is creation, right?
So A is annihilation.
This annihilates a boson.
So just for the simplest thing,
this annihilates a boson,
any annihilation operator,
and then what do we want to follow it by?
A creation operator for a fermion.
What do we call creation operators for fermions?
I can't remember.
C dagger, right?
C dagger.
Here's an operator
which, whenever it acts on a...
boson,
will always give a fermion, right?
What happens if it acts on a fermion?
It gives nothing, right?
It just annihilates the fermion.
So let's add something to it.
Let's add to it
A dagger times C.
This annihilates a fermion
and creates a boson.
So what does this object do to a boson?
Well, this eats the boson
and spits out a fermion.
So it creates a fermion.
What about this piece of it?
This piece of it annihilates a fermion,
but there is no fermion.
So this piece of it is dead.
This relationship is correct.
What happens if the same operator
acts on a boson?
A dagger...
Oh, this is a boson on a fermion.
So this piece of it is dead.
Plus C dagger A.
What does that do on a fermion?
Well, this one annihilates a boson,
but there is no boson there.
So, nothing.
This one annihilates the fermion
and puts back a boson.
So this one puts in a boson.
So, yes, we can make operators
which do have a boson,
but they don't have a fermion.
So, yes, we can make operators
which do have a boson,
but they do have the property
that they intertwine
between fermions and bosons.
OK?
Superpositions?
Superposition.
Does this imply
you can get a superposition particle
of a fermion and a boson?
Well, if it acts on a superposition,
it will produce a superposition.
But if it acts on a boson,
it makes a fermion.
If it acts on a fermion,
it makes a superposition by itself.
It's not a state that's an operator.
I think what he was
thinking was this is some kind of
a supervision state,
but really it's just an operator.
This is an operator.
If it acts on a general state,
it will make a superposition.
But if it acts on a boson,
it makes a fermion.
If it acts on a fermion,
it makes a boson.
What happens if it acts on the vacuum?
What does it do if it acts on a vacuum?
What does it do
if it acts on a vacuum?
It gives you the vacuum, doesn't it?
Doesn't it?
It doesn't make the vacuum.
It just makes zero.
Why does it make zero?
Let's try it on a vacuum.
Oh, yeah.
A annihilates a boson, but there is no boson.
C annihilates a fermion, but there is no fermion.
You just get zero.
Not the vacuum, but just zero, the zero vector.
So the one exception to the rule, the rule
being that when it acts on a fermion, it creates
a boson, when it acts on
a boson, it creates a fermion.
The one exception to this rule, I don't know
if it's an exception to the rule, just a funny
exception, is that when it acts
on the vacuum, it just gives zero.
So this is a class of operators
which has the properties of a supersymmetry generator.
Supersymmetry generators are of this form.
They involve fermions.
Bonsons and bosons in a way
that is mixed together like this.
Now the question is, here we can...
The question though about the dimension of that vector.
Dimension of what vector?
The state vector.
For a state vector, which state vector?
The boson state vector is usually
different dimensionality from a fermion state vector.
Okay.
Now what do you mean by dimensionality?
Well, let's say a half
spin particle would have two dimensions.
Two components.
Yes.
So for example, yes.
So for example, yeah.
Good.
You're now telling me a little more about
this operator Q. So let's suppose it acts
on a boson and the boson is spin zero.
It creates a fermion.
But a fermion has a spin a half.
And a spin a half particle has two components.
So does it create the spin up
or does it create the spin down?
Well the answer must be, if we're going to
make any sense out of this, that there can't
be just a single Q. There
has to be two of them.
One which takes the boson into the up fermion
and one which takes the boson into the down
fermion.
There has to be another index.
Q's always have indices.
And the index is always a half spin index.
It itself is a half spin index because it
has to be able to change the spin by half
a unit.
Now what happens if a Q with
a spin i acts on a fermion?
A fermion also has to have an index.
It's either up or down.
So we ought to put
indices on these fermion vectors here.
What happens if it acts on a Fj?
Well basically the answer is if i is
the same as j it makes the boson.
If i is not the
same as j it makes nothing.
So whatever these operators are here,
whatever these symmetry operators, the generators, these
are the generators of supersymmetry.
They're not the operators.
They're the operators.
The generators of supersymmetry not
only are built, they're fermionic.
They're fermionic in the sense that they have
an odd number of fermion operators in them.
They have an odd number of fermion operators.
Every interesting quantity that we've been experiencing
up till now, things that we measure
and so forth, always have even
number of fermion operators in them.
Super generators have odd number of fermions.
They have odd number of fermion operators
because they've got to change the fermion
number and they also have indices.
The indices are spin indices.
Really understanding supersymmetry and fermions and
fermionic symmetries, why do I call them
fermionic symmetries?
Because the generators themselves have
odd numbers of fermions in them.
They change a fermion into a boson.
Really understanding that the mathematics of
it really does entail a generalization
of arithmetic, of the notion of numbers.
Let's just remind ourselves of one thing about
fermion fields and boson fields or just fermion
operators, creation and annihilation operators.
Good enough.
Fields are made up out
of creation and annihilation operators.
Let's just remind ourselves what we know about fermions.
We know about creation
and annihilation operators for bosons.
Creation and annihilation operators
for bosons have commutation relations.
The commutation relations are commutator of A
with A. This could be any creation operator,
any bosonic creation.
These are annihilation operators, aren't they?
What's the commutation relation of an A with an A?
Zero.
In fact, they could be for different bosons, even so.
They commute with each other.
What about a dagger with a dagger?
Same.
What about A with a dagger
or is it A dagger with A?
I think it's that way.
What does that give?
One.
That's the algebraic properties of...
That's the algebraic properties of bosonic operators.
In particular, this particular relation over here,
let's take this one over here, this
could actually stand for two different creation operators.
One, let's say, for a particle of one
momentum, one for a particle of another momentum, or
for a particle at one place
and a particle at another place.
Let's take this relationship here.
Let's say that we're going to create a two-particle
state, two bosons, one with label I and one
with label J. As I said, label I
and label J could represent momentum, they could represent
position, they could represent anything you like.
How are we going to create two of them?
We're going to create... by just applying
the creation operators, this is the state
of two bosons.
One of type I and one of type J. How
does this differ from a state with the same exact
particles but in which they've
been introduced in the opposite order?
It doesn't differ.
It's exactly the same thing.
It's exactly the same thing, and mathematically,
the commutation relations here tell you that
A dagger I, A dagger J is the same.
The same is A dagger J,
A, I. They're equal to each other.
This is the symmetry of
wave functions under interchange of bosons.
When you interchange the arguments, the arguments
of the wave function or the labels labeling
the states, here these are related to each
other just by interchanging I and J, it does
nothing.
It multiplies the state by the number one.
That's the character of bosons
and the character of the state.
So, we're going to create a two-particle state.
The character of bosons is indicated by
commutation relations between fields or between things
that make up the fields.
What about Cs?
What about the commutator of two Cs?
Let's go after this one here first.
See.
Okay.
So, we start with Cs dagger.
Cs dagger.
Is that, one?
No.
That's not the way we do things with fermions.
With fermions, it's anti-commutator.
What does anti-commutator mean?
It means Cs dagger plus Cs dagger c.
Cs dagger plus Cs dagger c.
Not minus.
Let's see what that means. In fact, every
place where you saw commutator, replace it by anticommutator.
What does anticommutator mean?
Anticommutator of two things, A
with B, means AB plus BA.
AB plus BA.
Okay, first of all, let's see what this
says. What does this say about two particle states?
First of all, suppose there's only one kind
of fermion, just a C with no label.
Anticommutator of C dagger with C dagger just means
C dagger, C dagger, plus C dagger, C dagger.
It just means twice C dagger, C dagger.
That's equal to zero.
So it just says when you multiply
C dagger by itself, you get zero.
That doesn't mean that C dagger is itself zero.
C dagger creates a fermion.
What does it mean to say that
when you square it, you get zero?
It simply means you can't put
two fermions into the same state.
You simply can't put two fermions into the same state.
That's the Pauli exclusion.
So the Pauli exclusion principle is
simply obtained from the anticommutation relations.
Now, supposing you happen to
have two different kinds of fermions.
They might be the same kind of fermion, an electron, but they
might be electron at one place or an electron at another place,
or electron at one momentum, electron at another momentum, or
they might just be different spin states of the electron.
Let's suppose, again, there were two labels.
Now, let's make them fermions.
Fermions now, C dagger I, C dagger J.
How does that relate to the state C dagger J,
C dagger I, where I've interchanged the I and the J?
Well, the anticommutation relations say that
C dagger I, C dagger J,
plus C dagger J, C dagger I, equals zero.
Another way of saying it is that C dagger I,
C dagger J is minus C dagger J, C dagger I.
This is the anti-symmetry of the wave function of, the anti-symmetry of
fermion states with respect to interchange of the labels of the fermions.
So, the character of fermions,
and the character of bosons is
encoded in these commutation or anti-commutation relations.
Whatever fermions are, or whatever the mathematics
of fermions are, it's related to the mathematics
of bosons by replacing commutator by anti-commutator.
But particularly, the property of the square
of a fermion operator being zero is very,
very different than the square of a boson
operator. Now, boson fields, when you build up
a large number of bosons, behave very classically.
When we have a large number of photons, we
think of the fields as the electric and magnetic
fields, and we think of them as ordinary
numbers. We think of them as ordinary numbers, and
ordinary numbers commute.
Right?
Ordinary numbers commute. What about fermions? Well,
in fermions, you never build up large
numbers of fermions in the same state.
So field operators for fermions never get big.
They never get big because their square is
zero. So how can they ever get big? There's
a whole generalization of arithmetic, which I'll tell
you a little bit about, just a little
bit, in which the numbers commute.
The numbers of arithmetic are replaced
by numbers which anti-commute instead of commute.
And these numbers are extremely useful.
They're really just bookkeeping devices. They're bookkeeping
devices the same way that fermion fields
are bookkeeping devices. They keep track of various
relationships. These are not real numbers. These
are not numbers that you can measure.
They're not numbers that experiments can be answers to.
They're bookkeeping devices. They're called Grassmann
numbers, a whole theory of new kind
of numbers. As I said, it's a generalization
of arithmetic, and I'm just going to tell
you a little bit about it because
fermion fields are really Grassmann numbers. They're
really Grassmann numbers, and the generators
of these fermionic symmetries, these things
which take fermions to bosons, are also
Grassmann numbers. Grassmann numbers have the property
that they anti-commute.
So let me just tell you a little
bit about them. For our purposes now, they're really
just a curiosity, but they really are at
the heart of what supersymmetry is. We have a
collection of ordinary numbers to begin with.
Let's call them ordinary numbers. Let's call
them alpha sub i.
i just lays out a number. It's a number
that's actually a number, but it's also a number
that's a number. It's a number that's a number
that's a number. It's a number of things. It's a
number that we call an ordinary number.
So i just labels which number we're talking
about. I'm just labeling them alpha sub i.
Here's something which is true of any pair
of ordinary numbers. Alpha sub i alpha sub j
is equal to alpha sub j alpha sub i. Three
times five is five times three. Now we're
going to invent these new numbers called Grassmann
numbers. We're going to call them theta instead of
alpha. Theta i. I don't know how many there
There might be only one of them.
There might be two of them.
There might be three of them.
However many there are,
they have the properties that
theta i anticommutes with theta j.
In other words, theta i theta j
is equal to minus theta j theta i.
When you interchange them, they change sign.
That's one of the characters of Grassman numbers.
Now don't ask me what
the value of theta i is.
It's not 7.
It's not 6.
It's just theta i.
It doesn't have any ordinary numerical value.
Another thing you can say about
them is their squares are 0.
Theta squared, which is equal to,
let's say, theta j,
let's say theta 1 squared.
Theta 1 squared is just theta 1 theta 1,
but theta 1 theta 1 is just one half
of theta 1 theta 1 plus theta 1 theta 1.
And theta 1 theta 1
plus theta 1 plus theta 1,
that's just the anticommutator of theta 1 with theta 1.
So theta squared are equal to 0.
So now,
let's suppose for simplicity now,
let's suppose there's only one Grassman number.
Let's just call it theta.
One Grassman number.
It's like just having one number in arithmetic,
the number 7.
Oh, we'll also add an ordinary number.
We can have both ordinary numbers and Grassman numbers
in the same arithmetic.
I should tell you about,
oh, well, I should,
okay, so we should add.
If we take an ordinary number,
a commuting number,
let's call it an alpha,
the rule is ordinary numbers commute with thetas.
They don't anticommute with thetas.
They commute with themselves.
The only thing that anticommutes
is a Grassman number with itself.
known procedures
among the categories and being in contact with it.
Grassman.
Oh,
Got an amazing.
What do you get?
You put in
a large Peter Peters grocery...
on the 나учный Gröbab,
and İYes and Hi grant means.
oberg symptoms,
No,
ground provinces,
Wildlife P Ridge,
Urим surgery,
Grassmann.
Grassmann must have been a mathematician.
A German mathematician.
From the 19th century.
Now he was clearly smoking something when he invented this.
I mean, you know.
What?
So a Grassmann number times an
ordinary number is a Grassmann number?
Ah, good.
A Grassmann number times an
ordinary number is a Grassmann number.
Right.
This is, that's right.
We can easily prove that.
That Grassmann numbers times
ordinary numbers are ordinary numbers.
What about a Grassmann number times a Grassmann number?
So a Grassmann number times a Grassmann number is ordinary.
What about an ordinary times a Grassmann?
It's a Grassmann.
Right.
Now.
So ordinary times ordinary is ordinary.
Ordinary times Grassman is Grassman.
And Grassman times Grassman is ordinary.
So it's like odd and even numbers.
Odd times odd is even.
Even times even is even.
Odd times even is odd.
So that's the property of Grassman numbers.
What's that?
Okay, so let's think.
A real, well, yes, a real
times a real is a real.
A real times imaginary is imaginary.
And imaginary times imaginary is real.
So yes, it's also true of imaginary and real numbers.
But it's particularly true of these Grassman.
Now, what is unusual is that the
square of any Grassman number is zero.
Because it anti-commutes with itself.
What's that?
No, no.
I mean the cross product
of the same thing is zero.
Okay, yeah, I mean the cross product of a times
b is minus the cross product of b times a.
That's true.
But, yeah, I don't think the analogy goes too far.
But yes, that's right.
Okay.
Can't you think of this as
a generalization of like imaginary numbers?
Like one plus one.
It's just a generalization of numbers.
It's a generalization of numbers where you replace commuting the, you
know, one of the postulates of arithmetic is that multiplication commutes.
Here, the postulate of
arithmetic is that multiplication anti-commutes.
Okay.
Let's take the case of only one Grassman number.
Then the number, and think about functions.
Let's think about functions now.
Of Grassman numbers, we'll have
Grassman numbers and ordinary numbers.
Ordinary numbers are ordinary, but
there's only one Grassman number.
Okay, only one Grassman number.
The functions of Grassman numbers are very limited.
Let's see what kind of functions
we can build of Grassman numbers.
Well, we can start trying to build polynomials.
The polynomial might be an
ordinary number, any ordinary number.
Let's call it alpha.
Plus another ord, you can
multiply Grassman numbers by ordinary numbers.
So, the next thing you can
build is beta times a Grassman number.
There's only one Grassman number now.
Now, let's try to build a quadratic polynomial.
Let's call it plus alpha beta gamma times theta squared.
But theta squared is zero.
So, we've run out.
There are linear polynomials and that's it.
Those are the most general functions.
The space of functions is not very rich.
It consists of basically two functions, a constant
and a linear function of the Grassman number.
No more.
There are no more functions than that.
So, it's a pretty damn simple arithmetic.
Yeah?
Theta cubed is theta times theta squared.
And if theta squared is zero, theta cubed is zero.
So, everything beyond theta.
Theta is zero.
That's it.
There's not much of a space of functions.
Let's suppose that there are two
Grassman variables, theta one and theta two.
Then what kind of functions are there?
Well, again, there's alpha plus beta theta one.
Beta one, theta one, let's call it.
We can then add plus beta two theta two.
Beta one and beta two are just ordinary numbers.
Ordinary numbers could be complex numbers.
It's not important at the moment whether they're complex
numbers or real numbers, whatever they happen to be.
And then we can have
plus gamma theta one theta two.
Theta one times theta two is not zero.
Theta one squared is zero
because it anti-commutes with itself.
Theta...
It's an ordinary number, isn't it?
It's a commuting number, but
it's surely not an ordinary number.
Why isn't it an ordinary number?
Because it is not zero, but its square is zero.
Yeah.
Theta one, theta two, theta one, theta two, that's zero.
So it's surely not an ordinary number.
Okay, it's not zero, but its square is zero.
But it does have the
property that it commutes with this.
All right, so that's it.
That's the last...
That's the biggest function.
That's the most complicated function
you can make of two thetas.
Incidentally, this is not equal to alpha plus
beta one theta one plus beta two theta two
plus gamma theta two theta one.
Why not?
Because they anti-commute, and that means to make them
equal, you would have to put a minus sign here.
Question.
You said you...
An ordinary number times a theta, you get a theta.
So it seems like beta times
theta would give you a third.
A third.
Beta, you multiply beta times theta one, that
seems like that would give you a different theta.
But you're saying there's only two thetas in that equation.
No, no, you can...
Oh, sorry.
You can multiply a theta by a...
By a real number.
Yeah.
You can multiply it by a real number.
Right.
So what should we say?
We should say that thetas, there's
only two of them up to...
They really form a two-dimensional vector space.
Right.
So apart from multiplication by an ordinary
number, there are really only two of them.
Okay.
So the space of functions is very limited.
There's not much structure to it.
If there are three thetas, well,
it gets a little bit longer.
You can go up to beta three, theta three.
Then you can have theta one, theta two,
theta one, theta three, theta two, theta three.
And then finally, theta one, theta two, theta three.
And that's it.
Okay.
So polynomials in this theory are...
Polynomial functions are functions of functions.
Okay.
So...
Polynomial functions of theta.
Polynomial functions of theta are very limited.
And there are no non-polynomial functions.
Okay.
What about exponentials of theta?
That's an interesting question.
Let's see what exponentials do.
Let's see if e to the a...
Let's say there's only one theta.
I think we can do this with just one theta.
e to the a theta
times e to the b theta.
Oh.
Let's...
Okay.
Let's do this first.
e to the a theta
times e to the b theta.
Is that equal to e to the a plus b...
e to the a theta...
You know, the things add in the exponent.
All right.
So let's see.
e to the a theta is one plus a
theta plus a squared theta squared over two factorial
plus a cubed theta cubed over three factorial.
But we're dead after theta.
So e to the a theta
is just one plus a theta.
e to the b theta is one plus b theta.
The product of these is one plus a theta plus
b theta plus a b theta squared, but if the
theta squared is zero.
So this is one plus a plus b.
That's a plus b theta, and that is
just e to the a plus b theta.
So, exponentials exist, or the algebra of
exponentials is exactly the same as the algebra
of exponentials of ordinary things, but
exponentials are no more complicated than this.
I'm curious.
Let's see if it works with two thetas.
Hmm?
Two different thetas.
Let's try it.
Okay, so we have e to the
theta one, e to the theta two.
Hmm?
Okay, let's see what we get.
We get one plus theta one times one plus
theta two, which is equal to one plus theta one
plus theta two times one plus theta two.
So we get one plus theta
one times one plus theta two.
I think that's right, isn't it?
And that's it.
That's as far as we go.
Okay, let's see if that's equal to e, I hope
it is, e to the theta one plus theta two.
This should be equal to one plus theta one
plus theta two plus theta one plus theta two
plus theta one plus theta two plus
theta two plus theta one plus theta two.
Okay.
So, if we put this here, we
get theta two squared over two factorial, right?
Over two factorial plus higher.
But the problem with higher is
we're not going to get anything.
The reason we get something from here is
because we have theta one times theta two.
Theta one squared is zero.
Theta two squared is zero.
but we do have twice theta1 theta2 over
2 factorial, which is exactly what appears here.
But now what happens when you
go to theta1 plus theta2 cubed?
That's going to have things like theta1 cubed, that's 0.
It's going to have things like theta2 cubed, that's 0.
It's going to have theta1 squared times
theta2, that's 0 because theta1 squared is 0.
In other words, there's always going to
be some repetition of one of the thetas.
And a repetition means that it's equal to 0.
So this thing is not there.
And yes, it does reproduce this.
Interesting, just an interesting fact.
Exponential functions exist, but they're extremely simple.
Doesn't the square term there give you
theta1 theta2 plus theta2 theta1, which is 0?
No, it doesn't.
It doesn't.
Let's see why that.
That's a good point.
Why doesn't it?
Theta1 plus theta2 theta1.
You know, you may be right.
That looks right.
Theta1.
Theta1 squared plus theta2 squared plus theta1 theta2.
Plus theta2 plus theta1.
Yeah.
No, that's worrisome.
Does this mean that theta1 plus theta2
give you another theta type of thing?
Is the sum of two Grassman numbers another Grassman number?
Yeah, the sum of two
Grassman numbers is another Grassman number.
So the question.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Yeah, yeah.
Looks like the exponentials don't always make sense.
I didn't know that.
It looks like there is a failure of multiplication of.
Am I missing something?
I don't know.
Looks like it doesn't work.
I actually didn't know that.
That's the first time I ever tried that.
What's that?
Hmm?
Yeah.
That third term.
That third term is zero.
No, but this is not zero.
Theta1 theta2 is not zero.
Is it possible that if you go
to cube, you might get that term?
What's that?
If you go to the cubic
thing, you might get that term?
If you go to the cubic thing.
I don't think so.
Theta1.
No, I don't think so.
I don't think so.
No, I think it fails.
I think it really does fail.
I'll check it.
I'll, uh...
Hmm?
Just a dumb question.
You have 1 plus theta1.
What does that mean?
Because you have an ordinary
number and that's a crazy number.
Is that an ordinary number?
No.
1 plus theta1 is not an ordinary number.
So you're allowed to mix them.
Yeah, you're allowed to mix them.
You're allowed to add them.
You're allowed to add them, but it looks
like you can't exponentiate them and get the...
I got...
I'm confused by it.
I thought you could, but...
They're a little bit like
rotations about different axes, aren't they?
They are what they are.
I don't think they're like anything else.
I don't think like they're like anything else.
They're a bookkeeping device, which is
useful, but they're not like anything else.
They're Grassman numbers.
Grassman...
Functions of Grassman numbers
can be differentiated and integrated.
Which is a useful bookkeeping device.
When I say they can be integrated, I mean
you can define the integrals of a Grassman number
and the derivatives so that it satisfies certain properties.
If you have the derivation...
The derivative of a function
of a Grassman number is straightforward.
The derivative with respect...
With respect to theta of one or any...
One or any alpha is equal to zero.
The derivative of theta with respect to theta is one.
And so, for example, if we
have just one theta in a problem,
we have functions a plus b theta.
The derivative of that...
With respect to theta is very straightforward.
It's just beta.
That's it.
Supposing we have more than one theta.
This is easy.
I mean, this is just ordinary derivative.
And this is definition.
This is definition.
The derivative with respect to theta one...
Of a function alpha...
There are two thetas now, just as an example.
Two thetas.
Alpha plus beta theta one plus beta two
theta two plus finally gamma theta one theta two.
All right.
You go through it just as
if it was an ordinary function.
Derivative with respect to theta
one, you find something from here.
Just beta one.
Nothing from here.
And from here, you have gamma theta two.
So this is exactly what you would expect.
The only surprise in the definition is that if
I were to differentiate with respect to theta two.
Nothing from the alpha.
Nothing from here.
Beta two.
But what about here?
You might expect theta one, right?
Okay.
The rule is that the derivative
operation is also like a Grassman number.
And when you pass it through
another Grassman number, it changes sign.
The rule for Grassman numbers is when you
pass them through each other, they change sign.
The derivative of a Grassman number
is counted as a Grassman number.
With respect to sign.
So that means when you pass
it through theta one, you change sign.
And this will give you minus gamma theta one.
So you treat derivatives the same
way you treat the Grassman numbers themselves.
A derivative with respect to a theta
is also a Grassman kind of variable.
And when it passes through any
other Grassman variable, it changes sign.
That's the only peculiar thing about
differentiation with respect to Grassman numbers.
Incidentally, these rules ensure some
of the rules of ordinary differentiation.
For example, they ensure the rule that the derivative of a product is the first term times
the derivative of the second one plus the second one times the derivative of the first one.
The usual rule.
The usual rule of calculus for products.
If you didn't change the sign
here, you'd get into trouble with that.
So the calculus of Grassman variables is again simple.
You don't do anything unusual except to remember that whenever
a derivative passes through a Grassman variable, the thing changes sign.
We have to do integration of Grassman variables.
And integration of Grassman variables, which is too late
for now, we will be able to write a table.
Since there are so few Grassman functions, the
table of Grassman integrals will be about that long.
So we'll also define Grassman integrals.
Why I'm doing this is just to show you
that there does exist a sort of mathematical algebraic framework
in which you can write a graph.
In which supersymmetry and in which fermion operators
fit in to a new kind of arithmetic.
It is essential to understand all of
this, to understand supersymmetry at its deepest level.
It looks like the product of
any two Grassman numbers is zero.
No, theta one times theta two is not zero.
Add theta one and theta two and square them.
And if that's zero, you'll see the product is zero.
No, it's not true that the square of...
Square that.
That's not zero.
You square it, you get zero, right?
Yes, it is.
And therefore the product of
any two Grassman numbers is zero.
No, no, no.
This, no.
You see this is equal to theta one squared plus theta
two squared plus theta one theta two plus theta two theta one.
Right.
Not quite true.
This plus this.
Yeah, the result is zero but it doesn't prove that...
Yeah, it doesn't prove theta one
theta two is equal to zero.
It just proves that theta one theta two
plus theta two theta one is equal to zero.
Yeah, that's already a rule.
Right.
So theta one times theta two is equal to minus theta two
theta one but theta one times theta two is not equal to zero.
Good.
But I'm still puzzled about this exponential.
I had always thought that...
I never used it for anything and I don't know
what it's good for but I was hoping that exponentials existed.
Well, the fact...
Any time you have the sum of the two things,
powers of the sum of two things, you can't use it.
Yeah.
But if you multiply e to the theta one times e
to the theta two, it does look like you get left with...
It doesn't look like you have
a source of theta one theta two.
You do have a theta one theta two.
I'm saying that this expansion of the exponential gives you
square terms and higher but square terms are automatically zero.
Yeah.
So that means this is true.
This is true.
That can't go any further.
No source of theta one theta two.
Right.
But that's not the same as this.
So it's simply not the case
that this is equal to this.
Right.
Simply not the case.
Aren't you assuming that the exponential is valid?
Aren't you assuming that the exponential expansion is valid?
That may not be the case.
Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah.
That was the definition of the exponential.
Yeah.
I think there may be some other...
Can I also start addressing that?
There may be some other definition.
I have to think about it.
There may be another definition.
For more, please visit us at stanford.edu.