Stanford University.
Do we want to get
back into our favorite subject, supersymmetry?
Well, I started it and I'm going to
finish today by really showing you the mathematical
structure of supersymmetry in four space-time dimensions.
We did it a little bit with just
time, and then I'm going to show you
how quantum field theories are constructed, just give
you an example of the construction of a
supersymmetric quantum field theory, and show you what the
supersymmetry gives for the Feynman diagrams and
how the Feynman diagrams work a little
bit. This is for a simple model supersymmetric
field theory. It is not the most general supersymmetric
field theory. It's an example.
More general examples sort of follow a
very similar pattern. Okay. The simple example
that I showed you only had one direction
of space-time, and it was just time. I completely
ignored space, and for example, we
wrote down relationships between the super generators,
the Q's, and the Hamlet's.
Okay.
And the Hamiltonian, the energy. But
the energy belongs together with the momentum
in a single four vector. How can it
be that there is only a relationship which involves
the energy or the time component of the
momentum on the right-hand side? Mustn't there be some
generalization of that with more Lorentz invariance
where what's on the right-hand side of the
anticommutation relations involves not only energy
but also momentum? And the answer is
yes, it must be.
Okay.
The equations have to transform in
a sensible way on the Lorentz transformations.
All right. To get a bit of a feel
for it, although not in great detail, it's good to
go back to the Dirac equation. But
the Dirac equation in a particularly simple situation,
if the Dirac particle were massless, it
would have two components which would be unbalanced.
Okay.
And they would be uncoupled, namely the left
moving, the left, the left and the right spinning
fermion. Left and right spinning means relative
to the direction of motion. Okay. My right-hand
screw and left-hand screw. There would be
two of them, and the electron, of course,
does have two components like, two, a left-hand
and a right-hand partner. But if the particles
are massless, you could have two components.
If the particles are massless, you could
have a purely left-handed particle that did
not have to have a right-handed particle
associated with it. Do you know why that's
true? There's an interesting reason why massless
particles can have the property of only spinning
in one direction, but a massive particle has to
be able to have two spin states. And the
reason is kind of simple. Let's suppose we
had a massive particle, which could only spin
to the right. Now, to the right means
right-hand rule. So it has momentum, angular momentum
twisting around to the right. All right.
It's moving, it's moving along, but now I
decide to move faster than it. It's spinning
this way, but it's moving that way. The original
one was spinning right-hand and moving along my
thumb. If I'm going to be moving faster
than it, it's now still moving.
Okay.
It's still spinning the same way. It's
left-handed. It's left-handed. So a massive particle, because
it moves slower than the speed of light, you
can always outrun it and look at it, and a
left-hand particle will become a right-hand particle.
So you've got to have both. You
can't just have left-handed particles. But if
a particle is massless and truly moves
with the speed of light, then there's no
way to turn a right-handed twisting one into
a left-handed twisting one. You can try
a Lorentz star rotation, which rotates it all
the ways around, but that takes a right-handed one.
If I, just by virtue of rotating my arm
around, it doesn't change my right hand to
my left hand. Okay. So particles which move
with the speed of light can be monodexterous.
I don't know what the right word means. Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Actually,
I do know what the right word is.
The right word is chiral. Chiral means spins
only in one direction. The word chiral, C-H-I-R-A-L,
refers to having a handedness. And I think,
what's the Greek word for hand? Chiron? Well,
it comes from the Greek word for
hand, which is chiral, chirus, or hand.
Okay.
Chiron or...
Yeah
Closely related to helicity. It is helicity for a
massless particle. It's not quite helicity for a massive particle
Actually, I think it is
helicity for what you just described
It's chirality
Well, I think chirality is the thing
Depends on who you read, but it's
the thing that's associated with the gamma matrix
Yeah
Helicity and chirality are a little bit different
Chirality has to do with gamma 5
Helicity has to do with sigma dot P
I'm going to explain what sigma
dot P is in a minute
And it's only for massless particles that
gamma 5 is equal to sigma dot P
so they're not quite the same thing but
But in the case of
a massless particle they are. Okay
So a massless particle
Has half as many states
Spin states as a massive particle
the Dirac
particle
Describes the massive electron for example
and the Dirac field has four components
The massless particle the massless
chiral particle, let's say left-handed it's
standard to
Think about left-handed particles
Those particles or the fields the wave fields for those the
Dirac type fields have only two components and they're called psi 1
two components spinner
psi 1
psi 2
Which we can also write psi alpha
And they satisfy a Dirac type equation the Dirac. I'll write down
the Dirac type equation. It can also be called a Pauli equation
It has no mass in it and
It looks like I
Decide the T. Oh, well,
let's let's start up here first
There's a Hamiltonian for the particle and the
Hamiltonian is Sigma dot P. What does that mean?
It means that if it's spinning
in the same direction as its momentum
Then its energy is positive
if it's spinning in the opposite direction
Of its momentum its energy is negative, but
there are no negative part of negative energy particles
There are no negative energy particles we can replace them by holes
and fill up the sea of negative energy particles all that stuff so
Left-handed particles have Sigma dot P being positive
Okay now
You can convert this into a wave equation
H is of course ID by DT
P is minus ID by DX
There are three X's but I'll
simplify it minus ID by DX
Equals put an equal sign here and
There are three components to X here,
so this is X Y and Z and
Sigma are a set of three matrices
The three Pauli matrices so we
can put them in here minus I
Sigma and
this really means Sigma X D by DX plus
Sigma Y D by D Y plus Sigma Z
by DZ, we can even write it
as just Sigma dot D by DX and
all of this
acts on
SI a
and that's the analog or the simple version of the
Dirac equation
We can shift this to the other
side and write that I d psi dt.
And now let's call T x0,
the time component of a four vector,
d psi by dx0 plus
sigma dot d psi by dx.
x now means x1, x2, x3.
Sigma has three components.
This x over here has three components.
That is equal to zero.
And now we can even
make it a little bit simpler
by defining a fourth Pauli matrix.
The ordinary three Pauli matrices,
they are 1 minus 1.
This one's the z component.
This one's the x component.
And the last one is 0 minus ii.
That's the y component of Pauli matrix.
Let's add one more.
The time component of the Pauli matrix.
The time component is really simple.
It's just 1, 1.
The unit matrix.
There are four of them.
These are enough matrices to write any matrix
as a linear expansion in them.
Now there's a 1 multiplying this.
This is just 1 multiplying beside the x.
So I could put here the fourth.
This is x0, the time component.
I could put here sigma 0.
And this whole thing becomes...
just i.
Sigma mu, where there are
now four vectors worth of sigmas,
times d psi by dx mu.
Equals 0.
That's the chiral Dirac equation.
And it's perfectly Lorentz invariant.
It takes a little bit of working.
It takes a little bit of work
to truly prove that it's Lorentz invariant.
But it really is Lorentz invariant.
And these psi's transform.
The psi's here transform in
a particular way under Lorentz transformations.
We don't need to write it down.
All we need to do is to
know that two component spinners like this
have a distinct and simple
transformation property under Lorentz transformation.
All right.
So this is the Lorentz transformation.
And it suggests, and it gives the right suggestion,
that the Grassman parameters,
the Grassman parameters,
which are also...
The psi's, first of all, are anti-commuting objects.
Did I leave something out here?
Psi d by d, I don't know what this was.
Psi is a quantum version of
a Grassman number, an anti-commuting field.
It suggests that the Grassman algebra
consists not just of a theta,
but a theta alpha.
Just like psi.
Also, the complex conjugate.
Theta bar alpha,
which is theta bar one, theta bar two.
How many independent components
are there altogether of these?
There are four.
We can either think of
two real and two imaginary components,
or we can just think of the
thetas and the theta bars as separate objects.
That's okay. It's legal to just
think of them as separate objects.
But if you want to be a little more precise,
you can think of the four
real components of theta as being...
Right.
So, there are four components of theta.
Now, supposing we have a general function of theta,
for example, a superfield.
A superfield which depends on the coordinates of space
as well as these new anticommuting coordinates.
We can...
We can again expand it in powers of the thetas.
It will start out...
For example, if it were just
a bosonic object, an ordinary number,
it would start out with some ordinary
thing which was independent of the thetas,
might depend on the x's,
and then there would be something proportional to theta.
For example, we might call it psi bar theta.
There might be something with a theta bar in it,
plus theta bar psi,
plus theta bar psi.
How far would it keep going?
Previously, we ended it at the next term.
Why? Because there were only two thetas.
But now there's going to be more,
and it's going to go all
the ways to the fourth power.
Why? Because there are four thetas.
Right?
After the four thetas, they'll start repeating,
and that'll be the end of it.
So, we can go to what I'll call...
Either I can call it something else,
I can call it sometimes psi bar squared,
psi squared,
sorry, theta bar squared, theta squared,
times some coefficient here,
often called the d term,
or I can just call it theta
to the fourth and make it simpler.
But theta to the fourth doesn't
mean the fourth power of anything.
It means the product of the four distinct thetas.
Okay?
So I'm going to use simplified notation,
and in many cases tonight,
I'm going to use simplified notation
because the indexology gets awful.
So I don't want to do it tonight.
I want to simplify it.
Okay, so now we can ask,
what is the superalgebra?
What is the analog of the anticommutation relations
and the commutation relations
of the q's with other, with themselves,
and with other things?
I will write them down for you now.
You've seen things like it before,
but now there's the new added kick
that things have indices alpha.
All right, so there's going to be a q alpha.
q is also a spinner.
It belongs to the same family of objects as theta.
And it begins with d by d theta,
which is the commutation relation.
So I'm going to write it down for you now.
Oh, I don't want to do that.
I'll do that later.
Let's cut that for a minute.
q is an object which belongs in
the same class of things as theta.
Let's just think of it that way.
And let me write down
now what the commutation relations are.
I want to write the anticommutation relations.
Anticommutator of q dagger alpha with q beta.
Beta and alpha don't have to be the same.
Let's try to figure out what that is,
what that could be, what it possibly could be.
Remember in the previous case,
what did I have on the right-hand side?
Remember?
Twice the Hamiltonian, right?
All right.
So whatever goes on the right-hand side
is something like a Hamiltonian.
Hamiltonian means energy.
And energy is a component of a four vector.
There is a two there that's a four vector.
The two is a purely conventional,
there's no significance to it.
You could normalize it differently.
On the right-hand side, we should expect
that there is a p mu.
In the previous case, p mu just meant
p naught, the energy.
But you can't have a Lorentz invariant theory
where you have some structure here
with just a time component.
If you do a Lorentz transformation,
that time component will turn into space components.
So you better account from the beginning
for a p mu here.
But that doesn't look good.
There's no mu on this side.
There's an alpha and a beta on this side.
There's a mu on this
side and no alpha and beta.
So it means we haven't written a sensible expression.
We need something else in here.
We need something to soak up this index alpha
and give us an index alpha and beta.
What could that be?
Sigma mu alpha beta.
Sigmas are matrices, but they also have an index mu.
So we can make a nice formula out of this.
Sigma mu alpha beta.
Now both sides match in all their indices.
Mu, of course, this means sum over mu.
Einstein convention.
So we now have a potential possible Lorentz invariant
anti-commutation relation for two supercharges,
q dagger and q.
We can also write this as, let's see,
2i sigma mu alpha beta d by dx mu.
I'm using the connection between components of momentum
and...
derivatives, derivative operators.
Both of these are correct.
Next, the anti-commutators of q dagger with q dagger.
Any two components.
In the previous case, it was 0.
It remains 0.
Same as q q.
And the other thing that we have,
I'm going to write 0 in a minute,
0 equals...
For any alpha and beta.
We had that the super
generators commuted with the Hamiltonian.
That made them time independent.
That made them conserved quantities.
Here the generalization is they commute
with all four components of the momentum.
I'll just write p and
I won't bother writing which component.
Any q with any p.
And it's also any q dagger with any p.
All of those...
Oh, sorry.
When you have a Grassman variable
and an ordinary thing,
you use commutator.
Commutator.
And what about the commutation relations
between different components of momentum?
They commute.
Why do they commute?
Because they're represented by derivative operators.
Derivative with respect to x,
derivative with respect to y.
Their order of differentiation doesn't matter.
So all components of momentum commute
with all components of momentum,
including the time components.
This is the thing which generalizes
to a Lorentz invariant theory
the thing that we called the superalgebra last time.
Okay.
Any questions?
Is that the alpha, beta on that sigma,
is that the matrix index?
Yeah.
Okay.
Alpha and beta are the matrix index,
and mu is the space-time index.
And you see we needed it in the formula
because we had to soak up the index mu somehow,
and we had to put back
in an index alpha and beta.
Now there's a concept again of superfields.
I'm not going to write
out the components of the superfield,
but the superfield is a function of coordinates,
thetas, and theta bars.
And it's the role of
the q's and also the p's
to differentiate phi to shift it,
to make little shifts of phi with respect to x
and with respect to theta.
For example, the action of p on phi
is to multiply it by i times the derivative
with respect to x.
The action of q,
in the same way that p is,
depends on which upper or lower components,
but let's just write it as i d by dx,
in the same sense that
p is i d by dx,
q, q alpha, is almost just d,
well, it's not almost,
d by d theta alpha.
So q is like a component of momentum
in the theta direction.
Now the theta direction
is this infinitesimally small direction.
What it means to have a momentum in that direction
is not something you can conceive of,
but we're not quite finished.
It's the same deal as last time,
add plus i,
remember what we had last time,
theta bar d by dt is what we had,
or theta bar d by dt,
now it becomes theta bar beta,
I'm going to put all the indices in,
but after that I'm going to simplify,
d by dx mu,
theta bar,
theta bar d by dx mu,
this is the analog of
theta bar times d by dx,
but this doesn't look so good.
There's an alpha on this side,
there's a beta on this side,
that doesn't look good,
then there's a mu here
with nobody to soak it up,
we need a sigma.
Alright, so the sigma will be sigma mu beta alpha.
That's q.
And I'm going to rewrite that,
I'm going to simplify it and just
write it as d by d theta,
plus i theta bar sigma d mu.
Just to save myself writing
these indices over and over again.
Okay, the sigma is here to give
the thing the right alpha beta structure,
but also to soak up,
there should be a mu here.
But I'm going to simplify it,
I'm going to get rid
of all indices in the expression.
d means derivative with respect to x,
this curly d means partial derivative with respect to x.
Which x?
The one that matches the component of sigma here.
Okay, so that's just,
this is just written in shorthand.
q bar alpha is equal to d,
I guess I'm going to write
q bar beta just for variety,
d by d theta bar beta,
plus again i sigma mu beta
alpha theta alpha d by dx mu.
Again, hm?
No, no, this one's theta.
If this one is theta, this one's theta bar,
if this one's theta bar, this one's theta.
They're conjugates of each other.
Or more simply,
d by d theta bar plus i sigma theta d.
Alright, for shorthand.
Those are the q's.
Now what do the q's do?
The q's operate on super fields,
and they give you the small change
in the super field,
under a supersymmetric transformation.
In other words, the variation of phi.
Is sigma symmetric or?
It's Hermitian.
Here they are.
They're all symmetric except for this one.
Well, I just wondered if they should be alpha beta.
I think I wrote it right.
Beta on the left,
and beta on the right.
So, this is the same thing.
I think I wrote it right.
Beta on the left.
I think I have it right.
I'm saying if the sigma mu
is the second equation,
is that beta alpha or is it alpha beta?
I believe it's beta alpha.
So, do you have an alpha?
It's beta over here.
Yeah.
Beta over here.
Alpha alpha mu.
I think I have it right.
Okay.
A supersymmetry transformation
really just means
a small change
in the superfield
which is given by
either Q
times the superfield.
Now, what does Q times the superfield mean?
It simply means you hit the superfield
with these various derivatives.
Or,
Q bar
times the superfield.
That's a comma here.
You can do supersymmetry transformations with Q.
You can do it with Q bar.
Think of Q on phi
as a small change in phi.
That's the role of what the...
Now, we could go through.
We could take a superfield
and expand it out into components.
Components simply mean
the coefficients of the various powers of theta.
When people speak about that
they're not just saying
that the superfield is a superfield.
It's a superfield.
They're talking about the components of a superfield.
They're talking about the coefficients
of the various powers of the thetas.
We could work out
what the changes are in each component.
But I don't want to do that.
That's not useful right now.
Right now, I just want to follow the bookkeeping
and show you
how the manipulations work.
Okay.
So that's...
Good.
Alright.
What is the simplest superfield?
The simplest superfield, you might think,
is a general function
of the x's
and thetas
and theta bars, all of them.
But might there be something
simpler which depends on
fewer variables
which is still a
good
superfield in a sense?
Could there be some constraint?
Could there be a possible constraint
that you can impose
on the way that
phi depends on its arguments
which simplifies, which gives a
simplified superfield
which still has good
supersymmetry transformation properties.
So let me give you some examples.
Supposing we're talking about
rotation invariance.
Here's a
bad idea.
Take a vector field and say
I'm interested only in
vector fields which
satisfy vx
equals zero.
That's not invariant under rotation.
And I would discover it by making
a rotation of the vector
and discovering that after rotation
what's the change,
just two dimensions,
what's the change in the x component of a vector
under a rotation?
It's proportional
to the y component.
So, and if the y component is
not equal to zero to begin with
then after the transformation
the x component won't be
equal to zero anymore.
So in a rotationally invariant
theory you don't want to impose
a constraint like
vx equal to zero.
Bad idea.
Okay, how about the constraint
v squared
equals zero.
This means vx squared
plus vy squared.
Well that's a
very, very strong constraint, isn't it?
That just says v is equal to zero.
Let's make it
v squared equals one.
Is that a consistent
constraint in a rotationally
invariant theory? Yes.
It's just a length of v
and you've set it equal to one.
Now it may not be a useful thing to do
in any realistic field theory
but it's perfectly invariant
under rotations.
How do you check that it's invariant
under rotations?
You do a small transformation
under rotation
and then you see
if the resulting
components of v
satisfy the same relationship.
If they do, you've done something
that's consistent with the symmetry.
Okay.
Let's ask
whether there's an interesting constraint
that you can apply
to a super field
to
decrease
the complexity of a super field.
Not to decrease the complexity
of an already complicated one
but some constraint which would give you
a subset of things which might be simpler
than the most general thing.
This is simpler in the sense
that it is less
instead of having
two independent components, it only has
one independent component
in two dimensions.
So if v squared is equal to one
it has only one independent component.
Alright.
I'm going to guess
Question?
I'm going to make the guess
now of course it's not a guess
I know the answer
I didn't work this out
somebody else worked it out
that there is a constraint
that you can impose
that you may impose on a super field
which has a form of some differential operator
which I'm going to call d bar
times phi
is equal to zero
d bar
is a differential constraint
a set of derivatives
and a set of differential operators
on the super space
what is the condition
that this be a consistent thing
to do
which commutes
or which is consistent
with the supersymmetry
suppose I impose
such a constraint
that I have a constant
I haven't told you what d bar is yet
I'm going to tell you what d bar is
but supposing there was a constraint like this
then
it must be true
that if you do
if you make a small variation of phi
by hitting it with a q
it must be true
afterwards also
in other words
it must be true
that d bar
on phi
plus the small variation
of phi
which is proportional to q times phi
must still be equal to zero
otherwise
it wouldn't be a consistent thing to do
consistent with the supersymmetry
well
I'm thinking of d as a linear operator
of some sort
so d phi we already know is equal to zero
we're assuming d phi is equal to zero
and the question is
if d phi is equal to zero
will d bar
if d bar of phi
is equal to zero
will d bar of q times phi equal to zero
I haven't told you what d bar is
this is an abstract general question
about
what kinds of constraints
can be consistent
with a particular symmetry
alright now this says
d bar on q is equal to phi
suppose it were true
that q
which is after all
which is a grassman number type variable
supposing q
is either commuted with
or anti-commuted with d bar
in either case
we could write this
as plus or minus
q
d bar
times phi
but we've already agreed
that d bar of phi
is equal to zero
so therefore
this would also be equal to zero
so it's a sufficient
assumption
that there is a sufficient condition
for a constraint to be supersymmetric
that the constraint operator
the differential operator
of constraint
either commutes or anti-commutes
with the symmetry generator
that we're talking about
in this case q
so what does that raise
it raises the question
are there any differential operators
which commute with both q and q bar
if there is such an operator
then
we can impose a constraint
and possibly make
the superfield
simpler
a constraint like this would say
that the superfield depends
on its variables in a particularly
special way
and it may have fewer dependent variables
than you expect
now this is really not that complicated
I'll tell you what d bar is
and you can check
question
after the q
the very last
q d bar
phi
I just switched the order
of q and d bar
under the assumption
that q and d bar
either commute or anti-commute
if they commute or anti-commute
you can switch the order
and then use the original constraint
on phi to say it would be
true both before
variation and after variation
alright there's a very simple answer
for a d bar
and a d
which both
anti-commute with both q's
I'll show you what it is
and you can check
we'll do a little bit
but I'll show you what it is
d bar alpha
or let's
d bar beta excuse me
is exactly the same as q bar
with one exception
anybody care to
guess
hmm
the sign
minus i
sigma mu beta alpha
well let's just
simplify it
minus i sigma theta
times derivative
same
exact expression that I have here
except with the i
changing the sign
if you go through it and check whether it
lets see whether it anti-commute
or not with
these things
d by d theta bar
anti-commute
with theta bar to give basically a
one
so when I anti-commute this with this
I'll get this piece of junk over here
on the other hand when I anti-commute
theta with d by d theta
over here I'll get the same thing
the minus sign here
will cancel it out believe me
you can check it in fact
Michael
you've already checked this sort
of thing in the simpler case
right
exactly the same thing
this object anti-commutes
with both q and q bar
the same
happens to be true also
of d alpha
which is d by d theta
minus i
theta bar sigma
derivative
but I'm only going to be interested
for today
in one of them
and I'm going to say
what kind of constraint
what sort of simplifications
will be made on my
super field
if I insist that I have a very special
property namely
d bar
on phi is equal
to zero
you can't both do d bar and d bar
if you did d bar and d
that would say that
phi was equal to zero
but let's just take d bar on phi equals zero
I'm going to tell you
what the answer is
well first of all
this would be a constraint
on the components of the super field
it might eliminate components
of the super field
it might simplify the super field
okay
I'm going to give you the general
solution of this equation
the general solution of this equation
is that phi
phi of course depends
what does it depend on?
it depends on x and theta and theta bar
but the answer is
that it depends on
let's see
let's see what q bar is
you know
let me do something simpler first
supposing that d bar was just
d by d theta bar without this over here
what would
it say to say that
d by d theta bar on this
gives zero
it would just say that phi doesn't
depend on theta bar
that's all it would just say
phi is a function of x and theta
but it's more complicated
this condition
that d bar on phi equals zero
means that phi
depends on theta bar
in a special way
in a particularly simple special way
and I'll tell you what it is
phi is a function of
x mu
and theta
in other words
it only depends on the peculiar
combination
x plus i theta bar
sigma theta
it depends on
the combination
x plus i theta bar
sigma theta
it depends on
the combination
of x plus i theta bar
it doesn't depend independently
it doesn't have an independent
variation
with respect to theta bar
the only way it depends on theta bar
is through this combination
that's what
this equation says
let's check it
let's see if we can check it
it doesn't quite
say that phi only depends on theta
it says it depends on
theta bar in a particular
way that comes in together with x
well let's just check it
I'm not here
alright
um
let's differentiate this
with first
with respect to
theta bar
what happens when you differentiate
this with respect to theta bar
you get a derivative
with respect to this argument here
and you get a derivative
in other words a derivative with respect to x
times
i sigma theta
is that clear
that the derivative with respect to theta bar
of this
is equal to the derivative of phi
with respect to x
I'm simplifying it now
times the derivative of this variable
with respect to
I'm sorry
the derivative with respect to theta bar
is derivative with respect to x
times
i sigma mu theta
I've just done
standard calculus operation
of differentiating with respect to this
variable here
by differentiating with respect to the whole thing
and then
finding the derivative
of this whole thing
with respect to theta bar
alright
and that's that
on the other hand the other thing which comes in
is minus i
sigma
theta
derivative with respect to x
but that exactly
cancels this
so you see
any function of the
special form phi of x
plus i theta bar sigma theta
and theta
is automatically
annihilated by d bar
that's all this d bar says
d bar
or d bar equals zero says
it says that this is a particularly
simple form
another way to say it
is to call this whole variable here
y mu
everything under here
and then it says that phi
only depends on phi
of y
and theta bar
so theta
no independent
dependence
on theta bar only through
y that's the meaning of this
and the meaning of the whole
set of ideas here
is that you can have a super field
which has this simpler definition
of dependence and it still
is a representation of
the supersymmetry algebra
it still transforms
in a coherent way
under the supersymmetry algebra
a field like this which has
only this dependence
is called a chiral super field
it's called
a chiral super field
incidentally chiral super field
are always complex
they're not real things
they are generally complex
and the way you can show that
is you can see that a small
variation of the chiral super field
by hitting it with a q
gives it an imaginary part
if it didn't have an already
imaginary part
so a chiral super field
is also a complex super field
complex in the sense of complex
numbers
it's a complex thing
but that makes it a little more complicated
but it only depends on theta bar
in a particularly simple way
now
you know
this is a
sort of unending
story of
formal manipulation
but after a while
it gets kind of fun to do the formal manipulations
and to see how they work
so
let's do the next formal manipulation
which is to start
calculating a Lagrangian
for phi
for the super field capital phi
oh before we do
let's just see
what this says
this says that
let's expand phi
phi
might be some scalar
ordinary
number object
which depends on y
and what comes next
next comes
plus
psi bar
times theta
psi bar can depend
on y
and theta
have I left anything out?
how many components of theta are there?
two right?
remember it's a series of things
a spinor
an upper and a lower component
that means you can have theta squared
which really means theta one times theta two
so you can have plus
a thing which is always called
f times y
I'll call it theta squared
but it really means theta one times theta two
I could start adding things with theta bar
but this says no
no theta bars
theta bar dependence is all in y
no theta bar
theta bar dependence except what's in y
so
the super field the chiral super field
has a limited
much smaller number of components
than the general super field
it makes it simpler
it's the simplest example of a super field
and it only has
three independent components
phi
a fermionic component
in other words
a fermion field
a boson field
and then what looks like another boson field
we're going to find that f is not
really an independent boson field
but let's keep going
yeah
you have x in that
longer equation
and then you wind up with
y which is orthogonal to f
no no
y is
ok why is that
x mu plus i theta bar
sigma mu theta
definition
it's not x and y
it's uh yeah right
just y i've just used the term y
to denote this particular
combination
and once i work with y
the super field just terminates after the second term
that's a good thing it makes it simpler
however
y is not x
and after all
what we're really interested in is
how things vary with x
so at some point we're going to have to translate
back to x
ok
let's talk about
Lagrangians
Lagrangians begin
with super Lagrangians
which i think
the last time i called lambda
ordinary
Lagrangian i'll use the term L
and these Lagrangians
depend
on theta
theta bar
and the x's
an ordinary Lagrangian would only depend
on the x's
and what do we do with it we compute an
action
ordinarily
the action is an integral
of the Lagrange density
the Lagrange density over
the four directions of space
so we do have that
d4 x
but
also now
we have the integral
d theta d theta bar
now
how many components of theta are there
two components of theta
so this can really be read
d2 theta which means
d theta 1 d theta 2
and d2 theta bar
a four dimensional integral
over the four components
of theta that's the action
if we do the
integral over theta first
then we get left with
something which doesn't depend on the
thetas anymore and is just
the ordinary
the ordinary Lagrangian
so that's our goal is to
construct super Lagrangians
which have super
symmetry and then
to do these integrals and find out
what kind of ordinary field
theory we're talking about
ok it turns out
that the Lagrangian
is
is a Lagrangian
the construction of Lagrangians
in this context is
really quite simple
simpler even
than the things that we talked about last time
this is even
simpler and I'm going to give you
some examples of some Lagrangians
and then show you how they lead to
Feynman diagrams
as I said the degree of abstraction
is really unusual
you just have to follow your nose
follow the equations
and in the end
will pop out something
fairly recognizable
the end of all of this will be
a fairly recognizable structure
a Lagrangian for a fermion
and a boson some interactions
some Feynman diagrams
but it will be guaranteed
to do certain things
that only supersymmetric Lagrangians do
and we'll talk about those things
ok
so
let's take
the Lagrange density
big lambda
and expand it out
in a power series in theta
and theta bar
it will have many terms
the last of which
will be proportional to theta
theta squared theta bar squared
theta one theta two theta three theta four
theta one theta two theta bar one theta two
theta bar two
product of all four independent thetas
when I do the integral
of all the components of theta
it will simply pick out
only that last term
so the rule
is very simple
you construct Lagrangians
with all this crap
and all sorts of higher powers of theta
but in the end you pick out
the last term
it sort of sounds stupid
but it's very efficient
and very clever
the way that it works
so let's do a simple example
I'm going to take a very simple example
it seems too
it seems too simple to be interesting
but let's take it anyway
let's take for lambda
not theta
sorry
the super field
the chiral super field phi
times its own complex conjugate
now that really seems
much too simple
incidentally let's write down
what the complex conjugate is
the
ok
I'm going to erase this
but I'm going to write down
what the complex conjugate is
the complex conjugate
of the same thing
is the complex conjugate
super field
but it depends on
the complex conjugate variable
x minus i
theta bar sigma mu
theta
and theta bar
just complex conjugate
everything everywheres
complex conjugate phi
complex conjugate the
coordinate that it depends on
depends on this peculiar
complex coordinate here
and instead of depending on theta
it depends on theta bar
that's the complex conjugate
let's multiply those two together
and then see if we can
what kind of Lagrangian it gets
ok
so
what does phi depend on
phi depends on
x minus
theta bar
sigma theta
i theta bar sigma theta
and theta bar
that's phi star
and we're
multiplying that by phi
which is phi
of
x plus
i theta bar
sigma theta
which is plane over theta
and what are we going to do with it
we're going to integrate it
over the thetas
and also over the x's
d four theta
all components of theta
well before i do any
integration this is the action
this is the action
before i do any integrations
i want to shift the x coordinate
i just
what happens in an integral
is an integral of a function
what you're doing is calculating
the area of the function
what happens if i just shift the function
if i shift
this is a function
this could be a function of x
but i shift the function
f of x plus
and i shift the function
anything plus a
does the integral change
no
so you can shift the
argument of a function of x
without changing
the integral
but i must consistently
shift the argument
x if i shift it here i must
shift it the same way here
i can't possibly
shift away both
this thing
and this thing because one of them
appears with a minus sign
and one of them appears with a plus sign
but i can shift away one of them
at the expense
of the other one
so supposing i shift the x coordinate
by shifting
away the dependence over here
what happens to it over here
it doubles
we're going to let x
get shifted by this amount here
and when you do so
this will get doubled
let's see
plus two
and now we can get rid of it over here
you don't have to do this
but it's simple
this is a trick
which is unnecessary
but simplifies the calculation
a good deal
okay
now let's plug in
now we have to do some work
all of this up till
now has been just formal manipulation
it's still formal manipulation
but now we're going to do some work
we're going to write
not a lot of hard work
we're going to write that phi
is equal to a boson field
plus
psi bar theta
plus f theta squared
but that's as a function of y
in other words as a function
of x plus this thing here
I want to write it as a function of x
so let's see what I have to do
I have to Taylor series expand
in powers of the thetas here
to exhibit precisely how the thing depends on theta
so let's do that
let's start with this phi here
which is a function of this variable
we can write it as phi
phi of x
this is phi of x
this is phi of y
everything depends on y
and y
but y
oh no
what am I doing wrong
it's not y
it's just whatever this thing is
y was just x plus i theta bar sigma theta
this is x plus 2i theta bar sigma theta
let's not call it y
let's call it y prime
I could call it y prime but I won't
alright
so this is
this begins with phi of x
that's just a bosonic piece of phi
next
we have to differentiate with respect to x
d phi by dx
this is just a bosonic piece here
times the amount that I've shifted x
which is
2i theta bar sigma theta
then there's another term
which is the second derivative with respect to x
I'm going to simplify notation
and just call this the second derivative
with respect to x squared
of phi
times this thing squared
I'm not going to bother writing out that thing squared
I'm just going to notice that it contains
two powers of theta
and two powers
of theta
and two powers of theta bar
there's only one expression
that contains two powers of theta
and two powers of theta bar
it's the product of all
four components of theta
anything else will have
redundancies
so let's just call this
theta to the fourth
and I'm not going to bother keeping track
of the numerical coefficients
the next term
in the power series expansion
of little phi here
little phi is the bosonic piece of big phi
will contain higher powers
and will contain more powers of theta
and therefore will be zero
so that's the end
of the expansion
of the first term in the super field
the next term in the super field
involves
psi bar
of x
times theta
but I have to add to that
the derivative of psi bar
with respect to x
times the shift here
which is this
again this
2i theta bar sigma
theta times theta
we have psi bar of x
times theta
then we differentiated
psi bar with respect to x
and multiplied by this
let me simplify
and just write this as theta theta theta bar
it has
two powers of theta
and one power of theta bar
let's just get rid of all the crap
and just write it as two powers of theta
and one power of theta bar
just to be schematic
I'm being schematic now
where does that second line come from
oh
didn't we write that down
well we did some place
but I guess I erased it
I wrote down that phi of
y
is equal to little phi of y
plus
psi bar
theta of y
plus
f theta theta
alright
now I'm shifting the argument
of I'm writing that y
not this y I'm writing that this object
over here
alright
is x plus
this amount
so that means I have to shift the phi
and I shift the phi
by doing a Taylor series expansion
alright
this one ends at theta theta theta bar
if I try to add
another derivative I will have
too many thetas and it will kill it
ok I'll have three powers
of theta or something at least three powers
of theta so nothing after that
and then there's f
plus
f
theta squared
do I have to start
Taylor series expanding this
or
if I Taylor series expand this
it will give me a derivative of f
times
theta sigma theta
that's too many powers of theta
so I don't have to do anything with this
this is just f of x
now everything depends on x
we have
one two three
four five six terms
coming from expanding
out
and the Taylor series expansion
the x dependence
but truncating it when I
get two higher powers of theta
so this is
theta squared over the n
which one
oh sorry
yes theta squared thank you
you're sharp
over here
I don't have to do very much
that's this on the
in one bracket
and in the other bracket
not so hard
so I'm just
phi star
little phi star
the bosonic part of x
plus
ah
theta bar
psi
psi I think
theta bar
psi of x
plus
f star
theta bar theta bar
I don't have to do any shifting in this one
because it's only a function of x
I've undone the shift in here by
you know and stuck it into here
ok
now the trick is
to multiply
it's very complicated looking
but remember all we want out of it
is the last term
in the expansion
the theta to the fourth
so let's see what's going on
in the next term
so what's there to order theta to the fourth
let's start with
phi star here
well phi star has no
thetas so I have to find something with
theta to the fourth in it to multiply it by
here's the only thing with
theta to the fourth in it
so there's going to be one term
which is phi star of
x times a second
derivative of some sort
x squared
phi
now
later on we're going to have
to integrate this with respect to x
does this look familiar
it's the Lagrangian for a scalar field
ordinary Lagrangian for a massless scalar field
ok
so
we went through an enormous amount of effort
to get the Lagrangian for a scalar field
now let's see what else is here
let's take this one here
and we're going to get
this one here
that has to multiply two thetas and a theta bar
right over here
so
that gives us something with
two thetas and a theta bar
that gives us
plus something like the
psi bar with respect to
x times
psi
now this isn't quite sensible
there's an index alpha
and an index beta
and an index mu
so what really has to go here
had I kept all the indices
sigma matrix
sigma mu alpha beta
guess what this is the Lagrangian of
it's just a fermion Lagrangian
that gives the Dirac equation
when you work out
the Euler Lagrange equations for it
this one gives the Klein-Gordon equation
when you work out the variation of it
and I'm not keeping track
of numerical constants
because I've long
ago learned
not to do that on the blackboard
and one last thing is here
is f star f
of x f of x
now
boson
scalar boson
Dirac like fermion
and something
trivial this thing is extremely
trivial it has
no derivatives in it
in fact what would it's equation
of motion be
it would be partial derivative
of the this is the Lagrangian now
this whole thing here
is the ordinary Lagrangian
or the integral of the ordinary Lagrangian
if I have a thing with no derivatives
just like this
what's the equation of motion for it
it's just the derivative of Lagrangian
with respect to f equals zero
there's no derivative of Lagrangian
with respect to the derivatives of f
there's just dl by the f equals zero
or f star is equal to zero
f star is equal to zero
f star and f are complex conjugates
f is trivial
it doesn't do anything
it has no interesting equation of motion
there's another way of thinking about it
we can think about it
in terms of propagators
and in terms of
the
Lagrangians of course lead to
Feynman diagrams
the kinetic terms in Lagrangians
like this
just lead to the propagators
this guy over here
is going to give us a perfectly
conventional propagator
for phi
nothing going to be unusual there
phi is going to have a propagator
which propagates from one point
whatever the ordinary scalar field
propagator is
this is what we'll give it
this is going to be a perfectly
conventional fermion
and we'll also
have a
conventional
propagator
but what about
this over here
this is a little bit trivial
more than a little bit trivial
there's no derivatives in it
and that means
that if there were a particle
associated with this
that particle would not move
from one point to another
there's no term in it which couples
neighboring points of space
it would give a propagator
that propagator would be totally trivial
I'm going to draw a picture for it
I'll tell you what it
the propagator would not be
zero quite, it would be something
a little less trivial than zero
let's draw it like that
a little squiggly
line from one point to another
but does it really
propagate from one point to another
no, so you care to guess what it might be
it's a delta function
the particle
which is not really a particle
comes in and goes out
at exactly the same point, it doesn't get anywhere
so the propagator
for this very very
simple Lagrangian with no derivatives
in it is just a delta function
the
propagator begins and ends
at the same point
and the particle can't get anywhere
that's the structure
of the Feynman propagators
that come out of this term
in the Lagrangian
now, this in itself is not
an interesting Lagrangian
I mean it's mildly interesting
it has a boson and a fermion
exactly as we expect for a supersymmetric theory
they're both
massless
the particles have no mass
and they have no interactions
no interactions
so let's go on to interactions
let's go on to interactions
and see if we can find some interesting
Feynman diagrams out of this
we took
phi star times
notice something very interesting here
the super Lagrangian didn't even have
any derivatives in it
the super Lagrangian itself
was just phi star phi
it
was extremely simple
and didn't have any derivatives
of the super field
where did it get its derivatives from?
it came from the fact that we had
to shift the argument of the
super field
if it wasn't for that shift
we never would have generated any interesting
motion of the particle from one point to another
so super Lagrangian
does something interesting
it takes an extremely simple Lagrangian
or super Lagrangian
which seems to have no structure
to it
propagation from one point to another
but because of the shift of the argument
the shift of the argument of
x there
it really does shift particles from one point
to another in space
ok let's
add something else
simple
instead of phi star phi
let's add in just phi
squared
and while I'm doing that
I'll also add in phi star squared
but that's just the complex
conjugate of phi squared
so if I figure out what phi squared does
I will also have figured out what phi star
just the complex conjugate will be
this one here so let's concentrate on this
just plain phi squared
what does it do?
all we need to do
is
to square phi, let's square phi
but before we do
remember what we're going to
do, we're going to integrate this
d for x
and also we're going to integrate it
with respect to theta
ok but something
interesting or
simplified happens here
simplified compared to here
this is
this is capital phi
the super field
capital stands for super field
alright let's remember what we have
we have capital phi
of
x plus i
theta bar
sigma theta
and theta
times another phi
of exactly the same kind
remember what I did over here
I started with phi
star times phi
I knew that I was going to get
I knew that I was going
to integrate it with respect to x
so I shifted the x integration
I shifted x
I shifted
x to get rid of
the theta dependence here
but what did it do with here
it doubled it over here
how about in this case
what happens if I
shift the argument x
to shift away theta bar sigma theta over here
it does it in both places
but what happens if I
shift the argument x to shift
away theta bar sigma theta over here
in fact if this were any power of phi
not without any phi stars
if it was any power of phi
with no phi stars
it would just shift it away
everywheres
this one's pretty simple
let's write it out
oh
but now we have a problem
we have a problem with the theta integrations
d2 theta
d2 theta bar
there's no theta bar dependence here
what happens if I integrate d theta bar
against something with no theta bar dependence
you get zero
so on the face of it
this looks like zero
but the fix for it is very simple
it turns out to be
a completely supersymmetric thing to do
when there's no theta
dependence at all
is to just integrate over theta
that needs to be justified
that when you have a Lagrangian
or a function
which doesn't depend on theta bar at all
just integrate over theta
and you still maintain the supersymmetry
as I say that needs to be justified
but let's assume it's justified
this is the thing that you do
when there's no theta bar dependence at all
let's
what that means
is that we should expect
to expand things out
to power theta squared
and it's the theta squared term
which will give us the answer
the Lagrangian
alright, and let's put an m here
let's put an m over here
m theta squared integral d four x
let's see what we have here
phi
m phi squared, excuse me
phi of x
that's small phi of x
plus
psi bar
theta
plus f
theta squared
and we're going to square that
let's just write them side by side
the only way I can square things
is to write them side by side
plus psi bar theta
plus f theta squared
and
what we want to compute
is the term in this
which is proportional to theta squared
ok
what do we get?
well first of all we get
phi times f
twice
phi times f over here
and f times phi over here
so
there's a term
without keeping track of the constants
which will look like
f times phi
there will also be the complex conjugate
because we're supposed to add the complex conjugate
but just it'll be
that's one thing
and there's only one other term
can you spot it?
psi squared
psi bar squared
psi bar, psi bar
psi bar
oh sorry
that's it I think
yeah that's it
that's it
that's all there is from this term
in Lagrangian is
f times phi plus
psi bar psi bar
ok first of all let's look
at the Dirac part of it
it's m
psi bar psi bar
that's a mass term for the Dirac particle
a mass times a product of two
with no derivatives
is a mass term
it's called a Majorana mass term
it's a rather
different
slightly different mass term
than the kind we thought about in the past
but it is
it's a psi comes in
and a psi goes out
and there's a coefficient m
it is when combined
with the
with the conventional piece of the Dirac Lagrangian
here it gives rise to
a wave equation which has a mass
so this is
a mass for the Dirac particle
for the fermion
but this m f
phi looks a little peculiar
it's not like anything we've seen before
but
if we think about it for a minute
it will make a
Feynman diagram
in which a phi particle
the dotted line
becomes an f
now an f
let's just draw that f with that
little f propagator there
well that's a phi becomes an f
an f is a nothing
it doesn't do anything
it just sits there
but you can have a Feynman diagram
to second order
where the f becomes a phi again
that will involve
m squared
this term in the Lagrangian
f phi gives you a transition
from a phi to an f
but an f is not a real particle
it doesn't go anywhere
so you better get back to phi
that will involve two powers of this interaction
an m squared
and it will give us a phi in
and a phi out
in other words it's completely
indistinguishable from having
m squared
phi squared in the Lagrangian
m squared phi squared
is just a mass term for the boson
we can do this another way
we can do it in a more
sophisticated technical way
without diagrams
let's look at everything in this Lagrangian
which depends on the f's
first of all we have
f star f
and then
we have
plus m f
phi
and also the complex
conjugate
m f star
phi star
or
well as I said
f occurs in this awfully trivial way
in this Lagrangian
its equation of motion
is just gotten by
differentiating this with respect to f
and setting it equal to zero
there's no derivatives
so the equation of motion for f
is just f star
plus m
phi
equals zero
and
that's the equation of motion
for it
okay
let's solve this equation of motion
for f
f star
equals minus
m phi
and then plug it back
into the Lagrangian
and see what we get
well what's f star f
going to give
f star f
oh f star what is f
f is equal to minus m
phi star
f star f is going to give m squared
phi star phi
alright m squared phi star phi
what about m phi f
that's going to give
minus
m squared phi star phi
they cancel
but there's one more
left over here
and that one is also m squared
phi star phi
so that's
another way you can either think
diagrammatically that what
this f thing here
does
in a Feynman diagram
is give something which is indistinguishable
from m squared phi squared
or you can
solve for f plug it back
in and you see that the effect
on the Lagrangian is just m
phi star phi it is also
a mass term for the boson
and in fact
the mass of the boson
is exactly the same as the mass of the fermion
remember in boson
equations you write m squared
in fermion equations you write m
ah
so
the fermion and the boson
both get a mass
and in both cases that mass
is just m
again we see
this power of this symmetry
taking place making sure
that the boson and the fermion have
exactly the same mass
the power
of this really
becomes significant
we could have just done this by taking
a boson field a fermion field
and giving them the same mass
and they would be free field theories
no interactions
their masses would never change
there would be nothing very interesting
it would be supersymmetric the power of it
though is when particles interact
so let's go one
step further
and add a third
another term in the Lagrangian
g times
phi cubed
now phi cubed is more
interesting
d2 theta
same game but we have to
put one more
phi plus
psi bar theta
plus f
theta squared and let's see what kind of
things we get from here
remember we're looking for the coefficient of theta squared
that's all that counts in the Lagrangian
is the theta squared term
so let's see what we can find
we can find a phi
a
let's see we can find
a phi times a phi times an f
so this phi times a phi
is a
so this is a
a
so that's phi times
psi bar times psi bar
how many terms like that
I think there's also three is that right
I think there's also three
now first of all
all times g
all times the coupling constant g
g is a coupling constant
what is this term
phi psi bar psi bar
it's an interaction
in which two fermions come in
and one boson goes off
or a fermion comes in
and a boson goes off
in other words it corresponds to a diagram
with two fermions
and a boson
and it has a coefficient g
it's an interaction
it's going to create a lot of complicated Feynman diagrams
these Feynman diagrams
will become endlessly complicated
what about this one over here
three phi squared f
okay three phi squared f
let's forget the three
the three is not the interesting thing here
it gives us a g
with two phi's
and one of these
f
propagators here
you're not allowed to have an f
ending on nothing
there's just no particle associated with it
you've got to connect it up to something else
the only other thing to connect it up to
is another version of the same thing
there's a vertex
where two phi's become an f
and there's a vertex
where an f becomes two phi's
what is this
what kind of thing is this
remember the f doesn't go anywhere
it just really just corresponds
to a local vertex
where two phi's come in
two phi's go out from the same place
in other words
it looks like phi to the fourth
or really it's phi squared times phi star squared
it's a Feynman diagram
with four bosons coming in
at a vertex
and it has a g squared
where did the g squared come from
because there were two vertices
one where the two phi's became an f
and one where the f became two phi's
alright so this thing got
repeated twice
and it's got a coefficient
g squared
notice the really the interesting thing
here is
we could have written down
exactly these kind of things
what has the supersymmetry done
it has made the particles
have exactly the same mass
and it has related numerically
the value of
a
one kind of coupling constant
two fermions and a boson
with another coupling constant
which is four bosons
and in fact it's told us that this vertex
and this vertex
is the square
the coupling constant is the square of this one
that's a tight constraint
if you could do experiments
with these particles
you could check
by scattering
by decays and so forth
whether the Feynman diagram
for two bosons coming in
and scattering
is the same as the Feynman diagram
for two fermions to come in
and produce a boson
that's the kind of thing that supersymmetry
always does
gives you equality of masses
and relationships between
different coupling constants
now just before I finish
let me just show you simply
without actually doing any calculation
but just
what the implications
of relationships
between coupling constants like this are
we've talked about it before
but let's go through it carefully
let's think about the self-energy diagram
of the boson
here's one self-energy diagram
sort of the lowest order
and another one
is
boson becomes a pair of fermions
which become the boson again
this is what you can make
out of these vertices here
the five-fourth vertex
that's over here
four phi's at a vertex
and here's phi
psi times psi
what's the numerical coefficient
that goes with this one
g squared
what's the numerical coefficient
that goes with this one
also g squared
a g from here and a g from here
now the rest of the calculation
of course involves some calculation
of the integrals for Feynman diagrams
and so forth
but
you can imagine
now that we carried that out
I'm just showing you
that the coefficients
are the same
the integrals are also the same
and this persists to all orders
every Feynman diagram
no matter how complicated
which may also have fermions in here
there's always a collection
of other Feynman diagrams
which have exactly the same value
except for the opposite sign
and which cancel out
the opposite sign
you'll remember
that fermion loops
and boson loops
have the opposite sign
so this kind of construction
while it's rather tedious
long-winded
and
you know
just takes forever to explain
has a tremendous amount of power
if your goal
is to write down theories
which have exact supersymmetry
supersymmetry meaning
a boson fermion exact symmetry
now if you look at the
the
to tie up
one of them is the breaking of supersymmetry
supersymmetry is not a real symmetry of nature
and how that may happen
what it does
is that we have
nothing to do with supersymmetry
we have nothing to do with the
the
And then we'll talk a little
bit about the unification of forces,
SU3 cross SU2 cross U1, the standard model, becomes SU5,
and how it is influenced by the supersymmetry.
For more, please visit us at stanford.edu.