Stanford University.
Let me review first a little
bit about symmetry breaking in general.
How symmetry breaking influences
the energy levels of systems.
And of course the energy levels of systems can
be translated for our purposes into the masses of particles.
And I'm going to do that by
a simple example, a simple familiar example.
Then I'm going to show you how supersymmetry breaking works
in the simple supersymmetric field theory that we discussed last time.
Discuss a little bit about its relationship with gravity.
And what the implications of supersymmetry and
supersymmetry breaking are for gravity and vice versa.
And finally if we still have time, I think we
may, start the introduction to the guts, the grand unified theories.
Okay, so symmetry breaking.
A very, very simple model for symmetry breaking which
really does have all of the physics in it.
Of
of
continued UV radiation and the
of Adjusting the energy levels found ofutions,
scattering of energy into,
Industriально off the Cosarden mass.
Entire cosmic energy of the Sun,
K versatility of energy from the sun itself
by next nearest neighbor interactions
and next to next nearest neighbor
interactions and so forth but a
very simple mathematical picture of a ferromagnet
is that each little elementary
magnet interacts with its neighbor and
if the interaction energy is such that
it favors that means it's lower if the
two neighboring magnets are parallel to
each other then that creates a
ferromagnet if they prefer meaning
energetically to be anti parallel then
it creates an anti ferromagnet and there
can be things in between which have no
magnetization at all meaning to say
that the magnets are very random and
fluctuating and don't tend to depend and
don't tend to point in any direction at
all on the average ferromagnets
anti-ferromagnet
magnets and non magnets so let's imagine
an atom in a magnetic field first
before we talk about spontaneous
symmetry breaking let's just imagine an
atom in a magnetic field what
does a magnetic field do to
atoms even before we talk about the
magnetic field let's just talk about the
atom all right so the atom may have some
angular momentum
some spin at well some
combined spin orbital angular momentum
and you know that in quantum
mechanics angular momentum along a given direction
is quantized and you know this is
often drawn in elementary textbooks in a way
which is somewhat misleading but let's
draw it anyway you see pictures
frequently in chemistry books where
you have to possible directions of
magnetization vertically you can
eventually achieve creationsrutility as
vertically you plot some component of
the magnetization, of the, not the magnetization,
some component of the angular momentum, like the
z component, you pick out the z component, why?
Because z, I don't know, my
middle name is Zebulon, it is,
and then you say the angular momentum can point
in that direction, it can point in that direction,
it can point in that direction, it can
point in that direction, that direction, or that direction.
What happened to all the other directions? Don't worry,
the important thing is that the components of magnetization,
the components of angular momentum along
the z-axis are quantized in integer multiples.
Alright, but they all have the same energy.
They all have the same energy,
and that's a consequence of rotational invariance.
Roughly speaking, I missed some, didn't
I? I didn't put some down here.
I'll put some down here too.
Roughly speaking,
a rotation can take one of
these directions of magnetization of angular momentum
and rotate it into another, I keep saying
magnetization, that's because I keep seeing M up here,
can rotate one direction of angular momentum of the atom
into another, and of course a rotation
should not affect the energy of an atom.
Why not? What's the symmetry which says that
rotation shouldn't affect the energy of an atom?
Rotation symmetry. Since we believe in rotation symmetry, if the
entire atom were rotated, the energy should be the same,
and the implication of that, the quantum mechanical implication of
that is all these different states have exactly the same energy.
In terms of an energy diagram,
we could, all the states have the same energy.
There are what? 2j plus 1 of
them, where j is the total angular momentum,
and they all have exactly the same energy.
Now, what happens when you
put them into a magnetic field?
If the angular momentum has no component, now let's
imagine now we put it into a magnetic field,
so this direction is not just the z direction, but
also happens to be the direction of a magnetic field,
then if the atom's component of
angular momentum along that direction is positive,
the energy may get increased, if
negative, the energy may get decreased,
and all these levels get split a little bit.
Let's see.
Linear in the external, linear
in the external magnetic field.
Linear in the magnetic field.
What's this phenomena called? Anybody know?
The splitting of atomic levels in a magnetic field.
Zeeman effect. The Zeeman effect. Right.
It has been known for over
a hundred years, I believe, I think.
And, of course, this changes spectral
lines, spectral lines, new spectral lines emerge.
You can have a transition from
here to here, well, not very easily,
but transitions to other states can be all split.
And, uh, mucked up.
But the important thing is that the energies of states
which were otherwise in the absence of that magnetic field
exactly equal because of symmetry are split among themselves
by a process of symmetry breaking by the magnetic field.
Okay. Now, supposing that the magnetic field is
actually due to this ferromagnet that's filling space.
A ferromagnet is an
example of spontaneous symmetry breaking.
You realize that when you ask the
question, which direction does the ferromagnet point in?
Which direction, when the energy is as
low as possible, does the ferromagnet point in?
And the answer is, it could point in any direction.
As long as all the little magnets
are lined up, the energy is the same.
And so there's no preferred direction.
That's rotational symmetry.
All ferromagnets, no matter what direction they
point in, have exactly the same energy.
And if there's nothing else around
to pick out a direction of space,
the only thing that picks out
the direction of space is the ferromagnet.
Is the orientation of the ferromagnet.
So for that reason, all of the
ferromagnets, no matter which way they're pointing,
are physically identical to each other.
Even though from some abstract outside point
of view they're pointing in different directions,
there would be no difference between them
for creatures that live inside the ferromagnet.
However, supposing one of these
creatures happens to be an atom,
an ordinary atom, and it's under
the, it's interacting with the ferromagnet.
So here's the magnet, here's the atom.
The magnetic field of the ferromagnet
happens to be pointing in this direction,
this way.
That will have exactly the same
effect as the external magnetic field,
it's just a mathematical magnetic field,
and it will split the atomic levels.
It'll split them according to
the z-component of their angular momentum.
But what happens if the magnetic
field is pointing in another direction?
Just as good a direction, say that way,
Well, from the point of view
of the atom, there's no difference.
Its levels get split, it's
not the z-component of angular momentum
which determines the splitting, it's
the component along the magnetic field.
And exactly the same pattern emerges
with the atomic levels split like this.
So, um, the ferromagnet simulates, if you like,
the effect of explicit symmetry breaking.
Explicit symmetry breaking would mean that
the world was fundamentally not rotationally symmetric.
Of course it is.
And that's, uh, that's confirmed by the
fact that you could rotate the whole ferromagnet
and everything would be the same.
In other words, the symmetry
involves not only rotating the magnet,
but also rotating the entire world's worth
of, uh, magnet, of, uh, little magnets.
Somebody inside this ferromagnet, of
course, cannot do the experiment,
creatures made up out of
the little excitations of the ferromagnet,
could not do this experiment
of rotating the entire magnetic field.
So they would say,
well, it looks to us like the
world breaks the symmetry of rotational invariance.
But what is the difference?
What kind of experiment could
be done from inside the ferromagnet
to confirm that this was
a case of spontaneous symmetry breaking
rather than just the world being, uh, asymmetric?
And the answer is, the answer revolves
around this phrase that we've used before,
Goldstone boson.
Let me remind you what a Goldstone boson is.
First of all, if you take
all the magnets and rotate everything,
it costs no energy at all.
But now supposing you do something a little different.
Very slowly as you move through space,
slowly means, uh, slowly in space,
very, very slowly and gradually,
you imagine changing the direction of the magnets.
Um,
it's not gonna stay that way.
The magnets which are aligned over here
are gonna pull the neighboring ones into the same direction
and it's gonna create waves.
It's gonna create waves.
Those waves, or the quanta of those waves,
are called Goldstone bosons.
But the interesting implication
is that when the wave is very, very long wavelength,
extremely long wavelength,
in this case they would
be called spin waves or magnons.
Magnons.
Rotations.
Gradual rotations of the magnetic, uh,
of the direction of the magnetic field.
Those magnons,
the very, very long wavelength ones,
would cost arbitrarily small energy.
The longer their wavelength,
the less the energy they cost.
Because after all, if the wavelength was infinite,
that would be exactly the same as rotating everything.
And that costs no energy.
Long wavelength means low momentum.
And excitations,
which have no energy,
or whose energy goes to zero
as the wavelength gets longer and longer,
are called massless.
Massless particles are the ones whose energy
decreases as the wavelength gets longer and longer,
or as the momentum gets smaller and smaller.
So, a person living inside this ferromagnet,
or perhaps two people living inside this ferromagnet,
one over here, one over here,
could send messages to each other.
By wiggling the, uh,
wiggling, somehow grabbing a hole of their local,
they can't grab a hole of
all of the magnets and rotate them,
but they can grab a hole
of a couple of magnets nearby
and wiggle them a little bit.
And the effect of that wiggling a little bit
will be to create spin waves, or magnons,
and those magnons can propagate from one, uh,
from one person to another,
can send messages with them,
and those people living in this ferromagnet
after they've done lots of experiments
with these spin waves
will conclude from experiment
that those spin waves are massless,
that it costs no energy to
make very, very long wavelength ones.
If they were smart, they would conclude
that they're living in a
world of spontaneous symmetry breaking
and not that the fundamental
properties of the world are asymmetric.
It's just that the world that they live in,
the energies are such
that it tends to align everything,
but it doesn't matter which direction things align in.
That's the basic phenomenon
of spontaneous symmetry breaking.
It does not have to, necessarily have
to do with, uh, rotations of real space.
It could have to do with
all of, or all of, or any
of the internal symmetry groups of particle physics.
In particular, things like SU3-quadrant,
things like SU3-cross SU2-cross U1, and so forth.
One of the things that we learned, incidentally,
is that there's a kind of interaction
between gauge forces and goldstone bosons,
which has an effect which I'll come to,
which I'll remind you of later.
Anybody remember what the effect of mixing up together,
uh, spontaneous symmetry breaking and gauge invariance was?
Goldstone, uh, boson went away and became
an extra, uh, uh, parameter for the, uh,
For the gauge boson.
Became, that's right.
It, uh, turned the gauge boson
to a massive thing instead of massless.
And we'll come back to this.
We'll come back to this theme, but
I just want to remind you of it.
That was the pattern, or
the idea, of spontaneous symmetry breaking,
continuous spontaneous symmetry breaking.
There's also another mathematical statement,
one can make.
The vacuum, of course, being the state of lowest energy,
is just any one of these configurations
where the magnets, in this, in this particular context,
of course, of a ferromagnet,
where all the, uh, ferromagnets
are aligned along the same direction.
There's a, there's a vacuum for that direction,
there's a vacuum for that direction,
there's a vacuum for that direction.
Nobody in the world is big enough to get outside
and make, uh, rotate from one to the other,
so all of physics takes place in one of them,
and the people living in that vacuum in that world
call that configuration the vacuum.
Okay, so there are many vacuums.
Uh, let's take the vacuum that they live in,
and let's apply to it the symmetry operation.
The symmetry operation means the generators of the symmetry.
What are the generators of rotation symmetry?
The components of the angular momentum.
Angular momentum, sometimes I call it J,
sometimes I call it L,
let's call it J right now,
since it consists of all the angular momentum of everything.
Let's call it J.
And what does J do
when it acts on a state?
It infinitesimally rotates it a little bit, right?
It infinitesimally rotates it a little bit.
If...
the vacuum state was such that it really was symmetric,
that it really didn't have
this kind of spontaneous symmetry breaking,
what would happen... what would happen, uh, if you, uh...
if you rotated the state a little bit?
It would come back to itself, right?
Now, you have to remember that this
is, uh, this is the difference between...
J really represents the difference
between the rotation and the nonrotation.
It's not the rotated state.
It's the little infinitesimal change in the state
that's made by, uh, by a small rotation.
J corresponds to a small change in the state.
If the state, the vacuum state, was symmetric,
then when you apply J to it, nothing happens.
And the right-hand side is just zero.
No change whatever in the state.
Uh...
From a formal mathematical point of view,
the signal of spontaneous symmetry breaking
is that J, when it acts
on the vacuum, doesn't give zero.
It gives a state which is slightly rotated.
So, not equal to zero
means that the vacuum has a spontaneous symmetry breaking.
Now, we're gonna see that pattern repeat itself
in supersymmetry
with the exception of the
with the exception, of course,
that the symmetry, or the generators,
are these fermionic objects.
Oh, incidentally, what...
Let's, uh, let's suppose that
J on the vacuum,
rotate the vacuum, does not give zero.
Then what does it give?
What does it give?
Well...
It has the same vacuum.
It doesn't give the same vacuum.
It gives a slightly rotated one.
But the slightly rotated one
is equivalent to putting into the system
an infinitely long wavelength goldstone boson.
So you could say that
J on the vacuum creates a very, very long wavelength,
infinitely long wavelength goldstone boson.
Does J on the vacuum change the energy?
No.
It just rotated the vacuum a little bit.
And so, J, when it acts on the vacuum,
it gives a goldstone boson state.
Let's call it a Gb.
It gives a goldstone boson state.
And the fact that rotating the vacuum
doesn't cost any energy at all
tells us that the goldstone boson
has no energy.
This is the pattern.
Uh...
One more point.
All these points are important.
The magnetic field,
the magnetization of the ferromagnet,
is described by a little vector,
by a vector.
It's a vector at each point of space,
and so it can be thought of as a field.
It's the local properties of the ferromagnet.
And that little vector, of course,
is nothing but the direction
of the little magnetic moments
that are making up the direction and magnitude
of the magnetic moments
that are making up the ferromagnet.
And you can call it M.
It's not the same M.
It's capital M.
Capital M.
And it's a vector.
It points along the axis of the ferromagnets.
Um...
If M is zero,
that could be the case,
for example,
in a warm ferromagnet.
If you heat a ferromagnet up,
then the magnets fluctuate
and on the average,
there's no net magnetization.
In quantum mechanics,
it just may be that quantum fluctuations
wash out the magnetization.
If M equals zero,
that's the situation
where we say the vacuum is symmetric.
There is no magnetization.
If any component of M
is not equal to zero,
that's another way to represent
spontaneous symmetry breaking.
If any component of M
is not equal to zero,
then the system is magnetized,
along that direction.
And if you rotate that component,
other components will become non-zero.
All right?
So if the Z component is non-zero,
and you rotate the ferromagnet,
the X component may become non-zero,
or the Y component may become non-zero.
So all of these things
are the mathematical and physical correlates
of the idea of spontaneous symmetry breaking.
Okay, now let's review
a little bit about supersymmetry,
and I'm going to add a little bit to it.
We're not...
I haven't finished torturing you yet,
tormenting you.
We're going to add just a little bit.
If we want to do
it, we got to do it.
Let's just review.
We worked out a single example
of a supersymmetric quantum field theory,
or a supersymmetric field theory.
It involved one field,
it involved one fermion and one boson field,
and I'll just remind you about it.
Uh...
It involved a superfield
that I called capital Phi.
And capital Phi had the property
of being a chiral superfield.
I won't bother you with the definition of that now,
but the important thing about the chiral superfield
is that in one form or another,
it really only depends on two variables,
y and theta.
And I'll just remind you,
just to put up the equations here,
y was equal to the ordinary coordinate x
plus i theta bar sigma theta.
And that was called a chiral superfield.
Okay?
It's also complex.
It's important that it's complex,
and if you wanted to try to make it real,
what you would find
is that a supersymmetric transformation
would generate an imaginary part.
So it's not consistent with supersymmetry
to say that it's real.
That was Phi,
and we introduced a Lagrangian for Phi,
first a super Lagrangian.
The super Lagrangian,
I think I indicated by a capital lambda,
and it's a thing which you integrate
with respect to space, space-time,
and with respect to the thetas.
One term was integrated
with both respect to thetas
and their complex conjugate.
We could call it d fourth theta,
but I'll indicate explicitly
that there was an integral
over both the thetas and the theta bars.
And in the simple example
that I worked out for you,
lambda was just equal
to Phi star
times Phi.
And I'm not going to do it again,
I'm just going to tell you what came out.
Oh, what happens, what do you do,
yeah, remember what Phi was.
Let's just write down what Phi was.
Phi was a sum of several terms,
the first term being an ordinary scalar field,
the next term being
a fermion field times theta,
and the last term,
a super field,
F times theta theta,
theta one, theta two,
or however you like to think about it.
These were the three components
of a super field,
Phi, Psi, and F.
Those were the three components
of the super field.
If you plug that into the formula here
and integrate with respect to the thetas,
what does integrating with respect to the thetas mean?
It means picking out the last term,
the last term of the expression,
when you multiply Phi star times Phi,
you will get a term with
theta, theta, theta bar, theta bar.
When you multiply these together,
you will get a term with four thetas all together.
And if you work it out carefully,
keeping track of the details,
what we found was that this became
just the ordinary action
for a scalar field
and an ordinary fermion field.
In other words, this gave rise to an action
which was the integral dx of,
what did it have?
It had partial of Phi,
partial of Phi star with respect to X mu,
partial of Phi with respect to X mu.
That's just the ordinary Lagrangian
of a scalar field.
I won't bother, I'm not going to keep track
of detailed numerical factors.
We've seen this before.
If we varied that with respect to Phi,
we would get the simple Klein-Gordon equation.
Next, there was a term that was
psi bar sigma derivative of psi.
That's just the Klein, that's just the Dirac
or the massless fermion Lagrangian.
And finally, there was another term
which was just F star F.
Why just F star F?
When you square this, or when you multiply it
by its conjugate, you'll get a term
F times F star theta theta theta bar theta bar,
and so that's also here.
That's what we got, and that was the starting point.
Do you remember what we added to that
in order to get some interactions
and some mass terms and so forth?
We added something that only involved Phi
and not Phi star.
For example, Phi squared.
We added to the Lagrangian
or the super Lagrangian Phi squared, for example.
Now, Phi squared has no theta bar dependence at all.
It only has theta.
So if we tried to
integrate it over all four components
of theta, we would get zero.
We would get zero.
The right thing to do in this case
is just to integrate it with two thetas.
The theta, let's call it d squared.
Theta.
In other words, to pick
out the term of Phi squared
which has two thetas in it.
So I'm going to show you
how to do that more generally.
We did this, the effect
of it was to give us
a mass for the particles.
This is just a review from last time,
but I'm going to work it out in more generality.
Instead of writing Phi squared here,
I'm going to write any function of Phi.
But before I do any function of Phi,
let's be a little more modest for the moment
and just take Phi to the nth power.
Later on, we can add together terms with different powers.
This is a fairly, Phi to the nth,
we can add up different
n's and make a Taylor series
expansion of a function, as long as the function
is Taylor series expandable.
So let's take Phi to
the n, put that in here.
d squared squared.
Now we can write Phi squared to theta
and see if we can figure
out what kind of ordinary Lagrangian
for the Phi, Psi, and F come out of it.
This is not hard.
This is pretty easy, but I have
to do it each time over again
because I get confused.
So let's just take Phi plus Psi theta
plus F theta theta
and multiply it together n times.
OK, let's multiply it together n times.
Phi plus Psi theta plus F theta theta.
phi plus psi theta plus f theta theta, we're
going to multiply them, dot dot dot dot, phi
plus psi theta plus f theta theta. And
what are we looking for? We're looking for the
terms which have two thetas. Only the
terms which have two thetas will be interesting
because those are the only ones that
survive when you integrate it over theta. Alright,
so which kind of terms, there's really only
two terms here, only two kinds of terms in
all this multiplication here which have two
thetas. The first comes from multiplying a
product of phi's with one f. Pick out one
of the f's here and multiply it by all the
remaining phi's. How many such terms are there? n
minus one, n minus one, n minus one, n minus
uh, oh oh.
Oh, sorry, n, n terms.
You can pick this f, you can pick this f, you
can pick this f, you can pick any one of them,
and then multiply by all the remaining phi's.
So there's a term which is, it contains n
times f times phi to the n minus 1.
Yeah, phi to the n minus 1, right?
I think that's right.
And that's the important term for us now, but
let me just tell you what the other term is.
Then there's a term which is product
of two psi's and all the rest phi's.
Two psi's and all the rest phi's.
How many such terms are there?
Which is?
n times n minus 1 over 2.
So?
Well, there's another term here which is
n times n minus 1 over 2,
phi to the n minus 2 times psi bar,
times psi psi or something, psi psi, I guess.
Incidentally, you also have to add the complex conjugate.
So we also add the complex conjugate to this.
Okay, let me write this for you.
In a slightly different way, what is
n times phi to the n minus 1?
Yeah?
Is it phi to the n?
Where?
Phi to the n minus 2.
Yeah.
Just phi to the n with nothing.
Where?
Here?
Yeah, just from the first term
all the way to the n times.
So you do one of the times.
No, one of the factors is f.
You're talking about this term?
Hmm?
There's a term with nothing.
Okay.
No, no, no, no, no.
When you go to integrate over theta, it
always picks out the term with two thetas.
Right?
Okay.
Good.
And this arrow doesn't mean, well, it doesn't mean equals.
It means that the term with two thetas that
is picked out is the sum of these two.
And that's it, plus the
complex conjugate, plus the complex conjugate.
All right.
There's another way to write this.
It's exactly the same thing.
But let's just...
Let's just look at it.
n times phi to the n minus 1.
The original superpotential...
This is called the superpotential, incidentally.
This is called the superpotential.
The superpotential, and I'll write it as
v with a sort of Roman substantial-looking v.
It's a function of phi.
And in this case, it
is just phi to the n.
For this particular case.
Well, if v is phi to the n, what
is n times phi to the n minus 1?
This phi here is a little different than this phi.
This phi here is just
the first term from the superfield.
This v of phi is a
formal expression involving the full superfield.
But if the function v is the nth power,
then what is n times the
variable to the n minus 1?
It's the derivative.
So we can write, then, that the term that we
get out in the action after we integrate over thetas,
first of all, has f times the
derivative of v with respect to phi.
Okay.
Now, what happens if I have more terms with
different powers of n and coefficients in front of them?
Each one adds to this, but it
still adds just dv by d phi.
This is a linear operation here.
If we add terms to v for
v, more terms with other powers of n,
nevertheless, what we will get will be f
times the derivative of v with respect to phi.
So whatever v is.
If somebody gives you a v, you come back and you
say that adds to the action f times dv by d phi.
And you'll be right.
You also have to add in the complex conjugate.
f star dv star by d phi star.
All right.
Good.
Also, what about this term here?
n times n minus 1 over 2.
Times phi to the n minus 1.
That's 2.
Second derivative of v.
That involves the second derivative.
That involves the second derivative of v.
That's 1 half the second derivative
of v times psi bar psi.
But I'm not going to write it down because I'm
not interested in the things that involve the fermions right now.
I'm only interested in the things
that involve the boson field, phi.
There's also things involving the fermion field.
They're important.
But for the moment, I
don't want to write them down.
Just leave them here.
Okay.
For example, if v was phi squared, then
dv d phi would just be proportional to phi.
If v was phi cubed, there
would be a phi squared here.
And so forth and so on.
All right.
Now, f is a peculiar thing.
It only enters into the Lagrangian.
It has no kinetic term.
There's no derivatives associated with it.
That means the equations of motion for f.
Don't involve derivatives.
They're extremely simple, the equations of motion.
They're just algebraic equations
for f without any derivatives.
And you might as well solve them and eliminate f.
To do that, you write down that the total Lagrangian,
insofar as it involves f,
involves this coming from the d2 theta term
and f.
And so forth.
Plus f star f.
Coming from this term.
And now you have the full dependence
of the Lagrangian on this,
what's called an auxiliary field.
It's auxiliary because we're going to get rid of it.
I'm not sure that auxiliary always means
that the auxiliary fire department,
I don't suppose that means you're
going to get rid of it,
but I will use the term auxiliary
to mean we're going to get rid of it.
All right.
F times dv d phi plus
F star dv d phi star.
And now let's look, what is
the equation of motion for F?
Well, the usual equation of motion, it involves stuff like
derivative with respect to X mu
times the derivative of the Lagrangian
with respect to derivative of F
with respect to X, blah, blah, blah.
And then plus, minus, minus derivative
of the Lagrangian with respect to F.
Equals zero.
In this case, it's very simple.
The Lagrangian doesn't depend on the
derivatives of F, so this isn't here.
And our equation of motion is
just that the derivative of the Lagrangian
with respect to F is equal to zero.
Boy, is that simple.
Let's write it out.
What does it say?
The derivative of the Lagrangian with respect
to F has dv by d phi
plus
and plus F star
equals zero.
In other words, it immediately, and incidentally,
the equation of motion for F star
you can just get by
taking the complex conjugate of this.
And it's the derivative of
V with respect to phi star
superpotential
plus F
is equal to,
is equal to zero.
Let's see, one of these
should be complex conjugated over here.
Well, both of them are trivially solved.
The equations of motion just tell
us that F star is nothing but
minus dv d phi.
And the complex conjugate.
In other words,
if you saw F,
you can eliminate it and put in dv d phi.
Okay, where do we see F in the action?
We see the action here, F star F.
We see F star times dv star d phi star.
But what is F star?
F star is dv d phi.
So this is also going to give us
dv d phi times dv star d phi star.
Same kind of term as this one will.
And this one will, and the other one
here will give us exactly the same kind.
In fact, two of them have minus
signs and one of them have plus signs.
The minus signs come from here.
Minus signs in dv d phi are minus F star.
What's that?
You wrote the wrong phi in the derivative.
Oh yes, you're right.
Phi.
Right.
F star is minus dv d phi.
So both of these terms here
are going to have negative signs,
and this one will have a positive sign.
The net result is that all of this adds
up to a potential energy for the phi field.
It's a new Lagrangian.
It's a term, a potential energy.
It's not super potential.
It's just ordinary potential energy.
And what is it?
Let's just call it ordinary v now of little phi.
Not the super potential.
And it is just F star F or
just dv by d phi absolute value squared.
In other words, F times F star.
So if somebody tells you, let's do an example.
Let's do an example.
Supposing I give you that the super potential is,
here it is,
v is equal to m times phi squared.
m times big phi squared.
But at this point it doesn't
matter if big phi or little phi.
What is dv d phi?
dv d phi is just m.
As I said, I'm not going to
keep track of factors of two today.
Apart from a factor of two, dv d phi
is just proportional to m times phi.
And what about the potential dv by d phi squared?
This is small phi here.
Small phi.
dv d phi squared just gives
us an m squared phi star phi.
That's a mass term.
That's a mass term which when
added to the Klein-Gordon Lagrangian here
would give the Klein-Gordon particle a mass.
Would give the scalar particle a mass.
Alright, so that's an example.
We worked that one out last time.
What happens if you were to have added
a phi cubed term?
Then this would become m phi squared.
Again, not worrying about numerical coefficients.
dv d phi would be m phi squared
and the ordinary potential would be
v would be
let's call this g now, not m.
G coupling constant.
This would be g squared
phi squared
phi star squared.
This would correspond to a Feynman diagram
in which two particles came
in and two particles went out.
A phi to the fourth term.
So if the whole upshot is
that if you're given a super potential
you can read off from it very quickly
what the ordinary potential energy of the field is.
Just derivative of the super potential squared.
Or absolute value squared.
That's a very simple process.
That's what you have to know about
supersymmetric quantum field theory
to have to understand a little bit about
supersymmetry breaking.
Let's plot vertically
the ordinary potential energy, not the super potential.
The super potential and the ordinary potential
notice that they're quite different.
The ordinary potential energy involves
the derivative of the super potential squared.
But once you've got it, you've got it.
So let's plot v of phi.
Notice first of all that it's always positive.
Where is it?
Here.
Well it doesn't have to always be positive.
What else could it be?
Could be zero, right?
Could be zero.
But it can't be negative.
It can't be negative.
Alright, so the potential as a function of phi
I'm being schematic.
Phi is a complex variable.
I can't draw a potential as
a function of a complex variable.
It's a function of phi star phi.
But let's just be schematic.
It could have a minimum someplace.
The minimum is where the vacuum is.
The minimum of the potential energy
is the vacuum in a field theory.
The minimum value of the potential energy
is the ground state.
And that's where the theory likes to sit at rest
in the vacuum.
Alright, one possibility is that
the minimum of the potential happens to be
at exactly the bottom here.
At v equals zero.
The meaning of that is that the vacuum
has no energy at all.
The vacuum, the energy of the vacuum,
the potential energy of the vacuum is zero.
The kinetic energy has to do with time derivatives
and space derivatives.
In the vacuum, those are not there.
So the vacuum energy in this case
would be exactly zero.
What does that imply?
That implies that at the minimum,
at the place where dv d phi equals zero,
v is also zero.
Or in other words, that at the minimum,
dv d phi has to be equal to zero.
Well, also a complex conjugate.
Why do I say that?
For this to be zero,
each factor in here has to be zero.
For a thing to be zero,
if it's a thing times its own complex conjugate,
then the thing inside this also has to be zero.
Okay, so if there is a vacuum with zero energy,
then it says that dv
d phi is equal to zero.
But remember what dv d phi is.
It's the F term in
the expansion of the super field.
In other words, it's a component of the super field.
It's a component of the super field,
and what it says is,
well, what it says is that component of
the super field is zero in the vacuum,
but it also says that the vacuum is supersymmetric.
Why?
Because for something to not be symmetric,
some component,
in the case of angular momentum and
in the case of the magnetic field,
what we said is if the vacuum
has a component of the magnetic field,
which is not equal to zero,
then that breaks the symmetry.
In the same way,
if a component, in particular the
last component of a super field,
is not equal to zero,
that breaks the symmetry.
Why?
Because these different components get
mixed up into each other
under a supersymmetric transformation.
So if F is,
in the same way that
the components of the angular momentum
get mixed up with each other,
or the magnetization get mixed up
with each other under a rotation,
the same thing happens to
the components of a super field.
This statement here is equivalent to
saying that the vacuum is supersymmetric.
What's the other possibility?
The other possibility is that the minimum of the potential,
this is not equal to zero.
If that's the case,
then you can make two conclusions.
The first is,
that the energy of the vacuum
is not going to be zero.
The vacuum will have some energy.
Who cares about vacuum energy?
The only people who care about vacuum energy
are ones who worry about gravity.
If you don't worry about gravity,
vacuum energy has no implication whatever.
But if you do worry about gravity,
vacuum energy is something to worry about.
It means that the vacuum gravitates.
So, vacuum energy is a dangerous thing.
But if dv d phi is not equal to zero,
then that says that the vacuum has an F term.
It has a non-zero component of the super field,
roughly speaking, pointing in some direction in super space.
And a super transformation will kind of rotate that.
It will correspond to supersymmetry breaking.
Alright, so if this is not equal to zero,
then supersymmetry is broken by the vacuum.
It's spontaneous symmetry breaking.
The theory itself was supersymmetric.
The vacuum simply has an energy in it.
That energy explicitly would gravitate,
if this was a gravitating theory.
But the important thing is,
if you work out all
of the details of the vacuum,
of the details of the equations,
you will also find, in that case,
that it behaves like a magnetic field.
F. F is kind of like
a component of a magnetic field.
And it has the effect of splitting the masses
of the different particles which rotate into each other
under the supersymmetry transformation.
Which of the particles which rotate into each other
under the supersymmetry transformation?
The fermions and the bosons.
So, the main lesson to draw from this
is that there is a theory of supersymmetry breaking
which is very close in spirit
to spontaneous symmetry breaking,
to conventional spontaneous symmetry breaking.
It does not require the equations to be not supersymmetric.
It requires the solutions of the equations
to somehow be non-symmetric
with respect to the supersymmetry.
And the result is, just like in the magnet,
the atom and the magnet will have split levels
in the same way the analog
of the atom and the magnet
would be a fermion or a boson, a particle,
and the two things which
are interchanged by the supersymmetry
will have their energies split.
The fermions and the bosons.
That's the implication of all of this.
One more implication.
If the vacuum is not supersymmetric,
if the vacuum is not supersymmetric,
the simple implication of that,
just in the same way if
the vacuum is not rotationally symmetric,
then a rotation of the vacuum gives you something new.
It gives you something which is not the vacuum.
It gives you a goldstone boson.
What happens if
the vacuum of supersymmetry transformation
is not symmetric under supersymmetry?
Then a supersymmetry transformation on the vacuum
gives you something new.
Anybody want to guess what that something new is?
Well, remember that supersymmetry transformations
interchange bosons and fermions.
The vacuum is formally counted as a boson state.
It's formally counted as a boson state.
But whatever the vacuum is,
a rotation by a supersymmetry transformation
will change it by adding a fermion.
A supersymmetry transformation always takes,
always adds or subtracts a fermion.
So the result is
that whenever supersymmetry is
spontaneously broken in this way,
there is a massless particle.
And the massless particle is
a fermion instead of a boson.
It's what happens to the vacuum
when you do the supersymmetry transformation.
If the vacuum is symmetric,
then you don't get anything new.
If the vacuum is not symmetric under supersymmetry,
which means that this is not equal to zero,
then when you do a supersymmetry transformation,
you do get something new,
and that new thing is a massless fermion.
It has a name.
Sometimes it's called the goldstone fermion
instead of a goldstone boson,
if that makes sense.
And sometimes it's called a goldstino.
Eno usually refers to a fermion.
The goldstino or the goldstone boson
is the particle that's generated
by doing a small supersymmetry transformation on the vacuum
if the vacuum is not symmetric.
So the two consequences
of spontaneous supersymmetry breaking,
there are two of them.
One is that the vacuum energy is not zero.
The minimum is not when v is equal to zero.
Or...
That's one.
So the vacuum energy is not equal to zero.
And the other consequence is
that there's a massless fermion,
a new massless fermion,
unexpected and as...
as unexpected as a goldstone boson.
And they're for the same reasons,
that the supersymmetry transformation
acting on the whole world
has to give you a new state,
and that new state is called the goldstone fermion.
Okay.
That's spontaneous supersymmetry breaking in a nutshell.
One more...
Well, there are two more points.
I mean, I'm giving you some...
I want to give you some jargon now
so that you'll recognize the jargon.
The atom by itself,
call that a sector of the theory.
The atom interacts with the ferromagnet.
Call a ferromagnet another sector of the theory.
If the magnetic field of the ferromagnet
were exceedingly strong,
it would do something awful to the atom.
The atom would be unrecognizable.
It would make spaghetti out of it.
Do you know what an atom looks like
when it's in an incredibly strong magnetic field?
A long stringy spaghetti-ish looking thing.
Right.
The atom would be unrecognizable.
But if the magnetic field is very weak,
then the atom is quite recognizable.
And what you would say,
and that's the situation we're going to be interested in,
the situation where the magnetic field
due to the ferromagnet...
We're not interested in ferromagnets, but by analogy,
the magnetic field of the ferromagnet is very weak.
The atoms are ordinary atoms,
and their levels are only slightly split.
The reason we're interested in that situation
is because compared to the fundamental
scale of particle physics, string theory,
grand unified theories, or anything like that,
which tends to be up at 16 orders of magnitude
larger than the particle physics scale,
the splitting of the superpartners
is hoped to be very small.
It's hoped that the superpartners
have almost the same mass on that scale
as ordinary particles.
That would be analogous to the magnetic field
due to the ferromagnet being very weak,
and only splitting these particles a little bit.
If the magnetic field were very weak,
the atoms would hardly notice it.
They would hardly notice it,
they would hardly interact with those magnetic fields,
and in fact, one of the consequences of this
would be that it's rather hard
by manipulating the atom...
by manipulating the atom
to influence the ferromagnet
because the ferromagnet,
they're too weakly coupled,
and so manipulating the atom
would not be likely to stir up spin waves,
would not be likely to stir up these...
the properties of the ferromagnet itself.
And in the language that we use,
the ferromagnet would correspond
to what's called a hidden sector.
It's a hidden sector in that
unless this was a very sophisticated atom,
it wouldn't even notice the ferromagnet.
It would just be tiny, tiny splittings,
and the ferromagnet would be a hidden sector.
In the same way,
particle physics, supersymmetric quantum mechanics
also requires hidden sectors
and additions of new objects and new particles
in order to break the supersymmetry.
It's not a pretty business.
It's a contrived business.
You have to add particles,
you have to add fields.
By the time you're finished,
you have a rather complicated construction,
and a complicated construction is necessary
to split among the fermions and the bosons.
That's...
and the ingredient which does it
is often called a hidden sector.
It's the thing which precipitates
the symmetry breaking.
Those are some...
words that go along with supersymmetry.
Yes, one last point.
One last point before we leave supersymmetry altogether.
Well, not altogether, but for tonight.
Gravity has an effect on this whole story.
Gravity has an effect on this whole story,
and it's a significant effect.
Um...
What...
First of all,
this has an effect on gravity,
and second of all,
gravity has an effect on it.
What is the effect
of a positive vacuum energy
if supersymmetry is broken?
It says that dv d
phi is not equal to zero,
and it says that the vacuum energy is not zero.
What does a nonzero vacuum energy,
and in particular,
a positive nonzero vacuum energy,
do to the world?
Okay.
What does it do to the world?
Well...
Cosmological.
Yeah.
It's a cosmological constant.
It goes into the equations of gravity
as a source on the right-hand side of gravity,
and it causes, um...
accelerated expansion of the universe
and very rapid.
If the particle physics scales here
were ordinary particle physics scales,
it would be a very rapid,
uh,
inflation or a very rapid
acceleration of the universe,
and it would be quite intolerable
if the scales that appeared here
were anything like the scales
that appear in the standard model or anything
or the supersymmetric version of it.
Uh...
And so, this is a bad thing.
This is not a good thing
to have a vacuum energy in a theory,
or a large vacuum energy in a theory,
and this vacuum energy would be quite large
if it was what we relied on
to split the particles.
If it was what we relied on
to split the particles,
this vacuum energy would be huge,
and it would completely, uh, destroy
any possibility of this theory being right.
I'm going to tell you a fact
or a couple of facts.
One is the effect of gravity
on this equation right here.
The effect of gravity on this equation right here
is to add or actually to subtract
another term.
This other term is...
Uh...
Do I have a Planck mass in the right place,
or do I have it upside down?
Oh, boy.
It's going to take me an hour to figure out.
Um...
Uh...
dv d phi squared...
I think, um...
I think the added term is minus 3.
Now, don't worry about the 3.
The 3 is not...
I promised you I wouldn't put in numbers.
This is one I happen to remember.
Not important, though.
And I think it's the Planck mass
times v of phi.
That's something that gravity adds to this.
Don't ask why.
It's very complicated.
It's exceedingly complicated.
You have to build theories of gravity
that have supersymmetry.
That's an extremely complicated story.
We won't even try.
But the net result is that gravity
adds a term here.
The effect of that term
can be to shift
the potential up and down.
Right?
In particular, if you're very lucky,
it can shift it down
to something close enough to zero
that the cosmological constant
is the small number we know.
So, gravity is a thing
that can come to the rescue
and get rid of the vacuum energy here.
As I said, it's very complicated.
I'm not going to try even to...
I'm not even sure I understand it.
Um...
But...
A bad situation is rescued by coupling
the supersymmetric field theory
to what's called supergravity.
Hard stuff.
The other thing is a little easier to understand,
but not easy to understand,
but still easier to understand.
It has to do with this...
It's related to the Higgs phenomena.
And the Higgs phenomena had the property
that it took the Goldstone boson
and combined it together
with the gauge boson
and made the gauge boson massive.
So, let me just say a few words about that.
This is something that's a little bit easier to understand.
Um...
If you have a particle of spin j,
or spin...
Yeah, let's say spin j.
How many states does it have?
Well, the answer is 2j plus 1.
How many spin states?
2j plus 1.
So, for example,
if the spin of a particle is 1,
the photon has spin 1.
Any gauge boson has spin 1,
then it has 3 states, right?
2j plus 1 is 3 states.
And so forth and so on,
depending on the spin of the particle.
Now, a photon only has 2 spin states.
And that's connected with the fact that it's massless.
So, let's say some things about
particle masses and spins and so forth.
Um...
Supposing I told you,
that...
Let's not take an election...
Yeah, let's, uh...
Let's...
Let's suppose the photon were massive.
And I told you it only has 2 spin states.
Namely, spin along its direction of motion
as a spin vector pointing along the direction of motion,
or the spin vector pointing
opposite to the direction of motion.
It has spin 1, but only 2 states.
Okay?
If the...
Um...
Let's see...
I don't know why I want to say this.
Yeah.
Then you would tell me
there's something inconsistent about this.
You would say, if the photon has a mass,
you can Lorentz transform it,
or equivalently run along and keep up with the photon
so that it has no momentum,
but a spin.
Lorentz transforming it doesn't change
the fact that it's a spin.
So, let's take this spin state here,
and Lorentz transform it
so that we're moving up along with it.
The photon no longer has any momentum,
but it has a spin.
And now, Lorentz transform it in an opposite...
in this direction here.
What have we made?
We've made a photon whose spin
is not along its direction of motion.
Okay?
All right, so we brought it to rest,
and now we're going to run along its direction.
and then transformed it in some other direction.
So therefore, if a photon is massive,
it has to have all three spin states.
It has to have spin along its axis,
spin opposite to its axis,
and the third spin state also.
On the other hand,
if the photon is massive, massless,
you can't bring it to rest.
You can't bring it to rest.
You can't do this opposite thing.
You can't do this opposite operation.
All you can do is rotate
the entire state of the photon
without bringing it to rest,
and all that does is simultaneously
rotate the momentum and the spin.
So if the spin was initially along
the axis of the motion of the photon,
it will stay that way.
The upshot is massless particles,
or massless photon, for example,
can have and does have only the two spin states
along its axis
and opposite to its axis.
How does the gauge bosons,
how do the gauge bosons of the electroweak theory
get another component of spin?
It would be the component of spin
along the direction of motion
where the spin along the direction of motion was zero.
Plus one, minus one,
and no spin along the z-axis at all altogether.
Where does that extra component
of the spin come from
so that the photon,
or not the photon,
but let's say the z-boson
or the w-boson can be massive?
Where does it come from?
And it comes from the goldstone boson.
The goldstone boson,
together with the two polarization states,
the two spin states of the massless z and w,
combine together
and make enough states to be the massive,
the massive z and w,
which requires three states.
The same exact thing happens
when you combine two particles
from a supersymmetric theory.
The two particles are, first of all,
the massless gravitino,
sorry, the massless,
yeah, the massless,
sorry, I didn't have,
let's get,
the massless goldstino.
The massless goldstino,
where is it?
Goldstino, come out,
where are you?
Well,
some other board.
All right.
The massless goldstino
has two spin states like the electron,
exactly like the electron,
and the massless goldstino
can either have its spin
along the axis of motion
or opposite to the axis of motion.
There's another particle,
which is the supersymmetric particle,
partner of the graviton.
We haven't even talked about gravitons,
but you all know they exist,
or they have to exist,
in a gravitational theory.
So what's the spin of the graviton?
Two, spin two, right.
The spin of its partner
is not a half-spin particle,
it's a spin three-halves particle.
Spin two and spin three-halves
form a multiplet.
It's also massless
because it's a partner
of the graviton.
So we have two kinds of massless,
and it's a fermion.
So we have two kinds
of massless fermions.
They're distinct and they're different.
One is the gravitino,
which, if it's moving along this axis,
can have spin three-halves
along that axis
or spin minus three-halves
along that axis.
But if it were massive,
it would also have to have
two other spin states,
spin one-half and spin minus one-half.
It would have to have the rest
of the full spin multiplet.
It would have to have spin minus three-halves,
minus one-half, plus one-half,
and spin three-halves.
Where does, where can
those other two components come from?
They can come from the Goldstino.
So the Goldstino combines together
with the graviton
in exactly the same pattern
as the Goldstone boson
can combine together
with a gauge boson
to make a massive object.
That's believed to be the case.
Of course, nobody knows
that this theory is right,
but if it is right,
there will be a massive
spin three-halves particle,
something we have never seen,
an elementary particle
of spin three-halves.
There will be a massive
spin three-halves particle,
but it will be as hard
to produce in the laboratory
as it is to produce a graviton.
It will be no easier,
which means you're not going to see it.
That's supersymmetry.
I'm sure it's more than you thought
you wanted to know about it.
Believe me, it's more than
I want to know about it,
but I have to know about it
because I'm required to.
It's part of my contract with Stanford.
And, uh,
I'm not going to tell you
what it is.
I'm going to tell you
Um,
we're absolutely finished
with the mathematics
of supersymmetry now.
We'll come back to some
of the physics of it,
but not the mathematics of it.
So, that's the good news.
Unfortunately, the bad news
is that grand unification
also is a somewhat
mathematical subject.
Not as bad,
not nearly as abstract.
It's a little bit of group theory.
Maybe we should take a
seven minute break.
And then we're going to change subjects.
We're going to change subjects
to something much easier to understand.
Uh,
SU .
SU is a simple theory,
not too hard to understand.
So, I heard now that this, um,
story about Cp-violet
is a little bit more complex.
But, uh,
I'm not going to go into
too much detail about it.
But, uh,
we're going to talk about
the whole thing.
And, uh,
we're going to talk about
the whole thing.
And, uh,
we're going to talk about
the whole thing.
And, uh,
in this business,
I mean, you know,
very rarely will you be wrong.
Of course, those times you'll really be wrong.
But, uh,
Alright, so,
um,
the standard model
is based on
some group theory.
SU cross
SU is the group of
color, of quartz,
SU2 is the
weak interactions,
and U1
is closely
related to the electromagnetic
interactions in a way that
I'll be a little more precise
about today than I was last
time.
Um, SU3
cross SU2 cross U1 is a group.
It's a group that consists
of separate
transformations
of
three things, two things,
or one thing.
But
people have
wondered
whether the whole
structure
could be embedded in
some group which is
more symmetric and more
simple than SU3
cross SU2 cross U1.
SU3 cross SU2 cross U1
fits in very
nicely into the group SU5.
And so
it was
asked whether,
numerous people
asked,
a small number of people answered,
whether it was possible
that there might be some
bigger group
in which a
larger number of particles,
okay, let's, let's, uh,
in which a larger number of particles
would fit together
into a single multiplet.
Remember that
the SU3 multiplets
consist of the quarks.
The SU2 multiplets,
well, quarks have some SU2
but they also have some SU3
and, uh,
there are also leptons.
Leptons have SU2 but they don't
have SU3. The question is
might they all fit together in something
more symmetric
and bigger
than the other?
And the natural candidate is SU5
and the reason is because SU3 cross,
SU5 is the simplest group,
the smallest group,
that contains SU3 cross SU2
cross U1 as a subgroup.
So, I need to explain to you
a little bit about what that means.
And the easiest
way to explain it is in terms of
the generators of groups.
SU5 is just
the group of special
unitary 5 by 5 matrices.
Let me just remind you what
special means and what unitary means.
You know what unitary means. Unitary means
that U dagger U is equal to 1.
And
special means that the determinant
of U is equal to 1.
This doesn't mean absolute value, it means determinant.
Determinant of U
or the product of the eigenvalues
determinant of U
is equal to 1.
In general, a unitary group
can have a determinant which is a
phase, E to the i theta.
The special set
is the set which has determinant
U equal to 1. This can be
translated into the generators
of the group. Remember what the generators
mean? It means that
small deviate
group elements which are small deviations
away from the identity, this is the
identity element.
This means the number 1.
The
small deviations away from the
identity element, small infinitesimal
transformations
can be written in the form of
1, that's the identity,
plus
i times
a small number
times one of the
generators of the group. The
generators of the group correspond to
the different directions
about which the different independent
directions of
transformation that you can do. In the case
of angular momentum, what would be the 3 axes?
In the case of
SU5, there's some
independent set of generators.
How many generators are there for,
how many independent, linearly
independent generators there are?
We'll work that out
in a minute, but the
answer turns out to be 8.
I think we've talked about that before.
And
so,
you characterize the group by
the generators and the commutation relations
among the generators. But,
before we do that,
the unitary character
of the
group elements
translates
into the Hermitian character of G.
So G
is equal to G dagger.
That's an abstract group statement,
but it's also a concrete statement
about 5 by 5, well,
N by N matrices.
We might as well now specialize to 5 by 5
matrices, but everything I say here is also
true for N by N matrices.
For group SU5,
the generators, the 5 by 5
all matrices
are 5 by 5 matrices,
and the generators, first of all,
have to be Hermitian,
and secondly,
the
determinant condition
is the condition that the trace of G
is equal to 0.
Traceless
Hermitian
matrices. Now this is
analogous to the Pauli matrices
for SU2.
The Pauli matrices for
SU2 are Hermitian, and they have
no trace. They're traceless.
So the Pauli matrices would be a
special case.
Let's see if we can count how many
such independent matrices
there are.
5 by 5, linearly independent.
Well, the 5 by 5 matrices,
they're Hermitian. That means
that the
on-diagonal elements are real,
and the off-diagonal
elements, these are real.
Real, real,
real. The on-diagonal
elements, off-diagonal elements are
complex in general, but
when you
reflect them about the axis,
they just complex conjugate, and
that's the character of a Hermitian matrix.
So the question is
how many parameters are there,
how many real parameters,
real, independent real parameters
are there in such a matrix?
Well, you start off
with the
total number of them,
n by n,
that's n squared.
It looks like there's some
constraints,
c is equal to c dagger.
However, that sounds like it cuts the
number of components in half,
but not really, because a complex
number has a real and imaginary
part. So this is
two independent components,
or two independent real numbers,
and these two together
are simply two independent real numbers,
just as they look. So the number
of independent components
of a square Hermitian
matrix like this is n squared.
But then we have to subtract
one for the trace condition.
The trace condition is the
sum of the diagonal elements
add up to zero, and so
the answer is there are n squared minus
one generators
of the group
s, u, n. Let's just check that
for the
one case that we know. For s, u, two
n squared minus one would be
two squared minus one would be three,
and they would be the three Pauli matrices,
or the three components of
angular momentum would be an example,
three components of spin.
Okay, so for the case s, u, five
there are twenty-four independent
twenty-five minus one,
twenty-four independent
generators of the group.
That's a lot, but fortunately
we're not going to have to deal
with most of them.
The question is,
which subset of them
correspond to the generators
of the group?
We have s, u, three, s, u, two,
and u, one.
This is not hard to figure out.
You can divide
the five by five matrices
into
rows and columns,
two of them here
and three of them here,
two of them here and three of them here.
The two here are for s, u, two.
Okay?
If you put up here in the corners
the generators of s, u, two,
the generators of s, u, two
are three generators.
What are they? They're the Pauli matrices.
In the context of spin,
the Pauli matrices are usually called
sigma.
In the context of internal symmetries,
they're often called tau.
Tau one, tau two, tau three,
so I'll write them down over here.
Tau three is just one minus one,
zero, zero.
Tau one is one, one,
And tau two
is minus i,
i, zero, zero.
Okay, those are the three Pauli matrices.
And if you just stick in this corner
the tau matrices,
notice that they are traceless,
they're already traceless,
they are Hermitian,
and you put zero everywhere else.
These are the generators
of s, u, two.
These, the algebra of these,
the commutation relations of them,
everything about them
is equivalent
to the
properties of the taus themselves.
And so,
among the five by five matrices,
generators,
the subset which just live in this corner
over here
are generators of
the group s, u, two.
Okay? The ones down here
I won't write them down,
there are eight of them.
They're usually called lambda,
has nothing to do with the cosmological constant,
there are eight of them.
Three by three, they're three by three
Hermitian traceless matrices.
Those are the generators of s, u, three.
So,
so to speak, s, u, two lives up in here,
and s, u, three lives in here.
Now the s, u, two
and the s, u, three matrices
by themselves are traceless.
There's one
additional generator
which commutes
with all of these,
which commutes with all of them,
and which describes the
u, one
properties of elementary particles.
The u, one particle
and that's a diagonal
matrix which has zero
trace.
It commutes with s, u, two because it's
proportional to the identity in here.
Let's call it, let's see, what did I call it?
Well, we could call it
minus one,
it doesn't matter,
minus one or plus one doesn't matter.
You just change the sign of it.
That would just,
it's a convention whether you put minus one
or plus one in here.
But it's proportional to the unit matrix
of the unit matrix
in the two dimensional
sub,
substructure here associated with
two, so it's just the unit matrix
with a minus sign in this case
that I put in here
for reasons
that have to do with old conventions.
And then in here
you put, the whole
thing has to be traceless, and I
want to put something here which commutes
with all the s, u, three generators,
all the s, u, two generators.
It has to be proportional to the unit matrix
in here, and what do I need it to be?
I need it to be, if this is one,
so the trace of this is minus one,
I want two thirds,
two thirds,
and two thirds.
Zero everywhere else.
This generator has a name,
it's called y.
It's a generator of s, u, five
which distinctly
distinguishes the s, u, two block
from the s, u, three block.
It has different values
in the s, u, two block
than it does in the s, u, three block.
In the s, u, two block it has
values minus one, in the s, u,
three block it has value two thirds.
I've chosen two thirds
here, it was a convention that I
put minus one here. I could have
put anything here as long
as these two were the same.
But, in order to make
it have zero trace, in other words to make
the sum of the elements be
zero, I had to put two thirds here.
Alright.
These are the
generators of the group that are important
that
label the states
of particles.
Label the states of quarks
and leptons to be exact.
Label the states of
also Higgs bosons.
And so now I will tell you
how this structure works.
How it's connected with
the particles.
If we were just doing s, u, three
without s, u, two,
I might put here
what would I put there?
Quarks.
I would say
the s, u, three matrices
the unitary s, u, three matrices
act on a column vector
of quarks.
What are the column vector?
The colored quarks. Red, yellow, and green
or whatever we call them.
And mix them up among themselves.
What about the
s, u, two block?
In the s, u, two block here
I could put for example
neutrino and electron.
Neutrino and electron are mixed by the s, u, two.
There's five of them here
and so the question is
what particles shall I identify
with the basic
five-plet, with the basic
five-dimensional column vector here
that these s, u, five
transformations act on.
Alright. In order to answer that
well, we'll answer it
by just
some guessing
and some educated
guessing.
Okay.
But before we do it
let's write down
the whole
collection of
fermions that are in
the standard model.
The whole collection of them. Now I don't have to
write the whole collection because they
come in families.
They come in three families.
The electron
neutrino up-down family.
The
muon
neutrino
charm
strange family.
And the last family that involves the tau
and the other quarks.
Alright. So we just focus on
one family now.
The electron neutrino up-quark
down-quark family. Let's write them all
down, count up how many there are
and see how we might fit them
into representations
of s, u, five.
Now why
do we want to fit them into representations?
What would be the implications of fitting
them into s, u, five? Remember
that
the symmetry group
also has other implications.
There are gauge bosons that go
with the symmetry group. For example
for the s, u, three, what are the gauge bosons
for the s, u, three group?
The gluons.
Alright.
So there are eight gluons
associated with the eight generators
of s, u, three.
What about the s, u, two gauge bosons?
Those have to do with the w plus,
the w minus,
and z
and photon bar. Some combination
of z and photon.
So
For example,
if I had this
growth I'm going
to Orion you know
This
I'm going to stop calling them left-handed
they're all left-handed
the up quark
no, I didn't want to write that
the down quark
the anti-down quarks
now I haven't written
I obviously have not written all particles down
I've written down only five here
five, uh-huh, that's your five
but why did I write down
this five, we'll see in a moment
those are six
oh, one, two, three, wait, hold
on, what did I write here
up quark, no up quark
forget the up quark
neutrino, electron, down bar, down bar, down bar
what are these three here, what does that stand for
the three colors
alright, so this is one subset
and why I've broken them up this
way will become clear in a minute
okay, the next subset, the remaining ones over here
I will simply list also
let's see what they are
they're down, down, down
up bar, up bar, oops
down, down, down
up, up, up
up bar, up bar, up bar
and E plus
this is E minus
electron, positron
now, among the electron, up
quark, down quark they're all here
here's the electron, here's the positron
it is not believed, and
certainly not in the standard model
the neutrino is its own antiparticle
so there is not a
separate antiparticle for the neutrino.
The electrons, here's the two antiparticles,
here are the three down quarks, here
are their antiparticles, here are the three
up quarks, here are the antiparticle, and
here is the positron. They're all there.
Okay, the fact that I wrote them in this
way, I just chose to write them in this
list. There are five over here and I hope
ten over here. One, two, three, four, five, six,
seven, eight, nine, ten. Okay, so
all together there are 15 particles. Now
these 15 particles are replicated three
times. The electron neutrino system gets
replicated as the muon neutrino.
This is the electron neutrino. This
gets replicated three times. All of these
get replicated three times, but let's not
worry about the replication and
where that comes from. Nobody knows
about that.
Let's see where that comes from. Good. Now
the reason, let me show you why I chose
this particular pattern here. It's pretty clear that
what goes up in here, if I want
to write a column vector now of fermions,
it's pretty clear that what goes up in here
should not have color.
Right? Why? Because SU doesn't act on the
first two slots here. SU acts on it, SU
does not. So the first two slots here should
be things which have no color, but which mix
up under SU . In other words,
which mix up under these SU transformations, tau.
All right, so what can that be? Well,
neutrino and electron. So, neutrino and electron, they're
two electrons mixed up under, uh,
left-handed, neutrino and left-handed electron get mixed
up by SU . And they don't have color.
So it's the only thing you could put over
here would be neutrino, electron. Now the fact
that I put neutrino on top and electron
underneath it, to some extent that's convention. All
right, so the reason I put neutrino on
top, electron underneath is just because
that's the way it's usually written.
What should I put down here? Now down here
I want to put quarks, but those quarks have
SU , but no SU . Which of
the quarks have SU , but no SU ?
Anybody know? The right-handed quarks. Left-handed
quarks have weak interactions, that's SU .
The right-handed quarks don't. But
I haven't listed right-handed quarks here.
I've listed all particles as
either left-handed particles or left-handed antiparticles.
The group here, which don't have weak interactions,
are the antiparticles, uh, are the, are the
antiquarks, where's d-bar, u-bar and d-bar?
These are the ones that
do not have any SU properties
They are the antiparticles of the right-handed quarks
The right-handed quarks are not the ones that
interact in beta decay in the weak interactions
They are neutral, or they don't transform under SU
And neither do their antiparticles
So these are the guys here,
if you label everything as left-handed
These are the people here which don't transform under SU
Which of these two do I
want to put in this slot?
Okay, so now I will tell
you how you figure that out
You see, one of the gauge bosons
is going to have to be the photon
The photon couples to electric charge
The electric charge must be one
of the generators of this SU
Otherwise the whole thing wouldn't make sense
The SU
The quantum numbers are supposed to be all of
the quantum numbers of the electro weak QCD color theory
All of them
What does that mean?
That means the electric charge, the color quantum numbers, and
the things which have to do with Z and W
The electric charge has to be
one of the generators of SU
But all of the generators of SU are traceless
What does that mean?
That means that in a given multiplet, the sums of the
electric charge within a given multiplet have to add up to zero
That's the statement that the
generators of SU or anything else
It's exactly the same thing as saying you
have a plus one and a minus one
If a thing, if there's a multiplet of a...
If there's a multiplet of a...
Of a tau three, let's say spin
One of them is going to be up,
one of them is going to be down
The sums of the two spins, the
Z components of spin add up to zero
Same thing for SU
If you have a multiplet of
SU particles, it transforms into SU
Any given generator, if it describes a quantum number, the
sums of those quantum numbers must add up to zero
So whatever we put here
It has to be such that the
electric charges all add up to zero
This has zero electric charge
This has electric charge minus one
So the sum here must add up to plus one
Which of these particles has charge
which adds up to plus one?
That's this one
D quarks have charge minus a third
Anti-D quarks have charge plus a third
So zero, I'll just write the charges down
Zero minus one
And now if I put the anti-D quarks here
This all together has charge plus one
Plus one, plus one, plus one
Oh sorry, plus a third,
plus a third, plus a third
And the sums of all of them equals zero
If I were to put the U quarks there
Or the anti-U quarks
They have charge two thirds
Forget this here
And the charges would not have added up to zero
Okay
So it's a matter of group
It comes from the
Ultimately it comes from the trace
The tracelessness of the generators of the group
That we're trying to label the particles by
We're labeling them by generators of
SU and the sums of elements
The sums of elements of
SU always add up to zero
So the sums of these charges
have to add up to zero
That picks out the D quarks there
Or the anti-D quarks
Anti-D quarks because those are the ones
that do not have SU quantum numbers
Don't get mixed up by SU
And it really is that way
I mean the particles really are that way
But where do we put the rest of the particles?
The rest of the particles
There are ten of them
So the rest of the particles are
the same as the rest of the particles
So the next question is
Is there
It's nine o'clock
That's the next question
We're going to come back to this
We'll fill out the remaining ten particles
In another representation of SU
Not a five dimensional representation
But guess what?
A ten dimensional representation
There is a ten dimensional representation
Alright
And the ten dimensional representation
Has exactly the right properties
To be the remainder of these particles here
This is either a fantastic accident
Or it is something deep
And I don't think it's an accident
The remaining particles here
Exactly fill out the ten dimensional representation of SU
So we'll come back to that next time
And I'll show you how that works
I don't understand how the
different representations of the same group
Can allow the building to have a group structure
No
These particles do not get mixed with these
Under the group transformations
They don't interact with each other?
Oh, they do interact with each other
But not by
Yeah, they do interact with each other
But there is no gate
Okay, so let's
Good, good question
Alright
Let's take the gluon, for example
One of these particles can emit a gluon
And become one of the other ones
They cannot emit a gluon and become one of these
But a d-bar can emit a gluon
Which is absorbed by a U-quark, for example
So the generators take
The generators which are the same as the emitting particles
As the emission matrix elements for the gluons here
They take one quark to another
They take these to these
These to these
But they don't take this to this
However, that doesn't mean they don't interact
Same thing here, same thing
All of the generators of
SU mix these up among themselves
Mix these up among themselves
Do not mix these with these
But that simply means that in order
to have this side interact with this side
You have to emit and then absorb
And then absorb
So you can have
The group of five over here
Interact with the group of ten over here
By exchange of gauge bosons
Okay?
Yeah
Also the Higgs boson gets
into it and makes them interact
Yeah
For more, please visit us at stanford.edu