Stanford University.
Let's begin with tonight's subject.
Tonight's subject is grand unified
theories, or SU5 in particular.
There are many, many things
that are called grand unified theories,
and we're not going to study all of them.
We're just going to take apart one version of it,
and see if we can see
what it is that makes it tick,
what some of its problems are,
and if I have time
to discuss the connection with supersymmetry,
which does exist, I'll try to fill
you in on what the connection is.
The connection is not some deep
thing that supersymmetry implies grand unification,
or that you can't do anything about it.
It's not something that you can do anything about.
It's not something that
grand unification implies supersymmetry.
No, it's just that if
you put both of them together,
you get a numerically better fit to
certain things than either one by itself.
Okay, so I should begin with
a few words about group theory.
Grand unified theories, whatever they
are, are based on group theory.
The group theory extends the SU3 cross SU2 cross U1,
of the standard model.
And it fits, or that
group, SU3 cross SU2 cross U1,
fits very comfortably into the group SU5.
Special unitary transformations acting
on five complex variables.
But before we do, I think we
should say a few words about group representations.
The particle multiplets form,
group representations that means the
symmetry groups act among them and
scramble them up in various ways and
before you can start to classify the
particle the particle multiplets you
have to classify the representations of
groups okay so the reputation
the representations of groups let's begin
with s let's start with s un
oh incidentally in the case of su2 su2
has to do with spin not the su2 of
the su not the su2 of the weak interactions
but the su2 of the rotations of
space su2 happens to be very closely related
to rotations of three-dimensional space
the simplistic statement that is the
same that they're the same thing
and that's good enough for us
um
, su2 classifies the spin representations
of particles the angular momentum of
particles or the angular momentum of
atoms or the angular momentum of
anything an angular momentum comes
in different kinds of multiplets there's
the singlet which is sometimes just
called a scalar because it doesn't
transform on the rotation at all
and that corresponds to spin zero
this is the spindle which is the spin of
the electron half spin that corresponds to
spin a half and there's a rep there
is a yes a group representation of
su2 for every integer and half integer
multiple of for every integer and half
integer spin one spin three halves spin
Spin two, spin five, whatever comes next.
Zero, one half, one.
The next one must be one and a half, huh?
Three halves.
Three halves, four halves, five
halves, six halves, seven halves.
Got it.
Okay.
All right.
There are group representations, and they correspond to sets of
objects that the group acts on and mixes them up.
Okay.
Let me just tell you a little bit
about group representations, all that we'll really need.
For S-U-N, the basic representation is called the defining representation, and it's just columns,
column vectors of N entries, one, two, three, four, up to the Nth entry.
Altogether, N units big.
Complex entries.
Let's give them names.
Let's call them psi one, psi two,
psi three, dot, dot, dot, to psi N.
And the group is described by matrices, special unitary
matrices, which act on these entries and mix them up.
Psi prime, let's call them.
Mix them up, multiply them by constants.
You know what they do.
Okay.
So that's the defining representation.
And how many?
Dimensional is it?
It's N-dimensional.
Okay.
Now, the first and simplest thing that you can do to
the defining representation of S-U-N is to take its complex conjugate.
In other words, take the
collection of entries, psi one, star.
Let's see.
First of all, let's give these things names.
This representation can either be called
the defining representation or just the N.
I cut out the word representation because
we usually just say it's the N.
Or the representation of dimensionality N, which is
acted on by the defining special unitary matrices.
Now you take their complex conjugates.
Psi two, star, dot, dot, dot.
Psi star, N.
The matrices which act, if psi is acted on to
get mixed up by matrices, let's call them U, unitary matrices,
then psi star is acted upon not by
the same matrices, but by the complex conjugate matrices.
So the psi stars actually transform
in a different way than psi itself.
Okay.
conjugate representation. So first of all we
have the n representation and we have
let's list some representations over here. There's
the n and there's the n bar
associated if you like with particles and antiparticles.
Okay, next. What else can you do?
Did that terminology use whether n is even or odd?
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Does n refer to the matrices?
It defen- it depen- yes. It refers to the
size of the matrices, the size of the def- or
to the size of the defining representation.
I mean n is- it also is
a way of referencing the group itself.
Right. And for the defining
representation they're the same. Okay.
So the defining representation is the same.
The defining representation, if the group
is s-u-n, the defining representation is n-dimensional
and the unitary matrices are n by n matrices. Okay.
Now you can construct more complex-
and in that sense, to that degree,
the n and the n bar are both
n-dimensional representations and it's a matter of complete
convention which one of these you think of as defining
and which one of you think of
as the complex conjugate of a defining representation.
Closely connected to it with the
fact that the antiparticle of a particle-
the antiparticle of an antiparticle is a particle,
so it doesn't matter which one you call particle
and which one you call antiparticle.
Once you name it, you stick with it though.
Okay. The next thing you can do,
let's suppose that these columns here represent
the states, the possible states of a single particle.
Again, they could represent the spin states, up or down.
They could represent proton or
neutron in what's called isospin.
They could represent the three
colors of quarks, red, yellow, blue,
or whatever the appropriate degree of the quark is.
The degree of freedom is.
Alright, so here we have a particle over here,
and it can have any one of n states.
Let's put another particle in right next to it.
How many states are there?
And we're only thinking now about the
internal quantum number associated with the group S-U-N.
We're not thinking about its position, its
momentum, or even its spin right now.
If this particle can be
in any one of n states,
how many states can the two particles be in?
That's quite clear. It's n squared.
So there must be an n squared...
Minus one?
No.
No, no, no.
I'm saying that n squared would require superposition.
E?
Would it require superposition?
Superposition.
Superposition of what?
The violation of the exclusion principle.
No, no, wait a second.
This particle is over here,
and this one is definitely over here.
They're in two different locations.
We're just trying to do the
mathematics of group theory, but pictures.
Okay?
So they're definitely at
different locations on the blackboard.
There's no question of them being in the same state,
because one of them is nailed down over here,
and one of them is nailed down over here.
I'm saying if there's a fixed number of states,
and one of them is occupied...
Being in two different places is a change of quantum...
Right. Right.
The Pauli exclusion principle would say
you can't put two particles in the same state,
but being in the same state entails not only
these internal quantum numbers,
but being at the same place.
All right?
Now, I explicitly tell you,
they're not in the same place.
One of them is here,
and one of them is there.
Once you say that,
there are no further constraints
of the Pauli exclusion principle.
They are not in the same place.
They don't exclude each other in any way.
All right.
So this one's over here.
In fact, they could even be different particle types.
These could be one set of particles.
This could be another,
but it just happens that they transform
under the same...
n-dimensional representation.
All right. So how many states then,
just with respect to this SU ,
not with respect to their position,
angular momentum,
or other interesting quantities,
but just with respect to this n-ness,
let's call it the n-ness of the particle,
how many states there are?
It's clear. There are 25.
And that's correct.
25 such states,
n cross n times n, n squared.
Okay.
Now,
you could label the states,
if you label the states of one particle
as psi i,
you could label the two particles
system as psi ij.
Psi ij.
If psi i runs from 1 to n,
then psi ij runs from 1 to n squared
if you let i and j
run over the n squared possibilities.
So for example,
there would be the state psi ij,
in which both particles are in the one state.
There would be psi ij,
psi ij would be particle,
this particle in state i,
this particle in state ii.
There would be psi ij,
that would be the opposite.
This particle in state i,
this particle in state i.
Again, no exclusion principle is operative here.
And so there are n squared possible entries.
How do you transform these things?
You transform them by thinking of
the i index and the j index
separately rotating under the group.
And in fact,
an even simpler way to think about it
is to think of this as a product.
Psi i,
let's call it phi j.
This particle is described by psi,
this one by phi.
It's got n squared entries.
And how does the group
act on this collection of things?
By acting on psi and phi separately.
Rotating psi and rotating phi.
Alright, so that defines
an n squared dimensional representation of the group.
But that representation is not irreducible.
Now what is irreducible?
That's a new word.
What is irreducible?
What does irreducible mean?
What it means is that there are certain combinations
of psi i, j
which transform among themselves
and don't get mixed up with other combinations.
Certain linear combinations
which transform among themselves
and don't get mixed up with the other linear,
with the other combinations.
They can be pulled aside
and thought of as a rep,
or they can be pulled aside,
but they are not.
We use the same definition
of the same term
for the pressure of the moment in the model.
So for the moment of the moment in the model,
I'm going to give you an example in a moment.
But let's just talk about
what this would mean for ordinary spin.
We have two spin states,
each one labeled by either up or down.
Alright, so we have altogether four states.
Up, down, up, down.
and spins pointing down. Alright, now these
are two half spin particles. If you combine
two half spin particles, there are four
possible states, but the four possible states form
among themselves multiplets. What are the
multiplets that the four states form, you
know? One combination is a singlet, and
the singlet corresponds to zero spin, and the
other combination is a triplet of states, which
forms spin one. A spin a half and a
spin a half can form either spin zero or
spin one. What, how does one understand that from
the point of view of psi ij? That's what
I'll tell you right now. Psi ij, thought of as
a function of two spins, can be either
symmetric under interchange of i and j, or anti-symmetric.
Of course it could also be a linear.
It's only a combination of symmetric and anti-symmetric,
but let's consider all psi ij's which are symmetric,
so that if you interchange i and j,
they become the same thing. How many independent configurations
is that, you know? Three. Three
linearly independent combinations that are anti-symmetric,
that are symmetric.
I'm going to tell you what they correspond
to. They correspond to up, up, that's symmetric,
down, down, and one over square root of two,
up, down, plus down, up. Those are the three
which are symmetric with respect to interchange, and
they have the property that when you act
with the group SU on them, they mix up
among themselves, but do not mix in the last one.
The last one is the last one. The last one
is the last one. The last one is the last
one.
One over square root of two, up
down minus down up. The anti-symmetric combination.
So this is the symmetric combination, and
how many states are there? Linearly independent
ones, three. A spin one multiple.
So when you take two half spins, one way
of combining them can give you spin one, and
the other way is your pi past a. borderline. Is
that a Geeeees a three by two, a three by
unique there's only one anti-symmetric combination
it's up down minus down up
it's a singlet and that means it
just doesn't transform under the group at all
it's a scalar with respect to these
group rotations and that gives you the
zero spin combination so this is
a pattern you can take objects which
transform as not as an N and an N bar
but as two N's well N bar okay we can call
that N cross N psi ij is an object which
lives in the N squared or N cross N the
cross here simply means with combining two
systems the N cross N but we can
take the symmetrical
the symmetrical
the symmetrical combinations and the anti-symmetric
combinations they do not mix with each
other the group operations do not mix
the anti-symmetric and the symmetric so
there is symmetric and psi ij
anti-symmetric we'll count later how many how
many of them are there of each
kind
of the义总
i left you do the counting not too hard
to count i can't remember offhand this isваensally a smaller我有
representation than this one sigh IJ symmetric and sigh
ij anti-symmetric and mistakeothan популярRockchip-Implemented20xPsy koşت Luci Center size simmetri
and those are two distinct representations Beauty with Rac
in in sine oang Joey destroyexamples andanstro
phoe producto éthirez o' grown inscience taeherexrapeteris
symmetric
and n cross n
anti-symmetric let's call it
we're going to see some examples of this kind of thing we're
going to work it out for SU and see what kind of
representations they have
next
we've already said that you can take
that there's a complex conjugate representation
that could correspond to a particle
and instead of putting two particles down
to study we could put a particle
and an anti-particle let's put a
bar over it a particle and anti-particle
this is different than a particle and a particle
the question is what's the group theory or what's
the representation that describes a particle and an anti-particle
how many states are there
n squared again right exactly n squared
and again there are two ways of combining them well
there may be more than two ways of combining them
but no there are really n squared sorry n squared
you can combine them
again symmetrically or anti-symmetrically
no you can combine them
I'm sorry I take that back
alright
if you take these two things
you and you write a let's give a different label to it because it
doesn't it's not in the n squared it's in the n cross n bar
but there are still n squared independent elements
they again are described by some matrix
m i j this is
also a matrix psi i j
this is a matrix but you discover when
you start thinking about working out the transformation properties
that they're really not the same as the other
ones that we've talked about in the last lecture
there really are only two independent combinations
one of them being the traceless combination
and the other being everything else
we've seen this before we've seen it in SU where I
told you that there's a representation of SU which is eight dimension
of SU which is eight dimensional instead of nine dimensional
a particle a quark and an anti-quark
so you have nine possible states
but those nine possible states can be in a singlet
and the rest of them correspond to trace
equals zero or m trace of this equals zero
and those form what is called the adjoint representation
the adjoint representation has dimension n squared minus one
for SU three n squared minus one is eight
alright we've seen how that corresponds
to the eight gluons of quantum chromodynamics
for what is it for SU two
it's called the adjoint
what is the adjoint representation for SU two
three dimensional and it corresponds to spin one
for SU three it's eight
dimensional it's called the adjoint representation
but that leaves one more
linear combination namely just this one
that's a singlet that's a state which
doesn't transform under the group at all
alright so this is all we
need to know about group representations
that there's the representation n
which is the fundamental defining representation
there's the representation n bar
which is the complex conjugate
and you can multiply them together
which is really just the act of
putting down different numbers of particles and anti-particles
or group theoretically it's that
combining the representations together
and then sorting out and finding
which combinations are the most important
and then the combinations will transform into each other
under the group
separating the transformation
properties into different representations
and that is the process
for example of taking two spins
and discovering that they can
form spin zero or spin one
a three dimensional representation
or a one dimensional representation
spin zero is the one dimensional representation
in SU three similar kinds of things
SU five the same kind of things
now we're going to see
how this works by explicit example
the group that we're interested in is SU five
SU five mixes up five objects
which I don't know what to call them
let's call them just the fermions
which fermions we'll see in a moment
the fermions belonging to a single family
there are three families of fermions that are known
and only three is probably correct
I'll just remind you what the first family consists of
it consists of three quarks
well two quarks up and down
but each up and down quark comes in three
or each quark comes in three colors
so this is red, yellow, blue
red, yellow, blue
also there are the leptons
the electron and its corresponding neutrino
there's a neutrino for each lepton type
and this pattern gets replicated three times
and we'll just refer to one of these families
sometimes called families
sometimes called generations
one of these families at a time
nobody has a unified theory of how to unify together
the different replications of the same pattern
that is completely beyond us
we don't even know what it means
not what it means, we know what it means
but we don't know how to understand why it's so
so let's just focus on
such a combination of particles here
alright, so
what are the five entries
it's easiest just to write
down what the five entries are
for the defining representation
and then explore a little bit about it
just as you would put for SU3
you would put red quark, yellow quark, and blue quark
the three entries
that's what gets mixed up by SU3
then SU5 mixes up
neutrino
electron, which I'll write as E-
to indicate that it's a negatively charged electron
and the three down anti-quarks
which three?
the three of the three colors
now this is a bizarre thing to combine together
but as you see it makes a lot of sense
these are quarks, or anti-quarks to be specific
and only the down anti-quarks
neutrino and electron
they form a multiplet under the group SU5
and what is the group SU5?
it's just the five by five matrices
which mix these things up among themselves
in other words, transformations which
can take neutrino to electron
and electron to neutrino
we've seen those already
those are the SU2
of the weak interactions
the SU2 of the weak interactions
mix neutrino with electron
and what about the things which mix
the anti-dequarks
well that's just a color group
red, yellow, and green
so
the transformations which mix up
these things here
that's just color
quantum chromodynamics
but now we have some new things here
but now we have some new possibilities
and we're going to have to explore those
transformations which take neutrino to down
anti-down quarks
electrons to anti-down quarks
and so forth, something new
now remember that for each
one of these
mixing ups, let's call them
there's typically a gauge boson
which allows transitions between them
the gauge bosons which allow
one d-quark to go to another d-quark
or d-bar quark, what are those gauge bosons?
the gluons
what about the gauge bosons
which take electrons to neutrinos
and back and forth
those are the W's
and so
this is the corner here
that corresponds to weak interactions
and this is the bigger corner
that corresponds
this is SU here
and SU here
where U1 is hiding will come to
I hope will come to it, we'll see
we'll see
alright, so this is the defining representation
it's very strange, there's no up quarks
where's the up quarks?
one other point which I mentioned last time
is we always treat the point of the equation
of particles as left-handed
ok, left-handed particles
now what about the right-handed particles?
the electron
the left-handed electron comes
together with a right-handed electron
well the answer is that if a particle is left-handed
or if a particle is right-handed
its anti-particle is left-handed
so we can always enumerate the particles
by enumerating only left-hand particles
for example if we were enumerating the electrons
we would enumerate not electron and positron
but the left-handed electron
let me just put a little L next to it
and the left-handed positron
the left-handed positron
the anti-particle of the left-handed positron
is the right-handed electron
this is just a notational device
or
a way of enumerating particles
but it's useful because
these groups that we're talking about
do not turn left-handed particles
into right-handed particles and so forth
so we keep track of the particles as left-handed
we don't miss any that way
we just have to remember that
when we're looking for the anti-particle
for example
the d-quark
the anti-d-quark
this is the anti-d-quark
but the left-handed
these are all left-handed
and they form the basic left-handed representation of SU5
now where are all the other particles
in fact we probably ought to
write down what they all are
all the left-handed particles
let's list them
there's the left-handed neutrino
that's the one we see in weak interactions
there's the left-handed E-
there's the d-bars
three of them
then there's the left-handed E-
this is no particular order here
I'm just writing them all down
there's the left-handed positron
what about the left-handed d-quark
d-d-d
three colors of left-handed d-quark
and what am I missing?
I'm missing the up-quarks
the left-handed up-quarks
up-up-up
and also the left-handed anti-quarks
up-bar
let's see if I have everything
I have electron and positron
that's good
left-handed
I have d-bar quarks and d-quarks
and I have up-quarks and anti-up-quarks
what's missing is an anti-neutrino
okay
we're going to come to the question of anti-neutrinos
but I will tell you this
the standard model
the pure form of the standard model
does not have
an additional
let's call it left-handed anti-neutrino
the left-handed version of
sorry
the right-handed version
of the neutrino
is the anti-particle of the left-handed
there's a left-handed neutrino
and a right-handed anti-neutrino
there is no right-handed neutrino
and whatever the missing one that I didn't say was
yeah okay
this is the collection of fermions
in the first family of the standard model
and that's all there is
okay so let's see which ones we've captured
in the five here
neutrino electron down down down
that's it
okay now why did I group the down quark there
I have a question
yes
you had mentioned that
fermions get their mass from oscillating
changing
left to right yeah
and does that mean it also changes into an anti-particle
while it's
no it changes into the particle of the same
okay
depends on whether we're talking about neutrinos
or the other particles
say electron
electron nope
electron turns into an electron
left-handed electron becomes
left right-handed electron
otherwise it would violate charge conservation
if a left-handed electron
if an electron became a positron
something bad happened
charge disappeared
so but that doesn't seem to
fit into this picture so far
we'll come to it
right
but the mass is a transition
between left-handed and right-handed particles
of the same charge
okay of the same electric charge
now only the neutrino
only the neutrino
is a transition between
left-handed and right-handed particles
of the same charge
only the neutrino doesn't have an electric charge
so it's the only one
which conceivably could have a transition
from neutrino to anti-neutrino
but we'll come to that
this has to do with neutrino masses
okay
in the standard model incidentally
the neutrino is strictly massless
okay
which is not the experimental fact
the experimental fact is neutrinos have
very very small masses
extremely small
right
measured in fractions of electron volts
so
they're very light
okay
the question now is where
well let's see
do we want to say anything else about this
yeah let's think about
the transitions which can happen between these particles
by virtue of emission and absorption of gauge bosons
now
we're talking about su5
which is bigger than su3 cross su2 cross u1
so there may be new kinds of gauge bosons
first of all
there are the various transitions
or interactions
that take place just among these two
an electron can become an electron for example
if it emits a neutral gauge boson
a neutrino can become a neutrino
and an electron can become a
neutrino if it emits a w-
so in here
we have
the weak interactions
the emission
and absorption
of w
z
and also photons
the electroweak
theory
that's what's occurring in this block in here
and here we have d-bar quarks
and we have a neutral gauge boson
that's emitting d-bar quarks
becoming d-bar quarks
perhaps the third one here makes
a transition to the second one
or whatever
and that means the emission of gluons
which we also learned to think
about in a slightly different way
think of the gluon that's emitted
the d-bar quark goes through
the d-quark here
and turns around in time
I'm using a
you know
a metaphorical language
when it turns around in time it becomes a d-quark
and so the quantum numbers of the gluon here
have the quantum numbers of a d-d-bar system
of a particle and an antiparticle
in other words
they belong to
with respect to s-u-3
where did I write it
n cross n-bar
the adjoint
the n squared minus one
members of the adjoint
the gluon is an object
which lives in the adjoint representation
the quark
or the anti-quark in this case
belongs to the three-dimensional representation of s-u-3
but
there are new things
new kinds of
gauge bosons that have to exist now
if we're going to try to unify
s-u-3 cross s-u-2 cross s-u-1 into s-u-5
namely
transitions which take d
anti-ds
let's draw that
an anti-d
to
an electron let's say
this would be the emission of something
what would the charge of that thing be
one
let's see
d-bar has a charge of a third
this one has charge of minus one
four thirds right
four thirds or minus four thirds
four thirds
this would have a charge of four thirds
and I can never remember
whether this one is called
the x or the y boson
it's one or the other
I do not remember which
there are x bosons
I think this one is the x boson
but I cannot remember
there's an x and a y
and the y is the thing that takes
the d-bar
and makes a neutrino out of it
what's its
what is its charge
yeah one third
minus one third
charge one third
I believe that's called
the y
but I may have x and y backward
I don't remember
I meant to look it up before class
but I forgot
so there's the x and the y boson
which are the new gauge bosons
which take
quarks
and make leptons
or leptons and make quarks
there are also
there is also the anti-particle
of the x boson
which has charge minus four thirds
and the anti-particle of the y
which has charge minus a third
those are the new things
we're going to have to contend with
understand what they do
and understand what the potential
new kinds of interactions are
because of this possibility
new kinds of things in nature
do they disturb everything
we thought we knew about physics
well yes they do
but we'll see
alright so that's the gauge bosons
and the gauge bosons are the things
that are going to be in the future
and the gauge bosons live in the adjoint
which is the n cross n bar
but the piece of it
which has trace equal to zero
in other words the piece of it
which has dimensionality n squared minus one
if you're not comfortable with this
n squared minus one just ignore it
just n squared will do
ok
it's close enough to the truth
it will give you one extra particle
one out of twenty five big deal
are there three x's in the gauge boson?
uh
mhm mhm mhm good
the x bo that's right
the x bosons
and y bosons have color
why?
the d particles the d quarks
or d bar quarks have color
the electrons don't
and so the
the conserved color
the x bosons and the y bosons
must have color
that means that they themselves
can emit and absorb
gluons
they like the quarks
are strongly interacting things
which combine together by gluon
exchange and so forth
so
these particles
are among the particles
which carry color
and like quarks
they are never completely released freely in a reaction
they always
come together
in combinations with quarks
or with other things or with themselves
and so they have integer charge
alright so they're just like quarks in that respect
alright but we're missing
more than half the fermions
where are we going to put them?
well we could put them in another
oh oh one important point
yeah
one important point
electric charge
the quantum numbers of particles
in a theory like this
are related to the generators of the group
so
the generators of the group
are the traceless
Hermitian matrices
the n by n traceless
which in fact are in one to one correspondence
with the adjoint representation
the
the generators of the group
are traceless Hermitian matrices
how many independent traceless
Hermitian matrices are there
of dimension n
n squared minus one
so actually the generators of the group
are in one to one correspondence
with the adjoint representation
and in fact the generators of the group
are intimately connected
with gauge boson emission
one of the generators of the group
has to
be associated must be the quantum mechanical
operator which represents
electric charge
is one since
photons are included
among the things which can be emitted
here we are
talking about a theory that contains
electric charge among
the generators of the group
or among the quantum
numbers associated with those generators
now there's only
one thing that you need to know to
understand why I put d bar there
instead of something else
and that's that the trace of the generators
is zero
the trace of the generators is always zero
the implication of that
is that the sums of the charge
or the sums of the quantum numbers
within a given representation
always add up to zero
that is a general rule
for special
for S-U-N groups
for groups
which are defined in a way
which
the generators of the group
are in a way
that the generators are traceless
have zero trace
the generators having zero trace
what was that connected to
in terms of the unitary matrices
that was their specialness
specialness means determinant one
for the U's
that means trace equals
zero for the generators
trace equals zero is another way
of saying that
every quantum number that's described
by this group
within a given multiplet must add
up to zero
okay, supposing I had put
the d quark here instead
alright, let's add up
the charges of all the entries
charge zero
minus one
minus two
d bar has charge
minus a third
okay
doesn't work
doesn't work, you could not embed
the electric charge
into the charge
into the generators of SU5
if you tried to put d here
put d bar
electric charge of minus one
and then three times
plus a third
so the charges add up to zero
okay
that's a
that is a mathematical
well
it's the mathematics
of why I put d bar here
in order to get the sums of the charges
add up to zero
okay, now let's talk about
well, okay
let's talk about now the other
fermions which we left out so far
let me show you how to
construct another
representation
this is just
a bit of gymnastics
to do the group theory in a simple way
alright, to do the group theory in a way
that's easy to explain
what you do
you could try to build representations
this is the n
or this is the five dimensional representation
the defining representation
we could start taking things like
five cross five
and see what we get
it would be a good thing to do
but I'm going to do something slightly different
I'm going to begin with the five bar
and multiply it by the five bar
alright, so what's the five bar
the five bar
is the collection
is the column vector
describing the anti-particles
of this collection, this is the five
let's write down
what the five bar is
the five bar
is just the anti-particles
anti-neutrino
electron
d d d
let's not worry about the handedness
we're not worrying about now handedness
we're only worried about
we're only thinking about
group theory now
this is a trick for doing
some group theory
alright, now let's consider
five bar cross five bar
E plus
E plus, sorry
anti-particle
we're just, as I said
we're just doing some mathematics now
to see how group representations combine
let's consider the five bar
cross the five bar
five bar
cross five bar
to describe it we could make
a matrix
we could make a matrix of entries
I'll show you how to do it
these are going to be five by five matrices
but I kind of want to
separate the fiveness
into two-ness and three-ness
so let's put some
partitions here
these are two by two, this is three by three
this is two by three, this is three by two
okay, just to
guide the eye
and let's
make some labels
this is five bar cross five bar
so we should label
horizontally
across here, I'm going to put exactly
what I see here, neutrino
electron plus
d d d
d d
um
neutrino, electron plus
d d d
d d
five bar cross five bar
and also
I also want to partition these things up
so that I
one two three
four five, one two
three four five
okay, now
I imagine
this is only to be imagined
it has nothing to do with the truth
but let's suppose I made some
composite objects
in each one of these
entries
I will put a composite object
which has the quantum numbers
of the two
of the row and the column
and let's see what
kind of objects you make
oh, sorry, one more thing
one more thing
remember I told you
when you take the n cross n
representation
you can take it symmetrically
or anti-symmetrically
same thing with the n bar
cross n bar
symmetric combinations or anti-symmetric
combinations
we're going to take the five bar
cross five bar
anti-symmetric
anti
alright
so the first implication
is that we only put
we put zeros on the diagonals
that means
there will be no particles
in this representation
with quantum
numbers that belong on the diagonal
secondly
the lower half
triangle just replicates
the upper half triangle with a minus sign
so they're not independent objects
they're the same
they're the same things except for the minus sign
they're not new
particle states
alright, the only independent
particle states go here, here, here
here, here, here, here, here, here
and here, and here
let's see what the quantum numbers are
in particular the electric charge
all we need is the electric charge
the electric charge which goes here
will be the electric charge of a neutrino
plus a positron
what particle has the quantum numbers
of a, quantum numbers now
just mean electric charge
what particle in the table
of all of these
have the electric charge
of a neutrino and a positron
a positron
neutrino is neutral
so over here in this place
we put E plus
now
always the left handed particle
this is
this was a trick to construct some group theory
but we will always be talking
about left handed particles
all of this is left handed
ok, what about a neutrino
and a down quark
neutrino is neutral
so let's put here
down quark, down quark
down quark
the three colors
of down quarks
incidentally
this here was just an auxiliary
construction
we're not putting particles
into the five bar
this was just an auxiliary construction
so that I could show you what the five bar
looks like
let's erase this
so we don't get confused
ok, what particle has the
electric charge of a positron
and a d quark
positron
x
an x
no no no no
among the fermions
here we're just talking about the fermions
no no, we're talking about the fermions
what particles have
the quantum numbers of a down quark
among these here, this is all we're talking about
now, we're trying to construct
up bar
is it up bar? no, I think it's up
up
charge
one minus a third
is two thirds
that's the up quark
this is zero
not u
ok, what about a down quark
ah, what about a down quark
and a down quark
that's two thirds
no no
it's minus two thirds
down quark has charge
minus a third
this has charge
minus two thirds
what's it going to be?
anti-up quark
two thirds
what's it going to be?
a down quark
two thirds
power
and a down quark
two thirds
power
and a down quark
So the statement is that this entire collection of particles has the structure,
with respect to its quantum numbers, of a 5 and a 10 bar.
This is actually a rather remarkable fact, that
the particles fit so neatly into representations of SU5.
You may find it a little bit awkward
that half the particles belong to a 10-dimensional representation,
not half, but half of the
particles belong to a 10-dimensional representation.
Not half, but half of the
What happens when I multiply, if we have a 5 or
a 10 bar, both 3 and half belong to a 5.
The first toars belong to this 10
bar and the third belongs to this 5.
There is a bigger unification that is possible
into a group bigger than this, but contains SU5.
A group tooar and one more İstanbul Mix-In 010
harvesting donation, but contains 010 collection she had to add.
All the other particles are all
made from the same representation from 10.
called O10. All of these particles are
in one representation of O10, but you have
to add one more particle in O10,
and it's the antiparticle of the neutrino. But
we're not going to, if we get to it,
we'll get to it. But for the moment, this is
what's called SU unification of particles.
Okay, any questions up till now?
Yeah?
In the SU particles are there in the column matrix.
Well this set of particles are there in
the column matrix. This set of particles are in
an anti-symmetric matrix.
In the 10 bar, what's the column matrix?
What's the what?
What is the column matrix?
Oh, just take these in any order that
you like and line them up vertically. It's
better to think of it like this.
Think of it as a matrix. It's better to
think of it a matrix, but there's nothing to prevent
you from taking them and lining them up
into a 10 plat. But the transformation matrices
which act on that 10 plat are not the
full set of SU matrices. It's a smaller set
of matrices than that. But it's better to think
of it as a matrix. When you start combining
representations together..
You can always think of them as columns if you like,
just by taking them and just laying them out in a column.
But it's often much more convenient to think of them as
matrices, the transform as matrices, rather than the transform as column vectors.
All right, so this is the breakdown of the particle
multiplets into a 5 and a 10 bar of SU5.
Now, yeah.
In the third row and the fifth
column, why is that up and up?
Third row. Oh, sorry, up bar.
Yeah, thank you.
You also admitted the colors.
I assume the color is conserved?
Color is conserved.
All right.
In particular, where you have the D bar, D bar, D
bar in the columns, is one of them red, green, blue, or?
Yeah, red, green, blue.
This could be the red, green, blue.
Red, green, blue.
Now, what happens if you combine together
a green quark with a blue quark?
You get something anti-red.
Well.
So you would get an anti, yeah.
So, let's see.
So these anti-quarks here are, let's
see, red with green would be blue.
Red with blue would be green.
And the green with blue would be red.
Okay.
That's the pattern of SU5.
Any other questions?
Now, this is quite extraordinary when you think about it.
You're putting into one multiplet, one symmetry
multiplet, quarks, left-handed up quarks, and left-handed anti-quarks.
Okay.
Into a single symmetry structure, left-handed
up quarks and left-handed anti-quarks, up quarks.
On the other hand, the d quark, its particle
and anti-particle, left-handed particle and anti-particle, belong in different representations.
Same with a positron and the electron.
The left-handed positron and the
left-handed electron are in different representations.
representations. And there's the neutrino sitting all
by itself in the five with no counterpart
associated with an anti-neutrino. That is the
particle content or the fermion content of the
standard model. Okay, now let's see. Maybe
we should take a five-minute break here. Yeah.
You can transform within each of these, but that
means there's no way to get from the d-bar across.
The Higgs boson does that.
The Higgs boson cuts across here.
Various, the various kinds of Higgs bosons can cut
across here. They can take left to right and
that's sort of what's going on
here. But let's take a five-minute break.
Let's talk about the various gauge bosons.
The various gauge bosons correspond to the transitions
between these five objects. The same
set of gauge bosons, actually they're anti-particles.
Gauge bosons in general have charge. W's have charge.
X's and Y's have charge. So they also have anti-particles.
The gauge bosons mix up these five entries.
For example, between here and here we have the
Z, the W, and the photon, which act
in here. And in here we have the gluons.
The new things that we have now are the
X and Y bosons, and the X and Y bosons
take you this way. That's X. As I said, look
it up. I can't remember which is X and Y.
And Y bosons, according to my present
convention, take you from d-bar quarks to neutrinos.
Those are the transitions which happen
by emission of these particular gauge bosons.
How do those gauge bosons act?
They act among this 10-bar. In other words, when
a gauge boson is emitted by one of these particles,
which one does it become? Now the way to think
about this is that the gauge bosons can be thought
of as shifts. In the case, some of the
gauge bosons don't do anything. The photon, for example, takes
an electron to an electron. So that's a
kind of trivial shift, which doesn't take you anywhere
as in this column. The Y bosons shift you up or
shift you down. And then the Y bosons shift you up.
Or shift you down. And the gluons shift you
among red, yellow, and blue, so forth and so on.
So think of them as kind of
shifts, which shift you around in this space.
Okay. What do those same gauge bosons do
acting in this multiplet? And the answer is
that they either take you horizontally or
vertically according to the same pattern. For example,
the emission of a gluon can take you this
way, or the emission of a gluon, here's a gluon,
gluons are down here. It can take you this way
or it can take you this way. That's the rule
that whatever the various gauge bosons do, the
shifts that they make, the same thing is repeated
here except that it can happen in the same way.
So that's the rule. Now, let's look at the other
things that can happen in the same way. The
same thing is repeated here, except that it can happen
you can either emit a gauge boson
and go horizontally or vertically. Another way to
think about it is to pretend, to pretend
that these entries here really were composites of
pairs of particles or pairs of anti-particles
to be specific. One of the particles or
anti-particles represents the horizontal direction,
the other represents the vertical direction.
And a gauge boson could be emitted from
one or the other. If it's emitted from one,
it takes you horizontally. If it's emitted
from the other, it takes you vertically from
one entry to another. So let's see
what the, what the weak interaction gauge bosons,
the Z and the W, for example, do. Well, they
shift, they shift you in this upper two slots here.
So that means that the z and the w are in the
same place. And the z and the w are in the same place.
So that means, let's think about what
they do horizontally. Horizontally, they take you from
this column to this column. Moving horizontally, they
take you from this column to this column.
Well, that there's not much here to do.
The E plus doesn't do very much. Okay, but
they can also take you vertically from this
neutrino slot to this positron slot, which means
they can take you in this slot. And that means that they can take
you in this slot, and that means they can take you in this slot.
So what's the E plus? Well, that's something
that Z's, that's something that the W boson does.
The W boson does take down to up. The down to
up of the W boson is the source of beta decay.
A down quark becomes an up quark or an up
quark. In fact, yes, a down quark becomes an up quark
inside a nucleon, takes a neutron to a
proton. So the emission of a W boson
can take a down quark to
an up quark. That's going vertically here.
The color group acts among red, green, and blue.
It can act horizontally here, taking a down quark to
another color of down quark, or an up quark to
another color of up quark. But it can also act
vertically here, taking this to this, and that mixes
up the three U bar. It can take green to
red. Suppose you want to take blue to red. How do
you take blue to red? Well, you go over to here.
Let's see, where are we? Remember, this is really
an... I haven't put in the entries over here.
The entries over here are just the negatives of
the entries over here. If I wrote them down here,
we could go from blue to red on this
side directly. But okay, you can go this way,
or you can go this way. And that's good.
So you can see that the color acting on the U
bar quarks, all of this is the same as in the
standard theory. Nothing new here. The new things that I want
to get at is what the Xs and the Ys do.
What do the Xs and the Ys do among this
column here? Okay, we know what they do. They take,
for example, the X boson can take, and
it's antiparticle, take this entry to this entry,
if you like. All right?
That's... What is that? That's taking
this entry to this entry. In other words, the
emission of an X boson can take a D bar.
Here's a D bar coming along, emitting an
X and becoming an electron. That's over here,
the left hand of these particles. But exactly the
same kind of emission can take place, let's see,
between...this is the second to the third. So
it's two to three, namely positron to down quark.
Positron to down quark, which in
terms of this constituent model over here,
just takes this positron to a down quark.
That's the anti-X being emitted. The anti-X being emitted
takes...
Positron to down quark.
What else can happen?
Did I get that right?
Positron to down quark?
Let's see.
What can it do?
Yeah, I guess that's down quark to positron.
Or down quark to positron or
the antiparticle positron to down quark.
And that way you can figure out what
the various emissions of X and Y bosons.
Let's help with the Y boson.
The Y boson takes the
first entry to the third entry.
The first entry, where's the first entry person over here?
First entry over here to third entry
takes a down quark to an anti-up quark.
Down quark.
To an anti-up quark.
Also over here, down quark to anti-up quark.
Sometimes it helps to fill in the
rest of these columns and slots over here.
Takes down quark to anti-up quark.
So just go through it.
Play a little game of figuring out what the X boson,
what kind of transitions the X boson and the Y bosons make.
But they do exactly the same thing among these
columns and rows over here as they do over here.
They take, for example, first entry to third entry.
First entry, where's first entry?
There's nothing here.
Can't go here.
First entry to third entry.
That means there are new kinds of processes.
And one of those new kinds
of processes is very, very surprising.
So let's take a look
at what the new process is.
What about the fourth and fifth entries?
The fourth and fifth entry.
Those are the emission of gluons.
So four to five.
You go from a blue
quark to a green quark by...
First to fourth.
That would be a Y.
Yeah, that would be a Y.
Right.
That would be a Y boson.
So a fourth, the Y
boson can take down to anti-up.
The X boson can take up to anti-up, I think.
Can you just fill in just
one box of the anti-symmetric entry?
Yeah.
Minus E plus.
Minus D.
Minus U.
Minus U bar B.
Minus U bar green.
And minus U bar red.
The hell did I do, right?
Where?
Here?
Yeah.
Okay.
Right.
That's the rest of the table.
Now, it's redundant.
If a process can take you
from one place to another here,
it'll do the same thing up here going rows instead.
Just interchange rows and columns.
So it's redundant to keep track of these,
but you can draw it if you like.
Okay.
So let me show you a process which is unusual.
So the force of now is this.
So if let's look at a problem of, let's say,
the moment we have this window,
this is where 5
and h green go away.
Right.
x.
So an x boson is emitted.
And what's the charge of the x boson?
Is it 4 thirds?
Yeah, 4 third.
No, minus 4 thirds.
In this case, it's the x minus 4 thirds,
which is the antiparticle of the x
that we were talking about before.
So we can call it an anti-x.
But the x can also do something else.
Now let's see if I can figure out what.
It takes the first element to the second element
to third element, let's say.
Second element to third element.
So here's a second element in the column.
And here's a third element in the column.
Here's another process it can do.
It can take up.
Yeah, up to anti-up.
It can take up to anti-up
with an x boson over here.
But now is this an x
boson or an anti-x boson coming in?
Oh, it's an anti-x boson coming in.
Let's check that.
This had charge minus 4 thirds.
It went from minus 1 third to plus 1.
This must have had charge.
Yeah.
Okay.
It's
OK.
All right.
So what we've got to do from here,
is you reverse
the freedom function
emits an X, and that X now
grabs a whole of a U quark,
which then becomes an anti-U quark.
Well, that's interesting.
But now let's add one more particle,
which is pretty much just
a spectator in all of this,
another U quark.
A U quark does nothing, just becomes a U quark.
There's a process which takes a
D quark and two U quarks.
What's that called?
Proton.
This is a proton.
It's just proton.
And creates out of it a
positron, same charge as the proton,
and a U anti-U quark.
What kind of particles can you make
out of a U and an anti-
or a quark and an anti-quark?
Mesonauts.
Mesons.
In particular, pi mesons.
This would be a neutral
pi meson coming out of here.
Pi naught.
A neutral pi meson.
So we've discovered, or not discovered,
but we've postulated in doing this,
we've postulated something unusual,
namely a process where a proton,
if we just take a black box view of it,
proton becomes positron and a pi naught.
Another thing that could happen is the U quark
and the anti-U quark could annihilate and make a photon.
This would be a little less likely
because there's an extra factor
of the fine structure constant
in the probability, but that's
another process that can happen.
Proton.
It becomes positron and photon.
Now, this is potentially a very, very dangerous game.
If protons had a habit of
just decaying to become positrons and photons,
or positrons and pi naught,
needless to say, we wouldn't be here.
Our nuclei wouldn't be here.
Hydrogen wouldn't be here.
So this is a rather,
rather dangerous process.
It's called proton decay.
And proton decay is a consequence
of pretty much any kind of attempt
to unify the weak interactions
and the electromagnetic interactions
and the strong interactions into one group.
SU3 costs, SU2 costs, U1 is, of course, one group,
but it's a product of smaller groups.
To unify it,
it's a product of larger groups.
So we can put it into one non-product group,
a bigger group.
Almost any, in fact, every unification that I know of,
which tries to put these
particles together into a single multiplet,
or which tries to put
SU3 cross SU2 cross U1 together
into a bigger symmetry,
always has proton decay as one of its consequences.
This is very dangerous,
not something that we would want to happen to us.
And certainly not something we would want to happen quickly.
The coupling constant for producing X bosons,
is that the same as the
coupling constant for the whole group?
Yep.
That is basically just the fine structure constant.
You have the product of two coupling constants,
one over here and one over here.
Not different.
Numerically, it might be a little bit
different from what we have, but, you know,
it's not a problem.
It's a problem.
There are a number of effects, one
of which we may get to talk about.
But numerically is not the important thing here.
The order of magnitude of these coupling constants
is the same as the usual coupling constants.
Why?
Because they all belong to the same structure.
They belong to the same structure.
And in this SU5 theory, there's only one coupling constant.
The coupling constant for the emission of a gauge boson.
Why?
They wind up being different, uh,
in our laboratories is something we may
or may not have time to discuss tonight.
But, uh, yeah, the order of magnitude of
these coupling constants is just usual coupling constants.
Same coupling constant which governs the
decay of an atom when it de-excites.
The same coupling constants which govern beta decay.
Same coupling constants, uh, that govern
all the ordinary particle physics decays.
So the question then is why this doesn't work.
Why this doesn't happen in the blink of
an eye as fast as other particle decays.
Alright.
Answer or potential answer?
Not, uh, not the answer because we've never detected these
and we don't really know that it's a real process.
Um, but what leeway, what, um, what do we have
available to manipulate to slow down the rate of this?
The mass.
Okay.
The mass of the X boson.
Uh.
The mass of the X boson goes in here.
And it goes in in the form of a propagator.
Propagators always look like one over M squared.
They may have some momentum dependence also where
the momentum dependence would be the recoil momentum.
But that's generally small potatoes.
The important thing in the denominator here
is the mass squared of the X boson.
That would be one of the elements.
And then you would have a product of coupling constants.
Let's say a G times another G.
G for coupling constant.
G squared of some sort
divided by X by MX squared.
Now, if you sat down and calculated the Feynman diagram for this, which is a,
you know, reasonably simple Feynman diagram, this is what you would get times some number.
Okay.
The Feynman diagram gives an amplitude.
It gives a quantum mechanical amplitude for a process.
How do you calculate the probability for the process?
You square it.
Okay.
So there will be a G to the fourth
and an MX to the fourth in the decay rate.
The decay rate is the probability per unit
time that the proton decays in the decay rate.
The question is how big do you have to make MX in order that the
decay rate of the proton is slow enough so that it doesn't conflict with experiment?
Question then is what is the half-life of the proton?
This is the decay rate inverse
to the half-life of the proton.
Turn it upside down, it becomes a...
This...
There's other factors in here.
Factors of the mass.
The mass of the proton and so
forth, but this is the important thing.
If we measured everything in units of GeV, the mass of
the proton, this would be the decay rate, approximately, order of magnitude.
So how big do we have to make MX
in order that the decay rate is long enough?
That raises the question, what are the
bounds on the lifetime of the proton?
All right, there's all kinds of bounds.
The proton is clearly longer lived in the universe.
There are still protons around from the Big Bang.
Okay, so the proton, first of all, the proton has to be
longer than the age of a human being, otherwise we wouldn't be here.
It has to be longer than the age of
the universe, otherwise they wouldn't be here to make us.
So 10 to the 10th years, 10 to the 12th,
10 to the 14th, 10 to the 15th years for sure.
But now there's questions of experimental data.
You can't wait around for 10 to
the 15th years to see a proton.
Yes.
I'm not sure if that's the right way to go.
But what I'm sure you're right about is just that
the proton is going to be around for a long time.
years to see a proton decay.
But you can start with 10 to the 15th protons.
That's not a lot of protons.
It's a small amount, a very small sample of protons.
And see how often a decay takes place.
If the decay rate for a
proton, if the half-life for a proton
was 10 to the 15th years,
then if you start with 10
to the 15th protons, you ought
to see one decay per year,
approximately.
One decay per year.
A proton decaying is something which
can be detected in the laboratory,
even among 10 to the 15th of them.
This is easy.
This is really easy stuff, seeing a proton decay
in a sample of 10 to the 15th protons.
And you don't see any decay.
Lifetime is longer than 10 to the 15th.
If you put everything together that's known,
the lifetime of the proton is longer than 10
to the 35th.
So the proton decay is longer
than 10 to the 33 years.
10 to the 33 years is the
bound on the half-life of the proton.
Once this theory came out, it was immediately
evident that experimental physicists should
be trying to detect proton decay.
The way to do it is
to take 10 to the 33 protons
and wait for one of them to decay.
10 to the 33 protons.
What's the mass of 10 to the 33 protons?
10 to the 23 protons is a mole of hydrogen.
So this is 10 to the 10th moles of hydrogen.
Big vat or big swimming pool.
5 by 10 to the 8th.
Sorry, what?
You had a g to the 4th.
Doesn't that give you a 10 to the 8th?
It does.
But that's right.
g to the 4th is a
small number, but nowhere is near.
Right?
Right.
Remember, we should.
Nowhere is near the required.
I'm saying it's 10 to the 25th or so.
If g is about 1 over 100,
then you get to kind of take it.
Why are you measuring in years?
What should you be measuring in?
Protons.
Yeah, the light transit time across a proton.
So it's got to be a small number.
Right.
The expected lifetime, if everything
was of order 1 in proton units, would
be the light transit time across a proton.
Don't ask me how long that is.
10 to the minus 15th meters.
15 and 8 is what?
10 to the minus 23rd seconds.
Did I get that right?
10 to the minus 23rd seconds is the benchmark number.
OK.
10 to the 33 years is the observational bound.
Big number in between.
g to the fourth, not important.
Right.
OK.
The only thing it can save
us is m to the fourth,
if m is big enough.
How big does m have to be in order
to be consistent with the 10 to the 33 years?
The answer is about 10 to the 16th GeV.
Mm-hmm.
If this doesn't work, then it's not.
This number is 10 to the 16th.
Let's see.
Is that right?
10 to the 16th fourth is 10?
Yeah.
That's the right number.
10 to the 16th GeV is the minimum bound
on the mass of the
x and y bosons in order
that it not conflict with proton decay.
Now, is that a ridiculous number?
No, I don't think it is a ridiculous number.
OK.
First of all, it is, what is it?
It's three orders of magnitude smaller than the Planck mass.
So it's not above the Planck mass.
That's a good thing.
Three orders of magnitude below it.
But there is another factor
that makes this very, very tempting.
We've discussed it before.
It's the running of coupling constants.
The strong.
OK.
Weak and electromagnetic coupling constants
are not numerically the same.
The electromagnetic is somewhat with appropriate adjusted
various factors for the group theory, just for the group
theory.
In order to compare SU5 with
SU3 cross SU2 and so forth,
there are some numerical factors, numbers like 3 eighths,
trivial numbers.
But.
OK.
So, simply stated, with appropriate conventions,
all of the coupling constants in a unified theory
should be the same.
But SU3 cross SU2 cross, sorry,
SU5 is not a symmetry of nature.
It cannot be a true
symmetry or even approximately a symmetry
of nature.
Why?
Because of the enormous
difference between the necessary mass
of the X boson.
The X boson exists in the same
multiplet as the gluons, the W boson,
and the photons.
OK.
It exists in the same multiplet.
And if the symmetry was an ideal unbroken symmetry,
they would all have the same mass.
Well, the photon is a good deal
lighter than either the Z or W
bosons.
The gluons, their mass is zero in the mass.
OK.
And the quantum chromodynamics, so it's like the photon.
And now the X boson
has to have this gigantic mass.
That means the symmetry is broken, spontaneously broken.
What is it when spon-
I guess if it's not
broken, then all of these bosons
are massless.
Then all the bosons are massless.
Right.
You could arrange for them
to all have the same mass
and not be zero, but that's not really right.
OK.
What is it that gave
the W boson a different mass
than the photon?
It was the spontaneous symmetry
breaking, or the Higgs phenomena,
that created a different mass
for the W than the photon.
And at the same time, it
broke the SU2 cross U1 symmetry.
What's necessary is a Higgs type phenomena, a different one,
a different one.
And what's necessary is a Higgs type phenomena,
a different one, that splits this from this.
That splits this from this, breaks the symmetry
drastically between this block and that block.
And it is that symmetry breaking which
would account for the big mass difference
between the X and Y bosons
on the one hand, and the gluons,
or the Z.
All these particles are massless.
They have the biggest mass here is only 100 GeV.
We're comparing things with 10 to the 16th GeV.
So the first approximation in this kind of theory,
these are all massless.
In fact, everything on the blackboard is massless.
And the X and Y bosons have this large mass.
That's the theory.
I'm not saying it's true.
This is to be tested.
So with a mass of 10
to the 16th GeV, you're fine.
It's OK.
Now what other evidence do we have for a scale
of 10 to the 16th GeV?
We have a couple of other pieces of evidence
that the scale of 10 to the 16th GeV
is the scale of unification.
What does it mean, the scale of unification?
It means energies which are high in
the scale of 10 to the 16th
GeV.
And they're high enough that even
the mass of the X and Y
bosons can be considered to be 0.
In other words, if the mass
of the X or Y boson
is 10 to the 16th
GeV, or 10 to the 15th,
somewhere between 10 to the
15th and 10 to the 16th,
then well above that energy, let's
say 10 to the 18th GeV,
processes are insensitive to the mass
of the X and Y bosons.
They're massless in that limit.
In that limit, the difference between the X, Y bosons
and the Z and W
and so forth is not important.
In other words, above those energies,
the symmetry is a good symmetry.
It's a good symmetry.
So the question is, at
what point does, at what energy
scales, does the world appear to be SU5 invariant?
There's some answer to that.
And the answer goes as follows.
I've told you several times that coupling constants
are not constant.
They depend on energy scales.
The coupling constant that
you see in quantum electrodynamics,
the fine structure constant, actually depends
on the energy of a process.
It runs.
That's the terminology.
Coupling constants run.
They vary.
If you plot, it's traditional for, well, not just
traditional.
Useful.
Instead of plotting the coupling constant,
plotting one over the coupling constants.
And you plot them at laboratory energies.
In this direction, you have energy.
And you plot the measured
value of them at laboratory energies.
This is really logarithm of the energy here.
If you plot the value of the three coupling constants,
which three?
SU3 cross SU2.
And U1.
The three coupling constants, they are three numbers.
The biggest value of 1 over
G squared would be for the U1.
In other words, the weakest of the interactions,
the electromagnetic.
Next, the SU2.
And next, the SU3.
OK.
Now you plot how they run with energy.
Now, run with energy, how do you plot it?
You don't measure it.
They run logarithmically very slowly.
You calculate it.
You calculate it from the theory.
You have the particle content.
You have the Feynman diagrams.
Particular Feynman diagrams go into the running
of these coupling constants.
And you plot them.
And what do you find?
You find that they do something like this.
Now, that's approximately what they do.
They more or less come together, look
as though they're going to cross.
And what you'd like is that
they all cross at the same place.
What you'd like is that there
is one place where they all
come together.
And at that point, you would say, that's the unification
energy.
That's the energy where you've gotten high enough
that beyond that energy, all three coupling constants
are the same.
Now, why do they run differently?
Why do they run differently?
If there's a symmetry
between these three coupling constants,
why do they run differently?
And the answer is, they run differently.
They run differently.
That's probably why they're all—
see the unification energy is that the temperature
teraz that below this symmetry—
sorry, below this energy the symmetry is broken.
Above that energy, the symmetry is restored.
So that's the picture that you would like.
And you would like them to all
coalesce simultaneously.
They don't quite.
In fact, they miss each other by a fair amount,
but the tendency is certainly for them to come together.
here doesn't matter they do miss
each other by an appreciable amount
nevertheless you take them aim them do
the calculation and you find out that
there's if you allow 15% error you
will find that these things cross at an
energy of guess where the same energy 10 to
the 16th or 10 to the 15 GeV so
the implication is that if you
believe this theory the unification scale
really should be 10 to the 16 GeV and
then the mass of the X and Y boson would
be about that this is the reason yeah
if in this diagram for proton decay you replace the free
U with a free D then you're looking at neutron decay
but neutron decay decays by beta
decay so fast it doesn't matter
so if you look at the product of
that the X boson get involved at all
say that again?
replace the U on the right with a D
yeah
then you get neutron decay
yes but there's another mechanism
for you right so you would
that happens the free neutron will decay
yeah but not by this mechanism it doesn't decay
to a to a let's see this would be
it doesn't decay to a pi meson and a positron
that would have been noticed it decays to a proton
neutrino and an electron okay so
a completely different process yes but
you're right you could imagine a world
in which the neutron was stable with
respect to beta decay if the neutron
was a little bit lighter than the proton
imagine that the neutron was a this
would be a disastrous world you wouldn't
like it the neutron would be stable
the proton would beta decay into the neutron
but now take the neutron the neutron
would decay by this process but again
the lifetime could be very long right
so just by juggling the masses of the
proton and neutron you could imagine a
world in which this long lifetime would
apply to the neutron not to the
proton all right that's uh that's pretty much
it we're about out of time that's pretty much it
for what we have for now. Thank you.
So that's pretty much it for what a grand unified theory is
the only last thing I promise to tell you is what the
relationship between grand unified theories
and supersymmetry is not a lot
I mean no tight relationship one doesn't imply
the other but what is true is that
if you add all of the super
particles into the calculations for the running of
the coupling constants then you do much much better
within within about one percent these do
cross at the same place is this an
accident is it a one percent accident who
knows in any case this is why there
is excitement about supersymmetry
and about grand unification grand
unification is a quite beautiful idea of
fitting all of the particles into a
single multiplet like this into a
single group structure like this in a
slight extension of this theory incidentally
in the theory based on the
group O10 which is a little bit bigger than
su5 su5 fits into O10 in O10 all of
these particles exist in a
single multiplet the 16 dimensional
representation of O10 along with one
other particle the anti an anti-neutrality particle.
neutrino or the right-handed neutrino as
it's usually called and but that's a
separate story
ok that's the idea of grand
unification its connection with supersymmetry which
is not theoretically terribly strong but
empirically there's some reason to find
it attractive proton decay experiments
are ongoing the lifetime is getting
every year the lifetime gets a year
long no that's not right no that's actually
not right at all is it but
every year the bound goes up in supersymmetric
theories the lifetime calculations different and
can vary all over the map
but it never gets any bigger than about
10 to the 35 years or something like
that it's difficult to make it bigger than
10 to the 35 and the standard model
you can't make it short with with
this kind of number for the unification scale
you really can't make it shorter than about
10 to 32 years nothing you can do
can make it shorter than that
and supersymmetric theories it could go from
a fraction of a second to 10 to
the 36 years and with with various assumptions
about things so there is no
real prediction in supersymmetric theory for
the lifetime of the proton.
Alright may all your protons be stable
until the until the autumn quarter and I
wish you a fine summer with sunshine shine and rain.
For more please visit us at stanford.edu