Stanford University.
I have gotten into a pattern and I like the
pattern of first starting a lecture with a couple of preliminaries.
Sometimes they're reminders, sometimes they're new things.
By now, I've taught so many things so many
times that although I may remember that they're reminders,
you may think they're new things.
But, well, I suppose one of the things we
ought to go over really quickly, really, really quickly,
is the harmonic oscillator, and
I will do that exceedingly fast.
But the other thing I wanted to go over
before we begin is the spin of massless particles.
The spin of massless particles is
a little bit different in some ways
than the spin of massless particles.
The basic difference is that massless
particles can never be brought to rest.
They move with the speed of light, and if you
slow them down, they still move with the speed of light,
and if you slow them down more,
they still move with the speed of light.
Whereas particles with mass, you can truly
slow down and bring them to rest,
and that makes a difference
in certain properties about spin.
What shall we do first?
Spin or...
Well, let's do harmonic oscillator first
to get it out of the way.
Very quickly.
You know it all.
I'm just going to, just to set
the notation, mostly to get the notation consistent.
I'll just go over it with you again.
The energy, or the Lagrangian of
a harmonic oscillator, is x dot squared.
And then, for reasons that...
If you go back in your notes about
the harmonic oscillators that describe the oscillations of strings,
first of all, they had a little
index n, which had to do with...
Remember, there were cosines.
Cosine n sigma.
It was the n of that cosine.
How many oscillations...
How many oscillations over the interval
from 0 to pi the string makes.
So there are...
Those x sub n's are the
coordinates describing various kinds of oscillations.
That was there, and for reasons
that have no special depth to them,
it turned out there was
a 4 in the denominator here.
That was the kinetic energy, and then the potential energy.
If I want to write the
energy, I put a plus sign there.
The potential energy was proportional to x squared.
Same thing.
x sub n squared.
It looks like we've...
Somebody didn't do their...
It was x sub n squared, divided also by 4.
And then, sitting in front, is the
square of the frequency of the oscillator.
And that was actually just n squared.
That's what we got for the
energy of the nth mode of oscillation.
x dot squared.
And it's a harmonic oscillator.
Kinetic energy plus potential energy.
That's the Lagrangian.
That's the energy.
Call it E.
The Lagrangian is x dot n squared.
You know, I'm going to stop writing n.
But remember.
I'm talking about x sub n.
There's x dot squared minus
n squared x squared over 4.
That's Lagrangian.
From this, you can work out Lagrange's equations of motion.
And you can discover that
the oscillator oscillates with frequency n.
Okay?
Let's next go to the Hamiltonian.
We want to do quantum mechanics.
The way to go to quantum
mechanics is to first construct the Hamiltonian.
And then do some tricks with it.
Let's first construct the Hamiltonian.
I'll remind you.
Oops.
This is over 4.
Somebody should have corrected me.
You all fail.
x dot squared over 4.
Okay.
So what do you do?
The first thing you do.
What's the first step in constructing Hamiltonians?
The first step is to replace
the x dots by the momenta.
The momenta p.
So if you remember, the derivative of a Lagrangian
with respect to the velocity is called the momentum.
So in this case, with this particular factor of 4
here, the momentum would be x dot divided by 2.
Why?
Because when I differentiate with respect
to x dot, I get a 2.
That cancels a 2 in the
denominator and leaves a 2 there.
That's the first step.
Next step is you rewrite the energy.
In terms of instead of x dots, you use p's.
So we just have to solve for
x dot and plug it in here.
What does that give us?
That gives us, let's see, x dot squared
will be 4 p squared divided by 4.
So this will be p squared with no 4.
And then potential energy doesn't change.
Plus n squared.
And then n squared, x squared over 4.
And that we now call the Hamiltonian, H.
The quantum mechanical Hamiltonian is exactly the same.
Except that it becomes an operator.
An operator in the space of states.
Okay, now the trick is
always the same for harmonic oscillators.
Let's just erase all of this.
This could have been our starting point right here.
You look at this, it's the sum of squares.
A squared plus b squared.
You write that a squared plus b squared,
a squared minus b squared is what?
It's a plus b times a minus b.
How about a squared plus b squared?
That's a plus ib times a minus ib.
Work it out.
You get an a squared.
Minus i times plus i is plus.
So you get plus b squared.
And the cross term goes away.
So you look at this, it's the sum of squares.
And you rewrite it.
It's the sum of squares in,
what is this term a square of?
This term is a square of nx over 2.
Right?
Alright, so we write that this is
nx over 2 plus ip times nx.
Right?
nx over 2 minus ip.
That's the Hamiltonian.
Okay?
Next step.
You give these two things names, but not quite.
First, let's think about the
commutation relations between these two.
Of course, one of these is essentially
the creation operator or the raising operator.
The other one is essentially the lowering operator.
But we have to figure out which is which and the
numerical coefficients in order to make them creation and annihilation operators.
I'll just put over here for your, to remind you.
The commutation relations between annihilation operators, let's call
them a minus and creation operators a plus.
A plus when it acts
raises the energy by one unit.
A minus lowers the energy by one unit.
This commutation relation is just one.
So that's how we
identify creation and annihilation operators.
They're operators which are
complex conjugates of each other.
These two are complex conjugates of each other.
And their commutation relation is one.
So let's work out the commutation relations between these.
And just check if we get one.
We won't get one.
Alright?
What's the commutation relation between x and p?
Do you remember the commutator between x and p?
Anybody remember?
I'm setting h bar to one.
What else besides h bar?
I.
Go back and try to remember why that's true.
xp minus px is i.
Alright, now here we have x.
We have a commutator of n over 2.
A minus i times the commutator of x and p.
So let's first...
Oh, first of all, what about
the commutator between this and this?
That's zero because anything commutes with itself.
Likewise, p with p.
The only terms are the cross terms
x with p and p with x.
Alright, so if we just
look at the first term here,
or the cross term here,
that will give us n over 2.
It'll give us a minus i from here.
But then the commutator of
x with p is plus i.
So that gets multiplied by plus i.
All together makes it just n over 2.
So far.
That's the commutator of this guy with that one.
How about this one with this one?
Again, I see an n over 2.
I see an i.
But now I have the p's
and the x's in the opposite order.
The result is exactly the same thing.
Just double it.
So this one and this
one give you the same thing.
It just doubles.
All of this just gives us n.
Now, I wanted to get 1.
But I got n.
What do I do with it?
I just divide both equations,
both of these operators by the square root of n.
In other words, let's divide each of
these by the square root of n.
Likewise over here.
1 over the square root of n.
And that now eats up this n here.
And that's the way to remember
it if you're on a desert island
and you can't remember what combination of x's and p's
are creation and annihilation operators.
Compared with over here,
this is n.
This is 1 now.
If I had my
creation and annihilation operators interchanged,
I would get minus 1.
So we then identify the annihilation operator, a minus,
is 1 over the square root of n.
That means square root of n x over 2
plus i over the square root of n p.
And the creation operator is the same thing
except with a minus sign.
I just do that to remind you.
There are creation and annihilation operators.
The creation operators increase the energy by 1 unit.
And when I say 1
unit, I now mean 1 unit.
The frequency of this oscillator is n.
Oops.
n units.
Little n units.
Which n?
Well, it depends on which xn I'm talking about.
We can now put in, we
can now put back our n's.
There's a creation operator and an annihilation operator
for each oscillation, for each
possible oscillation of the string.
And the frequency is n.
The frequency of the oscillator is n.
The frequency, of course, is
the amount of energy that's added
by exciting the oscillator once.
So we can work out then what the energies are,
what the energy spectrum is,
and do the quantum mechanics of the oscillators.
And that's basically the spectrum of these strings.
Now, we'll come back to it in a minute.
The other thing to remember
that I talked about last time
was if we're talking about strings
in the realistic number of dimensions
of space and time, namely three dimensions of space,
one dimension of time, good old ordinary space,
and we think about the string
moving with a great deal of momentum
down the z-axis, then there are
really only two dimensions of oscillation
to take into account.
Another time, maybe even later today,
I'll talk about the third direction of oscillation
and how it's determined by the others.
But the independent degrees of freedom are the oscillations
in the plane of somebody watching
the string going down the z-axis.
And so how many oscillations are there altogether?
Well, there are oscillations along the x-axis.
That one's z.
Down that direction is z.
All right?
Toward you is x.
Toward the ceiling is y.
The oscillations can occur in the x direction.
They can occur in the y direction.
So that means that there's another term.
I really didn't write the full Hamiltonian here.
I should have written plus another
term where x is interchanged with y,
exactly the same.
That means for each frequency,
there will be two oscillators,
the oscillator for oscillations along the x axis,
and the oscillations along the y axis.
Let's give them names.
Let's call them A for the x
axis and B for the y axis.
Same equations, B minus, B plus equals 1.
And same equations here, except we'll substitute for A.
We'll put B.
And wherever I see x, I will put y.
What about Q?
What about P?
Sorry.
Yeah, this piece of x and piece of y,
the momentum in the x direction
and the momentum in the y direction.
I won't bother writing it down.
All right.
From this equation here, but let us
put in the little symbol n here.
Also goes here.
Let's solve this equation for xn.
Here's two equations.
Let's think of them as two equations for two unknowns.
X and P.
How can I solve this to find out what
x is in terms of the creation and annihilation operators?
This is something we'll use later.
I'm not sure we'll use it tonight or not.
But what I want to write
is the coordinate position of the string
in terms of the creation and annihilation operators.
That will turn out to be quite useful.
So let's do it.
This is easy.
If I want to isolate x,
I want to get rid of P.
That's easy.
Just add these two equations.
This term will cancel.
So what do we get?
We get a plus plus a minus,
and we should put a little
index n here for the nth oscillation.
That's equal to n.
I think it's just n square root of n.
Sorry.
n.
Square root of n times xn.
Square root.
So we simply find the nth coordinate
is just the sum of creation and annihilation operators
divided by square root of n.
Real easy.
It's just the square root of
n that you've got to remember.
Now let's, before we leave the harmonic oscillator,
let's just remember where these oscillators came from.
They came from writing x of sigma.
Remember what x of sigma was.
Oh, there's another one similar to it.
y sub n is equal to b sub n plus
plus b sub n minus over square root of n.
Same thing.
Incidentally, as I'm sure most
of you have heard the rumor
that string theory doesn't work very well
when there are only three dimensions of space,
and I can confirm that rumor tonight,
we need more dimensions.
To add more dimensions,
we just add more coordinates.
Fortunately, and I'll,
you keep adding coordinates until
you run out of coordinates.
So it's, that's the reason incidentally
that string theory is in 26 dimensions.
The ra-
Actually, actually,
yeah, okay, never mind.
All right.
Remember what x of sigma was.
x of sigma and y of sigma,
we have a string moving around in the xy plane,
looking at it moving down the axis.
It has n's,
and along the string,
we invent a parameter called sigma.
Sigma goes from zero to pi.
All right.
And,
and if we take any point on the string,
it's characterized by a sigma.
It's the sigmath point, if you like.
And it has a particular value of x and y.
Here's the xy axis.
Each point on the string has a definite location.
We call them x of sigma.
And y of sigma.
And we use our freedom
to Fourier expand x and y.
And we find,
or we write that this is the sum over n
of cosine of n sigma
times, let's call it x sub n.
And what is x sub n?
x sub n is simply the Fourier coefficient
of the nth cosine wave.
And the Fourier expansion of x.
And likewise with y.
Why did I use cosines and not sines?
Anybody remember?
The boundary conditions are such
that the derivatives of x
should vanish at the end points.
That's the condition that the force at the ends
not be strong enough to cause infinite acceleration.
But,
this is the right way to expand the x's.
Likewise with the y's.
Summation n, y sub n, cosine n sigma.
And now we can write these coordinates
in terms of creation and annihilation operators.
We can write them as the sum over n
of a plus of n plus a minus of n
over the square root of n
times cosine n sigma.
And the same thing down here with b's.
b sub n, blah blah blah.
Why is that interesting?
Well, the best way to manipulate the quantum mechanics
of harmonic oscillators
is through the creation and annihilation operators.
If you want to find out what a particular operator
does to a quantum state,
you apply the operator.
But if you apply it in
the form of creation and annihilation operators,
you immediately see what it does.
Increases the energy, decreases the energy.
And that, of course, will be very useful.
But for the moment, they're just equations
that I'm writing down on the blackboard.
Because we'll use them.
Okay, I won't go through these again.
So, if there are questions
about them, ask them right now.
But I want you to ask me philosophical questions
about the meaning of life.
The x sub n is a function also of sigma?
No. No, no.
x sub n's are the Fourier series coefficients.
All of the sigma dependence is here.
This is the sigma dependence.
What do the x n's depend on, though?
Time. Time.
There's time in this infinite momentum frame,
which we gave a name to.
We called it tau.
When I write dots, dots always refer to the time
in this non-relativistic analogy,
which I didn't call t because
I didn't want to confuse it
with time in the rest frame.
So I called it the last
time, I believe I called it tau.
That means that every point on the string
is not just a function of sigma.
It is also a function of tau.
It's the x n's which are dependent on tau.
Why are they dependent on tau?
Because they're oscillators.
They oscillate. They vibrate.
The x n's vibrate with oscillations.
They depend on time.
The cosines of sigmas,
those are the ones which depend on sigma.
Okay. Are there any other questions?
Yes.
I have two questions for you.
Aren't those for the creation of the distraction operators,
aren't they reversed?
In other words, you get
subtracting energy from A plus and...
No, you add energy with A plus.
Unless someone was along the line,
I think I got it right.
We could check it out, but...
Why do you think you subtract energy?
Why?
What makes you think so?
Well, I mean, it's a negative.
You're decreasing the value...
Of what?
Of A plus.
How can you see any...
How can you see...
How can you look at that and see which way...
You may be right, but how
can you look at it and see?
I don't think you're right, but I'll check.
We'll check in a minute, but let's see.
I think he's thinking of it as a real number
instead of a complex number.
I don't care if it's a
real number or a complex number.
I still don't see how
you could look at it easily
and see which one raises the energy
and which one lowers the energy.
He's just seeing the minus sign and thinking...
Oh, you're looking at this minus sign.
That doesn't tell you.
You have to go through the quantum mechanics
and you have to check whether the commutation relations
give you a 1 or a minus 1.
And I think I did that.
So, no, this minus sign doesn't tell you anything.
Well, it tells you something, but not...
Not...
Okay.
Next.
And that's purely by way of absolute review.
Now, what may or may...
Oh, oh, oh, oh.
Okay.
So how much energy...
Well, all right, I think I
said what I had to say.
Next question, next preliminary.
The spin of massless...
And massive particles.
How many components or, let's say, states
does a system of spin J have?
Let's start with spin 0.
How many states?
2J plus 1.
Right, 2J plus 1.
All right, so spin J has 2J plus 1 states.
Spin 0 has 1 state.
Spin 1...
All right, so spin 0, spin.
Okay, spin 0, 1 state.
Spin 1, 3 states.
Spin 2, 5 states, and so forth.
However, massless particles are special.
They don't fall into this category.
A massless spin 0 state only has 1 state.
But a massless spin 1
state has 2 states, not 3.
A massless spin 2 state
system has 2 states, not 5.
A massless spin 3, 2 states.
The only one which is the exceptional sort
of odd man out is the spin 0.
It has only 1 state.
All others have 2 states.
For massless, for massless.
How do we understand that?
How can that be...
The question is how can it be consistent?
How can it be consistent?
I will tell you what the 2 states are.
In every case here, yeah, the particle,
imagine it moving along a certain axis.
For the moment, it could be massless or massive.
And let's suppose it's moving along a certain axis.
Let me consider the component of spin along that axis.
What's the maximum...
Let's forget spin 0 here.
That only has 1 state.
But let's go to spin 1.
What's the maximum spin along any given axis?
Well, the answer is the spins along any
axis can be 1, 0, and minus 1.
How about for spin 2?
0, minus 1, and minus 2.
In each case, there is always a maximum spin.
In this case, a maximum and a minimum.
Meaning to say, maximum positive and
a minimum which would be negative.
Those can be thought of as the states where
the spin is maximally along the direction of motion
or maximally opposed to the direction of motion.
Now, as far as whether the spin is along
the direction of motion or against the direction of motion,
that's really an arbitrary choice of
right hand versus left hand rule.
Spin has to do with rotation.
Momentum is a vector along an axis.
My right hand, my fingers curl right-handedly.
My left hand, they curl left-handedly.
A spin that way is considered positive along the axis.
And a spin that-a-way is
considered negative along the same axis.
Well, simple reflection symmetry tells you if
you have one, you better have the other.
If you have a right hand and
you're in a world with reflection symmetry,
you'll have a left hand.
If there's a right-handed particle that can spin that way,
there'll be a left-handed one
that can spin the other way.
So, if you have a particle moving down
the axis with the maximum component of spin,
there must be another possibility.
The particle must also be capable of having
the opposite, namely the minimum component of spin.
But is there any reason why
it has to have spins in between?
So let's take the spin one case.
The spin one case, the three states along
that axis have spin one, zero, and minus one.
Those are the three states.
We see because of reflection invariance that if
it has a spin one along the axis,
it must also have a spin minus one.
Must it also have a spin zero?
Well, the answer-a z component of spin.
A z component of spin along that axis.
And the answer, as I said, depends
on whether the particle is massive or massless.
So let me show you why.
Supposing the particle is massive to begin with.
And supposing it has-let me argue that
there must be three states that it has.
If it's moving down the z axis,
and it has spin along the z axis,
so it's rotating this away.
Now imagine bringing that particle to rest.
Or better yet, moving in such a
way that you keep up with the particle.
It's not moving with the speed
of light. It's got a mass.
You keep up with it, and you look
at the particle, and the particle's at rest.
The particle is at rest.
So now you've discovered that there's a particle at rest,
but moving along with it doesn't change its spin.
If it's rotating this way and going down
that axis, and you keep up with it,
it will still be rotating that way.
So it still has spin one along this axis.
It has spin one along this axis.
But now that you've brought it to rest,
you can rotate it,
and then boost it back up.
In that case, you've created a
particle which is neither spinning about,
which neither has maximal spin in that direction,
or minimum spin in that direction,
but which now has spin pointing out of the blackboard,
even though the particle is moving down that direction.
And you did that by, first
of all, bringing the particle to rest,
and then saying, if you're living
in a world with rotation invariants,
if there's a particle at rest,
whose spin is pointing along that axis,
it must also be possible to
have it pointing along that axis.
Another way to think about it is,
you could imagine after having brought it to rest,
boosting it along the perpendicular axis,
either way, you wind up with
a particle whose spin is perpendicular
to the axis of motion.
And that must be the case, because
you can bring a particle to rest,
and then,
accelerate it in a perpendicular direction,
without changing its spin.
Okay, so, conclusion.
If you have a massive particle,
it must have all three states.
Spin along that axis, spin along that axis,
and that's not enough, you have to be
able to make up spin along the perpendicular axis.
On the other hand, if the particle is massless,
there is nothing you can
do to bring it to rest.
Any Lorentz transformation will leave it
moving with the speed of light.
You cannot bring it to rest, and then,
rotate out from under the spin,
and boost it in another direction.
The implication is,
that if particles have zero mass,
then it's perfectly consistent that
all they have is maximal spin,
and minimal spin,
and nothing in between.
That's typically the case.
Now, you know this in another guise for the photon.
What guise is it for the photon?
The polarization of light.
The polarization of light can be
described in a number of ways.
It can be described as linear polarization,
circular polarization,
but if you describe it in terms of circular polarization,
circular polarization, incidentally, corresponds to photons,
depending on whether the circular
polarization is right-handed or left-handed,
it corresponds to an assemblage of photons,
which are either right-hand spinning or left-hand spinning.
There are no photons which are not polarized at all.
Polarization is always perpendicular
to the direction of motion.
It's either right-handed or left-handed.
Now, what about linear polarization?
There's linear polarization,
and I'm going to tell
you now what linear polarization is.
Linear polarization, if you have...
Linear polarization is not zero angular
momentum along the direction of motion.
It's a quantum superposition of the two possibilities.
Circular polarization to the right
and circular polarization to the left.
What's the difference between saying it's
a linear superposition of polarization states
and saying it has no angular momentum at all?
It has equal probability for spinning to
the right and spinning to the left.
So doesn't that mean that it has,
on the average, no spin at all?
Yes, it does mean that on
the average it has no spin.
But if you measure the angular momentum of that photon,
it will either be right-handed or left-handed.
You will never measure a photon which
has no angular momentum along that direction.
So there are only two states of the photon.
And one other point.
Let's go back to linear polarization.
A photon moving down an axis can be polarized.
Here's the plane perpendicular to the motion of the photon.
If you send it through a plane polarizer,
it can be polarized, let's say, along the y-axis,
or it can be polarized along the x-axis.
The polarization is a vector.
But it's a vector which is always perpendicular
to the direction of motion of the photon.
It's always perpendicular, and the words for
that are the polarization is always transverse.
There is no polarization of the photon where the polarization where
the electric field arrow points along the direction of the photon.
That's not allowed by Maxwell's equations.
Maxwell's equations tell you
the electric and magnetic field,
and therefore the polarization of the photon,
are perpendicular to the direction of motion.
So you can have two states of two different polarizations.
You could call it the x-polarization state of the photon,
or you could call it the y-polarization state.
Neither of them is circular polarization.
What about circular polarization?
Circular polarization is a linear superposition,
a quantum mechanical linear superposition,
right-handed, let's call it right-hand polarization,
which means spin right-handed.
That's equal to the state x
plus i times the state y.
No, I won't say it.
Left-handed is x minus iy.
Is it the same like the
silver polarization, like the Stern-Berlus experiment?
If you said i-silver, is
it the same type of explanation?
No, it's just circular polarization.
Just circular polarization.
Just pure circular polarization.
Circular polarization is a quantum linear superposition.
For each photon, a circularly polarized photon
is a quantum superposition of a x-polarized photon
and a y-polarized photon.
Let me ask this.
Supposing I didn't put the i here.
Supposing I just considered x plus y,
what kind of photon would that be?
Linearly polarized.
That would be linearly polarized,
but at a 45-degree angle to the axes.
So, if all you are allowed
to do is put real numbers here,
you would make linear polarization,
which could point in any direction perpendicular
to the direction of motion of the photon.
But having i's available gives you something new.
It gives you circular polarization.
If you use as your basis of states,
the circularly polarized states,
instead of the linearly polarized states,
there are only two of them.
So the angular momentum of the
photon is either along the axis
or along the opposite to the axis.
And there is no photon which
has zero angular momentum along the axis.
The same is true of gravitons.
Slightly differently,
gravitons are spin-2 objects.
If they were massive, they would have five states.
But gravitons only have two states.
They, roughly speaking,
and this is an analogy I
want you to keep in mind.
It's a good analogy, and we'll draw on it.
A graviton moving down the axis
with maximal angular momentum
that means two units of angular momentum
moving along the z-axis
is mathematically the same as two photons
each with one unit of angular momentum.
Imagine taking two photons,
sticking them together,
letting them move down the axis.
The angular momentum of the two of them
there could be various possibilities.
They could both be circulating
in the right-handed sense.
Then the angular momentum would be two units.
They could be both circulating to the left.
The angular momentum would be minus two units.
What you don't have is a graviton
which corresponds to a photon of
right polarization and left polarization.
Gravitons have only two states.
Maximal rotation in one direction,
maximum rotation in the other direction.
And mathematically, you can think of
just having a pair of photons of right-handed.
You can multiply this by another photon
of the same kind
and think of it as a graviton.
That would be a useful
way to think about spin two
by combining two spin ones.
What's that?
Can we use this analogy only for spin one graviton,
two photons, or can we
do this with other quantum numbers?
Well, there's a whole field of study
which studies Feynman diagrams for gravitons
by thinking of them as roughly speaking
squares of Feynman diagrams for spin one particles.
But mostly I think it's trickery.
There's no real sense in
which a graviton is two photons.
It's just for combining the spins that it's useful.
I can't think of any other
sense in which it's particularly useful.
There are no other quantum numbers.
What other quantum numbers does a photon have?
Or a graviton?
It doesn't have anything else.
It has momentum.
It has momentum, it has energy, and it has spin.
It doesn't have charge.
It doesn't have baryon number.
It doesn't have anything else.
Well, it doesn't have a
jump in the spectrum either, so...
What doesn't have a jump in the spectrum?
A photon has a continuous spectrum, right?
Potentially?
A photon of a given momentum
only has one value of the energy.
Right, but you were saying that a continuous spectrum
is what distinguishes something that is
a particle from something that's not.
Oh.
A continuous spectrum of rest masses.
Or, if you like, a
continuous spectrum for a given momentum.
The pot of particles with...
moving inside, not a pot, but
in a container of some sort,
it doesn't really have continuous spectrum,
but it has extremely dense spectrum.
But what I mean by that is,
if the entire pot is at rest,
there are lots and lots of energy levels.
Okay?
Certainly we can generate a
continuous spectrum just by moving it,
but I was speaking about the pot at rest.
Now, photons, it's true, can't be at rest,
so you can't quite use that definition.
You use a different definition, say, for a given momentum.
So...
Okay.
So now we know something about harmonic dynamics.
So now we know something about harmonic oscillators,
we know something about spin.
And what I want to come to now
is the spectrum of strings.
The low-lying spectrum of strings.
The low-lying spectrum means the first few states.
Let's just remember that energy,
in this formal analogy between
non-relativistic physics and relativistic physics,
energy becomes not mc squared, not the mass,
but the square of the mass.
So when we speak about
the energy of a vibrating string,
and we add them all up to
find the total energy of the vibrating string,
it corresponds to the square of the mass.
Okay?
Not the mass itself.
That's just something to remember.
Okay, what are the discrete energy levels of the string?
And we're talking...
A string at rest, meaning to say it's
not moving in the perpendicular direction at all.
What are the energies?
Well, we just say, look, it's
just a collection of harmonic oscillators.
Let's see what we can make.
The first state and the lowest state
is the state which is annihilated,
that's the ground state,
by all the annihilation operators.
In other words, it's just the state, the ground state.
All the B's and all the A's,
all the annihilation operators give zero.
It's the state in which neither or
none of these oscillators are at all excited.
What's the energy of that state?
Well, if we were doing
ordinary quantum mechanical harmonic oscillators,
we might say it's a half h-bar omega, right?
That's the ground state energy of a string.
But let's leave it open for a minute.
Let's not prejudice the answer.
Let's leave it flexible for a moment
and call the mass squared...
Now, what does this stand for?
This does not stand for the vacuum.
It is not empty space.
It is the unexcited oscillators.
It's a particle.
It's a particle moving down the z-axis,
but it's in the ground
state of all of its oscillations.
I wouldn't say it has no oscillations,
because every harmonic
oscillator has zero-point oscillations.
Because of the uncertainty
principle, there's some fluctuation.
But every one of the oscillators
is as quiet as it can be,
consistent with quantum mechanics.
So this thing is a particle,
and I'm not going to begin by prejudicing
about what the mass of that particle is.
I'm just going to call it m-naught squared,
whatever it happens to be.
This is the energy of the ground state,
or the square of the mass of the ground state.
And we don't know what it is yet.
We don't have a tool yet
for finding out what it is.
But whatever it is, when we excite it,
we will increase it by integer amounts of energy.
So let's see how we can excite it,
what the lowest energy excitation is.
What's the cheapest thing in
energy we can do to it?
And the cheapest thing in energy
that we can do to it
is to apply the creation operators,
the raising operators,
but the lowest one,
a1.
Remember, each oscillator increases the energy
by n,
n units.
And so, if we want to consider the lowest energy,
we want to hit it
with the oscillator of smallest frequency.
The oscillator of smallest frequency
corresponds to n equals 1.
So we hit it with a1.
What's the energy of that state?
Oh, incidentally, what is the energy of that state?
We've increased it by 1 unit.
This 1 here indicates that the frequency
of that particular oscillator is 1 unit.
The energy that you add is 1 unit.
This has increased the energy of
the ground state by 1 unit.
So the energy of this state is...
Whatever m0 squared is plus 1.
Nobody's asking me about units.
How could I be talking
about energy and saying 1 unit?
1, 1 unit.
1, 1 joule, 1 horsepower, not horsepower.
Horsepower is power.
Horsepower second.
What's the British unit of...
Oh, a British thermal unit.
Maybe it's one British thermal unit.
Well, this seems pretty unlikely, doesn't it?
So what is this 1?
What am I talking about when I say 1?
It's something we'd better come back to.
We'd better come back to units.
I hope by the end of
the evening we'll come back to units.
But in some units, in some appropriate units,
the units that we've been working,
the first excited state,
which is a dagger 1,
gives us 1 extra unit of energy.
Now, that's not the only state
that has 1 extra unit of energy.
Is there another one you can think of?
B1.
Same energy.
What about any linear combination of them?
If you take 2 eigenvectors of the energy,
and you superpose them,
it gives you back another eigenvector with the same energy.
Okay?
So, any linear combination of these has the same energy.
Now, what are the properties
of these objects A and B?
In particular, I mean,
what are their transformation properties
when you rotate the circle?
When you rotate the space?
We have an axis, a preferred axis.
I've defined the preferred axis.
I've said boost the system up so
that it's moving like hell along the z-axis.
But I still have a
rotation symmetry of the entire thing
about the axis that I boosted things.
How do A and B transform under those rotations?
Well, you ask where they came from.
They came from x and y.
We wrote that x was some sum involving b's,
no, sorry, a's,
and y was some sum involving b's.
What is x and y?
x and y are components of a vector.
That's what they are.
They're components of a vector.
They transform the components.
x and y transform like
the components of a two-dimensional vector.
What about the a's?
The a's obviously also transform as a vector.
A and b, if you were to rotate the coordinates,
would transform into some a
cosine theta plus b sine theta.
They would just rotate like a two-dimensional vector.
So these a's and b's are vectors.
That means that you can consider these two things
to have a vectorial character.
This one is pointing,
they're always in the plane perpendicular to the motion,
always in the plane perpendicular to the motion,
which is large.
This one has some kind of
vectorial property in the one direction.
This one has vectorial property in the two direction.
So these two states transform into each other as vectors.
They have the same properties
as the plane polarization of photons.
The photon polarization is also a vector.
Namely, it corresponds to the direction
of the electric field at some instant.
It's a vector.
It points in the direction perpendicular
to the motion of the photon.
And so it's looking as if
these two things must correspond somehow
to a vector character to the particle.
How would, can we turn it into a circular polarization?
Yes, we can turn it into a circular polarization.
Instead of taking a1 or b1,
we take a1 plus ib1.
And that's a circularly polarized something.
It's a string which has the
properties of a circularly polarized particle.
And of course we can put minus there.
And the mathematics of it is
identical to the mathematics of the polarization states
of a particle moving down the axis.
They transform into each other in the rotations.
We could linearly superpose these with real coefficients.
And then we would just
be rotating the direction of oscillation.
Or we can add them with an
i and we turn them into circularly polarized.
Now this is not easy to visualize.
Don't try to visualize it.
It's the transformation properties which count.
Notice that there is not a
third state with the same energy.
There is no other third oscillator.
There's only the x oscillator, the y oscillator.
And that's it.
There is no third state.
So there is no third polarization state.
There's only one conclusion which
is consistent with Lorentz invariance,
with relativity.
With the properties of these things.
This object, these two objects must be massless.
They must be like the massless photon.
If there are only two polarization states,
that would not be consistent with a massive particle
because a massive particle you can bring
to rest and turn its direction of motion
and create the third polarization state.
So these two things, these two states,
behave exactly like the two
polarization states of the photon.
Moving down the axis,
let's not give them any motion perpendicular to the axis,
no overall motion.
Moving down the axis,
and there are two polarization states.
They do have the properties
of the polarization states of photons.
A vector character to them,
in the perpendicular direction.
In other words, they are transversely polarized things.
They are identified as photon-like objects in string theory.
And they must be massless.
If they are not massless, there is something deeply wrong.
Lorentz invariance cannot be maintained.
And so, we come...
You must realize by now we've come to a disaster.
We've come to a very unfortunate crash.
Where, at this point, we should throw away string theory.
Why?
Because m naught squared plus one has to be zero.
The mass of this object,
which is not the ground state,
it's been excited by one unit,
as this.
If it's to make sense as a relativistic object,
it has to be massless.
And that means m naught squared is negative.
Okay, big deal.
Who cares if m naught squared is negative?
The problem with that is m naught
squared was the energy or the mass,
the mass squared of the ground state without these a1s.
In other words, the string which was
not vibrating along the x or y axis,
the ground state of the string.
That's intolerable.
Having a particle with negative mass squared is crazy.
Mass squared is positive.
How can mass squared be negative?
You're going to have imaginary mass, right.
Okay.
Rotate what by 90 degrees?
And in what space?
Negative mass squared is a bad thing.
Okay.
Negative mass squared,
imaginary mass, is a bad thing.
So let me tell you,
why is it a bad thing?
So what?
Because you discovered something that
a certain parameter is negative.
What does it mean?
All right.
An object with negative mass squared has a name.
You know the name?
A tachyon.
The tachy comes from the same,
it's not that it's a tachy particle.
I mean, that's not the point.
It is tachy, but,
what's the thing in your car which
tells you how fast the man is?
How fast the engine is going?
Tachy, tachy, tachy, tachy.
Yeah.
Tachy, tachy is either,
I guess it's a Greek word?
Tachy, yeah, yeah, but tachy I think refers to speed.
Speed, I think it's a word for speed.
And, what's that?
No, I don't think so.
I think it could be linear speed too.
I don't know.
I don't know my Greek,
and I don't even know if it's a Greek word.
Maybe it's a Yiddish word, I don't know.
It does, it does, it does,
but I think the prefix
tachy refers to speed in general.
I don't know for sure,
but I do know why they called it a tachyon.
A tachyon meant that it moves very fast,
in fact so fast that it
moves faster than the speed of light.
Now, that's clearly something bad, okay?
Einstein told us there are nothing that
can move faster than the speed of light.
So, we seem to have encountered something
which is a tachyon with negative mass squared.
Let me tell, maybe I should stop at this
point and tell you a little bit about tachyons.
They're bad.
We want to get rid of them.
They're intolerable,
and if every string theory had a tachyon,
you would not have heard of string theory.
It would have been abandoned sometime around 1969,
and you would never have heard about it again.
So, of course, the answer is
that there are many string theories,
many good string theories that do not have the tachyon.
There are no string theories
that don't have this photon-like object.
This is a good thing because the
world has photons and it doesn't have tachyons,
but let me just tell
you about tachyons a little bit
and how physicists use the terminology today.
Only crackpots think that they move
faster than the speed of light.
So don't fall into that trap.
Or that they can somehow send
signals faster than the speed of light.
That's not the measure of the issue here.
But let me show you why there was
some idea that they exceeded the speed of light.
The important quantity of interest for the moment now
is the amount of light that is in the tachyon.
So what is the frequency of
a wave versus its wave number?
What is the frequency of a...
which is equivalent, of course, it's
equivalent to the energy of an object.
Apart from a factor of h-bar, it's the same
as the energy as a function of the momentum.
So let's write that down
for an ordinary non-relativistic particle.
E of p is p squared over 2m, right?
I'll just point something out to you.
We could prove something about this,
but the derivative of e with
respect to p, what is that?
p over m.
And p over m is?
The velocity.
That's a general rule.
It's actually a property of waves.
If instead of e you put omega
and instead of p you put k,
then it's a property of waves that the group
velocity is given by the derivative of the frequency
with respect to the wave number or
the energy with respect to the momentum.
Let's try it out for something else.
How about in relativity?
What's e versus p?
Let's start with a photon.
e over c.
Is it e equals p times
c or e equals p over c?
p times c.
p times c, right?
Yeah.
e is equal to p times c.
What is the derivative of e with respect to p?
p.
Which is of course the velocity of a photon.
Alright?
Let's try it a little more generally.
e equals the square root
of p squared plus m squared.
Okay, now it gets a little hard.
Derivative of e with respect to p.
That gives us one divided by twice the
square root of p squared plus m squared.
And then what's in the numerator?
2p.
Okay, so it's p over p squared plus m squared.
Sorry, p over p squared plus m squared.
Okay.
I'm not going to try to convince you
that this is the velocity of a relativistic particle,
but it does have one property.
Notice that it's less than one.
Square root of p squared plus
m squared is bigger than p.
Okay?
Square root of p squared plus m squared is
bigger than the square root of just p squared.
So p divided by this is always less than one.
That's another way of seeing
that relativistic particles are different.
So I'm seeing that relativistic particles always move
with speed less than the speed of light.
What if there was a minus here?
It goes faster than the speed of light.
That's why people call these things tachyons.
When somebody or other, and I
have no idea who it was,
first decided that it might be interesting to think
about particles that move faster than the speed of light,
they postulated a negative mass squared.
Okay?
The question is what is really wrong with that?
Other than it seems to
contradict something that Einstein taught us.
What does a tachyon really mean?
And the answer is it doesn't mean something moving or
that sends, transmits signals faster than the speed of light.
It means that the vacuum is unstable.
It means that something can
happen that can destabilize the system.
That's the usual source of tachyons.
So I'm going to give you an example.
But first, let's think about wave equations.
Let's start with wave equations.
These equations are also ways
of thinking about wave equations.
Here's a wave equation.
That's an ordinary wave equation for as a function.
Let's read it this way.
Okay.
What kind of wave is that?
What does it move with?
Speed of what?
d by dt squared.
d by dt squared stands for omega squared, right?
We've done this before.
We've done this many times.
If you have a wave, the time derivative,
each time derivative gives you a factor of omega.
What about each space derivative?
k, right?
Each space derivative gives you a k.
So this equation says that omega squared
equals k squared or omega equals k.
I've left out the speed of light.
I've set the speed of light equal to one.
So what's the velocity of this wave?
The omega decay.
One.
How do I turn it into something
that moves slower than the speed of light?
What do I add?
If I want to add
a mass term, here it is.
We have...
m squared times...
Yeah.
Which side?
Can you figure that out?
Is it this way?
No, it's minus this way.
It's minus.
Minus m squared phi.
Then we would have...
Incidentally, is the derivative with respect to
t, is that omega or i omega?
i omega, right?
If we have something that goes as follows.
If we have something that goes as e to the i
omega t and we differentiate it, it gives us an i omega.
So this gives us...
This is really another way
of talking about minus omega squared.
This is minus k squared.
And this is minus m squared.
Which is the same as omega
squared equals k squared plus m squared.
This one here.
So this is what you do to...
What does this correspond to in the energy?
Do you remember what it corresponds
to in the energy of the wave?
The energy of the wave
has d phi by dt squared.
One half.
It has plus d phi by dx squared.
And this is...
This is the energy of the wave.
And this gives us plus m squared phi squared.
Does anybody remember this from last quarter?
Wave equations and the mass term...
How you put in a mass for
a particle in terms of the wave equations.
Klein-Gordon equations with mass.
This was the rule.
Now notice that...
Imagine...
What is it? This is a
kind of potential energy for the field.
Notice that it's positive.
It's positive if the mass is positive.
That means that if you increase phi,
the energy increases.
The result of that is if you increase phi,
it will oscillate back.
It's just like a harmonic oscillator.
A positive energy when you
displace the field a little bit.
And because you gain some energy,
or it costs some energy,
because it costs some potential energy,
to increase phi,
it will swing back.
And the wave will oscillate.
What would happen if you had a negative term here?
So that the potential energy of phi looked like that.
You fall off the cliff.
So it's an instability.
It's an instability of the vacuum.
If you thought that the
vacuum was just phi equals zero,
and you gave it a little push,
down you would go.
Here's a kind of interesting question.
Supposing you really did start
with phi very carefully balanced
at the top of the potential everywheres.
Everywheres in space, phi was
absolutely balanced at the top.
Well, it would sit that way
forever if it were absolutely balanced.
It would be like a sharp pencil, perfectly balanced.
You give it a push, the tiniest push,
and off it goes.
But supposing you pushed it only at one point.
You want a model for this.
Can we make a model for this?
Yeah, I can make a model for it.
Here's a model for it to think about.
You have a bunch of vertical pendulums.
And they're coupled together by springs.
They're in a gravitational field.
If you set them all up,
perfectly vertically,
they will stay that way.
If you only had a single pendulum,
and you gave it a little push,
what would happen?
In fact, it wouldn't fly off to infinity,
but it would make a big deviation
from where it started.
So the starting point was unstable.
What happens if you push all of them simultaneously?
Well, you know what happens.
They all go flying over the top.
But here's an interesting question.
Supposing you pushed one of them,
only one of them,
this one right over here,
how fast would the signal propagate outward?
You push one of them,
it pushes the next one,
and sure enough, if you wait,
they all go flopping over.
But how fast does that signal spread out?
It is sound, which is...
Well, we're thinking about light being...
the velocity of waves.
Does it go faster than the speed of light,
the way the tachyon suggests it might?
It doesn't.
The falling over, the domino effect,
proceeds with the edge,
or the outer boundary,
the outer envelope of the domino effect,
will spread out no faster than the speed of light.
So the conclusion is that tachyons are not
to be thought of as things that go faster
than the speed of light.
String theory has not provided a way
of exceeding the speed of light.
What it's done is it's given us a theory
with an unstable vacuum.
A little tiny push will destabilize the whole world.
That's not a good thing.
That's something that we need to avoid.
And that's where superstring theory comes in.
That's why we need it.
That's why we have to do better than just this
very simple string theory that I've described.
But okay, so far what we've found,
if we ignore the tachyon,
just say somehow, by magic,
we're going to get rid of it,
we have found a theory which has
a photon-like object in it.
A massless photon-like object
with two polarization states.
And it's a candidate for something like the photon.
I said to you that there are tricks and ways
of getting rid of the tachyon.
You might ask me, are there tricks and ways
of getting rid of the photon-like object,
the massless thing?
Well, the answer is nobody ever found one.
Within months of the discovery of string theory,
people have figured out how
to get rid of the tachyon.
They never got rid of the photon-like object.
Why might they have liked to
get rid of the photon-like object?
Massless spin-1-2.
The photon-like object is a spin-1-2 particle.
Why not?
Well, it sounds like a good thing.
It could be the photon.
The reason was, at the time,
string theory was not supposed
to be a theory of photons.
It was supposed to be a theory of hadrons,
mesons, baryons,
and there is no massless meson.
There are no massless mesons.
So this was thought to be a wart,
not a feature.
But at the time,
people wanted to get rid of not only the tachyon,
but also the massless photon-like object.
In all the years that
people have been doing string theory,
the tachyon was very easy to get rid of,
and nobody ever got rid of the spin-1 object,
the photon.
Yeah?
Is this the one they decided
comes out of string theory, the graviton?
No, this is not the graviton yet.
This so far is the photon.
Or a...
To call it the photon,
would be a little bit misleading.
There are many sources of
a photon-like object in string theory.
Which one is the real photon,
and what do we do with all the others?
Those are very model-dependent.
Those depend on details.
To say that this is the photon would be misleading.
It is a photon-like object.
It is a gauge boson.
It is a thing which behaves
like a photon in many ways.
It is a thing which is a photon.
It is a thing which
is a photon in many ways.
And we'll need to come back to it,
but I'll just show you this.
Let's...
Shall we...
Hmm?
To summarize,
right now, if you develop it,
you have an M squared less than zero,
which is the tachyon.
Yeah.
And that's not allowed.
Not allowed.
And we're not yet at the point where
we know how to get rid of it.
I wouldn't say so much...
From a strictly theoretical point of view,
quantum mechanics with an
upside-down potential is perfectly good.
There's nothing wrong with it.
It just doesn't have a ground state.
And that's bad.
Yeah.
So...
It doesn't look like the world.
Now...
Of course...
Yeah.
Good enough.
In this case here, we know
what would happen to these guys.
They would just turn over,
and I'll wind up oscillating about the bottom.
Okay?
Here, who knows if there's a bottom?
Yeah.
To get to gravitons, we have to study something new.
Something new is closed strings.
So far, these are open strings.
Open strings means they have two ends.
Ends, period.
It's hard to have a string with one end.
Unless you're a Buddhist.
Never mind.
Zen Buddhist.
I apologize to any Zen Buddhists in the class.
It seems that you're looking at
the properties of photons with polarization
and the properties of these strings,
and...
As far as that goes, it matches up.
Yeah.
Are there other properties of photons and
other properties of strings that also match up?
Absolutely.
Yeah.
The interesting question is what would have
to do with the radiation of photons.
Now, to have a radiation of photons,
you have to have objects which carry charge.
We haven't yet discussed what
kind of objects might correspond
to the things which carry charge.
But once if we found string
objects which played the role of charges,
we could ask, if we knew the rules,
and we're going to talk about the rules,
we could ask about the rules
of emission of photons by accelerated charges.
And the answer is yes.
We would find out that they behave exactly
the same way that emission of photons is.
That emission of photons from charged particles works.
Definite rules.
Definite rules, definite probability
distributions, definite radiation patterns.
And those patterns would be reproduced quite precisely.
So, yeah.
Okay.
Let's move on.
I think I mentioned this last time, but...
I'll tell you anyway.
The basic process of interaction that takes place.
So far, we're talking about free strings.
Free strings means an isolated string moving by itself,
unaccompanied by any other,
and doing nothing except propagating along some axis,
and doing its own internal wiggles,
but its wiggles, the manifestations of its wiggles,
are simply a discrete collection of
energy levels and also angular momentum.
A string can move internally in many ways.
For example, one of the ways it can move...
Remember, these strings, the mathematics of them,
is the mathematics of non-relativistic strings.
One of the things a string
can do is it can rotate.
It can rotate about an axis.
Rotate like a dumbbell about an axis.
The centrifugal force being the
thing which stretches it out.
So this must be something
that these relativistic strings can do.
This means that they can
have all sorts of angular momenta.
Not just one unit of angular
momentum or two units of angular momentum,
but you can spin them up.
But when you do,
because we're doing quantum mechanics,
each unit of angular momentum costs
you an additional unit of energy.
Can you have pitch-pole rotation?
Can you have what?
Pitch-pole rotation.
What's a pitch-pole rotation?
Like one of them stays in the other.
No.
That's not possible.
No, they'll rotate about the center of mass.
Right.
Any system, when it's rotating,
will rotate about its center of mass.
So the question is where is the center of mass?
And if it's a nice straight
string like this rotating about an axis,
of course the center of
mass would be at the center.
So,
of course if you had something to
anchor the end of the string to,
then it could swing around that anchor.
And there are anchors in string theory.
Could it swing around the energy level of an atom?
Can it?
Like the photons holding the electrons
in the center of the atom,
can it pitch-pole out from that?
You're asking whether an electron
can circulate around a nucleus.
The electron circulates around a nucleus.
The reason that the electron circulates around a nucleus
with the nucleus standing still
is because the nucleus is very heavy.
So the center, really, strictly speaking,
they both rotate about a common center of mass.
But because the nucleus is a couple
of thousand times heavier than the electron,
it looks like the nucleus is not moving.
What did you call this, pitch-pole?
Pitch-polling.
Where you pull this in fixed,
and this end rotates and gets thrown out.
It's like the Scottish do,
with the big logs and pitch-polling.
Oh, yes.
No, I don't know.
I thought it was the Jews who invented that.
Ah, the Russians.
Yes.
Okay.
The basic process of interaction
that allows strings to talk to each other,
to interact with each other,
to do things,
I think I discussed this last time,
but I'll tell you what it is.
We're not going to do anything mathematical with it tonight.
We will try to describe
this a little bit mathematically later,
but just qualitatively.
The things that happen,
particularly to these open strings,
is very simple.
It's really the only process.
Everything is built out of it.
And we're going to find even a simpler description,
but at the moment, this is very simple.
The only thing that happens,
apart from these strings wiggling and doing their own thing,
the only thing that allows
them to talk to each other
is that when endpoints
find themselves at coincident points in space,
in other words, when they touch,
there is a probability
or let's call it an amplitude
for them to join.
That's called a joining interaction.
So there is some probability.
They don't inevitably do it.
There is a constant in the theory.
It's called the string coupling constant.
And what it does is
it takes a pair of strings,
here's a pair of strings
moving along in space-time,
upward is time,
there's a string,
here comes another string,
their endpoints meet at this point,
and they join together to form a single string.
That's the analog
in string theory
of what in quantum field theory is the vertex,
where two particles come together and join
and make a third particle.
This could be an electron
and an electron
and a photon,
or it could be any of the other interactions
that we've studied.
Two particles come together,
join and make a third particle.
Two strings come together,
join and make a third string.
But the process is very simple.
It doesn't just happen any old way.
It happens by the endpoints coming together,
touching,
and combining to form a single string.
Now, anything that can happen in quantum mechanics
can unhappen,
meaning to say that quantum mechanics
is a reversible theory.
Anything that can happen in time in one direction
can happen the opposite way in time.
So that means that there is also an amplitude
for a single string to break and form ends.
If that probability were large,
the string would have very little integrity.
It would constantly be breaking up.
If that probability is very small,
then the string might last a long time
before it breaks up like that.
So one of the assumptions in string theory
is that this probability is small.
The probability is called the string coupling constant.
I think I said that.
And it's the analog of the constant
of nature, which would be,
what would it be for the electron-electron photon?
It would be the electric charge.
It would be the fine-structure constant, right.
It would be the square of the electric charge,
that probability.
Probability is the squares of amplitudes.
So the probability for two strings to join
is like the electric charge.
But it's the same.
It's quite independent
of which kinds of strings
are joining in the sense that
they could be the excited strings,
they could be the rotating strings,
they could be the vibrating strings.
There's some probability when two endpoints
touch each other that they fuse.
And that same probability,
that if the string is just moving along,
minding its own business,
that a, that, what's the opposite of fuse?
Fish.
Right.
It can fuse or it can fish.
Break.
Break anywhere along its length.
And those are,
all right, so,
this is the basic structure.
But one of the things that can happen
is just like a snake which encounters its own tail
and is too stupid to know
that it's found its own tail,
might bite its own tail,
the same thing can happen with strings.
They're also rather stupid.
And if the string happens to come around like that,
in the course of its evolution,
it might just do that.
And when it does,
بحد
detects a tail, and guess what happens?
They join.
So it's inevitable. There is no way around it
that if you have a theory of
open strings, and those open strings interact
in other words, have this
joining and splitting process happening,
then it is quite inevitable that the
same theory has to have closed strings.
Closed strings are unavoidable.
Can you have a theory with closed?
We're going to work out the mathematics of closed strings.
I don't think we're going to do it tonight.
We'll work out the math.
The mathematics of closed strings
is very similar to open strings.
We'll work it out.
Question?
When you have these fission and fusion situations,
does that change the energy state of the string?
Yeah. Yes, it does.
Does the theory say how?
Yes.
Absolutely.
Absolutely. It does.
But for our purposes now, I
just wanted to motivate for you
why closed strings are inevitable in a theory of strings,
or in a theory of interacting strings.
Now, what about a theory of closed
strings that ab initio starts with closed strings?
Is it inevitable that there will always be open strings?
No. No. Hmm?
I mean, I don't agree.
It doesn't make sense to me
that there would have to be.
It doesn't make sense that there would have to be.
But then you can ask, all right, but
then how do closed strings interact with each other
if they don't interact by
splitting and then touching other strings?
And the way they interact is different.
They interact, here's two closed strings,
and they come together,
and then fuse to form a string.
And then fuse to form a string.
And then fuse to form another closed string.
At no point did they ever form open strings.
They came together like this,
touched, and formed another closed string.
So the answer is, it is quite possible
to have theories of pure closed strings
with no open strings,
but it is not possible to
have a theory of open strings
without closed strings.
That's interesting.
It means that a prediction of string theory
is that there are closed strings.
There is not a prediction of string
theory that there will exist open strings.
It is a prediction of string theory
that there must exist closed strings.
Just because they can be closed,
they can be open string theories.
No.
They can be closed string theories without open strings.
What do you think the,
the clos,
if they open string,
if the,
if the closed string,
interesting low excitation of an open string is a photon
what do you think the interesting excitation,
lowest excitation of a closed string is?
absolute
the graviton
and so one of the things that string theory
literally predicts because you can't not have it is gravity
there are many many string
theories that have things like electromagnetism
but some of them don't
but there is no string theory that doesn't have gravity
every string theory necessarily has gravity
just because it will have close
I never heard of a string
theory that didn't have closed strings
it's got to have some kind of strings
why is a string theory closed string necessarily gravity?
ah well that's what we're going to come to
why was the open string necessarily photons?
well we did some manipulations and
found out it was the only interpretation
we'll do the same thing exactly
the same thing with closed strings
exactly the same thing I
don't think we have time tonight
can an open string convert a
closed string into an open one?
if
in some string theories
the rules involve the splitting and joining process
in those string theories a closed
string can become an open string
but there are also string theories that don't have
this particular process of breaking like this
well if they do have open
strings will that also be possible?
which? which?
if you have a string theory
that has both open and closed
then can a closed one be interact with
an open one such that it becomes open?
yeah there's a number of ways that a
closed string can interact with an open string
but the simplest is the following
once you have closed strings
in fact
once you have them
this is even implicit in open string theory
you can have
the basic thing that can happen
is two ends can touch and join
but there's something else that can happen
the other thing that can happen
is two strings can touch at
a point which is not an end
and then they can rearrange
alright
so let's see what we started with
we started with two strings
did we start with two or one?
yeah we started with two
this way
and this became this
again it's the same process
where two things come in touch
and then rearrange
alright
that's a process that can happen
in string theory
I will have to prove
to you that it can happen
I'm telling you now
ok so let's see what happens if
you have a closed and open string
if you have a closed and open string
the closed string
here's the closed string
the simplest thing that can happen
is the closed string can come
here's the closed string
and then it comes
touch the open string
start the open to you
rearrange
and now
what is it informed?
one big open string
ok so let's think about what that means
that means an open string
is moving along to begin with
let,s draw it
here's our open string
A closed string comes along, closed,
and what's left over at the end?
Open.
That process will turn into the absorption of a
graviton by a particle which is not a graviton.
So here's something we found out.
Closed strings can absorb gravitons.
Same way.
Open strings can absorb gravitons.
In fact, everything can absorb a graviton.
That, in string theory, is why everything gravitates.
In essence, and in a simple-minded way, the fact that an open string or
a closed string can always absorb a graviton by this process is the ultimate...
Well, it's...
One of the ways of
thinking about the universality of gravitation.
Do we ever get into locked and closed loops?
Say it again.
Oh.
Yeah, well...
Okay, we should talk about that.
In weakly coupled string theory, where the interaction
is weak, the strings are transparent to each other.
But they can do this, but with a small probability.
With a small probability.
They come along, and they do that.
But they can also pass right through each other.
So these strings are not obstacles like
shoelaces that they can't pass through each other.
They can pass...
Ah, yeah.
Yeah, they can pass through each other.
I'll bring you a superstring next time,
and I'll show you how it works.
Remind me.
Somebody send me an email to bring a superstring.
I'll bring you a superstring, and then
I'll show you what it can do.
So joining out.
No, no, I'll bring you a real one.
So you said the joining amplitude was kind
of independent of the state of the string?
Yeah.
And just, I mean, if I have something spinning really fast,
then you might anticipate that it has a higher probability of dishing.
Is that just a choice in the theory,
or is there some reason why that doesn't work?
No, no.
The basic probability...
The probability per unit time, if they're touching,
to interact, is the same for all strings.
But keep in mind, if they're moving
fast, they spend less time near each other.
So if the probability per unit time is the same, if they're moving
past each other fast, there will be less of a probability of them joining.
Right?
So it's basically a probability per unit time that's...
Yeah.
When you're showing these strings, and you've
got smaller ones, you've got bigger ones, right?
Is there a fundamental characteristic of, like, math
or energy or something that represents that length?
Okay, so the first thing we
should take up next time is units.
I think that's what you're asking me about.
Is there a unit?
Right.
Now, there must be a unit, because I've done
all sorts of equations which didn't really make dimensional sense.
What is x?
x is a length, right?
Right.
So it must have units of length.
What about a creation and annihilation operator?
Well, they have commutation relations.
a a dagger is equal to one.
So what's the dimension of a?
No units.
No units?
Hm?
No units.
So how can x be proportional to a?
There's some missing units in the story.
Frequencies.
How many units are frequencies?
Inverse time.
But my frequencies are integers.
Integers don't have any units.
There's some missing units that I haven't put in here.
And I think the first thing we
want to talk about next time is units.
What units?
Another way to ask the
question is, I tell you that
adding an excitation of energy increases the mass
or the mass squared by a certain amount.
In what units?
Mass, that's what we were saying before.
In kilograms, in giga electron volts, in slugs.
What unit does one unit of excitation,
how much does it increase the mass by?
What answer would you guess?
Planck's mass?
No, that's too big.
In a fundamental theory of gravity,
you might think it's the Planck mass.
You might.
It's too big.
That's too big, though.
It is too big.
Yeah.
So we're going to find it's a little
smaller than the Planck mass, but that's something.
Next time we will take up explicitly
the issue of units, which is clearly important.
It's impor- yeah.
Within one theory, is coupling constant the same, or
can strings have different ends and different probability of joining?
In the simplest string theory, it's just a single constant.
And generally, it's a single constant.
Yeah.
In fact, really strictly speaking, there are no
constants in string theory, but we'll get to that.
Before we beat this sex of strings to
death, there's the open and there's the close.
Is the possibility of a string splitting on its own?
Splitting means breaking-
Lengthwise.
But not separating.
Oh, you mean-
Like a Y.
Hm?
Like a single splitting, but not-
Lengthwise.
I think I know what- lengthwise.
No.
Like splitting.
That is not-
You're not allowed to split hairs.
Right.
Going an edge to a midpoint?
I think you're asking whether you can
have a more complicated object like this.
Now, this doesn't correspond to a Feynman diagram.
It corresponds to three strings joined
at a vertex at the center.
Is that what you're asking?
Yeah.
That- they're all straight.
They're all straight.
Yeah.
So, there's a- there's a really açık range
of string theories that do have that possibility.
There's an enormous variety of different string theories.
The question is, what do they all have in common?
If you ask, what is the generic
prediction of string theory, then you're really asking
what do they all have in common, and the
only thing that I can really think of that they
all have in common, is they all
have closed strings, and they all have gravitons.
Some versions have open strings, other
versions have- I call this a BOLO.
uh... you know what a bolo is
Argentinian cowboy swings it around and entangles uh...
entangles his feet in it and falls
over and falls on his face and
uh... yeah
in fact in Hadron physics
remember Hadron physics is a version of string theory
when we talk about units next time
i will tell you the difference between
string theory
as a but
in the theory of Hadrons
do you know what this kind of thing would be?
versus this kind of thing
three quarks and a quartet
three quarks
a baryon
this would be a quark and an anti-quark
so yes string theories can have these kind
of things but the one thing they always
have is the closed strings
do the coupling constants change depending on the
dimension of interaction of the strings as well?
uh... i'm not sure what the question is
if the strings are colliding in one dimension
and then we have another dimension
the coupling constants will change as well?
yes
um...
there is a dimensional by dimensional i mean the
number of the strings that are in one dimension
there is a number of
dimensions of space there is a
story about the values of the coupling constants
as a function of dimensions yes there is
but uh...
we'll take that as we come to it
one more question i want
to go home but uh... yeah
i missed the first fifteen minutes so you may have
already answered but when they're moving and they combine and break
what is the... i mean is it
the gravity that is making the movement?
no
charge or...
no, um... think newton, think newton for a
minute is it gravity that makes things move?
no, it's inertia that makes
things move once they start moving
uh... it was it was aristotle who said
there has to be a cause for motion
it was newton who said nonsense things if
you set them in motion will keep moving
strings are the same
it's not gravity which makes things move
what does gravity do?
gravity causes things to accelerate
so we haven't gotten to gravity
yet and where gravity comes from
uh... so far this is a theory which we have no
particular reason up till now to have any gravity in it
what makes things move in general?
inertia
inertia keeps them moving
what starts them moving?
an exchange of momentum with another particle
possibly
something in the out of time
I think you have to think about that
supposing something weren't moving
now you look at it from
another frame of reference it is moving
so what made it move?
changing the point of reference
if you have a system you
have the energy of the whole system
the whole system which is divided among the particles
all I'm telling you is even if a
thing is not moving in one frame of reference
it is moving in another frame of reference
so even Galileo understood that
so Galileo knew enough not to
ask the question what causes motion
but to ask the question what causes changes of motion
and that's forces
forces cause changes of motion
so um
hm?
quite a fluctuation
well in classical mechanics forces cause change of motion
what causes the motion in the first place?
well
initial conditions
what caused the initial conditions?
Woody Allen
for more please visit us at stanford.edu