Stanford University
We haven't discussed units at all.
And let's discuss units a little bit.
In Hadron physics, we've discussed the idea that a
Hadron is a string, and that it can be excited.
That it can be excited by setting
it into rotation, or setting it into vibration,
by exciting the harmonic oscillators
that make up the string.
The stringy character of the proton,
or whatever it happens to be.
There's a certain energy scale, or a certain
amount of energy, that each excitation will give you.
In particular, the energy jump from the
ground state to the first excited state.
How much is it? What does it depend on?
Well, in a string theory, there's really only one thing.
There's only one parameter.
We talked about it a little bit.
We discussed the idea that if you stretch a string,
let me just go back a little ways.
If you stretch a string from one point to another,
then it behaves pretty much like a spring.
It does behave like a spring.
It has an energy, if this is a non-relativistic string,
just an ordinary non-relativistic string, a rubber band,
or an idealized rubber band,
its energy, its potential energy,
let's call it E,
what does Hooke's Law give for the energy?
Some k, which is some spring constant,
times the square of the distance between the two.
So it's the distance between the endpoints.
Missing something.
Factor of two.
Okay.
Yeah, that's the potential energy that's in a string.
And we've identified energy,
this non-relativistic energy,
we've identified it not with the mass of the string,
but with the square of the mass of the string.
Why? Because we're thinking about
this in a frame of reference
that the string is moving very, very fast,
and when non-relativistic physics actually works
for the motion of the string
perpendicular to the direction of motion.
So let's keep that in mind.
We're looking at a string that's
going down the z-axis like this.
It's been stretched to a distance x,
or let's call it l.
Let's call it a distance l.
This becomes l squared.
And we've identified the energy
with the square of the mass,
l squared.
There is some spring constant.
Okay.
That spring constant I'll just call k.
It says that the mass of the string,
which in the rest frame,
in the frame of rest at
which the string is at rest,
that mass is
the usual energy.
That's going to be the
square root of that spring constant
times l,
perhaps divided by the square root of 2.
I'm not interested in square roots of 2 now.
So the mass of a stretched string
is proportional to its length
times some parameter,
which I've called the square root of k.
The square root of k has another name.
It's called the tension.
It's the tension in the string,
the energy per unit length.
Take a mass,
now we have a string at rest.
We're not looking at it in
this frame in which it's moving fast.
Its energy is its mass.
We stretch it.
We stretch it out.
And the energy of it grows proportional to the length.
It's like surface tension,
except now it's linear tension instead of surface tension.
Energy proportional to length
is called the coefficient of the string.
The coefficient is called tension.
It's the tension in the string.
And so there's a tension,
which is just the square root of k.
We don't even need to
call it square root of k.
We can just call it tension.
Now, how much energy do we get
for each oscillation?
For each oscillation,
oh, yeah, what are the units
of the square root of k?
Let's work in our favorite units
in which the speed of light
and Planck's constant are equal to one.
In those units,
energy has units of one over length.
So if energy has units of one over length,
what's the units of k here,
the square root of k,
the string tension?
Yeah, it's energy squared,
or one over length squared.
Energy squared, if you like.
So this object over here,
let's call it t, t for tension.
That tension in the string
is the thing which sets the fundamental scale.
And it sets the scale for everything.
It sets the scale.
It has units of energy squared.
And I'll tell you what it does.
It tells you that each excited state,
each time you excite the string by one unit,
it adds to its mass squared
essentially that tension.
It adds to the...
So the thing which has units,
the thing which determines the units of the theory,
are this string tension.
The bigger the string tension,
the bigger the jump in mass
when you excite something.
The same thing,
the same thing is true of an ordinary spring, incidentally.
If you have an ordinary spring,
if you have an ordinary spring,
let's take the mass of the spring to be one.
The spring constant, call it k.
The frequency is just,
well, it's the square root of k,
k over m.
The frequency is proportional to this tension.
And of course the energy that
you bump up the string by,
every time you excite it,
is also proportional to omega.
So the energy jump,
the energy jump between the ground state,
the first excited state,
next excited state, and so forth,
is controlled,
the unit is controlled by this string tension.
Okay, you could ask,
what is the string...
And string tension is force per unit,
or sorry,
is energy per unit length.
You know another name for energy per unit length?
Energy per unit length.
Force.
Force times length is energy.
Force times work,
force times distance is work.
Right.
So all this tension is,
is if you pull this apart,
that's how much force is pulling you back.
That's how much force is pulling you back.
It's the force within the string.
Another way to say it is,
if you took one of these strings
at the surface of the earth,
and you anchored it at some place,
and suspended a weight from it,
it would be the weight that the string could support.
A heavier weight would just shrink,
or would fall down.
A smaller weight would be pulled up.
Okay.
That's the character of these strings.
If you had one in the laboratory,
the force,
the weight that it can support,
is independent of its length, incidentally.
You see that from this formula.
You see that from the formula that
mass or energy,
same thing,
energy is equal to
spring con...
or tension times length.
Force is energy per unit length.
Energy per unit length is force.
And so the force that this string can support
is independent of its length.
That's the character of these strings.
Okay, so then you could ask,
how much weight
at the surface of the earth,
how much weight could a
a hadron, a meson,
if you could somehow anchor
one of the quarks in a meson,
to some support over here,
the ceiling,
how much weight could a meson support?
And the answer is about a truck.
About a, I can't remember if it's an 18-wheel truck,
or a 16-wheel truck,
or maybe it's just a half-ton panel truck,
I don't remember,
but it's that order of magnitude.
That's what a meson could support.
So they're pretty strong.
They're microscopic little things,
but they're pretty darn strong.
And the stronger they are,
the higher the frequency of the oscillations,
and so the larger the gap between
the lowest energy state and the highest energy state,
how do I actually know this?
Did anybody ever support a truck with a hadron?
Of course not.
What we actually know is the amount of energy
that it takes to excite string.
And from that we deduce what the tension is,
and from the tension,
I can then tell you what you can support.
These are not the strings that string theorists imagine
are associated with really fundamental problems.
They're not the strings that string theorists imagine
They're just regular particles like gravitons,
photons and so forth.
Those strings are much, much stronger.
Very much stronger.
The tension in them is vastly larger.
If, again, you took the Earth,
and you supported a weight,
namely the weight of the whole galaxy,
galaxy
Now of course this is nonsense
It's not the galaxy that's going to
move. It's the earth that's going to move
but if you could concentrate if you could concentrate
a mass of the galaxy in some small volume and
Make the earth heavy enough now you say if
I make the earth heavier I increase its gravitational field
Well, not necessarily so we can make the earth
much bigger, but keep its gravitational field the same
If you could somehow keep the gravitational
Acceleration the acceleration due to gravity the same than the weight
that you could support would be about the weight of the galaxy
so the strings that we're talking about in
Fundamental string theory of vastly higher intention
much higher intention the meaning of that is
That the energy in an excitation to excite the
string is much much larger. These are much stiffer strings
They have much much larger spring constants
and therefore much larger frequencies of oscillation
if larger frequencies of oscillation
than larger energies in
Exciting them how much energy?
Well, the thinking goes that it's probably somewhere is
up near the Planck energy if we're talking about gravitons
It's the gravitational scale
Does everybody know what the Planck
energy is? I know I know
You've heard of it. Do you know actually what it
is first of all in number first of all in?
Numerically and second of all what it actually
Where it comes from?
Times C squared
Right that's a fairly big energy it's enough to
That's a car bomb
boom
How much we didn't hear it 10 to the minus 5 grams 10
to the minus 5 grams and then you take that in square and
Multiply it by the square of the speed of light
right
But when I asked you if you know what the Planck
energy is or the Planck length or the Planck whatever it is
I was asking a more theoretical question. I
Was asking do you know?
What it is in terms of the other constants of nature. Maybe
we should go through that. I mean this is this is worth doing
So how long are these strings?
Ah
Okay dot. That's the other question. That's the other
question the stiffer they are the smaller they are
now of course, you can
stretch them out to any length
There's no limit to what you can stretch them to but if you
ask how much in their ground-state and remember things in their ground state
oscillate
How much do they oscillate in the
ground-state then? What's the what's the mean?
fluctuation in the size of these strings
the vibrations of them, then the larger
the spring constant, the smaller they are.
They're much stiffer, much harder to pull
apart. Pulling this thing apart by one
centimeter may cause you, will cause a
lot of, the smaller the bigger the
spring constant is. Alright, so how big
do people think they are? Oh, somewhere's of
order the Planck length. The Planck mass,
the Planck length. How fast is one vibration?
The Planck time. Okay, so let's talk
about these Planck units. There's some reason
to believe it's a little bit smaller than
that. Maybe a factor of 10, maybe a
factor of 100 smaller, but that's
a fine point. So let's talk
about what the Planck length is. I didn't
prepare this, so we're gonna have to work
it out in real time.
What is the Planck, Planck length?
What are Planck units, first of all?
What are any units? In physics we need
to have three units, mass, length, and time.
And our usual choice of units is, the usual
units that we use in a laboratory, are not
determined by any fundamental physics. The meter
is a convenient unit for measuring rope.
Okay? That's where it came from, measuring
rope. You measure rope like that, or cloth,
or whatever it is. So no doubt it
originated from the length of a human arm, probably.
A foot, of course, is also a similar
kind of unit, and I assume came from somebody's
foot, the king's foot.
So what's the real physics, then? Or what's the
real science of what a meter is? The real
science is, how many atoms does it take to
make a length of an arm, or a useful arm?
Has nothing whatever to do with any fundamental
physics, has to do with biology, how long
it takes to make an arm. Not a very
deep unit. That's mass. Mass, same thing, a kilogram
is a kind of weight that
you can manipulate in the laboratory.
and a second is about the time
that you could measure with a pendulum
That's it, that's where they came from,
and they have no deeper meaning than that
We would like, for really fundamental reasons in physics,
to choose units which have some very fundamental meaning
Now, for example, and if we do, then
many of our equations will be much simpler
For example, if the size of a
proton comes into various equations in nuclear physics
and the size of the proton
is 10 to the minus 13 centimeters
If we work in centimeters, or 10 to the minus
15 meters, there's going to be 10 to the minus 15
It's not just 10 to the minus 15, there's
1.73498, and physics is going to be very messy
On the other hand, there's nothing to prevent us
from
saying, let's use the unit in which
the radius of the proton is exactly 1
Then nuclear physics will turn out to
look a little bit simpler, and it will
Nuclear physics will turn out to be a little bit simpler,
but atomic physics won't look a hell of a lot simpler
The physics of sub-nuclear particles, sub-hedronic
particles will not look a lot simpler
There's nothing universal about the proton
The proton is just some particle, that's all
Why use the proton instead of
some other particle? No good reason
So there's nothing really universal about the proton, and the rules of physics
will not in any way be especially simple if we use the proton
Time, same thing
So we would like three units
which have some deep fundamental significance
It's equivalent to saying, we would like to choose
three constants of nature and set them equal to one
It's completely equivalent to choosing three units to choose
Constants of nature now mean dimensional constants
All right
The size of the proton is
1, but that's not a good one
You want to use things which
are really, which really are very universal
Three constants
There are three constants which are universal, and
there are three constants which are not universal
There are three constants in nature which are
truly universal, and I'll tell you what they are
The first constant is the speed of light
Why do I say it's universal?
Because there's a rule, and the rule is
nothing can move faster than the speed of light
Nothing
Everything moves, every velocity of every material
object is bounded by the speed of light
The use of the word every there
tells you there's something fundamental about it
That there's something, whether it's protons
or electrons or photons, it's something fundamental
It's something fundamental
It's something that's the same in every reference
frame, and it's the same for all particles
Now, when I say it's the same for all
particles, you say, wait a minute, wait a minute
Protons don't move with the speed of light
The limiting velocity for a proton
is the same for all particles
So, I mean, I don't know
that it's the same for all particles
But it's the same for all particles
And I think that's the point
I think that's the point
That's the point
That the limiting velocity for a
proton is the speed of light
So in that sense, it's very universal
So that's the first thing
We want to set c equal to 1
Sounds like a good thing to do
And we do that all the time, of course
The next thing which is very universal is Planck's constant
Let me give you an example
Planck's constant is not just some any
old constant like the radius of a proton
But it's connected with the uncertainty principle
For every object in nature, the uncertainty
principle between the momentum and its position
Is greater than or equal to h bar
There's maybe some four or some
two in there, I don't remember
But it doesn't matter what object you're talking about
You could be talking about an electron
You could be talking about a proton
You could be talking about a bowling ball
They are all constrained by
the same uncertainty principle, right?
And so in that sense, h bar
And it doesn't much matter whether you use h bar
or h, the one without the 2 pi in it
That's not the point here
The point is that Planck's constant
applies to everything in the world
It's universal
So the next thing you might want to use
Not might, but we will
Is to set h bar equal to 1
So what's the last really universal?
Is there another?
Truly universal constant
The gravitational constant
Remember, according to Newton, every object in the universe
No matter what it's made out of
No matter what it is composed of
Every object in the universe has a gravitational force
Which is the product of the
masses divided by the distance squared
Times the universal constant g
So again
Something which applies to everything
Are there units in which c, h
bar, and g are equal to 1?
Now that's the same as asking the question
Can you combine c, h bar, and g
into a combination that has units of mass?
Can you combine them into a
combination that has units of mass?
combination that has units of length?
And can you combine them into
a combination that has units of time?
And the answer is yes
Let's see
Let's do length
We want to do length
Tell you what, even better
Let's do length squared
Let's see if we can find a
combination of g, h bar, and c
units of length squared
Okay, so here's what we do
Just some simple dimensional analysis
Everybody here knows how to do dimensional analysis?
Okay, we'll do some simple dimensional analysis
We want to find a combination
g to some power, let's call it p
h bar to some other power, q
And c to some other power, pqr
Which has units
of length
I'm going to choose length squared
Let's say it has units of length squared
Now this doesn't mean it's equal to length squared
It means it has the same units
Sometimes people put a bracket around a thing like that
to indicate its units
The units of g to the p,
h to the q, c to the r
should be length squared
I'm choosing length squared to avoid a square root
in the final formula, that's all
There is another reason
It is widely believed that the fundamental unit
is a unit of area, not a unit of length
But we'll come to that some other time
Let's see if we can find p, q, and r
Okay, first question is what
Now we have to figure out what the units
the conventional units of g, h bar, and c are
The units of c, that's easy
What's the units of c?
That's length over time, right?
What about the units of Planck's constant?
Momentum distance
Mass velocity
L squared m over t
Again?
L squared mass
Momentum times
Momentum times distance, right?
Delta x, delta p
Delta x, delta p, so that's a length
And then a momentum is a mass
times a velocity
And a velocity is a length over time
So that's length squared over time
L squared mass over time
That's Planck's constant
And the last one, the one
that I can never really remember
These two I remember
The one I can never remember is g
But how do we figure out
what the units of g are?
Acceleration equals mass times g times
Yeah, we use one of
the equations that g appears in
Alright, so here's an equation that, let's see
Which was your equation?
Acceleration, distance
Alright, acceleration equals
L squared over time
Yeah, we'll get that in a minute
But that's equal to
Mass g over r squared
So that's length squared
Acceleration is what?
L over length
L length per time squared
And again, equal means, doesn't mean equal
So it's L cubed over t squared
Divided by m it looks like, huh?
Right?
Okay, let's now go through the exercise
Can I say something?
By the way, that's like
Kepler's law where the amount of
You're right
You're right, you're right, it is like Kepler's law
Okay
So now, we have on the left side
Length squared
Now let's go g to the power of p
What's g again?
L cubed over t squared
Alright, so that's L cubed over t squared
Times m in the denominator
Alright, so that's L to the 3p
T to the 2p
m to the p, right?
Did I get that right?
That's g to the p
Now what about h bar to the q?
h bar to the q is
Length squared
Length to the 2q
m to the 2q
No, m to the q
And then t to the q
Did I get that right?
Okay
And then the last one is
Speed of light to the rth power
Which is length to the r
Over time to the r
Now all we have to do is
Find three constants
So that everything on the right hand side
Cancels out except two powers of length
Okay, so the first thing you can see is
Mass only appears in two places
Mass to the q and mass to
the p, so what does that mean?
So what does that say?
It says p better be equal to q
So let's just set p equal to q
We now know that
And we can cancel out the masses
That's done
Now, what else do we have?
We have to get rid of
all the times it looks like, hein?
Alright, so how many times do we have?
times do we have? We have 2p, 2p plus, q
is the same as p, so that's 3p plus r
equals 0. 3p plus r is equal to 0,
so that tells us that r is equal to minus
3p. Did I do that right? Let's just check.
We have 2p, 3p plus r equals 0, r equals
minus 3p. Okay I hope
I'm doing this right. Minus 3p.
Did I make a mistake?
Yeah yeah but q is p.
We've already figured out that q is p. So
if I'm not mistaken, I think we can get rid
of all the t's. p is equal to q, so let's
see what we have. We have p is equal to q,
that looks like 5p. Boy do I not recognize
that. 5p. L to the 2q, that's not going to
be a p.
Okay.
So we've got all the t's taken care of and
now r is what? r is equal to minus 3p.
Yeah and you're done.
Oh.
Yeah 3p minus 2, 5p?
Yeah you guys, yeah. 5p minus 3p and you're done.
2p.
So we get 2p right? We get 2p. Altogether 2p.
2p. And that now tells us what p is. p
is equal to 1. Okay? So let's see what we
have now. p is equal to 1. It tells us that
we have 2p.
It tells us that the Planck area, this
is the Planck area, the Planck area L squared
is g h bar, looks like over c cubed
right? C cubed. C cubed. This is usually expressed
by saying the Planck length is the square of this.
Okay.
The root of it.
The square root of it, thank you.
Okay.
So let's see. Let's see. Should we put in
some numbers? My problem is I can never remember
what Planck's constant is. Anybody
know Planck's constant? 10 to the?
1 times 10 minus 34.
10 minus 34?
Yeah.
Okay.
Yeah g is 6 times 10 to the minus 11
which is about 10 to the minus 10. Order of magnitude
10 to the minus 10. What is
h bar? 10 to the minus 34?
Yeah.
10 to the minus 34.
In usual MKS units. 10 to the minus 34. And what
is c cubed? C is 3 times 10 to the 8th,
3 times 3, 10 to the 17th, oh my god
how many? Times 10 to the minus, how big is?
10 to the minus 24?
I think it's more like
10 to the minus 25. Huh?
Yeah, or 10 to the minus 25. So
how many square meters is this? Pretty small. Pretty
small. Yeah. Some tiny, tiny number. Okay? The
Planck length is very small. If we had
done it right, we would have gotten 10 to
the minus 35 meters. So 10 to the minus, should
be 10 to the minus 70th square centimeters.
I'm not sure I got everything right. Hmm?
Yes, about 70.
About 70. All right. So that's
small. That's smaller than anything. What's that?
It looks like a symbol.
Good. Okay, now the Planck time. That's the,
the Planck length is the square root of this.
What about the Planck time? Think of the
Planck length as being the size of a little
thingy.
Yeah.
It's the size of a little thingy. All right?
There's a thing the size of the Planck length.
What do you think the Planck time is?
It's the time for a light ray to cross
that thing. All right? What else could it be?
Right. So it's the time for a light ray
to cross that little distance. So does that mean,
that means we have to divide
it by the speed of light?
Yeah. We have to divide it by the speed
of light. So the Planck length, L Planck length,
The Planck is 10 to the minus 35 meters.
The Planck time is 10 to the
minus 43 or 42, something like that.
42 seconds?
10 to the minus 44, 43 seconds, something like that.
Now what about the Planck mass?
We haven't figured out what the Planck mass is,
but we could do exactly the same calculation,
work out what the Planck mass is from H bar,
and the Planck mass would be
about 10 to the minus eighth kilograms.
So this one's big. That's a big mass.
10 to the minus eighth kilograms is an observable thing,
it's a little dust grain.
It's a little dust grain.
These are impossibly small, small times and small distances.
Okay, this is a Planck unit.
Things measured in these Planck units are
measured in some very, very fundamental units.
Okay, I'll tell you some things.
The universe has a radius, the known.
Observable universe, the horizon size is
about 10 to the 60th Planck lengths.
10 to the 60th Planck lengths.
The age of the universe is also
about 10 to the 60th Planck times.
And, good, that's a gallon of, sorry,
a tank of gasoline is about the,
an energy content, a tank of
gasoline is about the Planck mass.
Okay.
So that means you could drive across
the country with 10 Planck masses of energy.
Okay, right, that's what it means.
These are the units that string theory is in.
In other words, the size of a vibrating,
vibrating string, the fluctuations in
it due to quantum uncertainty,
order of magnitude, the Planck length.
The frequencies of oscillation or
the time, not the frequency,
but the period of oscillation of
order 10 to the minus 43 centimeters.
Sorry?
Sorry, 10 to the minus 43 seconds.
Right.
And the amount of mass that would be involved
in exciting a fundamental particle such
as a graviton or an electron.
Let's take the electron.
If the electron is a string, you could ask,
how much energy does it take to excite it?
The units are expected to be somewheres in
this range, 10 to the minus eighth kilograms.
Now, that's a huge number.
How many, how many GEVs, giga-electron volts is that?
Five.
One other useful number.
The one useful number to remember is that one
Planck mass is about 10 to the 19th GEVs,
which means 10 to the 19th proton masses.
One Planck mass is about
10 to the 19th proton masses.
10 to the 23rd proton masses is, you
know, a little gram of water or something.
10 to the 19th, which
is four orders of magnitude smaller,
is a tiny tiny little droplet, but visible,
quite visible, well if you have good eyes
so exciting an electron by a particle physics collision
you say well we don't need to do a particle physics collision,
we'll just explode a tank of gasoline in the vicinity of an electron
and it will start the electron vibrating
yeah, it's just rather hard to get the
energy to be concentrated in such a small distance
so these are the reasons that
Is the mass of the
site above its natural ground state?
Yeah, above its ground state
At its ground state?
Well, remember it's mass squares
which come in integer multiples
Alright, so it's mass squares
so if you want to know what the unit is, square the
Planck mass and that's the amount that it takes to bump you up
but to go from the ground state, if the ground state
is almost massless, then it's about one Planck unit of energy
That's why you can't excite an electron
Right, right, right, it's just much too much
energy to pump into such a small volume
and so you can't excite an electron
Right, right, right, it's just much too much
energy to pump into such a small volume
and so you can't excite an electron
and you know, it's for this reason
that string theory is way, way, direct detection
How would you detect that a thing is a string?
The same way you detect that a proton is
a string, you hit it, you set it into vibration
and you discover that there's a bunch of excited states
where the mass squared is proportionate to the mass squared
That's the kind of thing you'd like to do with an electron,
that's the kind of thing that you'd like to do with a photon
But the increase in mass here is
just way beyond what can be done
Yeah
In order to have the structure of the string that we've been describing,
wouldn't the string as a whole have to be somewhat bigger than this?
Yeah
Mhm, yeah
Question?
Question? This is just a bunch of arithmetic over here. What makes us think that when we get a
number out, 10 to the minus 35th, that it has anything to do with the length of a string?
It's a guess. It's a guess. It's
a guess based on a number of things.
No, no, it's not just numerology. It could
be wrong. It could be a thousand times less.
Nobody thinks that the string length scale could be
smaller than the Planck length. That looks quite impossible.
But that the string length scale
could be larger than the Planck length.
If the string length scale is larger
and the energy scale lower, that is possible.
How much lower? Well, I think from
the things that we know about particle physics,
we can't say with any precision
at the current time really at all.
But from the precision with which particle physics
standard model and so forth seem to work,
I think there's plenty of evidence that the string
length scale is lower than the Planck length scale.
The energy scale is very, very high.
Whether it's Planck scale or a hundredth of the Planck
scale or a thousandth of the Planck scale, we don't know.
There is another scale in physics. There is another scale
in physics which keeps coming up over and over again.
We've talked about it. It's the unification scale.
If you remember at all from last quarter, we talked about
the scale at which the various coupling constants seem to come together.
The scale at which the electroweak forces and the
QCD forces seem to merge into a common structure experimentally.
And there there are experiments. They're not experiments
to get to that energy, but experiments to extrapolate.
The extrapolation of what we know about physics seems to say that
ordinary quantum field theory probably holds to something like a distance scale
of roughly a thousand times larger than the Planck scale.
So we do have evidence that ordinary quantum
field theory without any stringy structures and so forth
or equivalently that the electron is fundamental to scales perhaps a
thousand times smaller, sorry, a thousand times larger than the Planck scale.
But that's not the case.
That's not the case.
That's still pretty small.
Then you wouldn't be able to suspend the galaxy.
Maybe you could only suspend, I
don't know, some globular cluster somewhere.
It seems that a Planck length can be thought of as the fundamental
unit of, smallest unit of length in the Planck time, smallest unit of time.
Clearly a Planck mass is
not a fundamental unit of mass.
No.
Just to clarify.
The Planck mass is believed to be
the mass of the lightest possible black hole.
One Planck area, one unit of entropy.
And how long would it take to evaporate?
Very fast.
One Planck time.
Here today, gone?
Today.
When you showed the coupling coefficients unifying, I believe one time you
put down a fourth one for gravity and so that comes down.
That's a connection.
What's the coupling unit of gravity?
That's okay.
I'll tell you what the various pieces of evidence are.
I'm not going to explain what the various
pieces of evidence are, but I'm going to explain
what the various pieces of evidence are.
I'm not going to explain them in detail.
This is just to remind you.
If you plot the coupling
constants of which coupling constants?
The ones that we measure in the laboratory.
The electric, let's just call it the
electric coupling constant, E, E squared really.
The weak interaction, sorry, the electroweak.
I'm getting a little confused.
There are three of them.
There's U1, SU2, and SU3.
This is energy this way.
And energy is the same as inverse length.
Inverse length.
So as energy gets large, wavelengths get short.
Energy, high energy means small distance.
Okay.
We measure these coupling constants at some energy scales.
Remember, coupling constants are
things which change with time.
They change with energy or change with distance scale.
We measure them somewheres.
Where in laboratories, which means 50 GeV,
100 GeV at most, we measure them here.
We get three numbers.
We also measure slightly indirectly
the derivatives of these things.
In fact, we can compute the derivatives of them.
We can compute the derivatives of them purely theoretically, but
with good confidence because we know the theory here very well.
What we find is that if you extrapolated these,
they would all cross at about a common point.
That point is way, way out here at
an energy which is not the Planck scale,
but it's about 100 or maybe 1,000 times,
somewheres between 100 and 1,000
times smaller than the Planck scale.
I think maybe more like 100.
So this could be m Planck
roughly divided by 100, somewheres in between.
And the Planck scale would be over here.
Or this is a logarithmic scale.
On a logarithmic scale, it looks like this.
So on a logarithmic scale, a given gap
can mean a very, very big change in energy.
And it looks like this.
Now, of course, we don't know with certainty that there's not all kinds
of things going on at higher energy here which would muck this up badly.
We don't.
But what we do know is that if there
is nothing in here to muck things up badly,
and there's some reason to believe that,
that these coupling constants would
just come together at this scale.
The meaning of that is that
quantum field theory, conventional quantum field theory,
seems to be working to about here.
There's other evidence for this scale coming
from neutrino masses and a few other places,
but it's far from tight.
It will become much tighter if LHC
is lucky and makes the right discoveries.
It will become much tighter and we'll
have a much better knowledge about this extrapolation.
So this is one of the
things we're going to learn from LHC,
is how reliable this extrapolation is.
So, we're going to look
at the mass of the particle.
The Planck mass being out here.
And this in itself doesn't tell
us where the string length scale is.
What it tells us is that the stringy character of
particles does not become important until energy is above this.
So somewhere between here and here,
F string theory is all right,
somewhere in here is the scale of strings.
Remind me again what the three coupling constants are.
There's, what is it, QEDQEQC?
No, QED, QCD, and the weak interactions.
Oh, weak, right.
Yeah.
At one point you did put down,
I think you put down something for gravity.
Yeah.
Yeah, if you were to plot
the gravitational coupling constant behaves differently,
has a different character.
But, let's see, it starts very, very small,
and it goes up something like this.
So it would cross,
it doesn't cross at the same point.
It crosses somewhere nearby.
But basically the place where this
one gets to be about order one,
that's the Planck scale.
So it really, it's really exactly the same statement
to say that the gravitational
constant, the running coupling constant,
crosses at roughly the same place as to say this
unification scale is not too far from the Planck scale.
So does the gravitational constant depend upon capital G?
Yes.
So does capital G change as you
start to measure the higher and higher energy?
Okay, I'll, no, capital G does not change,
but capital G is not
exactly the right measure of things.
It's capital G, alright, let's
do, I'll answer your question.
Let's look at the force law between two objects.
In electromagnetism, it's E squared,
divided by R squared.
And that's the force.
And that's the electromagnetic coupling constant here.
In gravitation, it's G M squared over R squared.
So the thing which is analogous to
E squared is G times M squared.
But what M should you use there?
Well, the M that you use there
is associated with the particular
scale of physics that you're studying.
Alright?
So you can see then in that sense,
this quantity here increases like M squared.
Yeah, so this is the relevant thing here.
It's the dimensionless thing.
Okay.
Let's do units.
Where on that scale, if
you can build accelerators big enough,
is it that you start
producing nothing but little black holes?
Real black holes?
Yeah, the small ones, you know, if you build galaxies.
Oh, it's all the way up there.
In quark mass, yeah.
There's two ways to produce black holes.
One way or another, you've got
to have a lot of pressure
to squeeze things into a small volume.
One way is kinetic energy.
Small objects with lots of
kinetic energy blast them together,
and you have a chance of making a black hole.
The other way is not kinetic energy but gravitation,
gravitational potential energy pulling things together.
That takes a star.
So to make a black hole using gravity,
you need something as heavy as a star.
To make a black hole by the collision of particles,
you need energies of order of the Planck energy.
Now, if you think about that for a minute,
imagine an accelerator.
I don't know, is it fun to...
Let's explore the following question.
How big, what kind of accelerator would it take
to do experiments of the Planck energy,
to do interesting experiments of the Planck energy?
Well, basically, the energy of an accelerator,
of a linear accelerator, scales linearly
with the size of the accelerator.
In other words, you get a
certain number of GeV per unit length.
Slack is a good example.
It takes approximately two miles to accelerate a thing
to 100 GeV.
So two miles for 100 GeV.
Two miles, 100 GeV.
All right, the Planck energy
is about 10 to the 17th times bigger than this.
It's 10 to the 19th GeV,
so it's 10 to the 17th times larger.
So with just the parameters of the slack accelerator,
you can multiply this by roughly 10 to the 17th.
So it would take 10 to the 17th miles.
How big is 10 to the 17th miles?
Oh, man.
10 to the 17th.
I think 10 to the 13th
miles is about a light year.
10 to the 13th kilometers or something like that,
if I remember.
10 to the 13th kilometers, 10 to the 17th,
10 to the 4th light years.
Galaxy size.
Galaxy size to accelerate something up the Planck mass.
We're not going to do it.
At least not tomorrow.
But suppose you could build such an accelerator.
Next question.
What kind of luminosity do you have to have?
An accelerator has to have a luminosity.
The chances of...
What we want to do now is
we want to collide particles head on
to make a black hole.
But remember, the radius of that
black hole that we want to make
is itself the Planck mass, the Planck radius.
So that means we've got to aim these particles
to collide within a Planck distance.
Well, no.
Accelerators don't do that.
That's not the way accelerators work.
The way accelerators work is you just get
a lot of particles going to the left,
a lot of particles going to the right,
and you get enough of
them so that some will collide
at the distance scales that you're interested in.
In other words, you need big luminosity.
What kind of luminosity would you need?
Oh, I don't know.
Let's say...
What's a slack luminosity?
10 to the 13th particles per second or something.
Anybody know?
I don't know.
Well, 10 to the 13th particles, but that's just...
But, you know, the distance scales there are pretty big.
How much better are you going to have to do?
I don't know.
Let's say 10 to the 20th particles.
10 to the 20th particles
colliding, each with the Planck energy.
That's 10 to the 20th tanks of gasoline per second.
Yeah, 10 to the 17th barrels
of gas per second to fuel it,
as big as the galaxy,
we ain't going to do it.
That's what we would need to explore small black holes
and something pretty close to
it to explore string theory directly,
a really direct test.
The question is, are there indirect tests?
All right.
I think the indirect tests
will pretty much be very theoretical,
and unless somebody constructs a
very, very convincing string theory,
that gives rise to the standard
model exactly in some very computable way,
the hope of direct tests, I think, is very remote.
So that's what we're facing.
That's what we're up against.
Okay.
We didn't get where I really had intended to go.
In fact, we didn't even touch
on what I intended to do.
I just wanted to touch on.
Professor, these extra dimensions that you had talked about,
are they in the range of
the Planck's in this third minus 35?
Oh, which dimensions?
The extra dimensions of the Planck.
Yes.
Yes, it is believed,
again, without really terrific evidence,
but again, it's the same kind of evidence.
It's the same, where is it,
where is our plot of coupling constants?
If there were extra dimensions,
and the extra dimensions had any sizable distance,
if they were at all sizable,
then ordinary quantum field theory would break down
when particles begin exploring the extra dimensions.
The conventional use of quantum
field theory, as we use it,
would break down at points
where the energy became large enough
to explore these extra tiny dimensions.
If it's true, and if we continue to get evidence
that quantum field theory makes sense as it is,
out to these distances here,
then we'll know that the extra dimensions must lie
somewhere between the Planck length and maybe
a thousand times bigger than the Planck length.
So, exploring extra dimensions will also be
something that is extremely indirect and extremely hard.
Why couldn't it be significantly,
orders of magnitude less than the Planck length?
What's the argument?
Orders of magnitude, that's another question.
That's another question.
The theory really doesn't work
at all under those circumstances.
Let's put it this way.
If you tried to make
them smaller than the Planck length,
you would wind up making their
mass larger than the Planck mass.
Making a small thing with big
mass means you make a black hole.
So if you're trying to think of strings
which were much smaller than the Planck distance
and their mass would accordingly
be larger than the Planck mass,
you would be talking about black holes.
You wouldn't be talking about strings.
That's the problem.
They would collapse.
Their mass and their small distance would cause
gravitation basically to turn them into black holes.
So that's the reason that string
theorists do not ever consider the possibility
that the string scale is smaller than the Planck mass.
And I think it's a very good reason.
Did you say that the mass here is
derived from the choice for L and T?
From the what?
Well, you gave us why we have
an L and why we have a T.
Yeah, yeah.
You do exactly the same thing.
You say, let's make a mass
squared out of these parameters here.
And I forget exactly what it is.
We could figure it out.
But the others were a physical choice.
Sorry?
The other, L and T
and time were a physical choice.
What do you mean they're physical?
They're all physical.
Well, yeah, but I mean, the time, for
example, is the time to cross L and A.
Yeah.
And what is, that's a physical quantity.
Well, each one is a physical quantity too.
And what do you say about mass?
You just put it down.
Well, you can.
Does it follow from our choice from L and T?
Yes, it does.
Well, no, it doesn't follow
by itself from L and T.
But if you asked, ah, good.
Let's see.
Once you have L and T, you can
get mass from either H bar or G.
You could ask, here's the way to think about it.
Take two particles.
Take two particles whose distance
apart is the Planck length.
Now, because their distance is so small, the uncertainty
principle says that they have a lot of energy.
Right?
The uncertainty principle says if things are very
well localized, then they have very large momentum.
The fluctuations in the momentum are very large.
So take two particles whose distance is
known to be within the Planck distance.
And that says something about their momentum.
Their average momentum is extremely large.
And from that, you can compute what their
average kinetic energy of these two particles are.
That kinetic energy will be the Planck mass.
So two particles.
If you try to take two particles and localize
them to a distance comparable to the Planck distance,
the answer will be that the energy that you have
to put in to do that will be the Planck mass.
So it's just uncertainty principle.
We can work it out, but, you know.
All right.
Okay.
Let's take a rest.
We'll be right back.
All right.
Let's take a rest.
I'm going to tell you next about some mathematics.
I'm going to tell you
about the mathematics of conformal transformations.
Why?
Because that's the basic mathematical tool of string theory.
Well, we have our choice.
I can either tell you why there
are 24 or 26 dimensions in string theory,
or I can start to tell you about conformal transformations.
We'll get to both of them at some point.
Are we having a class on Thanksgiving?
Yeah.
As long as it's not on Thanksgiving.
Thanksgiving is always Thursday, so
I think the answer is yes.
Okay.
We have 45 minutes, and I will try in 45
minutes to give you the easy version of why there
have to be 26 dimensions in bosonic string theory.
The easy version is not easy, and it
doesn't really get to the root of it.
The hard version is very hard.
But that doesn't mean that we can't talk
about it qualitatively, but I thought I would
do what I call the
easy version, which is not easy.
And not satisfying, but nevertheless is correct.
Let's, you know, when people see this, they
walk away and say, gee, that's sort of magic,
but in the bad sense.
But it is correct, and it is sort
of the way that we're going to do it.
And I think that's the
way we're going to do it.
I think that's the way we're going to do it.
And to the other side of the canal, that's
sort of the way that the need for extra dimensions
was discovered.
It has to do, if you remember, in order to
get the photon to come out right, we had to
do something odd.
We had to take the mass squared
of the ground state of the oscillating string.
You remember...
Let's take the open string, in the case of the
open string, the mass squared had to be minus one unit.
That was so that when we applied a creation
operator to create the photon polarization, it came out massless.
Minus one, one unit on top
of that gives us something massless.
We haven't talked yet about how we get
rid of this particle of negative mass squared.
I assure you that can be gotten rid of.
But let's not worry about it. Let's agree.
The mass squared of the ground state is minus one.
Why is it minus one?
How do we get minus one?
Well, harmonic oscillators have zero point energy.
So the ground state energy of this vibrating string should be
nothing but the sum total of all of the zero point energies.
Zero point energies are all positive.
And in fact they depend on the frequency.
Anybody remember what the zero point
energy of a harmonic oscillator is?
A half h-bar omega. Let's forget
h-bar. Set it equal to one.
One half omega, and do you remember
the frequency of the nth harmonic oscillator?
It was just n.
n. Each one of the oscillating modes of the string,
there's the string, each one of the oscillating
modes, the nth oscillating mode has frequency n.
So the ground state energy of the nth oscillator is
just n over two, in some units, is n over two.
Now this doesn't sound good.
We have a lot of oscillators, one for each integer.
We have to add up all that energy.
It's not quite easy to imagine how we
can add all this up and get minus one.
Right. So there's something strange going on.
And there it is.
But actually we don't have to get minus one.
We have to get to something a little bit different.
Let's go back to the energy
of a very, very fast moving system.
The energy of a very, very fast moving system
has, first of all, it has the overall momentum.
Moving down the z-axis, it has the overall momentum.
And then on top of the
overall, and that's a conserved quantity.
And we really don't care about it very much since it
never changes during the processes that take place in particle physics.
And then for a particle which is not moving,
whose center of mass is not moving in the plane,
what's the rest of it, do you remember?
Mass squared.
Divided, I think, by twice the momentum.
And that's why we began to identify the energy,
the non-relativistic energy, with m squared rather than m.
This was the energy.
And to make precise this idea
of very rapid systems which become non-relativistic,
you have to let p become extremely precise.
And you have to let p become infinitely large.
Basically, you have to take the
limit of an infinitely large momentum.
In the limit of infinitely large momentum,
this is the form that the energy takes.
You say, well, I'm going to
take the form of infinitely large energy.
This thing just goes to zero.
But what you really do is you take e
minus p, you subtract the momentum from the energy.
That's all right.
This is a perfectly conserved quantity.
If it never changes, you
don't care very much about it.
And then multiply the whole thing by, let's say, 2p.
And that gives you m squared.
This 2p here, the reason you multiply by
2p is that's got to do with time dilation.
The faster a thing moves down the
z-axis, the slower its internal motions go.
The slower the internal motions, that
means the smaller the internal energies.
For example, if you have an atom,
what's the ionization energy of a hydrogen atom?
13.5 electron volts or something.
Okay.
Now you take that atom and you
speed it up and you send it down.
In other words, the energy difference between the ground
state of the atom, let's not take the ionization energy.
The energy difference between the ground state of a
hydrogen atom and the first excited state is what?
3 volts.
Oh, 3, 4 volts, something like that.
3 or 4 electron volts.
Now what happens as you boost the atom?
What happens to the overall energy of it?
It increases, of course.
Right?
That's this.
But what happens to the energy difference between the first
excited state, between the ground state and the first excited state?
Does it get bigger or smaller?
Smaller.
And it gets smaller with this 1 over p here.
And in fact, the energy of that atom or the differences of energy between the
atoms are proportional to the square of the mass of the atom divided by 2p.
So that's what this formula is.
Well, we don't want to,
we don't care about this piece.
That just has to do with
its overall motion down the z-axis.
Just subtract it off.
It doesn't have to do with the internal motions.
And then the p in the denominator here.
That's just associated with the
slowing down of the internal motions.
So let's just multiply through by it.
And this is the way we really think of energy.
This quantity is the energy and
it's proportional to the mass squared.
Okay.
The point is now that the actual energy of the ground state
has an infinite piece, a piece with, or let's put this piece back.
Let's put this piece back.
Let's put, let's not subtract this.
Let's add this back on this side.
Plus, what is it?
Plus p squared plus 2p squared.
Let me just get this right.
p times e.
Let's take p times e
is m squared plus 2p squared.
Okay.
Notice that first of all is the interesting thing
which is the mass squared, which we're interested in.
But there's also this infinite piece here.
This infinite piece.
So it's not really quite true that the
energy has to add up to minus 1.
It would be okay if it added up to something like
minus 1 plus an infinite constant that was similar to p squared.
So I'm going to show you how that works.
I'm going to show you how that works.
How you can add up.
1 plus 2 plus 3 plus 4 plus 5.
This is all the internal energy.
And get something which looks like a constant, namely minus 1, which is what we
want to get, plus an infinite piece that can be absorbed into something that's already there.
This is a trick of physics
that takes place all the time.
It happens all the time.
All kinds of content.
I mean all kinds of context
where you get some infinite answer.
And you don't know what
to do with the infinite answer.
But you realize that the thing which is becoming infinite already has a constant
piece in it that you just add the extra infinity to the constant piece.
An example is the energy of vacuum, the energy of
just the mass of a particle or a self energy.
All sorts of things like that.
Where you can hide infinite constants
into things which are already there.
I'm not saying this is a satisfactory state of affairs.
It's just something that we do all the time.
The energy in this room, it has zero point
oscillations from all of the photons and everything else.
Not from the photons that are here,
but from the oscillations of the electromagnetic field.
How big are those oscillations?
The energy? Infinite.
What do we do with it?
We just subtract it off by saying we could add a constant
to the energy of the room and it wouldn't make any difference.
So just get rid of it.
It's the same thing here.
We're going to get a constant
piece which is just infinite but constant.
As long as it's constant, it never affects anything.
Plus a term which looks like
this with an additional mass squared.
Let me show you the mathematics.
And we can then discuss another topic.
Another time, the physics.
The mathematics is tricky but easy.
The mathematics is just a question of adding
up 1 plus 2 plus 3 plus 4.
It's just a sum here.
1 plus 2 plus 3 plus 4.
There's an overall factor of a half outside.
That comes from the half h bar omega.
But the basic calculation is to
add up all of the integers.
Obviously infinite.
But let's see if we can extract out
of that infinite piece an infinity plus something finite.
This is always the way quantum
field theory and relativistic quantum mechanics works.
So 1 plus 2 plus 3 plus 4.
This is not something we're going
to easily add up, is it?
So let's do something to
it and then take a limit.
Let's multiply each one of these.
Let's introduce a small constant, epsilon.
e to the minus epsilon
is a number less than 1.
But when epsilon is very, very small,
this number is close to 1, right?
Okay.
Let's add to it plus 2
e to the minus 2 epsilon.
And then we get a constant.
Let's do something to it.
e to the minus 2 epsilon.
This is just a trick for making the sum converge.
Each term in it, we're going to
put in something which gets smaller and smaller.
But when epsilon goes to 0, it'll
just give us back the original sum.
So epsilon is going to go to 0.
In fact, you know what?
Yeah, all right, let's leave it this way.
1 plus 2 epsilon, what's the next one?
3 e to the minus 3 epsilon.
Plus 4 e to the minus 4 epsilon.
But now, if epsilon is not 0, then
the sequence of terms e to the minus epsilon,
e to the minus 2 epsilon, e to
the minus 3 epsilon do get smaller and smaller.
Now, if epsilon is small, it takes
a long, long time for them to shrink.
So if we were just to plot,
the e to the minus...
epsilon e to the minus
2 epsilon would be a very...
as a function of the integers,
it would fall very slowly
if epsilon is a small number.
All right?
But eventually, the e to
the minus n epsilon will win,
and it will be...
make each term successively smaller and smaller,
and you'll be able to add them up.
All right?
So what you do is you add these up,
and then after adding them up,
you let epsilon go to 0.
All right?
It's a mathematical trick.
So let's see what we get.
It takes a bunch of steps,
and I'll show you that the steps are elementary.
Okay.
This can be written as the sum
from n equals 1 to infinity
of n e to the minus 1.
So what we get is n
e to the minus n epsilon.
e to the minus 1 epsilon times 1,
e to the minus 2 epsilon times 2,
and so forth and so on.
All right?
That's the sum.
Now, the trick is to get rid of this n.
First trick is to get rid of this n,
and the way to get rid of this n
is just to take the
sum without the n in it
and differentiate with respect to epsilon.
So what happens if we differentiate
with respect to epsilon?
What does the derivative with respect to epsilon give?
It brings down minus n.
All right?
So this is equal to minus.
So in other words,
we really want to put minus here.
This is equal to the
original sum we were interested in,
n e to the minus n epsilon.
Okay.
That's the first step.
The second step is to observe
that we can add the series up.
This whole series is a geometric series.
It starts out, let's just see what it is.
It has an e to the minus epsilon
plus an e to the minus 2 epsilon
plus an e to the minus 3 epsilon,
which also can be written in another form.
It's e to the minus epsilon.
Times 1 plus e to the minus epsilon
plus e to the minus 2 epsilon and so forth.
I pulled out a factor
of e to the minus epsilon.
Do you know what this is?
Exactly.
This is a geometric series,
1 plus a number plus the square of the number
plus the cube of the number.
And so we can add all of this up.
And what do we get?
We get e to the minus epsilon
divided by 1 minus e to the minus epsilon.
Okay.
That's the thing that we want to differentiate
with respect to epsilon.
That's this.
I put a minus sign in front of it.
Okay.
This is something you can do for homework,
but I'm going to show you roughly what happens.
Oh, but in the end,
we're interested in small epsilon.
We're interested in small epsilon.
So let's see.
What do we want to do with that?
Yeah.
Let's expand it for small epsilon.
Let's first expand it for small epsilon
and then do the operation and
then the epsilon go to zero.
We're interested in small epsilon.
So what is e to the minus epsilon
when expanded in terms of epsilon?
1 minus epsilon plus epsilon
squared over 2, dot, dot, dot.
We're only going to need things to power epsilon squared.
We won't need things beyond that.
And of course, there are
more, but we won't need them.
Now what about the denominator?
What's in the denominator?
We have 1 minus.
Okay.
So let's write out e
to the minus epsilon minus 1.
I think it's plus epsilon minus epsilon squared.
Let's go to the next one.
I think we're going to need
the next one, as you'll see.
Epsilon squared over 2, right?
What's the next one?
Epsilon cubed over 60 plus.
Let me just check the sign.
1 minus 1 plus epsilon minus epsilon squared over 2.
And the next one?
Plus epsilon cubed over what?
Epsilon cubed over 6.
All right.
Now we have trouble.
The trouble is the 1s cancel.
The denominator is proportional to epsilon.
Let's factor out 1 power of epsilon.
Let's see.
We want to take the derivative.
This is the object whose derivative we want to take.
Let's factor out a factor of epsilon in the denominator.
Since everything in the denominator has epsilon,
we're going to factor it out.
1 over epsilon.
And then this becomes 1 minus epsilon plus epsilon squared.
Did everybody follow that?
Okay.
Plus higher terms.
But as I said, the
higher terms are going to disappear
when we go to small epsilon.
They won't be important.
Which is the minus sign?
That was the minus sign?
The 1 minus the quantity 1.
Well, I thought I got it right.
All right.
Should we do it over?
1 minus.
Put in brackets.
1 minus epsilon plus epsilon squared
over 2 minus epsilon cubed over 6.
All right.
Everybody happy with that?
Now, the 1s are going to cancel.
And the minus times the
minus will make plus minus plus.
I have no idea if that's what
I had written down before or not.
Then we pull out a factor of epsilon.
And that turns this into 1 minus epsilon over 2
plus epsilon squared over 2.
And that's going to be
1 minus epsilon squared over 6.
All right.
Now, the trick is we're
expanding everything in powers of epsilon.
But here we have a thing in the denominator.
I don't want this in the denominator.
I want in the numerator.
So how do you deal with
a thing in the denominator like this?
You use the formula that 1
minus a small number, like this.
A small number.
Let's just call it s.
Is equal to 1 plus s plus
s squared plus s cubed and so forth.
Here's your s.
Oh, did I leave out something?
No, I think I got it right.
Did I?
I think I did everything right.
So what we do is we
take what's in the denominator here.
We expand it to get all
the epsilon dependence in the numerator.
Let's see what we get.
I think we're going to get 1 plus
epsilon over 2 minus epsilon squared over 6.
But then there's a term coming
from squaring the small quantity here.
If I keep things to order epsilon squared,
all I'm going to get is, let's see,
I think plus epsilon squared over 4, I think.
Okay.
But you can expand it out yourself.
Something like this.
Plus higher order in epsilon.
Is that the epsilon cubed over 4?
No, I think it was epsilon squared.
Right.
Mm-hmm.
It was just epsilon squared.
It was not epsilon cubed.
No.
So this is epsilon cubed in the denominator here
became epsilon squared when I pulled out the epsilon here.
And I was purposefully keeping
everything to powers order epsilon squared.
I know that the next order is not important.
Okay.
So let's see if we can combine this together.
I think the chances that
I'll get this right are negligible.
But all right.
So we get minus d by d epsilon.
1 over epsilon.
Times.
Okay.
1 times 1.
Let's put everything that you get from 1.
1 plus epsilon over 2 minus epsilon squared over 6.
Oh, can we combine these two together?
What's epsilon squared over 4 minus epsilon squared over 6?
Epsilon squared over 12.
Right?
Okay.
How did you do that so fast?
Who did it?
You didn't?
What?
It took me about 30 minutes
to get that epsilon squared over 12.
Okay.
No, 3 minus 2.
That's where you want it.
You know the common denominator is going to be.
I know.
I know how to do it.
1 plus epsilon minus, sorry,
1 plus epsilon squared over 12.
Right?
That's this times this, this, and this.
Then we get minus epsilon, minus epsilon times 1.
And then minus epsilon.
Minus epsilon.
Minus epsilon squared over 2.
But then from here we
get something of order epsilon cubed.
And I'm not interested in
keeping anything of order epsilon cubed.
That's too high an order.
I don't care about it.
We'll see why in a moment.
And then we have plus epsilon squared over 2.
And nothing past that because the next one would be.
Epsilon fourth.
I think this is everything to order epsilon squared.
Should it be plus?
No?
I think it should be plus, right?
Yeah.
Right.
Looks right.
1 times epsilon squared over 12.
Okay.
Now.
Epsilon over 2 minus epsilon.
That's minus epsilon over 2.
We get rid of this.
And these two cancel.
So there's our formula right there.
As we'll see, anything of higher order
is not going to be interesting to us.
Okay.
Look at.
Let's first focus on the one that's easiest.
The easiest term is this epsilon over 2.
It gets multiplied by 1 over epsilon.
That means it's just 1 half.
And what happens when you differentiate
1 half with respect to epsilon?
Zero.
So this is.
We don't have to write it.
It's not there.
Okay.
Now we have a term which is 1 over epsilon.
That's bad news.
This is.
This is something infinite at epsilon equals zero.
And remember we're going to go to epsilon equals zero.
All right.
What's the derivative of 1 over epsilon?
Minus 1 over epsilon squared, right?
Minus 1 over epsilon squared.
Oh, and there's another minus sign here.
So that's plus 1 over epsilon squared, I think.
Yes.
And then 1 over epsilon times epsilon.
One of the epsilons cancel.
And then you differentiate with respect to epsilon.
What do you get?
Minus 1 twelfth.
This is a famous formula
which is usually stated half jokingly.
That 1 plus 2 plus 3 plus 4
plus 5 is equal to minus a twelfth.
We tend to forget about this term over here.
Okay.
And the reason is that this term combines.
Well, this term is an
infinite constant which really doesn't.
I would have to convince you that where it.
Of what happens to it.
It gets absorbed into the
p squared term in the energy.
The infinite term in the energy.
And a careful, a really careful analysis of
it allows you to absorb this into something.
Into an additive constant in
the energy that doesn't do anything.
For the moment, you'll have to accept that.
The real answer.
The really right answer.
The really right answer is that in good string theories.
Properly defined string theories.
This isn't there altogether.
But I'm not going to tell you why now.
I'm not going to tell you why now.
I'm just going to tell you
this infinite constant is not important.
You know the famous story of Dirac and Pauli.
That Dirac calculated the vacuum energy
and found out that it was infinite.
And they said, well, since it's
infinite, I don't care about it.
We'll throw it away.
And Pauli turned around to him and said,
just because it's infinite doesn't mean it's zero.
Right.
Well, in this particular case, Dirac wins.
But this is something we will have to come
back to and explain why this one over epsilon squared.
Remember, epsilon is going to go to zero.
This is going to be an infinite constant.
And in this particular case, the
infinite constant really is not important.
And I'm not going to pursue it right now.
I'm going to tell you
the answer is minus a 12.
Okay.
Minus a 12.
Now, this is not yet a particularly good answer.
This is not a particularly good answer yet.
Remember, what we wanted to get was altogether minus 1.
We wanted to get this minus 1, which when we excite
it by one unit of energy will give us the massless particle.
Okay.
In fact, the minus a 12 is not quite right.
And the reason is because of this factor
of a half from the half h bar omega.
So it's actually 1 over 24.
Okay.
1 over 24.
That minus 1 over 24 is the energy
of the ground state, including the zero point oscillations,
but throwing away a certain infinite term, which
we're going to have to explain away later.
But, okay.
How do we get...
Oh, oh, have I left anything out?
I left out one thing.
Remember, for each mode, there is
not one oscillator, but two oscillators.
The a's and the b's.
Remember the a's and the b's?
The x oscillators and the y oscillators.
So actually, it's twice this.
Twice this.
One for the x oscillators, one for the y oscillators.
It's still not good.
It's only 2 over minus 24.
You really want to get minus 1.
How do you get minus 1?
You say, there weren't two dimensions of oscillation.
There were 24 of them.
24 directions of oscillation, plus the direction
going down the z-axis, plus time make 26.
That's where the 26 is.
Now, this is a crazy story.
At the time, nobody believed it, that this
is a little bit too silly to be true.
But, in fact, the mathematics did fit together.
And this is the simplest way.
This, which is fairly complicated already, is the simplest way
to see, and it is historically the way it came about,
that requiring, let's say there are d dimensions
of space perpendicular to the direction of motion,
then requiring this to come out to be minus 1,
just so that when you excite
it, you can get the photon,
that was the original argument about the,
about d having to be 24,
or the total space-time dimension having to be 26.
Now, as I said, the arguments, this
was hardly a convincing argument at the time,
but it's true.
Its virtue is that it's easy to present.
Relatively easy to present.
What is the history?
What was the history of this introduction?
How did this come about?
Yeah, well, I was just wondering.
1990s?
Oh, God, no.
Yeah.
Oh, 69.
No, no.
No, this goes back to 1969.
1969, I would say.
Maybe early 70, but I think it's still 69.
That was for Hadron?
Yes.
Well, by this point, people were
just exploring the mathematics of string theory.
And they had, and...
So you did have those regi trajectories?
Well, experimentally, you had the regi trajectories,
but at some point, when the
mathematical structure was put in place,
people began to explore it for its own sake.
It was realized rather quickly that there
was some kind of funny thing going on
that there was a spin one particle
one unit up, one unit up from...
But it didn't have all the states that it needed.
It had two polarizations and not three polarizations.
And it was realized rather quickly
that this could only be the photon
or something like a photon.
But that then left the question,
what was this zero point energy
that had to be minus one?
And it was realized fairly quickly
that that required 24 dimensions of oscillation.
Now, as I said, this was
by no means a convincing argument.
Other much, much, much more convincing arguments came about,
but they were highly
mathematical, really highly mathematical.
And I'll tell you about
them in words, but not now.
We need one more mathematical constant.
Is there a similar trick to get eight?
To get eight.
Yes, yes, there's a similar trick to get eight.
But before I tell you that, let
me go back to the closed string.
Remember, the closed string you had to excite twice.
You had to get spin two.
You had to hit it with two oscillators.
That meant that the ground state had
to have minus two units of energy.
Okay?
But now we have a problem.
D over 24, if D
is 24, is only minus one.
What's the answer?
48 minus 48.
Hm?
48 is minus eight.
Why 48?
Get a minus two. One twelfth, right?
Hm?
Get the minus two.
Yeah, yeah, but where do you...
I know, but you only have 24 directions.
We can't change the number of directions of
space when you go from closed string to...
Hm?
No, no, no, the same theory, the
same theory has both closed and open strings.
You can't change that.
Right, you can't do that.
No, we'll agree, the theory has 24 dimensions.
Now what happens to the closed strings?
Secular for a right?
Hm?
Well, something like that.
Remember, you have twice as
many oscillators for the closed strings.
You've got the ones that go around to the left,
and you've got the ones that go around to the right.
Everything gets doubled once again.
You have not only an
oscillation for every direction of space,
but you have one for right-going
modes and one for left-going modes.
So in fact, it's true
that you get twice as many,
which means that the ground state energy is minus two,
which is just exactly the right thing so that two
units of oscillation will bring you up to massless again.
That began to smell better.
It began to smell better, but still.
Far from a convincing argument.
The real thing has to
do with something called conformal invariance.
So we're going to take up conformal invariance next time.
What conformal invariance means.
If you want to prepare yourself, learn
a little bit about complex function theory.
Very little, not much.
We're going to do a very little bit.
Learn what the Cauchy-Riemann equations are.
If not, I will explain it.
And we will come to why string
theory is the theory of Turkish taffy.
You know what Turkish taffy is.
You pull it this way, you pull it
that way, you stretch it out that way,
you stick it together and somehow it all stays together.
It's conformal.
It's a little bit complicated.
It's conformal transformations.
Anyway, I think we're finished for tonight.
What was the equation
you mentioned, the Cauchy-Riemann equation?
Cauchy-Riemann equations.
Cauchy.
Just learn a little bit about them.
For more, please visit us at stanford.edu.