Stanford University.
Okay, so fermionic strings have been a
part of the subject since almost the beginning,
not quite the beginning. And as
I said, they solve two important problems.
I forgot what they are though. Oh, they give
you fermions and they get rid of the tachyons.
They leave you with ten dimensions instead of twenty-six.
So they don't solve that problem. That problem
turned out to be less of a problem
and more of a feature, feature means a
good feature, than people had expected at the time.
But we'll come to it, and
it's a subject known as compactification,
taking the extra dimensions and doing
something with them to make them innocuous.
Or if not innocuous, an interesting feature of the theory.
But we'll come to that not now though.
What I wanted to talk about a little bit
was not really historical, but the scattering of strings.
The subject really began
with studying scattering of particles.
Elemental particle physics was
always about scattering of particles.
Not because it's the most
interesting phenomena that can happen.
It's not. It's rather dull.
You send some particles together and a bunch
of junk comes out in all sorts of directions.
But it's about all we can
do in the way of experiment.
And so we try to unravel from the
scattering data what was going on inside the collision.
And inside the collision, of course, means
the properties of particles and so forth.
So the natural tool of experiment,
the scattering, and the natural thing
that a theorist would ask is,
if I have a theory of particles,
how do you compute the scattering amplitudes?
The scattering amplitudes, what is a scattering amplitude?
A scattering amplitude, you have some incoming
particles that are part of your incoming information.
I'm going to have time running this way tonight.
Horizontally instead of vertically.
I don't know why. Variety.
Particles come in, something happens inside
a black box, and particles go out.
Not necessarily the same number of particles.
The particles come in and they carry momentum.
Of course, they carry other things.
They carry spin, they carry charge,
they carry labels, like for example, is it a
muon or is it a whatever it happens to be.
But let's simplify the story and ignore everything else.
They carry everything except their momentum.
So particles come in and they carry four momentum.
Four momentum means energy and momentum.
Let's write down what a four
vector of energy and momentum is.
The energy and the three components of momentum.
Of course, if we're working in
26 dimensions, we have 25 components here.
But I'll just write down four of them.
So we have a four vector, relativistic four vector.
Each particle has a momentum.
And we're going to call it K.
K mu.
Where mu goes from one to four.
From zero to four, excuse me.
From zero to three. This is usually
called zero, one, two, three, doesn't matter.
Four components of momentum.
Now, what do we know about
the components, the four components of momentum
in a particle?
They have something to do
with the mass of the particle.
Well, of course, they are the energy and the momentum.
What's the relationship between energy and
momentum and mass for a relativistic particle?
Anybody remember? C is one.
We will take C equals H bar equals one.
What's the connection between the
components of energy, momentum, and mass?
E squared.
E squared equals P squared plus M squared.
Or, let's write it the following way.
E squared minus P squared equals M squared.
And just in order to keep my notation
consistent with notations of physicists for many, many years,
I am going to write this as P squared
minus E squared equals minus M squared.
Same formula, I've just taken the negative of it.
Now, that can also be written
in terms of the components of K.
In terms of the components
of K, that's, what is it?
It's K naught squared, sorry, it's
K vector squared minus K naught squared.
Nought standing for the time component, E.
The spatial component squared
minus the time component squared.
And this is often just called K squared.
Just call it K squared.
The left-hand side here is the square by definition.
It's the definition of the relativistic square of a vector.
It's called P mu P mu.
Or, to simplify it, let's just call it K squared.
It's the space component squared
minus the time component squared.
That's called K squared.
And for every particle, K squared
is equal to minus M squared.
You can't vary K squared.
Of course, K squared consists
of the energy and the momentum.
When you say you can't vary K squared,
it doesn't mean you can't vary the momentum.
It means when you vary the momentum,
the energy varies in a certain way.
And the way that it varies
is that E squared minus P squared,
or K times K naught squared minus
K space squared, equals minus M squared.
So that's the first thing about...
It's not even about collisions. It's just about particles.
You characterize them by their four momentum,
three components of which are independent.
The fourth component has to be subject to this constraint.
And then a bunch of momentum.
Let's call this K1 for the first particle.
Is that the way I label them?
I like to keep my notation straight.
Yeah. I think I call this one K1.
This one K2.
And then outgoing over here,
we'll call the incoming momentum K.
I'm going to call the outgoing momentum Q.
These are also four momenta.
I'm going to call it Q3.
Q4, dot dot dot.
Let's take the very simple case
in which two particles go to two particles.
Q4.
These particles come in.
Those particles go out.
How do you represent momentum conservation?
Momentum and energy conservation.
Momentum and energy conservation are simply
that K1 plus K2, thought of as four vectors,
equal to Q3 plus Q4.
All components.
The space components define momentum conservation.
The time components define energy conservation.
Okay.
Now, because of the perversity of physicists,
what physicists like to do
is to redefine the outgoing momentum
and think of them as incoming momentum.
Now, that's crazy.
The incoming momentum and outgoing momentum are outgoing.
The incoming momentum and incoming momentum are incoming.
But to do it, all we really have to do
to make it symmetric
with respect to incoming and outgoing momentum,
just take each Q,
Q4,
change its sign
and call it K.
Minus K3.
That means changing the sign of its energy.
It means changing the sign of all of its momentum.
It's a trick to be able
to write this in a symmetric form.
Instead of writing K1, well, let's see what it is.
Here's what it is.
K1 plus K2 minus Q4 minus Q3 equals zero.
Now becomes K1 plus K2
plus K3 plus K4 equals zero.
You treat all particles as incoming,
but you have to remember
that the label for the outgoing particles
is labeled with minus the
actual momentum of the outgoing particle,
but once you do so,
momentum conservation is completely symmetric
between the four particles.
A useful trick.
It's a useful trick that keeps labeling
especially consistent.
Notice that when you change the sign of the momentum
to redefine the momentum with a minus sign,
it does not change the fact
that the square of the momentum
is equal to minus M squared.
So we have in this particular process,
we have four momenta.
Think of them as all incoming,
although the energies of two of them may be negative,
the outgoing ones.
Each one of them subject to this constraint.
The,
the question that a physicist would ask about this collision
is what is the amplitude?
What is the probability?
The thing, the amplitude is the thing that you square,
the complex number that you square
to find the probability for that collision.
But the collision is a function
of a number of variables.
It's a function, or the probability for the collision
is a function of the momenta of the incoming particles
and a function of the momentum of the outgoing particles.
So it's a function of the k's.
Let's call that amplitude A.
It's the thing that you square.
And it's a function of all of the k's,
k1, k2, k3, k4.
But there's some redundant information here.
First of all, the momenta have to be conserved.
Second of all, the square of
each k has to add up to,
to minus the mass squared.
So there's really too many variables here.
There's too many independent variables.
How many independent variables are there?
Before we impose any constraints,
each momentum has four variables.
This is 4 plus 4 is 8 plus
4 is 12 plus 4 more is 16.
Okay, that's a lot of
variables for something to depend on.
Fortunately, you really don't depend on that many variables.
Let's think about, physically,
how many variables does a scattering amplitude
or a scattering process depend on?
Well, the first thing you can do is,
whatever the momenta are,
you can use relativity to
go to a frame of reference
where the center of mass is at rest.
In other words, where the two momenta,
the two space components of the momentum,
are equal and opposite.
You can always do that.
If the particles are both moving down the z-axis,
well, you just move fast enough
to be halfway in between them.
If they also happen to
be moving in some other direction,
just move in that direction.
You can always go to a frame of reference
where the particles are equal and opposite,
the space components,
in other words, the spatial momenta.
Next, you can always rotate the momentum,
you can always rotate the system,
so that the momenta are coming in along the x-axis.
What's left over in the initial state,
what does it depend on if you
know that the momenta are equal and opposite?
What does the whole thing depend on?
It only depends, what does the initial state depend on?
The initial state only depends
on the magnitude of the momentum.
Not the magnitude of the square of the momentum,
I mean, sorry, not the magnitude of the four vector.
The four vector has to have magnitude m squared,
but the magnitude of the space momentum.
Or the energy, if you like.
Once you go to the center of mass,
the only thing left over is
the total energy of the collision
in the center of mass frame.
So that's one thing, e center of mass.
Now let's suppose that our particles
are all of the same kind,
for simplicity.
The particles collide,
what can you say about the outgoing momentum?
First thing is they have to be equal and opposite.
Why?
That's momentum conservation.
Momentum conservation says they have
to be equal and opposite.
What about the energy of the outgoing state?
It has to be the same
as the energy of the incoming state.
What is the only thing that can
differ between the incoming and the outgoing particles?
The angle.
That's it.
The angle of scattering.
Think of that.
So the scattering amplitude, although it's
written in terms of 16 variables,
really only depends on two.
Two independent variables.
Those variables should be expressible
in terms of relative momentum.
Relativistically invariant things.
We can think of it in the center of mass,
but we also ought to be able to
think about it in any frame of reference.
We should be able to construct two independent invariants,
relativistic invariants,
which are enough to completely characterize the scattering.
So let's talk about the
invariants describing a scattering process.
Two particles collide.
Two particles come in.
Two particles go out.
Let's think of them as all coming in,
changing the sign of the momentum.
What is this?
k1, k2, k3, k4.
What can you do with a four vector?
What can you do with four vectors to construct invariants?
There's only one thing you can do, really.
You can square them.
That's about all you can do.
But you don't have to be
talking about k1 squared or k2 squared.
You could be talking about k1 plus k2 squared, right?
That's a good invariant.
k1 as a four vector.
k1 plus k2...
k1 plus k2 squared.
Now remember what that means.
That means the space components of k, k1 plus k2,
which I'll label with arrows,
squared,
minus the time component,
which means the energies.
Let's label them.
k0, k0 means energy.
k0, 1 and k0, 2 squared.
You sum the momenta, square it.
You sum the energies, square it and subtract.
And that's called k1 plus k2 squared.
Let's see if we can figure out what it is.
It's an invariant quantity.
Let's see if we can figure out what it is
by going to the center of mass frame.
In the center of mass frame,
the momentum of this particle,
what should we call it?
Well, it's k1.
It's the space component k1.
What about the momentum of this particle?
It's equal and opposite.
Hm?
Minus k1, right?
So, the total space component
of the momentum in the
center of mass frame is 0.
We don't have to worry about this one.
What about this one over here?
That's the energies.
We didn't talk about it,
but what about the energies of the two particles
in the center of mass frame?
They're equal and opposite.
They have the same mass.
The energies are equal.
The center of mass frame is one in which
the particles are equal.
They're perceived as moving with exactly the same momentum,
magnitude of the momentum.
And so the two energies are the same.
So this just becomes twice k0 quantity squared.
Very simple.
This is the center of mass energy here.
In the center of mass frame,
you add the two energies.
It's the total energy,
and the square of it is just the square
of the center of mass energy.
So this quantity here,
which is called minus s,
it's just called minus s,
is nothing but the square
of the center of mass energy.
Just look at it.
Or s is the center of mass energy.
Why?
In the center of mass frame,
this is 0.
And this is just the total energy.
So minus s is just the square,
minus the square of the center of mass energy.
Square of the center of mass energy,
we call s.
Now, can you think of any other invariant
that you can build?
How about k3 plus k4 squared?
We took k1 plus k2 squared.
It's the same thing.
Why?
Because k1 plus k2 is minus k3 plus k4.
Energy conservation,
so we don't get anything new there.
k1 plus k2 squared is the
same as k3 plus k4 squared.
It's the energy,
and this just says that
the energy in the initial state
is the same as the energy in the final state.
Okay?
What about k1 plus k3 squared?
That could be something new.
So let's see what it is.
Let's see if we can figure
out what k1 plus k3 squared is
by working in the center of mass frame.
In the center of mass frame,
all the particles in and out
have the same total energy,
have the same energy.
Each particle has the same energy.
Particles just get scattered through an angle.
That's all that happens.
So they come in and they
go out with the same energy,
but they scatter through an angle.
Okay.
So let's take k1 plus k3 squared.
Ah, here it is.
k1 plus k3 squared,
k3 squared,
k1, k3 squared.
How about this?
What is this in the center of mass frame?
It's the same as k2 and k4.
It is the same as k2 and k4,
but that doesn't help.
I want to know what it is, though.
How big is it?
All the particles have the same energy,
incoming and outgoing.
All they do is scatter through an angle.
Zero.
Why zero?
Why not twice the energy?
Yeah, because k3 and k4,
we flip the sign on them.
All right.
So this isn't there.
And this is just k1 plus k3 squared.
So let's see if we can see what that is.
k1 comes in.
Particle 1 comes in.
And of course, also particle 2.
Particle 3 goes out.
Here's particle 3.
One goes in.
Three goes out.
But,
if we label these particles with the k's,
k1,
and let's call this one now q,
q3.
Let's make it an outgoing particle.
Then really what this is,
is it's k1 minus q3 squared.
It's really the difference of the momentum
of the incident particle and the final particle.
It's called the momentum transfer.
It's the momentum transferred.
If you were to think
of particle 1 and particle 3
as the same species of particle,
then it would just be in the collision,
it's the momentum transferred from 1 to 3.
Bing, bing.
There's a momentum transfer.
And that's the momentum transferred from 1 to 3.
That's what this is.
Momentum transfer.
It can also be expressed in
terms of the angle of scattering.
I will tell you what the formula is.
The formula,
the formula for
k1 plus k3 squared
is, it's just twice
the energy squared minus the mass squared.
All right, we already have
worked out what the energy is.
The energy is the s variable.
It's twice e squared minus m squared
in the center of mass frame
times one minus the cosine of the angle of scattering.
This is the interesting thing here.
The angle of scattering
is the angle between 1 and 3.
All right.
k1 comes in,
q3 goes out.
The particle gets deflected through an angle
and it's that deflection angle, here it
is, theta, the deflection angle of the
particle between the incoming state and
the outgoing state, and that's what's
here. Why is that interesting? Well
of course that's what's measured in an
experiment. You put detectors in
different places, you scatter particles,
and you find out the probability for
them to get deflected to an angle at
different values of the energy. This variable,
the k1 plus, let's see what did
we do. I'm sorry. The definition of S,
I forgot to erase the S over here.
The definition of S was k1 plus
k2 squared. That was the definition of it.
1 plus 2 coming in, and it was the
square of the center of mass energy. So S
equals k2 squared.
equals energy center of mass squared.
K1 plus K3 squared, that's called,
anybody think up a name for it?
T. T, good, T.
It is called T. I knew
you were going to get that.
And that is some combination of
the energy and the momentum transfer.
It's the center of mass
energy squared minus the mass squared,
big deal, we already know what
the center of mass energy is,
times one minus cosine of the angle of scattering.
Alright, so we have K1 plus K3 squared.
How about K2 plus K4 squared?
Right.
Is that different?
Well if you go back up to here,
K1 plus K3 is minus K2 plus K4.
So K1 plus K2 squared is
the same as K3 plus K4 squared.
It's also T.
Is there another combination?
We have K1 plus K2, we have K1 plus K3,
K1 plus K4, right?
That's another one.
Alright, so one more quantity is K1 plus K4 squared.
What can that be?
Well, if you were going to give
it a name, what would you call it?
Oh, minus T equals K1 plus K3 squared.
U. U. Minus U.
Minus U equals that.
These are the STU variables.
But what's going on here?
There are only two quantities
that the scattering depends on.
Energy and angle of scattering.
Well, we seem to have three independent things.
Well, the answer is there are not three independent things.
If you use the momentum conservation,
and you use the fact that
each K squared is M squared,
what you'll find is that S plus T
plus U is equal to minus 4 M squared,
or something like that.
There's a constraint among them.
There are not three independent ones, only two.
These are the two interesting quantities.
The third one is dependent on the other two.
And as I said under this demonstration,
we're not going to apply other
than minus 2 to realized weight.
Do you have to consider the
vacuum at all on these collisions?
What does that mean?
Well, maybe the vacuum could just slow
down a particle going through free space.
Well, we know that doesn't happen, don't we?
Oh, okay.
It's momentum conservation.
Okay, well, just a wild idea.
Yeah, it could be.
I mean, it's a possible world.
A vacuum has friction.
It's not our world.
Momentum conservation says that particles
aren't slowed down by the vacuum.
ありがとうございました
At some point I think you said
that Q3 and Q4 have the same energy.
In the center of mass frame.
Why can't there be a, I mean, K1 and K2,
the center of mass frame is kind of defined that way.
Yeah.
But then...
The center of mass frame is defined as
a frame where the momenta are equal and opposite.
If the momenta are equal and opposite,
the energies of the particles are the same.
If their masses are the same.
Now they scatter, but they have to go
out equal and opposite for momentum conservation reasons.
Yeah.
So that's...
Alright, these variables S, T, and
U, the other one which is there,
those are called Mandelstam variables.
And they're very symmetrically defined.
Mandelstam.
Mandelstam is a currently active physicist in Berkeley,
but this notation comes from the early 60s.
The very early 60s.
Mandelstam variables.
And notice what they have,
they have this beautiful symmetric structure.
That's what's interesting about them.
Now let's talk about Feynman diagrams for a moment.
And I'll just tell you what
the answer is for certain Feynman diagrams.
Okay.
So let's suppose two particles collide.
This is a Feynman diagram.
Create a third particle of a different mass in here.
Let's call it capital M.
And then those particles go out like this.
Particles come in.
A Feynman diagram.
So they come in together.
They coalesce to form a second
particle or a third particle or whatever.
And then that particle decays.
And it goes out.
That's a Feynman diagram.
That Feynman diagram has a value.
I'm going to tell you what it is.
It's the product of two coupling constants.
There's always coupling constants in Feynman diagrams.
And then there's the propagator of the particle in between.
And that has a very simple form.
1 divided by S minus capital M squared.
It has a...
Is it...
Yeah.
S min...
S minus capital M squared.
That's the characteristic structure of a
scattering amplitude where two particles come together
and merge and form another particle.
And notice, it's a function of
S, the energy of the process.
It doesn't depend on T. It
doesn't depend on the other variable.
You want one that depends on the
other variable, you draw a similar diagram.
Except in which, instead of
1 and 2 merging, you have...
I'll draw it over here.
1 and 3 merging.
It looks like exactly the same
diagram except turned on its side.
But it represents a very different kind of physical process.
1 and 2 come in.
Exchange a particle.
It's a very different kind of physical process.
And then you have a particle between them.
And then go out as 3 and 4.
What would you guess if you had
to guess the amplitude for this process is?
It's going to have G squared again.
The G's are the vertices.
What else?
1 over T minus M squared.
Exactly.
Now, you can imagine a third process, which
would be 1 over U minus M squared.
You're going to have to bring in all these particles.
1 over this.
One.
Let's see.
That's a little hard to draw.
One.
It looks like this.
1 and 4 merge.
You have to switch the lines like that.
Let's ignore it.
It's there.
And it's important.
But it's too hard to draw.
I don't like drawing cross.
Are they perpendicular to the other two?
They're not perpendicular.
It's just a question of which way to go first.
which particles came together, and I hate drawing
cross lines on the blackboard so we won't.
But there is, in principle, there can be another one.
This one depends only on the energy.
Doesn't depend on the angle of scattering altogether.
T contains the angle of scattering.
S is only a function of the energy.
That means that when this process happens, to
say that it doesn't depend on the angle
of scattering means that every angle
of scattering is equal, equally probable.
When the particles go in, they have
equal probability of getting deflected through any
angle whatever.
That seems odd, but that
is the property of this process.
And the reason is very simple.
The particles come in from some direction,
they form this compound state, and then when
they decay, they've forgotten which
direction they came in from.
So they come in, they form the composite.
And then when they decay, they've
forgotten which direction they came in from.
So they come in, they form the composite.
And then when the composite decays, it
decays at an arbitrary angle, uncorrelated to the
initial directions.
That's this process here.
This one is different.
It depends on the energy, but
also on the angle of scattering.
This is the one that depends on the angle
of scattering, and if you work it out, it's
easy to see that it favors small angle scattering.
This favors large angles.
So this one.
It depends on angle and this one depends.
But notice how similar the two expressions are.
There's a real symmetry between them.
In fact, if you interchange S
and T, the scattering doesn't change.
This is a property of relativistic scattering
amplitudes that they have this kind of symmetry.
They sort of forget which were the
incoming and which were the outgoing particles, but
only if you express it in
terms of these kind of invariants.
Ok.
Good.
So now we have one.
We have three.
We have two.
have some basic idea of what it
is that a theoretical physicist wants to compute
about a model of particles to compare,
not because he's so interested in it, but
it's the thing that he can give
to the experimentalist and say measure the
probabilities for scattering as a function
of energy and so forth, and
here's my prediction. Okay. Are you saying that
the dependence of ST and U causes this
amplitude to what shift around if you, I
mean you still have three turns but, but
the value shifts around if you... Depends
on the angle of scattering, all right, so
if all that was there was this, this would
favor the value of the value of the
energy. This would favor the value of the energy.
This would favor the value of the energy.
This would favor the value of the energy. This would favor small angle scattering and
be, not forbid, but make it less likely, let's see if we can see why.
I think I, here it is.
I'm just asking, do you have a third term?
The third term is there. What about it?
Oh, well, but you say that you didn't want to write it
up there or that it, you didn't want to write the diagram.
I didn't want to draw the diagram, but if there
was a process in which one and four could come together
and do the same thing, then we would want to
put a g squared, 1 over u minus m squared.
And because the three are not completely independent.
Yeah, they're connected.
Then that has an effect on the...
The 1 over u minus, okay, so what is u?
It's interesting, u is equal to e
center of mass squared minus m squared
times 1 plus cosine theta.
Okay, so both...
So they're clearly related.
If you know s, you know the energy.
Therefore, if you also know t,
you know the angle of scattering.
And this is just a function of
the energy and the angle of scattering.
So they're all connected with each other.
Another way to say it is
if you add s and u,
you'll cancel out the angle altogether,
and you'll get just a function of energy.
Which is clearly dependent only on s.
Right.
But they're all...
But they're separate finding diagrams,
and in general you have to add them all.
Okay.
But I want to focus on this here.
Here.
This does not describe...
The scattering of mesons, for example, very well.
It gives a poor description of the scattering of mesons.
And the reason is simple.
The reason is that there are many, many different particles
that can be produced when two mesons collide.
Whole stacks of them with
different mass and different angular momentum.
Okay.
We haven't described what the
angular momentum would do here.
What the angular momentum would do would be
to change the dependence on the angle of scattering.
Let's not get into it.
Formulas like this are too simple
to describe the realistic scattering of mesons.
It's too easy to excite
higher vibrations of these particles here.
And when two particles collide,
they could make some ground state,
they could make some first excited state,
they could make some next excited state,
they can make a whole raft of
different particles that can go in there.
And people in the 60s,
basically beginning sometime around 1965, 66, 67,
tried to concoct mathematical amplitudes
with interesting mathematical properties.
That would represent all of the
possible particles which could go in here.
This was trial and error.
It was just making up formulas to try to
represent the different particles which could go in here
and different particles which could go in here.
The first attempts tended to be to add particles.
This is called an S-channel process.
Why?
Because it involves 1 over S minus M squared.
Particles coming together, K1, K2.
That defines S.
This is called the T-channel process.
K1 and K3 coming together.
So they began by saying,
let's just add more and more stuff into here, S-channel,
and let's add more and more stuff into here, T-channel,
and then let's add more stuff into here, T-channel.
And so this is basically the same thing.
You add up all the particles that could be scattered.
Well, that lasted for a certain period of time,
adding up the various particles which could go in there.
And then people tried to find more comprehensive formulas.
Just by...
I don't even know what the right word is.
Sort of a kind of curve fitting,
but a very sophisticated kind of curve fitting.
And a rather dramatic formula was discovered,
the physics of all of the particles in the S
channel and all of the particles in the T channel.
Just replaced this combination here
with, but not just one particle, but
many of them, whole towers of them,
with a formula which I'm going to
just, this is of historical interest mainly,
with a formula which I will write down
and you can explore its beauty, its great beauty,
is very, very simple. It's called the Veneziano amplitude.
Veneziano amplitude. A young Italian physicist, he was
young at the time, he's not young anymore,
but he's still Italian.
He just
I don't know how he made this guess. He
just randomly wrote down some things which had some
right properties and which really did look like adding
up things like this. It was a function of
S and T. Everybody know what the gamma function
is? Well the gamma function, you don't need to
know it, but I'm just going to write
down the formula for fun. The gamma function
is a generalization of the factorial function.
But the factorial function is only defined for integers.
The gamma function is defined, interpolated between
integers. The gamma function for the integers
is equal to n minus one factorial, gamma
of n. But it's defined for non-integers too,
and I won't tell you. It's defined by an integral
and it continuously interpolates between the integer, and the non-integer.
And I apologize if I'm paraphrasing here.
But this is it. This is the
Veniziano amplitude multiplied by the coupling constant squared.
If you examine this amplitude, you'll find out,
I'm not going to go there. They're somewhat different Conservatives, Comb plates,
consigliere plinuses, et cetera. I'm not going to go there. But you're bound
I'm not going to go into its mathematics.
Its mathematics is very simple.
All you have to know is about gamma functions.
And if you want to explore it, it's actually
quite a simple construction.
But I'm going to tell you what it looks like.
It looks like an amplitude that
you would make by summing up
large number of particles.
This is representing some composite particle
or some particle that could be in there,
of different masses in the S channel.
But it also looks like, oh, notice that it's symmetric.
It's symmetric with respect to S
and T, exactly like this is.
The peculiar thing about it is you
can represent it as a
kind of sum of Feynman diagrams
with all the particles in
the S channel, diagrams like this.
But because it's symmetric, it's not
symmetric under S and T, you can also represent it.
You don't add.
It is also equal to the
same kind of thing going this way.
Something odd was afoot about this formula.
It had all the important features
that the scattering amplitude should have.
It could be analyzed as if a whole
bunch of particles were produced and then decayed.
But it could also be analyzed as
if a whole bunch of particles were exchanged.
This was something new.
This had not been seen before.
Previous to this, everybody would have
added contributions for S and T.
And this thing replaced this.
The question was, what is this?
Where does this come from?
What kind of physics gives rise to this?
What kind of physics can you
imagine would give rise to this,
to a formula like this?
The answer, of course, turned out to be string theory.
The invention and the discovery of string
theory was just looking for a physical model
which would give this for its answers, for
its answer for scattering of two mesons, or
two particles.
I'm going to go back to the first part
of the lecture, which is the theory of the
mass of particles.
I'm going to go back to the first part
of the lecture, which is the theory of the mass
of particles.
I'm going to tell you, without a lot of
drama, what physical model gives rise to this scattering
amplitude.
And I'll show you a little bit.
I'll show you what the
logic that went into it was.
It wasn't very hard to guess
that this was a theory of strings.
It wasn't too hard.
Just because...
Well, it wasn't too hard.
You said exchange particles versus...
The S-channel and the T-channel exchange...
Direct production and exchange.
Sometimes called the direct channel and the cross channel.
The S-channel is called the direct channel.
Those are the direct particles come
in, coalesce, and then go out.
The cross channel is when the particle
jumps across from one side to another.
All right.
I'll show you what the physics of that formula is.
You begin with two strings.
I'm not going to do a calculation, but
I'll show you everything that went into it.
It's a little bit tedious.
What you have to know about...
You have to know a lot about what you're doing.
You have to know how to do it.
You have to know how to
do it, how to do it.
You have to know how to do it.
All right?
What you have to know
about harmonic oscillators and that's all.
Nothing much more than that.
You start with two strings.
All right, here's a string.
Now, remember, the string has a
coordinate along it, which we call sigma.
Let's draw the sigma axis over
here from sigma from zero to pi.
And here's a string.
But the string propagates in time.
Let's draw time horizontally.
Here's the end of a string.
at sigma equals zero, sigma equals pi.
These are open strings.
Now the string, of course, moves around in spacetime,
but it's always located between zero and pi.
That's not spatial position, that's
just its parameter along the string.
And the material of the string, the
particles that make it up, are in here.
Each point in the history of the string, think
of the string as sweeping along, here it is,
it's sweeping along some spacetime sheet.
It's called a world sheet, instead of a world line.
Each point in that world sheet
is characterized by a point sigma,
and a time which is called tau.
Tau goes this way, it's a time,
and sigma is a...
a coordinate along the string.
Not a real spatial coordinate, just a
label for labeling points along the string.
Tau is this time that we've used previously,
the infinite momentum time, but that's not what's important.
What's important is that the idea of
a world line becomes a world sheet.
And instead of being parameterized by a single variable tau,
it's now parameterized by two variables.
Each point in here has a position
in spacetime, x mu, or just x.
And we've already worked out what
the equations of motion of x are.
They are the wave equations describing
waves moving up and down the string.
The wave equation, let's write it.
It was d second x by d tau squared
minus d second x by...
d sigma squared equals zero.
That's the wave equation that
described the oscillations of the string.
But we don't even have to think about this.
We can just imagine that this string is
a collection of a large number of particles
replaced the world sheet by a bunch of
world lines narrowly spaced with springs between them.
With springs between them.
That's the picture of the evolution of a particle.
Now what we're going to
do is begin with two particles.
We're going to have two
particles coming in from the past.
And we're going to put
them right next to each other.
Let's see, I think we need
another color for the second particle.
We're not going to put them right
next to each other in space necessarily,
but just in the parameter space.
Here this goes from zero to pi.
We need to put another one in going from pi...
also from zero to pi.
Here's the other string.
There's no meaning to the fact that
I've drawn them right next to each other.
I've just drawn them.
Their actual position in space-time might not be adjacent.
So this just parameterizes...
this half parameterizes the world
sheet of the left particle.
This half parameterizes the world
sheet of the right particle.
And they might be far away from each other.
That means the x's over here may
be very different than the x's over here.
But, with any luck at all,
with some probability,
the end of the string might
touch the end of that string.
And when it does,
they can coalesce.
That's an assumption, that they can coalesce.
But that's the basic process of string theory,
that they can coalesce,
and then form a single string.
Now,
they really are connected.
If you like, a new spring developed.
When these touched each other, a spring appeared,
connecting the last particle of this string
with the first particle of that string,
and the whole thing becomes one string.
That condition persists for a while.
It persists for a while until
a quantum mechanical event happens,
and the strings separate again.
Randomly, but you can
transform around, cleverly,
to make it be at
the same place along the string.
So, you have enough symmetry,
enough symmetry of the equations,
that you can
put this point at the same point,
the same horizontal level as this point.
So, what do you have to...
Alright, so what is the nature of this process?
Given this,
it's possible to guess what
the answer is for the O.
The important quantity in here is the amount
of time that the strings,
the spins coalesce.
It's the amount of time that the compound state stays
before it breaks up into its final constituents.
Alright?
And let's just call that tau now.
Let's call that from this time here, tau.
I'll tell you what we
do with it in the end.
In the end, we integrate over it, but...
Let me tell you what you put in.
If you're interested in a quantum mechanical amplitude,
you want to start with an initial state.
The initial state...
Let's start with one particle.
The initial state can be thought of
as the state of a whole bunch of little points,
namely the points that make up the string,
x1 through xn.
Let's start with the first string.
It's just a collection of mass points.
x1 dot dot dot through xn.
And the wave function of it
is just a function of x1 through xn.
That's its wave function to begin with,
in the start.
What do we know about the wave function?
Does everybody understand why a wave function
is a function of the n positions of the particles?
That's quantum mechanics.
Quantum mechanics says wave functions,
or state vectors,
are functions of the position of the constituents.
What's the probability to find the particles
at position x1 through xn?
Psi star psi.
So that's what this is.
This is the wave function
of the starting assemblage of particles.
Of course, I'm purposefully not taking the continuum limit
to show you what goes on.
At the end, you have to take the continuum limit,
but let's not do that.
What do we know about this?
Well, the first thing we know about it
is that this particle comes in with momentum k1.
I'll tell you exactly what that says.
That says that this wave function contains a factor,
e to the i k1,
times the center of mass position.
This is the wave function,
e to the i kx,
is the wave function of a particle
with definite momentum.
What momentum do you use?
You use the center of mass momentum.
So what is the center of mass position?
Sorry, the center of mass position.
What's the center of mass position of these points?
It's the average position.
x1, the sum of the x's, divided by n.
So you have x1 plus x2, dot dot dot,
up to xn, divided by n.
That factor, and that factor alone,
tells you that this initial particle here
had momentum k1.
Now, what about the rest of the wave function,
which depends on the relative coordinates,
not the sum of them,
but the distances between the neighboring particles?
That's some wave function
which characterizes the ground state.
It depends on everything
except the sums of the x's,
and the sum of the x's.
It's some wave function.
Let's call it sine naught for ground state.
And it depends on the x's,
same x's,
but it actually doesn't depend on the sum of them.
The sum of them here,
the differences between them here.
Differences of x's here,
neighboring x's and so forth here,
sum of them here.
And this wave function is computable.
It's just the ground state,
including the ground state of all the harmonic oscillators
making up the string.
And you can really work it out.
With enough room on the blackboard,
I could tell you exactly what this function is
as a function of a collection of x's.
It's not very hard.
It's a bunch of exponentials.
It's workable. You can do it.
This is the wave function of the first particle.
What about the wave function of the second particle?
It's exactly the same kind of thing,
except it doesn't depend on these coordinates.
It depends on the coordinates of the red particles here.
So let's write it down.
E to the i k2.
Now, what shall I write?
Shall I write x1 through xn?
No. That's the original particle.
Those are the original constituents of the first string.
I want the constituents of the second string.
So let's write
x
n plus 1
x n plus 2
all the way up to x2n.
The second half of the particles
is grouped together into the second string,
also divided by n,
also times psi nought of
1 through n.
This is x n plus 1
to the end of the chain.
Can that be read?
It is read.
But can you read it?
Okay, you can read it.
Now, that's the initial state.
But now you say with some probability
the two endpoints merge.
To say that the two endpoints merge
simply says
that you set x1,
sorry, xn equal to xn plus 1.
You look for that piece of the wave function
where the two endpoints are at exactly the same point.
So, you begin with this.
The next step is to say
let the nth particle on the first chain
be at exactly the same place as the n plus,
sorry, as the xn being at
the same place as xn plus 1.
Alright, so we're going to put in here then xn.
All the others left unchanged.
That's now not,
that's the wave function of the state
right at the point
after the two particles have coalesced.
When they coalesce,
at the point where they coalesce,
they come together,
nothing happens to the rest of the chain
but the two particles.
So this is, if you like,
it's the amplitude that the two particles,
the chain touched.
This is the amplitude that the two particles,
the endpoints touched.
Now we have a new starting point
which is a function of x1 through x2n.
It's a state of that many particles.
And what do we do with it?
We have to evolve it.
We have to evolve it using the Hamiltonian.
Remember what a Hamiltonian is.
A Hamiltonian is a thing which updates you
from one instant to the next.
So you take this initial state.
It's a well-defined thing.
And you propagate it forward in time
using the Hamiltonian.
You take it.
What's the right rule for updating a state
from an instant to a later instant?
You multiply the state by something.
e to the i ht.
e to the i.
So you take this wave function
and you evolve it.
You solve the Schrodinger equation for it.
But that's the same as multiplying
it by e to the i,
the total Hamiltonian times tau.
But what is the total Hamiltonian?
The total Hamiltonian is just the collection
of springs and mass points.
A collection of harmonic oscillators.
It's just a collection of harmonic oscillators.
We know how to do this.
And that gives us the state of the system
after time t.
What's the last step?
The last step is to project the final state,
here it is,
onto two separate particles again.
To project it onto a state
with two separated particles
and a state of the final state.
And that's the final state.
So you have two separated particles
of momentum k3 and k4.
It's very, very straightforward,
if tedious.
Slightly tedious.
You take the two initial states
of the two particles.
They're well-defined ground states of the particles.
You insist that the two endpoints
are at the same place.
That constrains the wave function.
You let it evolve as a single string
for a ways.
And then you let it break up again.
And that simply means multiplying it again
by some final state.
I'm not going to write it all out.
It's the same kind of thing.
And that gives you the transition amplitude.
To make a long story short,
you start with the two particles.
You constrain it so that they're at the same place.
You evolve it.
And then you project it onto the final state.
A very, very well-defined thing.
That gives you the amplitude
that the strings coalesced
for an amount of time, tau.
But how should you choose tau?
The things in black and red there
are added together and then you multiply?
Multiply.
Those are multiplied together.
Yeah.
If you have two separate systems,
each having its own wave function,
you multiply to create the wave function
of a composite.
So this is just a wave function.
This is a wave function
of a composite of two particles.
To begin with,
you don't set the first particle
equal to the last particle here.
Then you look for the amplitude.
You look for the piece of the wave function
where those two particles are at the same place.
You say, aha.
Now that they're at the same place,
fuse them together and evolve it
as if it were a single string.
A single collection of mass points
and springs.
For an amount of time, tau.
And then basically you take your scissor
and just cut the spring in the middle
and let it evolve after that.
That calculation is quite doable.
Not even very hard.
It's just too much for the blackboard
for one evening.
But I'm going to tell you what the answer is.
I'm going to write down the answer.
I'm going to write down the answer for you.
Don't try to remember.
This is the answer.
It's an integral over the tau.
Did we say that we integrate over tau?
I think I said we integrate.
Why do we integrate over tau, incidentally?
Why do we add up the amplitudes
for all possible times
that this composite could exist?
This is the Feynman rule
of summing over all possibilities.
The only parameter here
is the time that it takes for this
to break up again.
And Feynman's rule is
sum over all paths, which in this case
just means integrate over the time
that they spent evolving together.
And that gives you the amplitude
for the two particles in the initial state
to become the two particles in the final state.
The result is an integral.
It's the integral over the time
that they spend together.
That's it.
I'll tell you what the integrand is
after a certain amount of calculation
which is actually not very hard.
It becomes the integral of
e to the tau
that's the time
times s plus 1.
This s plus 1 is exactly this s.
It's the s variable
or the center of mass
square of the center of mass energy
of the two particles.
You have a factor like that.
You have another factor
which is 1 minus e to the tau
to the minus t minus 1.
t is the momentum change
between the initial particle here
and the final particle here.
Remember, those momenta
are coded in this wave function
which I've erased.
They were coded in the wave function
in terms of those exponentials.
The center of mass energy
and here is the momentum transfer
it appears in the formula.
And then you have to integrate it
d tau.
There happens to be another factor
I think of e to the minus tau
in the integrand.
You're right.
I have d tau twice.
ありがとうございました
E to the minus tau, yeah.
It's not plus?
Tau.
The first term is tau times S plus 1?
Yeah.
No, yes.
Yeah, that's what you get.
Is that plus E to the minus tau?
What's that?
When you combine the E to
the minus tau hanging out the end,
does that multiply or add it together?
It multiplies this, but I've
left it out here on purpose.
I've left it out here on purpose, the tau.
Now, that doesn't look particularly symmetric
between tau and between T and S.
But after it was computed, it
took about a half hour to realize
that you should change variables in this integral.
Change variables from E to the
tau, from tau to something called Z.
Let E to the tau equals Z.
Okay? Let E to the tau equals Z.
Now rewrite this.
E to the tau is Z,
so this becomes integral of Z.
I'm missing some minus sign.
No, E to the minus tau must be.
Blah, blah, blah.
This must be minus here.
It is.
E to the minus tau there.
This thing just becomes Z
to the minus S plus 1.
E to the minus tau, so this is minus minus.
E to the minus tau is Z
by definition, just a change of variables.
What about Y?
What about 1 minus E to the minus tau?
That becomes 1 minus Z
to the minus tau minus 1.
Oh, incidentally, this integral goes,
I think, from 0 to infinity.
Is that right?
From 0 to infinity.
Yes, it does.
This becomes 1 minus Z
to the minus tau minus 1.
What is D tau times E to the minus tau?
Hmm?
It's just DZ.
I think I got it.
Did I get that right?
I've lost track of whether
this is plus or minus here.
I don't remember.
But it's just DZ.
This is the formula.
And where does the integral go?
The integral goes from tau equals 0.
Where Z is equal to 1 to, this is minus.
It is minus.
I'm sorry.
I'm making a mess out of it.
E to the minus tau is equal to Z.
To tau equals infinity.
In other words, you have tau equals 0.
That's when it very suddenly
merges and then falls apart instantly.
To tau equals infinity when the separation is infinite here.
And what happens when tau goes to infinity?
Z goes to 0.
So it's an integral from 1
to 0 or 0 to 1.
There's probably some sign in here
of an integral that looks like this.
The amazing thing about this integral, the
whole upshot of it, is that this integral
is completely symmetric between S
and T. Can you see that?
How do you see that
it's symmetric between S and T?
Right.
You just substitute for the integral.
You substitute for Z, Z minus 1.
You make a change of variables
between Z and Z minus 1.
And you see that this integral is completely symmetric.
So although a completely unsymmetric starting
point between energy and momentum transfer,
somehow it wound up giving a completely
symmetric answer between the two of them.
I lost track of the minus sign.
The minus sign comes from E to
the minus tau D tau going to DZ.
Yeah.
I've lost track of the minus sign.
So you get a minus sign.
That's why you switched to an order.
There's a minus sign somewhere.
I'm saying E to the minus tau D tau.
Yes.
And then you're going to make that just be DZ.
So you get a minus sign.
Yeah, there's got to be a minus sign out here.
Right?
Right.
Then you switch the order of integration and
it becomes from 0 to 1 like this.
That's right.
That's correct.
It's symmetric.
It's symmetric whether or not
you switch the order of integration.
Right.
And that's the answer.
It's symmetric between S and T. And what is it?
It's a process in which two particles join, form a
composite which wiggles around for a while, and then breaks up.
In other words, it's the analog of the Feynman
diagram in which a composite is formed and then decays.
Composite is formed and then decays.
But it winds up being
completely symmetric between S and T.
In fact, this function is called the Euler beta function.
It's a function of two variables, S and T.
It's called beta of minus S and minus T.
It's the Euler beta function.
It's a famous function of mathematical physics.
And guess what it's equal to?
It's equal to the Veniziano amplitude.
It's exactly equal to the Veniziano amplitude, namely
this product of gamma functions over another gamma function.
How did it get to be
that it was symmetric between the two?
Now, this is not obvious at all.
It's symmetric between the S channel and the T channel.
Completely symmetric between the S
channel and the T channel.
I'm going to come to that next time.
That has to do with a fundamental, extremely
deep symmetry of string theory called conformal symmetry.
It's a symmetry which allows you to take these world sheets
and deform them in crazy ways as if they were Turkish taffy
and stretch them out in different directions.
And, for example, turn this picture.
Into a picture which looks much more
like two particles coming together and exchanging something.
It's the character of...
So the gamma gamma over gamma function is reminiscent
of the probability function of, I think it's factorial A,
factorial B over factorial AB.
Mm-hmm.
Right.
Combinatoric coefficients.
Yeah, so what's the finding between the two of them?
Or is there anything that just blends them?
It is true that the beta function
evaluated at integers is the combinatoric coefficients,
the inverse of the combinatoric coefficients.
You know what he's talking about.
He's talking about n factorial m
factorial over n plus m factorial.
Which occurs all over the place in combinatorics.
So what's the physical interpretation?
It just happens to be the same function.
No simple connection.
First of all, it's the inverse of it.
The inverse of it is not a combinatoric coefficient.
But it just happens.
It's an integral which defines
the same combination of gamma functions.
There is no simple relationship.
It's not that something combinatoric went on
here, at least not to my knowledge.
And it's certainly not the way Veneziano found it.
I don't know what magic
he pulled up to find it.
So this was, if you like, partly historical.
But part of the important logic of the theory
is that, number one, you can calculate with it.
All it is is harmonic oscillators.
Anything can be done with harmonic oscillators.
It's a bunch of harmonic oscillators.
You break the process up into pieces.
And then you integrate over the time in between.
You can calculate.
You calculate and you find an integral.
The integral by, at this point,
by magic, has the property that it's,
it's symmetric between s and t.
And somehow looks like, not the sum, but
has the features of having processes where particles coalesce.
That's the direct process I drew here.
But somehow buried in it is
also somehow processes where particles are exchanged.
And that was the magic of it.
That was the surprise.
That a whole new logic of
putting processes together to make new processes.
Okay.
Any questions about this?
Yeah.
I think I'm missing something.
In the beginning, you described two strings coalescing.
The string of n oscillators and n oscillators.
They come together and two n.
Because bosons.
But remember, when you're taking the limit, n goes
to infinity, two n is the same as n.
Sure.
But it still has the property
of a boson or a fermion.
Oh, yes.
So far, yeah.
Right.
But the question is, when you wrote down
the wave equation, you had the two points coalescing,
which is two n minus one.
So it changes from positive
to, it seems inconsistent, I'm sure.
You lose two, not one.
Well, n and n plus one becomes one.
No, actually, n and n plus one disappear, basically.
Oh, okay.
If you like.
I mean, I think that's the
right way to think about it.
Yeah.
Yeah, they eat each other.
They eat each other like that.
And you're left with, right?
So, the new spring that forms connects these two.
Right.
So it's two n minus two.
Yeah.
Otherwise, we'd have big trouble.
We would lose one fermion.
Right.
So that's a good one.
One way to think about it is
that a particle and an antiparticle coalesced.
And if you thought of these as quarks on
ends of strings, you could think of the last one
being a quark, which annihilated with
the first quark of the other string.
So, yeah, you lose two of them.
But who cares about two when there's an infinite number?
Yeah.
Right.
But you're right.
You have to be careful not
to lose an odd number of fermions.
That's something that shouldn't happen.
Yes.
The next quarter, you continue on with
string theory when you talk about superscripts.
Yes.
Well, we're not going to spend a
lot of time on superstrings, although the things
that I will tell you, strictly speaking, apply
to superstrings and not to the bosonic string.
Are we going—no, I am not going
to go—I'm into the heavy mathematics of superstrings.
What I think we're going to do next time
is I'm going to tell you—well, I'll tell you
a little bit more about string theory.
string theory and about the properties of world sheets
and the symmetries that allow you
to stretch this thing like Turkish taffy
and make different kinds of Feynman diagrams out of it.
But then we're going to move
on to another subject called M-theory,
which is another way of deriving
string theory from a totally different van-
well, I think we have to
talk a little bit about compactification,
about what you do with
these extra dimensions, and we will.
Maybe next time.
But then we will move on to
a totally different origin of string theory
that evolved much, much later
in time, sometime around 1995, 1996,
which started with a completely different picture,
and in which a great many of the
features, the more complicated features of string theory,
are completely transparent, and it's called M-theory.
And we'll start.
We'll start a different starting point,
which leads to exactly the same physics.
So, yeah.
So this process that you just described was
based on the clues from two mesons colliding?
Yes, but it's also the way
two photons collide in string theory.
It's the way any two
open strings collide in string theory.
Incidentally, the analog for closed strings is very similar.
You have two closed strings,
and you pick a particle
from here and one from here,
and you require that they be at the same
point, so that they do this kind of thing.
And then you evolve it as a single string.
Same rules.
Same kind of rules.
And that would correspond to
the scattering of two closed strings.
If you scatter two closed strings, the intermediate thing
that you make will again be a closed string.
Does this only apply to
strings where the particles are fermions?
No, no, no, no, no, no, no, no.
This calculation was originally done for the bosonic string.
And of course, it's more complicated when you
have to keep track of the fermions also.
But you get the same...
Extremely similar. Extremely similar.
But there are some slight
differences that are not important.
What I should say about
this is that the scattering amplitudes...
We said that there was a
photon and a graviton in the system.
Alright, it looked like there was a
spin two particle and a spin one particle,
and you could force them
to be massless if you wanted.
You didn't have much choice.
There weren't enough components to make a massive particle.
So you did that.
Well, then you take these particles and you collide them.
And you work out scattering amplitudes.
Scattering amplitudes are very distinctive and
characteristic for emission of photons and gravitons.
They are not just any old scattering amplitudes.
They have very, very definite
properties which make them extremely special.
The emission and absorption...
of photons cannot be mistaken for the emission
and absorption of scalar particles or other things.
They satisfy some very, very important rules.
Those rules originate from
the conservation of electric charge.
Conserved electric charges emitting photons...
There's almost very, very little ambiguity in what
the emission and absorption of photons look like,
or what a scattering of
photons by charged particles look like,
or even the scattering of photons by photons.
And it was at this point, calculating these diagrams,
where it became completely clear that
these things which we were calling photons
were behaving exactly like photons,
and the things that we were
calling gravitons were behaving exactly like gravitons,
that they satisfied all
the rules for graviton-graviton scattering.
Just saying there was a
particle that looked like a graviton
was a very weak thing.
When all of the scatterings were constructed,
and the rigorous tests of
whether it was satisfying the rules
for scattering of gravitons by massive
things, by massless things, and so forth,
fit perfectly, exactly,
then people realized that they really
were dealing with something that looked like
the scattering of gravitons and photons.
So, these scattering amplitudes played a big role
in establishing with precision that
we were dealing with objects
that did behave like photons, gravitons, and...
Okay, I think we're finished. Yes?
Where does charge come from?
Where does what?
Charge.
Oh, yeah. We haven't talked about that, but...
Okay, we'll talk about it
next time. Remind me. Remind me.
For more, please visit us at stanford.edu.