Stanford University
Alright, we were talking about something called T-duality.
T-duality was very, very important
to the history of the
mathematical developments of string theory.
Let's go back over it again
and discuss it a little more fully.
And then I want to tell you
how it led to the concept of D-brains
and how D-brains have become
something of a mathematical tool
for studying quantum field theories,
the kind of quantum field theories
that have nothing to do with gravity,
but the kind of quantum field theories
that we use in a day-to-day basis
to understand hadrons, quantum electrodynamics,
and even quantum field theories that
are interesting to condensed matter physicists.
We won't get to all of them,
obviously we won't get to this today,
but I'll just try to give
you some picture of what it's about.
Alright, we imagined that there
were some compact directions of,
compact means these small ones which are rolled up.
For simplicity, I will imagine that
the compactification is toroidal, on tori.
In other words, not necessarily two-dimensional torus,
but a one-dimensional torus is
a circle or a line interval
with endpoints being identified.
A two-dimensional torus is a parallelogram,
it doesn't have to be straight,
a parallelogram with opposite sides identified.
A three-dimensional torus is a cube,
or not necessarily a cube, but a...
Parallelipiped, thank you.
A parallelopiped with opposite faces identified,
this point and that point,
and, you know, in front and the back.
So, in general, in any dimension,
the concept of a torus is a well-defined concept.
And those are the easiest cases to study.
Those are the easiest cases to study.
In these cases, of course, supplemented on top of this
is the ordinary four dimensions of space-time.
So this is what's present at every point of space-time,
ordinary space-time.
There are other directions that we can move in,
or that somebody small enough can move in.
And that's the setup.
Let's focus on one particular place in space-time
and ask what could be there.
A particle can be there.
But now let's zero in and zoom in
and ask what that particle looks like
on scales which are so small
that these compact directions become visible.
So let's start with a simple picture that we had.
Just to get started,
we imagined one large direction
and one small direction.
The small direction now would be called a circle.
A circle not because it's embedded in two dimensions
and looks like a circle,
but just because its head meets its tail.
That when you go around, come back,
you come back to the same place.
All right, so that's our space-time.
Where's time?
Oh, I don't know. Time is...
Add time into it.
Time is not drawn on the blackboard.
This is pure space.
In this case, two-dimensional.
But if you like, we
can generalize it to higher dimensions.
The compact directions become tori.
The non-compact directions, the big ones,
just become our three dimensions of space
or however many dimensions of space we want.
Now, in string theory,
particles are strings.
Let's take the case
of...
Not all string theories are the same.
They're different from each other,
but there's a fairly small classification of them.
The string theories that I'm interested in right now
have only closed strings.
We're going to come back to what happens
when you have open strings in a little while.
But for the moment, only closed strings.
No end points.
That's number one.
So they're like rubber bands.
They're like rubber bands.
Here they are. They're closed.
And furthermore, they're what we would call oriented.
Oriented means that there's an intrinsic difference
between going around the string in one direction
rather than the other direction.
It's mathematically like a rubber band
in which on the rubber band
we drew a series of arrows
to indicate direction around.
And we'll keep track of that
orientation.
An example of what that orientation would say
is when the string splits,
when it splits like this,
it will split into two strings
with the same orientation on the blackboard.
So in that sense, orientation
is preserved for these strings.
They remember a sense of which...
Now, of course, that doesn't mean that they're inequivalent.
I mean, there may be a symmetry
in the sense that a string with the opposite orientation
may have all the same properties,
but what it does mean is
that you can compare two strings
to see whether they have the same orientation
or the opposite orientation.
Same with electric charge.
Positive electric charges behave exactly the same way
as negative electric charges in that, for example,
if you replaced in the real
world every electron by a positron,
every proton by an antiproton,
and with it every neutron by an antineutron,
chemistry would remain exactly the same,
or at least to a very, very high precision,
would remain unchanged.
So in that sense, plus
charges are identical to minus charges,
but you can tell the difference between a plus...
No, you can't tell the difference between
a plus charge and a minus charge,
but if you have two charges,
you can tell whether they are the same or opposite.
How? Just see whether they attract or repel.
You can't tell whether they're both
plus or whether they're both minus,
but you can tell...
Okay, so the same is true of oriented strings,
that they have a sense of orientation.
If you replaced every string in string theory
by a string of the opposite orientation,
the theory would be the same,
but if you have two strings,
you can tell whether they're
the same orientation or the opposite.
Let's just call them oriented strings.
Now you can wrap them...
Well, you can do two things.
You can have a string
which is not wound around some compact direction.
There it is.
It's just drawn on the
surface of the two-dimensional world here.
It's free to move.
It can move in this direction,
or it can move around.
So it can have momentum.
And that momentum can be along
the direction of the large directions
or it can be along the short directions.
Or it can be a combination of both.
It can...
When I say it has momentum,
we can think of that as motion.
And it can move this way,
it can move this way,
or it can even move in a...
in a helical pattern like that,
having both components of momentum.
The components of the momentum in the short directions,
in the finite compact directions,
are quantized.
They are quantized in integer multiples
of the inverse radius
or the inverse circumference,
the distance around the closed...
It's called a cycle,
around the closed cycle.
Do the strings have to go all the way around?
Do they have to go
all the way around the cylinder?
Or can they be like you drew it there?
This one isn't going all the way around.
Well, they didn't...
I thought they went from like zero to two pi,
they're closed.
Oh, gosh.
Good point.
In what space?
Sigma?
Ah!
No, no.
This is not sigma.
This is some x.
This could be x.
We could call this direction y around here.
That's space.
That's real space.
Sigma is just a parameter
which changes along the string.
It's just naming the points along the string.
You have a rubber band,
and the rubber band is composed of molecules.
Okay?
The molecules can be named.
The first molecule is Harry.
Then George.
Then Fred.
Then Sarah.
And so forth.
That's sigma.
It's naming the particles as you go around the string.
Okay?
And if the string is closed,
then sigma comes back to itself.
Yeah.
Does the size have to be the same along...
What?
Does the size of the compact direction
have to be the same at
every place in the long direction?
We'll come to that.
The answer is no.
No, it does not.
But we'll come to that.
Okay, so sigma varies along here, along the string.
And it goes from 0 to 2 pi.
But that has nothing whatever to do
with whether the string is wrapped around space.
So, yeah, think of...
I'm sorry, I didn't bring a rubber band.
Think of a rubber band
where on the surface of
the rubber band we've marked off.
Sigma equals 0.
Sigma equals a small number or twice the small number
as we go around the rubber band.
Here it is.
Rubber band.
And we mark off points on the rubber band.
That's sigma.
That sigma has nothing to do
with whether I wrap the rubber band
around my wrist or not.
It's always there.
It's sigma.
It goes around once as the string goes...
As we follow the string around its own shape,
sigma goes from 0 to 2 pi.
It's a completely separate question
of whether the string is wrapped around the extra dimension,
in the same sense that a rubber
band could be wrapped around my wrist.
You can wrap the rubber band around your wrist
if it's an oriented rubber band.
You can wrap it so
that the arrows point this way
or so that the arrows point this way.
So we have two kinds of rubber bands.
One is a rubber band
that's a little bit more rounded.
It's a rubber band that's a little bit more rounded.
So we have two kinds of wrapped strings.
Here's a wrapped or a wound.
The correct term is wound.
Wound around a compact direction.
Here is one of them.
It comes around the other side,
and it points that way.
Okay? That's one.
The other one
goes in the opposite direction.
Let's take two wound strings like this.
Two wound strings like this.
Let me just draw it a little differently.
Let's put...
Do it this way.
This one goes.
What can happen to two wound strings
which are wound in opposite direction?
Well, remember, the basic process of string theory
is for strings to come together and join and split.
Now the rule is
that when they join and split,
orientation is remembered.
A string like this and a string like this can...
Let's put some more orientation arrows on it.
Let's ask how they can join.
They can join like that.
I don't think I need words to describe it.
I think the picture describes it well enough.
The lines have to be...
Or the arrows have to be continuous.
Okay?
What you can't have
is a string splitting somehow like that.
Here the line can't be continuous.
You run into a contradiction
as these points come together.
All right.
So this is the kind of thing that can happen.
The opposite,
namely the opposite,
the time reversal of it can also happen.
Strings which are like this can come together and join
and so forth.
All right.
That's the basic phenomena of splitting and joining.
And it's the thing which
is governed by a coupling constant.
So what can happen here?
What can happen is clear.
This can happen.
Let's see.
Oh, I lost track of the orientation.
Now it's not really wound anymore.
As from the point of view of topology,
you can unwind it into this.
All we've done here is we've taken this,
we've stretched it around,
and then joined it on the far side
to form the original wound pair.
Well, we can undo that.
And now it's unwound.
It's just a...
a single unwound string.
All right.
Now, one way to think about it
is to keep track of winding number.
Winding number can be defined to be positive
for windings which look this way.
We'll call that winding number one.
And if it's wound the other way,
we'll call it winding number minus.
I won't try to give you a mathematical definition,
but winding it on my wrist,
if the...
if the arrows point this way,
we'll call that positive winding.
If they point the other way,
we'll call it negative winding.
If I have a single string
which is wound like so,
what's the winding number?
The winding number is plus one.
If I have another one,
forget this one for the moment,
just throw it over on the side,
we have another one
which is wound this way,
that has winding number minus one.
The two together,
all together have winding number zero.
This has winding number zero.
It's not wound around at all.
So what's preserved
is winding number.
Let's take another case.
Let's imagine now two strings
which are wound the same way.
There's two strings wound the same way.
What can happen to them?
They have winding number two.
The sum of the two of them
have winding number two.
What can happen?
Well,
let's draw it over here again.
These are going this way
and they come around here.
They're both going the same way.
You can't unwind this.
You can do something.
You can have a process of splitting and joining
which does this.
Which interconnects them a new way.
Can you see what I've drawn?
We've crossed them.
We've crossed them,
but still after they've crossed,
the arrows are still continuous.
There's no contradiction
in the direction of the arrows.
This also has winding number two.
It's one string with winding number two.
This is two strings,
each one with winding number one.
Each one with winding number one,
but the sum total of the winding numbers is two.
All right, so here's again another example.
Winding number is conserved.
You can't change the winding number,
although you can change
the number of connected components.
So if you have winding number of a hundred,
you could have one string wound around a hundred times.
You could have two strings each wound
the same way fifty times.
You could have a hundred strings each wound once,
and they can all communicate
in the sense that you can morph
from one configuration to the other,
but you can't change the winding number.
So winding number is an absolutely conserved quantity
in this kind of string theory.
It never can change.
Let's forget winding,
we're going to come back
to winding number in a moment.
Well, maybe we should discuss winding number.
Yeah, okay.
This one over here,
that can just be thought
of as a tiny little particle.
Let's just think of it as a little particle.
It's a string, but it's a particle.
What's it characterized by?
It's characterized by components of moment,
it's characterized by many things,
shape and all sorts of other things,
but in particular,
let's characterize it by its components of momentum.
In particular, the component of momentum
in the, um,
in the,
this direction over here.
The component of momentum in that direction
has to be an integer number,
let's call it n,
integer number of a quantum of momentum,
and the quantum of momentum
has to do with the circumference.
Let's just call it the radius around here, r.
Distance around here I'll call r.
It's a circumference strictly,
but I'm just going to call it r,
uh,
because r is the standard term for it.
Um,
the quantum of momentum in this direction,
and also incidentally,
the quantum of energy in that direction,
if these are massless particles,
energy and momentum are proportional to each other,
for example, if they were gravitons,
if they were gravitons moving this way or this way,
the energy
is also quantized in that unit,
and so,
the energy of the momentum is,
the momentum can have either sign,
it can be plus or minus,
the momentum,
the energy is always plus,
but the same amount,
n over r.
It has momentum,
n over r,
and it has an energy,
also n over r.
That's the, uh,
these are,
that's the n over r,
and that's the, uh,
and that's the n over r.
And that's the energy due to momentum,
and in particular,
momentum along the small direction here.
It's quantized.
So that's, uh,
that's unwound particles,
and the contribution of energy due to momentum.
Oh, let's think about now what,
uh,
yeah.
What is the momentum of,
what is the momentum of a string moving in space?
Basically, it's just the velocity
of the center of mass.
It's just the velocity of the center,
just like a rubber band,
just like a rubber band.
Its momentum
is its mass density,
which for simplicity we can take to be one,
uh,
times, uh,
it's just its mass,
which we can take to be one,
for a rubber band,
times its velocity,
so,
the velocity,
the momentum is proportional to the velocity,
and we can think of this as
the x d tau.
Tau is the time variable
that describes the motion of the string
in the quantum,
in the simple quantum mechanics of,
uh, that we've described previously.
And it's got to be,
it's got to be an integer multiples.
Now let's think about the wound strings,
the strings which are wound around.
What is the typical energy of a wound string?
Well, strings have a certain tension.
Let's just, uh, work in units
in which that tension is one,
but tension is energy per unit length.
So for energy per unit length,
if there's a given energy per unit length,
then the energy of a wound string
is not in divided by r,
but it's some other integer,
I'm going to call the other integer w,
w stands for winding number,
times r.
The energy of a collection of strings
which are wound around here
are the integer winding number times r,
whereas the energy of a string
which is not wound around the compact direction
is in divided by r.
So I think we talked about this last time,
but let's discuss it again a little bit.
Let's suppose that r is very small.
All right, here we have the spectrum
of the strings which are not wound.
The separation between the levels,
is large.
Large because one over r is large.
So it looks like this.
With the separation being of order one over r.
Here's n equals zero,
here's n equals one, and so forth.
Now let's look at the spectrum of the wound strings.
In other words, the energy levels of the wound strings,
those also come in integer multiples.
Zero.
Winding number one,
winding number two,
winding number minus one,
winding number minus two.
But now it's w times r,
so that means if r is large,
what did I say, r
is large or r is small?
I think I said r was small.
What did I say?
I said r is large or small?
r is small.
Okay, so that makes the separation large here,
but it makes it very small here.
Now let's go to the other extreme.
I know that we talked about this before,
but I want to reiterate it again.
Let's go to the other extreme.
This is r much less than
some unit of length in string theory,
the natural unit of length in string theory.
Let's just call it one.
Here's r much bigger than one.
What do the energy levels look like?
Well, for r much bigger than one,
one over r is small,
and these excitations here are very close together.
What about these?
Here r is very large,
so it takes a large energy to wrap around.
They look like this.
Suppose all you knew,
all you could measure about these particles,
namely the things associated with the compact directions.
The only thing that you
can measure about the compact directions,
let's suppose,
was the energy of the particles.
And you're trying to figure out
what the radius of compactification,
that's known as the radius of compactification,
what is the radius of compactification?
Well,
your problem is,
how do you tell the difference
between particles which have energy
with respect to the compact direction
because they have momentum,
or because they have winding number?
You can't, obviously.
Just from the energy levels, you can't tell.
So,
with this particular spectrum,
there's an ambiguity.
Are you,
in the theory with a small compactification,
in which large separations between different momenta,
small separations between different winding number,
or are you in a world
with a very large radius of compactification,
and in which the role of winding number
and momentum has been interchanged?
You think, well,
maybe you can do a
lot of other kind of experiments,
maybe you could scatter these particles together,
see what comes off.
One of the very, very remarkable mathematical facts
about string theory
is that
the inability to tell which kind of world you're in
is rigorously correct
for everything that you can calculate about these strings.
Collisions between them,
that two different theories
with very different radii of compactification,
if you interchange winding
with, let's call it with momentum
around the compact direction,
the theories behave in exactly the same way.
So, conclusion.
In certain sense,
it doesn't make sense to think of the compactification
as smaller than a certain size.
There's a certain size where they cross over
and where they interchange,
and if the size of the compactification
is smaller than that,
it's just entirely equivalent
to a larger compactification
with winding and momentum interchanged.
Does that mean that the winding number
is a mathematical convenience
rather than a physical property?
Well, I don't know what to say.
It says that there's a symmetry.
It says there's a symmetry
and that there's...
Physicists use the term duality.
Which means an equivalence
between different descriptions
of the same thing.
Is there an R of interest
where these two things are the same?
Mm-hmm.
In some units, it's R equals one.
And there you have some extra special symmetry
that you...
Not only can't you tell
which kind of theory you're in,
but you can't tell which are which.
They're the same.
Yes.
There is a special point.
Now, I wrote an equation over here
that momentum is equal to dx d tau.
Let me make that a little more precise.
Every point on the string has a motion.
In particular, I'm thinking about the motion
around the compact direction.
But different parts of the string
should, in principle, be moving different
than other parts of the string.
It could be differentially moving
in different directions,
different speeds, and so forth.
The full momentum that we're talking about
when we talk about the momentum
is actually the sum of the momenta
of all the little bits of string.
You can either sum it
or you can think of it as an integral
over the entire string
of the velocity,
dx d tau.
And which x am I talking about?
I'm talking about y, actually,
the one that goes around the string,
the y d tau.
What about the winding number?
Anybody got a mathematical expression
for the winding number?
Imagine now a string
which is wound.
The simplest possibility
is that it's wound around here.
This is the y coordinate.
The y coordinate is periodic.
It comes back to itself.
But the string also has a sigma coordinate.
The string also has a sigma coordinate.
And that's embedded in the string.
If the string is wound
in this very simple way,
then another way of saying it
is that sigma is the number of points,
and sigma is proportional to y.
Actually, y divided by
the total radius of compactification,
I guess.
If y comes back to itself
after going distance r,
and sigma comes back to itself
after going around once,
then the right relationship is that
sigma is y over r.
It's just another way of saying
that as you go around sigma,
as you go around the rubber band,
the rubber band goes around
the y direction.
Well, now look at this.
Let's look at d sigma by dy.
That's just 1 over r.
d sigma by dy,
let's just take d sigma by dy.
d sigma by dy
is proportional
to the little spacing
between here and here,
and the total winding number
is the sum of the little bit
of d sigma by dy
as you go around the string.
In other words,
the winding number
actually, this is right.
The winding number
is the sum of the little bit
of d sigma by dy
as you go around the string.
r times this.
And the winding number
I believe is
I had an equation.
Where did it go?
y over r
is equal to sigma.
So d sigma by dy
is 1 over r.
The total winding number
is 1 over r
times the integral
dy by d sigma.
Does this make sense
that the total winding number
what's the integral of a derivative?
Would you start with the y?
Usually the integral of a derivative
in lots of cases is just plain 0.
If a thing comes back to itself
when you go all the ways around.
But y doesn't come back to itself
y itself
changes by 2 pi.
So the integral dy by d sigma
is just the total number
of times that the string wraps
around that direction.
So this is kind of curious.
t duality
this funny duality between
winding number and momentum
is equivalent to interchanging
n and w,
interchanging r and 1 over r,
and interchanging dy by d tau
with dy by d sigma.
Funny mathematical construction.
Keep that in mind.
That t duality
is interchanging winding
and momentum,
interchanging r with 1 over r,
and interchanging the derivative
of y,
that's the position of the string,
dy by d tau
with dy by d sigma
where
yeah, dy by d tau
with dy by d sigma
derivative. This is partial derivative.
It's pretty abstract.
But this is an exact
symmetry of string theory.
If you make these interchanges,
nothing changes.
Say it once again.
If the symmetry is
dy by d tau
swap dy by d tau
Swap dy by d tau
for dy by d sigma.
Now, the reason I introduced this
we'll see why.
I didn't have to tell you this,
but I'm telling you now because
we're going to use it later.
Wouldn't that apply
a relationship between
tau and sigma?
No, it's not a relationship.
You interchange them.
Wherever you saw the expression
dy by d tau,
you replace it by the expression
dy by d sigma.
It's a weird thing to do,
but
in all
observable quantities,
scattering amplitudes, energy levels,
all of the properties of
string theory don't change
if you make those changes.
Let's talk about something else.
Why would the string
want to be
wound around the dimension?
They don't want anything.
Why would it ever
get in that state?
If it can be
in the other state?
Somebody may hit this string
over here with some energy.
Hitting it with some energy
among other things may stretch it out.
In fact, it may stretch out
to look like this.
You blast it with a lot of energy.
I've drawn a very neat
configuration over here, of course.
But if I blast it with
a lot of energy, it might be much more
complicated than that,
but still have this kind of
configuration.
Now, once you've done that,
and you take into account that
strings split and join,
then this can
separate itself into two
strings with opposite winding number.
Once you've
created two strings with opposite winding
number that are no longer connected,
they can separate from each other.
They can separate from each other,
and when they separate from each other,
well, then you've got an isolated
string with winding number one,
and another one that you can
just send off to Alpha Centauri
and never see it again.
The answer is,
that in general, you cannot prevent it
from happening. You may have to
in particular,
if the distance around here is large,
then it takes a large amount
of energy to create these
winding strings. Here it is.
The, uh, well, let's see, we...
Yeah.
The energy
itself was proportional to R
for winding number.
So, with a small
amount of energy, it's not going to happen.
You don't have enough energy
to stretch the string that far.
But, if you collide
two strings with a large amount
of energy, they splatter
all over the place, they stretch out
in wild and chaotic
directions, and there's
some probability that, uh,
that they'll reconnect.
It will not change the total winding
number, but it will take
a single string
or perhaps two strings which are
not wound, which collide with each other,
and convert out of them
something with, uh,
two strings of opposite winding
number. Once that happens,
they can separate and they go off.
So the answer is generally
that it will happen
in collisions if you don't
have it that way to begin with.
The same question occurs for electric charges.
If you start with a neutral world,
why
are there electrons?
Well, even if there weren't electrons,
there's got to be something to start with.
If there's nothing, there's nothing.
But maybe you just started with photons.
You take some photons,
you collide them together,
and what comes out is electrons
and positrons.
If you take the positrons and you throw them
away, you don't throw them away, but you push
them off to some distant place, you're left
with electrons. That's all.
So, um,
you can't have,
you can't forbid these things.
You can't forbid them,
and eventually you will create them.
Now, these winding numbers
and these momenta,
these momentum quantum numbers,
these quantized momentum,
are not only in some sense similar
to electric charge,
but they have all of the properties
of electric charge.
In particular,
two strings of opposite momentum,
one
is the opposite of the
electric charge,
and the other is the opposite of the
electric charge.
Two strings going around one,
can I do this? Let's see.
Oh yeah, I can do it.
Two strings going around the opposite way,
with respect
to the big dimensions of space.
So here they are.
Two strings,
these have the same, no, these have the same
winding number. Okay, that's easy, that's this.
Two strings with the same
winding number will repel.
I'll tell you why in a moment.
Two strings with
opposite winding number will attract.
What is this
attraction and repulsion?
This attraction and repulsion
actually corresponds to the
gravitational attraction and
repulsion of the higher dimensional
theory. If we live
in
a world of, let's say, three dimensions,
three space dimensions,
and we add in one more tiny
direction,
then strings which are
wound oppositely,
maybe in different places in
the big dimensions, different places
in space, we have a string wrapped
this way, we have a string wrapped that way,
they'll attract each other.
If they have opposite winding number,
they'll attract each other in our
ordinary three dimensional sense.
Likewise, if they
have the
same winding number,
they will repel each other.
So they behave like electrical charges.
Where does electrical repulsion
and attraction come from?
It comes from the electromagnetic field,
and of course the electromagnetic field
is deeply connected with photons
and so forth.
Where does this attraction come from?
And the answer is
it comes from gravitation.
But not gravitation
in the four dimensional sense,
but gravitation in the five
dimensional sense, in the extra
dimensional sense.
In the theory of extra dimensions,
the Einstein gravity
in the extra dimensions
manifests itself
in the phenomenon
of attraction
between like momenta,
nope, cross it out,
attraction between opposite momenta
in the compact direction,
and repulsion
of things with the same momenta.
That's not obviously easy to see,
I've told you this before,
it's not something I'm telling you for the first time.
And in fact, you can
relate it to
Einstein's field equations.
Let's, uh, let's
I'm not going to
relate it to Einstein's field equations
in any depth, I'm just going to
discuss the origin
of the electromagnetic
field,
or the analog electromagnetic field
that's associated with this
electrical type behavior of these particles.
There must be something
like an electric field, there must be something
like a magnetic field if they're behaving so much
like electrically charged particles.
What is it?
Okay, so
first, just ordinary Maxwell equations.
The electric and magnetic
field are
describable in terms of a vector
potential, a four-dimensional vector
potential, a
mu.
You build up
the
magnetic field as the curl
of the vector potential
and the
electric field as related to the
time derivative of the
vector potential. It's a four
vector, it has four components.
Let's go
to gravity
in five dimensions.
Gravity is described by
a metric tensor.
The metric tensor, let's call it
G M N.
Why don't I use mu and nu?
I'm saving mu and nu for the four dimensions
of ordinary space-time.
But we're now talking about
a five-dimensional world.
So let's use for the five-dimensional world
M and N.
But what do M and N run over?
They run over the ordinary
dimensions of
ordinary space-time
plus one more direction.
So we can write G M N
as having various
components. G mu
nu, that's the ordinary
dimensions.
And then G
mu
five. Five is the
fifth extra dimension.
And then what else?
G five
five.
Those are the components
of the gravitational field.
What about G five mu?
I wrote G mu five. What about G
five mu?
Symmetric tensors.
The same thing.
These are the independent components
of the gravitational field
in five dimensions.
Well, this one here,
that's just a metric of four-dimensional
space-time. So it's just a usual
Einstein gravitational field.
Nothing new there.
Here we have something
that has an index.
It has a
five index here, but the five index is
this hidden direction. We can't see it.
But it also has a mu index.
Which means that it's a four
vector. We would mistake
this object for a four vector. It has
four components. It's like a mu.
Let's make that identification, because that's
the correct identification.
And what about G five five?
That has
no components
in the usual four-dimensional sense.
So it must be a scalar.
That scalar is usually called
phi. It's called a dilaton, or
sometimes called a dilaton.
But it's almost always called
phi.
What is G five five?
It's the component of the metric
around the fifth direction.
It tells you how
big the fifth direction is.
If G five five is big,
it's just a metric. It's the
square of the distance around the fifth
direction is what it is.
If G five five is big,
the fifth direction is big.
If G five five is small, the fifth direction
is small.
The metric tensor in five
dimensions is a field. It can vary
from place to place.
All of these things can vary from place to
place. This is
just the usual gravitational
field varying from place to place. This
becomes
an analog of the electromagnetic
field, which can vary from place to place.
And this is a scalar, which can vary from
place to place. But what does that scalar mean?
That scalar
is the size of the fifth direction.
That can vary from place to place.
Somebody asked me that before.
And you can imagine waves in space
where the waves
of space are not waves of
electromagnetism, they're not waves of gravity,
they're waves of varying size
for the fifth dimension.
Okay, but
nevertheless, the quiescent ordinary
vacuum doesn't have
such waves. It's fixed.
But in general,
the size can vary from
place to place.
Okay, this is an
electromagnetic field.
If this is an electromagnetic field,
then it's
also a gravitational field.
And it's an analog
electromagnetic field.
Thought of as a gravitational field, what are the
sources of gravitational field?
There are things like
energy and momentum. In
particular, the sources
of mixed components
of a field like this are components of momentum.
So the
source of this component of
the gravitational field is actually the
momentum in the fifth
direction, the flow of momentum
in the fifth direction.
That means that the
source of
this analog vector potential
is going to be the
component of momentum going around
the fifth direction.
Lesson?
The momentum quantum number,
the one, where is it?
The momentum quantum number
over here
can be thought of
as electric charge
in an
analog, what's that?
In the
theory in which the mu5 component
of the gravitational
field is the
electromagnetic field. Electric charge,
momentum, electric field,
are
component of the metric.
Well,
good, that's easy, that was
easy.
That was
What about, and of course
we go a little bit further, and
we can say that
the
electric, that the electric
field is associated with the
graviton, with the graviton
itself. Okay,
now let's come to the
winding number.
So I'm sorry,
is phi then proportional to n, or?
No.
N,
no,
n is an integer.
It's related to r.
It's not quantized. It's related to the
size of that dimension.
And it can vary from place to place
continuously and smoothly.
Right?
It's called a
dilatant, and it's a
wave field that, if string theory
was right, should exist in some form or another.
But in any case,
it's part of the mathematics of
string theory.
Let's come to the
winding number now. I told
you that the winding number also behaves
with this property that opposite
winding numbers attract.
Like winding numbers
repel, they also
behave like electric charges.
But not the same
kind of electric charge
as the momentum quantum numbers.
It's as if there were
two kinds of electric fields,
two kinds of electromagnetisms
living
side by side, two kinds
of photons,
two kinds of charges,
winding number
associated with something we could call
winding photons,
and
momentum
quantum number associated
with momentum photons,
but momentum photons are just
a piece of the gravitational field.
In other words, they're gravitons
which are polarized along
the mu-5 direction. So what
are the
field, what is the field
or the analog of photons
which
is emitted and absorbed
by winding number?
Not by momentum, but by winding number.
And here we know the answer.
We'd have to go back
several lectures,
fairly early lectures,
but let me remind you.
This is probably
something you've forgotten.
I told you, but I don't think
I stressed it very hard.
Let's go back
to the spectrum of closed
strings. The closed strings
what kind of states
are there of closed strings?
We start
with the closed string
being totally unexcited,
and then what do we do with it?
We excite
oscillations on it. We excite
oscillations with the creation and
annihilation operators
which create and excite
waves on the string.
They're not creation and annihilation operators
for particles, they're creation and
annihilation operators for waves
moving along the string.
These are closed strings.
Let me just remind you
what kind of operators there are.
There are creation
and annihilation operators.
I'll just think about creation operators.
And I won't put a little plus
because we'll wind up with too many indices.
A creates a unit
of excitation.
What labels it?
Well, first of all, the A's
are labeled by directions
of space. Directions of space
are perpendicular to the momentum
of the object, of the string.
So they're labeled by directions
of space. Let's call it I.
I
can equal
if the string is going down the
z-axis, it can be
x, it can be y,
it can be x1,
x2,
or it can be a compact direction,
y.
So the I's vary over all the
directions of space, including
the ones which are wrapped up.
That's one thing there.
Now what's the other index that
depends on?
The frequency of the oscillator.
And that was an integer,
and it tells you how much energy
when you create one of these oscillations.
Creates an energy
proportional to n.
Alright, so n
is related to the frequency.
I
is related to direction
and space.
And one more thing.
Remember what it was? For closed strings.
Whether the wave is propagating
around the string. Remember, the
string is oriented, there's little arrows.
Whether the wave is going one way
around the string or the other way around the string.
I don't remember,
does anybody remember how we labeled the two?
Let's just call it left moving waves
and right moving waves.
A, I, N. And left and right
here are purely some
symbolic, they refer to
the direction
on the string, not left and right
in real space.
Okay, now there was a rule.
I told you the rule, I called it
level matching.
It's a rule, I'm not
going to go into the rule
now, I think I explained it
a little bit, what it had
to do with, but it's a rule.
And the rule is the amount of
energy in left moving waves
must equal
the amount of energy in right moving waves.
That's a fundamental rule,
the rule of string theory, the mathematics
goes to hell in a hand basket if you
violate it.
And so let's see what kind of states
we have. We can first of all have the state
with no energy in it at all.
That's a tachyon.
It's not there in super string theory, but
in the simple versions of the string
theory, and it has minus
two units of energy. We work
that out. Minus two
units of energy, and it's a tachyon.
Bad thing, we don't want it.
What's the first excitation?
What's the next
energy up? Well,
the next energy up is to hit it with
the lowest frequency
oscillator to excite
one unit of energy
with n equals one.
So, for example, we could
hit it with a
i, i can be
any one of the directions of space,
one,
the lowest oscillator,
left,
or
a1
i right
o.
But neither of these states
are a legitimate
option. And the reason
is because this one has one unit of
left moving energy and no units of right
moving energy. This one has one
unit of right moving energy and no units
of left moving energy, and so it doesn't
satisfy this principle that the amount
of energy in left and right have to balance.
Okay, so these are gone.
They're not there.
What's the next thing up?
The next thing up is to
apply
two units of the
lowest oscillator,
one left and one right,
to make sure that you have balanced energy going
left and right.
And that means a i
one
left
times a j
one right.
i and j
are two directions of space.
Okay, they are
the two directions of space.
For simplicity,
let's imagine the directions of space
are the usual three directions
of space plus one more,
namely the fifth direction,
the thing that I called y here.
One more direction of space.
The one more, and we apply this of course
to the vacuum.
These are the things we identified with
graviton and other massless
particles
with polarizations
that have to do with i and j.
Well,
there is something
new when we add this fifth
direction.
One or both of these indices
can now be in the fifth direction.
Earlier,
before we discussed the fifth direction,
i and j could only be ordinary directions
of space, and these
corresponded to gravitons
which have polarizations
which are like photons,
they have polarizations, and the polarization
is characterized by two directions
of space.
But now we have something new.
We can have i be the ordinary direction
of space,
and this one being the fifth direction of space.
The internal direction,
the small direction.
Okay, now we have something
which has a vector index.
The fifth direction
here, we don't even call that a direction
of space normally,
and so it has the same kind
of index structure
that a photon would have.
This is like a photon.
It has a polarization,
let's say moving down the z-axis,
this could be polarized either x or y,
or however many dimensions
we have to worry about,
and this is very similar to a photon.
But there are two ways to do it.
You could have this one being left
and this one being right,
or you can have
a i 1 right,
a 1 5 left.
There are two possibilities now,
and it seems like that means
that there are two kinds of particles
that behave like photons,
that are similar to photons.
So, let's say
that there are two kinds of particles
that behave like photons,
that are similar to photons.
The correct thing to do is
to add them and subtract them
in the sense of quantum mechanics
to linear superpositions,
but whatever there is,
there's going to be two types of objects
which have the index structure
of a photon.
There's going to be two kinds of photon fields.
The one with the sum,
that's identified with ordinary
graviton moving down the z-axis.
The other one
is identified
with another field
a separate field
that also has
a structure similar to a photon
and guess what it is connected with?
It is the field,
the electromagnetic-like field
whose sources are what?
Winding number.
So one linear combination
is associated with momentum
and one linear combination
is associated with
winding number.
These two things work together
and they're not linked.
One of them is associated with gravitons
which are
the field quanta
of the gravitational field
and the other one
is associated with something called
B mu nu
which is different than the graviton
different properties
but also
gives rise
its mixed component
is also like a photon.
So here's what we can say now.
What is T-duality?
And this is a field.
This is a field
which exists in string theory
called the Ramond
the Kalb-Ramond field
not important what it's called
it is another field
which appears in string theory.
Which one is the singlet
and which one is the triplet?
Which is the singlet
and which is the triplet?
Oh no no no no no no no
wait a minute
both of these are polarized like photons.
There's one more
nobody asked me about
what about A5-5
A5-A5
left-right
that one's the one that behaves like the scalar
that's the one
associated
whose field quanta
these are the field quanta
of this one over here
okay
namely the radius of the
of the compact direction
They're all here
which one corresponded to
the winding number
the other corresponded
the one with the plus sign corresponds to momentum
and that's the one that's associated with gravitons
the one with the minus sign
is associated with
with the winding number
yeah
okay so now we have a more complete
idea of about T-duality
it involves
momentum being interchanged
with winding number
it involves R being
interchanged with one over R
it involves
replacing the x by d sigma
with the x by d tau
this is the integral of this
is winding number
the integral of this is momentum
and finally it involves
interchanging
g mu 5
with b mu 5
alright
so these theories have more
now of course
not clear that the ordinary world
does have such fields
we don't know
of real particle candidates
for all these fields
we don't
so this is at the moment
a mathematical construction
and we're exploring a mathematical construction
there's lots of ideas
about how to use these
constructions
but
for the moment
I think we should regard this as an exploration
of the mathematics of the theory
there's plenty of room in physics
for these objects incidentally
but I don't want to get into
the phenomenology of them
good so there we are
that's what T-duality is
after five minutes
we're going to come back and talk about
T-duality for open strings
and how it leads to a new concept
a completely new concept
called D-brains
so let's take a break
um
yeah
ok
so we've figured out what
T-duality is
this very strange interchange
of big compact geometries
with small ones
and various other things going on
I want to concentrate
now
on the aspect
of T-duality that has to do with
well let's erase
some blackboard here
ah this one
now you're going to see
the kind of gymnastics
that
the kind of
deductions that people have made over the years
as T-duality is one of them
they're
implicit in the mathematics
many of them are very surprising
we're going to talk about
D-brains
and how one was forced to have these
new objects in the theory
which are called D-brains
D stands for Dirichlet
Dirichlet had nothing to do with them
he was dead for many hundreds of years
they should be called P-brains
for Polchinski
but P-brain was already a term in use
brain is spelled
B-R-A-N-E
it's a membrane
and one speaks of
D-N-brains
D stands for Dirichlet
not for the dimension of space
N stands for the
dimensionality of the brain
a string is a one-brain
a membrane is a two-brain
a solid three-dimensional
is a single-brain
a string is a one-brain
a membrane is a two-brain
a solid three-dimensional chunk
which may be embedded in higher dimensions
but solid three is a three-brain
and so forth
so there's D-N-brain
where do they come from
what do they do
what's their
they're not just made up things
they were essential to the consistency of the theory
the mathematics absolutely demanded them
and
and which the mathematicians were entirely surprised by
and they turned out to be able to confirm them
but this is some of
this is now part of the gymnastics of string theory
and
D-brains have played an enormously powerful role
also in the applications of it
so let's talk about open strings now
D-brains have to do with open strings
open strings
what's the winding number of an open string
open strings don't have stable winding numbers
if you have an open string
on a compact space
now this picture
is sort of short-hand
for all of the compact directions
of which there are presumably six
in superstring theory
and all of the open
uncompact directions
alright but let's imagine now
that in addition to closed strings
there are open strings
open strings now have endpoints
we can't classify them
with winding number
it doesn't make sense to classify them
they're not wound
so we have to
we have to think
about what happens to them
when we do this process of T-duality
T-duality
was a phenomena discovered
in closed string theory
but surprisingly
it also makes sense for open string theory
and I'm going to show you what it says
there's something rather remarkable
something which is confirmed in other ways
but this is the simple way to think about it
there's a string, an open string
and what are the rules for open strings
do you remember what the rules are
for what goes on
at the end of an open string
the boundary conditions
on the end of an open string
Neumann
the end of an open string
should satisfy
dx or dy
again
this is y
this is x
any of the coordinates
but let's in particular
well let's write them both
dx by d sigma equals 0
dy by d sigma equals 0
and what does that correspond to
that corresponds to
the idea that the end of the string
here's a string
it's made up of a lot of tiny
infinitesimal mass points
and supposing the end of the string
had some net stretching
the x by d sigma was not equal to 0
that would exert a force
on the very last molecule
well
as you subdivide the molecules
into smaller and smaller structures
to go to the continuous limit of the string
the molecules get lighter and lighter
and lighter
and what can you put on a mass
on a thing of arbitrarily small mass
without having it accelerate
with an infinite acceleration
the answer is 0 in the limit
that means that
the string cannot afford to have any
net stretching at the end of the string
so that's where these conditions come from
the x by d sigma
the y by d sigma
should be equal to 0
and that's to forbid infinite accelerations
either in the x direction
or the y direction
of course
there is another possibility
and that's that somebody is
holding the end of the string
and applying an enormous force
to keep it from moving
but if nobody is standing there
holding the end of the string
then
if there's any net tension
in the end of the string
it will accelerate infinitely
to basically
to remove that stretching
ok now
what about
t duality
so suppose now
that this was a small compact direction
and we want to replace the theory
it's very very much smaller
extremely small
we want to say wait a minute
this is supposed to be equivalent
to a theory with a large compact direction
here's the large compact direction
enormously large
could be cosmologically large
what do I do with these open strings
ok
well we're supposed to replace
winding number by momentum
and momentum was
what was momentum related to
it was related to dx by d tau
right
velocity
what was winding number related to
dx by d sigma
namely
exactly what goes on here
ok
I should actually write
since I'm mostly interested in the
compact directions for the moment
let's concentrate on
the compact direction
t duality involves
among other things
replacing
every place you see it
dy by d tau
by dx
or dy by d sigma
by dy by d tau
so what does it say then
about open strings
open strings
when they undergo this process of
t duality
what you have to do is you have to
change the boundary conditions
and the boundary conditions at the end of the string
become the
x by d tau equals zero
or in this case
we're not
sorry the t duality is
associated with the compact directions
we don't want to do that
only the compact directions
are being interchanged smoothly
small with large
we're not diddling at all with the
uncompact direction
one compact direction
y goes
y
radius in the y direction
becomes big
alright
the rule was
we were supposed to replace dy by d sigma
by dy by d tau
if strings
originally moving on the surface
had Neumann boundary conditions
that's dy by d sigma equals zero
after t duality
they have Dirichlet boundary conditions
what does it mean to say
that dy by d tau
is equal to zero
oh incidentally
this is only at the end points
this is at the ends of the string
it means the end points
are forbidden from moving
so wherever they started
they are stuck at
where are they
stuck?
well wherever they are stuck
there is something holding them there
it means that this theory has
objects in it
which can nail down
the ends of strings
there are strings
there must be
if t duality is to make sense
there must be objects in the theory
which can nail down the ends of strings
you start with a theory with no such object
and the strings just move freely
and after t duality
you discover there is some kind of object
in the theory which has nailed down
the location of the string
it's nailed down only the y component
we have not played around with the x's
the x's are still free to move
the compact direction here
is now nailed down
so where is it nailed down
let's uh
here's a space
it's nailed down some place
some place
and y
y goes around this way
let's put that place right over here
there is something here
which is capable of holding the ends of strings
nailing them down
that object is called a d brain
d for Dirichlet
and
it wasn't put in by hand
instead one asked
what if there are open strings in a theory
and the theory has t duality
which it must have
for reasons that are
by now well understood
then
what happens to the open strings
when you interchange
the small compact direction
for the large compact direction
and the answer is that you discover something new
you discover some new kind of object
which
is holding down those things
excuse me
is it necessary that the
y value be the same
for the two ends
no
I think you're asking whether this can bend
well you've just drawn it
I drew it so that it
but it can't be up here
oh yeah yeah yeah yeah it could
that's right
but the simplest case is where it's just fixed
fixed in some position
now what position can you
do you put it at here here here
well the answer is
that you better be able to put it anywheres
so
this has to be a movable object
because there was nothing special about one point
in space and the other point in space
along these axes
so there's got to be a movable object
which functions
as an anchor point for the ends
of strings
if it's movable
then you can be quite sure that it's also bendable
ah
relativity can't make sense
with absolutely rigid objects
and so it will also be bendable
ah
but let's just not bend it for the moment
and
strings can attach themselves to it
strings attached to it
can exist
a string can come
oh well let's let's good
these are called D-Brain
first of all
supposing we took
let's take an example
supposing we took 10 dimensional string theory
which has 9 dimensions of space
9 dimensions of space
and we made a string
and we made one of them compact
and then
introduced a D-Brain
in this way
what would be the dimensionality of the D-Brain
would it be 1
no
we've pinned down
one direction
and left the other
the other 8
and we've got
8 directions of space
free to move around
alright here's a tabletop
that tabletop is 2 dimensional
if there's an object attached to the tabletop
how many directions is it free to move in
and how many is it constrained in
it's free to move in 2 directions
here's a string
here's a string with 2 ends
or my finger is the end of a string
it's free to move in 2 directions
and constrained
in it's 3rd direction
so if I constrain
one dimension
if I constrain
it creates for me in 3 dimensional space
a 2 dimensional surface
supposing
I'm now in 9 dimensions
of space
and I constrain the end of a string
I constrain
one of the dimensions
it becomes
an 8 dimensional surface
that the string can move around
now suppose
there was no reason
for only constraining
you can do the same thing
with any number
of compact directions
you can
play this
t-duality game with any
subset of the compact
directions
you can play that same game
and you can in the same way
construct v-brains
which pin down any number
of the coordinates
that the end of a string can move in
alright so let's take 3 dimensional space again
let's suppose now
we've played this game
and we've constrained the vertical position
by
doing this t-duality trick
with respect to the vertical direction
supposing I also do it now
with respect to the front to back direction
I constrain the motion
of the position of the end of a string
so it's constrained
vertically and
this way
that means that
the end of the string
has to move
along
the
the intersection
of this plane
with that plane
so if I constrain 2 dimensions
what kind of brain am I talking about
a d
in this case d1
but if I started with 9 dimensions of space
I would have
so each constraint removes a direction
that's free to move in
alright
for that reason
you can have in 9 dimensions
by playing this game over and over again
with the different directions
associated with the compact space
you can have
d8 brains
d7 brains, d6 brains
all the way down to
what's the maximum number
you can
just get rid of the freedom
to move in any of the directions
of space
then what does the
then what would you call the brain
d0
d0 it's a point
it's a point in space
that the string is connected to
and it's not free to
move along any of the directions
that's a d0 brain
d0
d0 dimension means a point
you can have from d0 brains
to d8 brains
they all make sense
and they're all
their existence
in some sense is all necessary
to the consistency of the theory
d0 brains are a new kind of particle
an unexpected new kind of part
yeah
you said you weren't removing them from
non-compact directions
so wouldn't you really start subtracting from 6
subtracting from 6
yes
no no no no
not really no
no
I'll show you why in a moment
ok
we've played this game with the compact directions
but now let's imagine
having done this operation
let's imagine shrinking and shrinking
this until it becomes
arbitrarily small what happens on this side
it gets bigger and bigger and bigger
ok so eventually
on this side it can be so big
that it's completely mistaken
for a non-compact
for a non-compact dimension
in other words
if a dimension of space
is big enough
for all practical purposes
it becomes non-compact
what we've demonstrated by this series of arguments
is that even in the non-compact directions
there must be objects which are
the anchors of strings
they can be oriented along
compact directions
they can be oriented along non-compact directions
any number of them
and of any dimensionality starting with
0 and going up to
8 dimensions
actually
you can go up to 9 dimensions
but that means they completely fill space
and that simply means that we're talking about
open string theory in which the open strings
are just free to move
but we wouldn't call them brains
there are things that people call
d-1 brains but you don't want to know
they're not
real concepts
ok so you start here's a d-0 brain
it's a point in space
and a string end can end on it
where's the other end of the string
it could be on another d-0 brain
or
it could be stretched out to infinity
that's not a good thing
because it becomes infinitely massive
or it could even come back to the same point
the same d-brain
that's a d-0 brain
what's the next one up
a d-1 brain
something called a d-1 brain
something very interesting about a d-1 brain
it's a line
now as you already pointed out
it does not have to be a straight line
we deduce their existence
in this way
but once we know that they exist
and once we know we're talking about a relativistic theory
they have to be bendable
if they're bendable
they can even bend around on themselves
their structures
which are physically
physical objects
and they have to be
they have strings connected to them
but now let's forget the strings
that are connected to them
the strings connected to them could be like this
let's forget the strings
that are connected to them
and just look at them
this is a one-dimensional object
it's called a d-1 brain
it's a one-dimensional object
it can bend
what's another name
in fact it can not only bend
but it can also bend
it can bend
but it can even come back on itself
what's another name for one-dimensional objects like this
strings
but are they the original strings
no
they are not the original strings
they're called d-1 brains
and they're distinct from the original strings
how would you expect
they might be distinct from the original strings
they're not the same all the way around
you have points on them
that have particles
and points that don't
I mean you have strings that are attached some place
and they're not attached
well they may or may
not have strings attached to them
but let's for a moment
suppose they don't have strings attached to them
they're much heavier
in string
that makes a lot of sense because
how did they start out
they started out as anchors
like infinitely heavy things that could
that could hold the strings down
but they're not really infinitely heavy
their mass depends on some coupling constants and so forth
depends on various things
they're heavy
they're much much heavier than the ordinary strings
and so in that sense they're anchors
but they are string-like
does the t-duality hold for them as well?
what's that?
does the t-duality hold for the brains?
yeah it also holds for the brains too
it does hold for the brains
what's the next one up?
a d-2 brain
a d-2 brain is called a membrane
membranes
are being d-2 brains
and those are simply sheets
like the table top here
that string ends can move around on
or pairs of strings can
move around on them like that
these are d-2 brains
next one up
d-3 brains in a three dimensional world
a d-3 brain fills
all of this, fills space
alright so it fills space
it's a space filling brain
in other words it's just space
and if we had a d-3 brain
then that would simply mean
that we can have open
strings that can just move around
they have to be attached to the brain
but the brain is everywhere
and so it's just open strings
that are free to move around everywhere
so it's often said that ordinary
open string theory is string theory
on a space filling brain
but if we're living in a world
with higher dimensions
then a three brain doesn't
fill all of space
it's like a two brain and a three brain
it's a three dimensional space
it's a surface
and strings can move on it
ok that's the idea of d-brains
and as I said and as I emphasized
they are mathematically important
to string theory
but they also are the origin
of a lot of applications of string theory
so let me very quickly tell you
what's known
you're going to start with one of these d-brains
I assume that the unconstrained directions
that are left over can be
compact directions as well
yes yes yes
that's correct
that's certainly correct
ok let's imagine a d-brain
and I'm going to draw it
as a d-2 brain
there's the d-2 brain
now if you say to yourself
this is awfully slick
though I really believe that this has to be
not from the arguments
that I've made obviously
I'm giving you some sketches of arguments
whether string theory is the right theory of nature
is not the issue here
the mathematics of this is very very tight by now
many many cross checks
many different things point in the same direction
mathematical theorems that have come out of it
mathematical speculations
have been confirmed in mathematics
so it's remarkable
and presumably correct
alright
here's
an empty d-brain
think of it
as empty
empty means it has no strings ending on it
think of it as empty
and think of it as empty
there's an empty space
the space now
is not the full space
but it's just a
surface in space
but think of it as a space
it's empty
we can put things into it
we can put strings into it
like this
little open strings
and these open strings are free to move around
now I'll tell you what
the basic process of them
is
the basic thing they can do
is their endpoints
these are oriented strings
so they have arrows associated with them
when the endpoints
come together
in string theory
let's say the endpoints come together
if we have two endpoints
one with an arrow coming into it
and the other with an arrow coming out of it
they can do the obvious thing
namely the endpoints
come together
and lift off the surface
and form a single string
with two endpoints like that
how do we think about that
if these strings
like this
are thought of as particles
which are free to move around
and in string theory
particles are strings
these are very much like the original open strings
that we started with
if we think of them as particles
which are constrained to move
on the surface or very close to the surface
then
what we discover
is that these particles
can split and join
two of them can come in
join into one
one of them can go out
separate into two
we're starting to build up
something that looks like particle processes
something that looks very much like
Feynman diagrams
two of them come in
join to form one
maybe it hangs around there for a while
and then the reverse process happens
and it becomes two again
we're building up the kind of processes
that quantum field theory describes
creation and annihilation of particles
transmutation of the number of particles
and so
it's not completely surprising
that
the mathematics
of the interactions between these particles
looks very much like quantum field theory
in fact
at low energies where you don't have enough energy
to really excite the vibrations of the strings
it is simply quantum field theory
where the particles of the quantum field theory
are these open strings
in fact
the open strings
behave
like photons
moving around on the surface
they're not photons in the sense of
the ten dimensional theory
they're photons in the sense of a
theory which
lives and whose particles live only on the surface
that's the basic
connection between brains
and their application in studying quantum field theory
brains
like this define quantum field theories
and they define quantum field theories
in exactly the way that I've just described
but
yeah
let's um
briefly
these open strings connected to the brain here
do behave like photons
moving around in the brain
they behave like photons in the lower dimensional theory
but
let's imagine now
that we had more than one brain
there's no
reason why you can't have several brains
for example
parallel to each other
here's two brains parallel to each other
you can move them closer and closer
until they touch
in which case they just form a
compound brain
or you can leave them separated
let's leave them separated for a moment
let's put three of them in just for fun
three parallel brains like that
and let's think
of the kind of excitations
that can move around on them
well you can have
and the excitations means
ordinary strings
an ordinary string
let's give them names let's give the three brains
the three of these names
and the names I'm going to give them
are red
uh
green
and what yellow
blue sorry blue
blue red green and blue
this is just the names of the three brains
of course we could have four
or we could have seven or we could have fifteen
but I'm
particularly interested in having three of them
for the moment
what kind of strings do we have
we can have strings which begin
on red and end on red
oh remember these strings
are also oriented
keep in mind that they're oriented
and so what would you call this string
I would call it a red
anti-red or a red red string
this is a red red string
and therefore some kind of
red red particle
we can also have red green particles
red green particles
are ones which look like this
where one end begins on red
the other end
on green
so what do we have what
are the class of particles we have
we have particles that are labeled
by two indices
two colors
for the case of three brains
we have three distinct colors
and we have particles
which are labeled by pairs
of colors one
associated with the outgoing
and the other associated with the incoming
does this sound like anything
you've seen before
gluons
gluons in quantum chromodynamics
how do you go from red to green
what's that
can you go from red to green
yeah go right there
of course
sure
no problem
maybe you should
keep in mind that this is
embedded in a higher dimensional space
so to mimic that
let's think of lines
in higher dimensional space
now there's no problem in going from here to here
or from here around to here
you're worried about passing through here
well I'm worried if you have to merge a red
green with a green blue to get a red blue
well we have
there will be some rules
um
and the basic rule
what is the basic rule
is that if you have a red green
the basic rule is really only one rule
but we can use it over and over again
um
a
red green string
what can it do if
it hits a red red string
alright
let's suppose this is going out here
and coming in here
let's suppose
this is going
let's see what I want to have
I want to have in here
and
out here
ok
what can happen
this end
can join with this end
they can come together
and join and form
a single string which goes all the ways
from here
to here
in other words
the red anti-red the thing coming into red
and the thing going out of red
one in one out
can join and
simply make a single string
this is very much like a
green
red gluon
coming together with a red red gluon
and forming another red green gluon
same rules
exactly the same rules
as for gluons
but this string cannot
annihilate or lift
itself off the
surface
on the other hand if we had this situation
here
then these can come together
and they can lift themselves off the surface
that's incidentally why
there are eight gluons instead of nine
because one linear
combination can disappear
and is not stable
ah
so
the
mathematical rules for
splitting and joining are exactly
the Yang-Mills
quantum chromodynamics
rules for gluons
ok what about
quarks ok so now
what about quarks what is a quark in this language
a quark in this
language only has one color
it's either a quark
or an anti-quark
it only has one color it doesn't have
three colors
sorry it doesn't have two colors
and an anti-color
a quark must be a thing which only has
one end
a quark in this language
is a string
which ends on one of these
brains and goes off
to infinity
ok now it doesn't
really have to go off to infinity
it could go off to some distant
brain of a different kind
but it
doesn't have another end which
ends on one of these three
that's a quark and it's either a string
coming in or a string going out
when a string coming in and a
string going out meet each other
they can join and just
disappear out into
off the brain
they can join
and disappear from the brain
that's annihilation of a quark and an anti-quark
if there's
two quarks they can't annihilate
they're stuck there
and that's exactly the same rule
as quarks
the mathematical structure
of the field theory that describe
these strings moving around is essentially
with some little extra
added ingredients because of supersymmetry
it's a supersymmetric version of
quantum chromodynamics
and it is
part
of the reason that
brains are interesting
for exploring quantum
chromodynamics
I'm not going to show you how they're used
in detail I'm just showing you what the
connection between things is
let's suppose there's only one brain
then it's not like quantum chromodynamics
what do you think it might be like
now we have objects
we don't have to name them
red, red, green, blue, it's just a
string
it's like quantum
electrodynamics
it has only photons
it doesn't have this complicated gluon
structure, these would be photons
and
what would these things be
charge
electrons
they could be coming in
or they could be going out
in which case they would be electrons and positrons
when two of them come together
they can annihilate
one last point
which is really quite fascinating
remember
I told you that there are
ordinary strings
and d-strings
d-strings were these new
objects that we discovered
these new objects which are a good deal heavier
but they're also strings
an interesting question is
can a d-string
also end on a brain
like this
incidentally I'm thinking about
three brains because I'm thinking about
mimicking three dimensional space
d-three brains
so these are really d-three brains
interesting question
can a d-string
a d-string is itself something that ordinary
strings can end on but let's forget that
can a d-string
end on a three brain
a d-three brain, the answer is yes
I'm not going to try to prove that for you
that's a much more elaborate question
but then
if ordinary strings
the ones we started with
make electrically charged particles
what do d-strings
make
at their ends
when they intersect
the three brain here
can you guess
hmm? neutral? nope
well they're in some sense neutral
but they
they gotta be something
which is similar to what happens when ordinary
strings end
magnetic
magnetic monopoles
remarkable, the magnetic monopoles
are much heavier than the electrons
because d-strings
are much heavier
magnetic monopoles are expected to be much heavier
than electrons
they become magnetic monopoles
the relation between
magnetic monopoles and electrical monopoles
in
in quantum
electrodynamics is mimicked
by the relation between d-strings
ending on these things and
ordinary strings on them
so I've told you a
lot of stuff, I don't expect
that you're going to follow every detail
but I'm trying to show you how
string theorists discovered
it took a long time to make
I mean this didn't happen all in one day
this happened over a period of 20 years
basically or more
no more than
more than 20 years, 25 or more
30 years that all these pieces were put
together by various people
a very wide variety of people
who saw these connections
and today
um
string theory
and its description in terms of
brains is the primary
tool for studying quantum
chromodynamics
it's very bizarre
the whole thing made a full circle
made a full circle from a theory
of hadrons to a theory
of quantum gravity
to the presence of d-brains
that was
necessarily there
which when you put them together
in the 10 dimensional space
put together 3 dimensional d-brains
all of a sudden becomes
the theory of
quantum chromodynamics
that we
that it started out as
so
that's
I don't know what to describe
I describe it as sort of mental gymnastics
but I think it's more than that
I think it's a process of discovery
and unraveling of the
mathematical structure of this thing
it has
wide application to
quantum chromodynamics
other quantum field theories
fluid dynamics
all kinds of things
so far it has not had application
to a direct application
to understanding the particle spectrum
and that's probably because
it's just too complicated
what determines which
of the dimensions the t-duality
is applied to?
oh you can do it to any dimension you please
any compact dimension you please
you choose one that's convenient
but that eventually just winds up saying
that these d-brains
can lie along any axis
and what chooses it?
the history of the universe
is the membrane for magnetic monopoles
I mean magnetic monopoles
three
d-three
the universe here
from our point of view
is a three brain here
d-three brain
but if from some of the other time dimensions
which the people who live on this world
don't even know about
but a string ends over here
and happens to be a d-string
so that means
these d-strings are oriented as well
what's that?
the d-strings are also oriented
absolutely
they're also oriented
you use two planes for SU2
and how do you get the
feature where it's not
reflective in other words
SU2 if you have a
reflective universe
the physics doesn't work the same way
parallel
oh you're talking about charge conjugation
and violation
I don't know the term
but I'm talking about
how we have left handed and right handed
or particle and anti-particle
more interesting
yeah
there are answers
string theory
certainly has
potential possibility to describe that
but not at this level
at this level you need
when you have kalabi-yao manifolds
they can have more complicated
asymmetries that allow that
this toroidal compactification
doesn't allow it
there's a lot
there are many many other objects
in the theory which I haven't gotten into
this is
these are the simplest to describe
there are lots of other constructions
and other kinds of objects
that the theory has to have
and
some
some of them
break various symmetries
and
we can talk
we can discuss them some other time
I'm out of
time
I'm out of energy
and I'm out of momentum
and
applause
for more
please visit us at
stanford.edu