Stanford University.
Okay, so we've talked about
a lot of things so far.
Fields, quanta of fields, the
relationship between fields and particles,
that's the relationship between fields and their quanta.
What are the quanta?
The quanta are the discrete indivisible units of energy that
quantum mechanics implies for waves, for
waves, and waves of course are fields.
Fields and waves are more or less the same thing.
We've discussed the properties, not the
properties of individual particles very much,
but we've discussed some general properties,
the properties of having energy, momentum,
the properties of having spin, and the property
of either being a fermion or a boson.
Every particle is either a fermion or a boson.
Fermions are the particles that don't like
to live together in the same state.
Bosons are the particles that do like to
congregate and do condense into the same state.
We've talked about wave equations on occasion, or
the field equations if you like, more generally,
various kinds of field equations.
And we talked about how field equations
can be generated from Lagrangians, from action principles.
The answer is no.
The quantum mechanical version of the Lagrangian is
a kind of tool for codifying, or codifying,
whatever the right word is,
codifying the interactions between particles.
Various terms in the Lagrangian, things like,
for example, products of fields, represent processes,
which we can call vertices, where particles
come in and other particles go out.
That would, for example, be a term in the Lagrangian
which would have four powers of a field in it.
So we've talked about these general things.
We haven't talked very much about specific particles.
Tonight, well, I expected to spend the first
half hour beating around the bush a little bit.
Looks like we're going to spend a
few more minutes beating around the bush.
But then I want to come to really writing down what
the particles are, you know, who are the players in the drama,
and start going through them more or less,
well, not quite one by one, but in groups,
and trying to give them some
personality, give them some names, some properties,
and also what it is they do and
how they come into physics, into ordinary physics.
Okay, but before I do that, there's kind of
a triangle of concepts that we've discussed two legs of,
but not the third leg.
The triangle is particles or field quanta, particles,
fields, and in modern physics,
pretty much for every elementary particle.
Now, we're going to have to think
very hard in the future, not tonight,
what is an elementary particle?
And what is a composite particle?
We will come back to that.
And you might think, I mean,
everybody here probably has some answer,
if I were to ask you, how do
you distinguish a composite particle from an elementary particle?
And you will always be frustrated.
You will always find some slippery
reason that your definition didn't work.
But for the moment, let's nevertheless
imagine that there are elementary particles,
and that the elementary particles
are the quanta of elementary particles.
So these are elementary fields,
fundamental fields in the theory.
And so they're more or less in one-to-one correspondence,
but there's a third leg to this triangle.
Anybody know what it is?
Of course, you don't know what I'm thinking,
so even if you did know what it was,
you still wouldn't know it.
Forces, forces, forces.
And in a certain sense, forces, force, forces, okay?
Okay.
basically for every field there is a particle
for every field there is a force
electric field gives rise to electric forces
gravitational field give rise to gravitational forces
it may be less obvious
to you what the electron field
electron has a field
it also gives rise to forces and
we'll talk about them a little bit
so there's kind of a correspondence that goes this way
there's a correspondence which goes this way
there must also be a correspondence which goes this way
a way of thinking about forces
which is not based on fields
but which is based on particles
if this correspondence or this triangle really makes sense
so I want to talk about that a little bit
many of you know the idea
but let's just discuss it for a moment
let me first discuss it in
the context of the field
in the context of electrodynamics
how forces come out of thinking
now this is classical electrodynamics for the moment
the complete field view of things
supposing I put two charges into space
and I want to know the force between them
how do I calculate it?
well you could know the rule that the
force is equal to the product of the charges
times one over r squared and so forth
or you could try to calculate it a different way
you could try to say what
do these two charges do to space
what they do to space is they create electric fields
essentially that's the thing they do
they create an electric field that fills space
and I don't want to write down
the details of what that electric field is
but let's just say this is the electric field
let's forget the second particle
and just write down the electric
field due to the first particle
whatever you want to call it
whatever it is
the electric field due to the first particle
incidentally it's proportional to the
electric charge of the first particle
so let's explicitly put that in
e of the first particle
times the electric field
uh divided by the electric charge
this electric field here I've
divided out the electric charge
maybe I shouldn't call it e
let's call it e without
the factor of the electric charge
and put a little hat over it
that's this electric charge
and what is the field energy
anybody know what the formula for the field energy is
in an electric field
electric fields have energy
they store their energy as
a distribution of energy in space
and the field energy
the density of field energy
is the square of the electric field
so we square this
and we integrate it over all
the other fields in the field
so we have the space
the volume
and that's the energy stored
in this in the electric field of the particle
now this energy does not depend
on where we put the particle right
the field will move
if we move the particle
the field will move with it
but the field energy will always be the same
the electric field will adjust
to the position of the charge
the field will always give rise
to exactly the same field energy
and this field energy here
remember e equals mc squared
that field energy is part
of the mass of the particle
it contributes
the field contributes to the energy of the particle
and therefore it contributes to the mass of the particle
there's another way of thinking
about a bit of renormalization
that there's some extra mass there
because the field surrounds the particle in this way
okay i don't want to belabor that now
what about the second particle
supposing the first particle wasn't there
but the second particle was there
this of course is the energy e
not the electric field
this is the energy
if there was only particle two
the field energy would be
the integral of e2 times
the electric field
of the second particle squared
now if the two particles
are not at the same place
well let's not worry about the two particles
this one would also be independent
of the position of this particle here
what about the energy if i have both particles
if i have both particles
then i have to add up the field first
before squaring it
so the electric field
if i have two particles
then i have to add up the field first
so the two particles
will be the sum of the two electric fields
electric field not energy
let's call this energy
e n
h
well let's not call it h
energy just e n
the energy
first of all the electric field
the electric field will be the sum
of the two electric fields
the electric field will be
e e1 plus e1 e1 plus e2 e2
where these are the electric fields
of particle one and particle two
this will be the total electric field
incidentally the electric fields are vectors
and so we might put little vector signs above them
the field energy you get by squaring this whole thing
so the field energy
is the integral of the two particles
and you can see
is the integral over space, there are three terms.
The first term is e1 squared, e1 squared.
It's gotten by squaring this.
The second term is plus e2 squared, e2 squared.
And the third term is the interesting one.
It's the product of e1, e2,
twice as a matter of fact,
times e1 dot e2.
Actually, dot product.
All right, what is this first term here?
It's the self-energy of one particle by itself.
It doesn't depend on the position of the particle.
It's just a number.
It's part of the mass of the particle.
Let's forget it.
It's already there as part
of the mass of the particle.
What about this one?
Also.
Part of the self-energy of the second particle.
What about this one here?
This one is not the energy of either particle separately.
It's proportional to the product of the charges,
and it's proportional to the product of the fields.
What if the particles were infinitely far away,
so far away that their
Coulomb fields hardly overlapped at all?
You take one particle so far away,
that the Coulomb fields are hardly overlapping.
Then this is going to be zero,
because wherever e1 is not zero,
e2 will be zero or almost zero.
Wherever e2 is non-zero, e1 will be close to zero.
So this will be very, very
small as you take the particles apart.
But what about when you bring them together?
When you bring them together, the product
of e1 times e2 will not be small.
Nearby,
nearby,
where the particles are, both fields will be appreciable,
and you will get a contribution from this.
What is that contribution?
That contribution as a function of distance,
well, first of all, it's proportional
to the product of the charges.
It depends on the distance.
And of course, if you work
it out, as you might expect,
it's nothing but the Coulomb force,
one over r squared.
But I like to say it this
way because it gives you the following picture,
that putting in both charges,
taking them far apart,
they don't affect,
well, they're simply just independent objects.
As you bring them together,
they deform and distort the field in a
way that depends on the distance between them.
And the distortions of the field in between them,
that field energy,
which is the contribution because both of them are there,
that's the force law.
So that's a purely field point of view of forces.
A purely field point of view of forces.
But if fields are nothing but collections of quanta,
and quanta are particles,
there must also be a way to
think about forces in terms of particles.
So let's talk about that a little bit.
Before discussing electrodynamics in this way,
let's talk about a slightly different setup,
a completely different, well, actually
a very completely different setup.
Let's talk about molecular forces.
What do molecular forces come from?
I'll give you one source of, there are several,
there are several origins of molecular forces.
But here's the setup I want to think about.
Let's begin with a pair
of protons and a single electron.
What is this?
Proton over here,
a proton over here,
and a single electron,
and a single electron.
If this proton were very far away,
then the ground state of the
electron in the presence of the proton
would just be the hydrogen atom ground state.
It would be governed by
some sort of Schrödinger wave function.
Let's draw the Schrödinger wave function.
The ground state would be the
ground state of the hydrogen atom.
And in the ground state, if
this proton weren't there at all,
not there at all,
the electron in its ground state would certainly be found,
in the position nearby this proton.
Now, what if there are two protons over here?
Not one proton over here, another proton over here,
pretty far away, but not infinitely far away.
Then there is another possible state of
the electron with exactly the same energy,
where the electron is not over here,
but it's over here with the
corresponding wave function pushed over to here.
It has exactly the same energy, but it's far away.
Why?
Because the two protons are of the same kind,
and everything is completely symmetric over here.
So if the electron is in orbit,
well, in quantum mechanical orbit around this proton,
or if it's in quantum mechanical orbit around this proton,
the ground state energy will be exactly the
same as if there was only one proton.
But it's not quite true.
Why isn't it exactly true?
Well,
if the protons are not infinitely far away,
there are processes that could happen which could
not happen if they were infinitely far away.
Anybody know what the process is that
can happen to the electron if the two...
Tunneling effect.
Which?
I would guess the tunneling effect.
Tunneling effect.
Yeah, the tunneling effect.
The electron placed over here into its ground state
can, with a small probability,
suddenly appear in this position.
Suddenly appear in this atom over here.
That's called quantum mechanical tunneling.
It has to overcome an
energy barrier in between the two.
It takes some energy to pull
the electron out of this atom.
It'll get that energy back
when it drops into this atom,
but it has to go over this hill.
Can it go over the hill?
Classically, it can't.
But quantum mechanically, it can
tunnel from one place to another.
Don't stand there and try to watch the tunneling.
What happens if you try to watch
for the electron going back and forth?
Like anything else in quantum
mechanics, watching it ruins it.
You can watch over here.
You can say, well, you can stand over here
and wait for the electron to appear over here,
but if you watch it from
in here, you'll ruin the phenomenon.
So the electron can hop back and forth.
Hop back and forth simply means that
it's going to go back and forth.
What happens is that there's
a tunneling transition, a tunneling rate,
or a tunneling probability that if you put
it over here, it can appear over here.
If it appears over here and you wait
a while, it'll reappear over here and so forth.
Okay, this process sets up
a kind of equilibrium, long-term equilibrium,
in which the electron has an equal
probability of being over here and over here
with a wave function.
Which looks like the sum of the two wave functions.
Well, the sum divided by the square root of
two in order for probability to add up to one.
Alright, so it looks like the sum of the
two wave functions, which I didn't draw very well,
but in the middle over here, it's slightly different.
You might draw the exact wave
function of the electron orbiting the tunnel.
And particle one as if particle two were not there.
Same thing for particle two.
And then add them up.
Well, the correct tunneling wave
function, the correct equilibrium wave function,
is not exactly the sum of these two wave functions.
It's a little bit different in here.
A little bit, not much.
But the point is the energy
of the system is not exactly what it would be
if the two protons were
infinitely far away from each other.
If they were infinitely far away from each other,
you could put the proton, the electron over here,
it would have a certain energy,
or over here, and it
would have exactly the same energy.
When you put them closer together,
the energy of the electron is not
exactly the same as it would be
if the,
if they were far apart,
if they were infinitely far apart.
So, if I were to plot the energy,
if I were to plot the energy
as a function of the distance between them,
when they're very, very far apart,
the energy of that electron is
simply the energy of the electron
with only one proton.
And the other one just not there at all.
At large distances, the energy
would just be whatever it was.
But as you bring the protons together,
the energy of that two protons
plus electron is a little bit less.
It turns out to be a little bit less.
And that little bit less is
a function of the distance between them.
So, now we have a situation.
When the system is in equilibrium
with the electron tunneling back and forth
and in equilibrium between the two,
the energy is a function of the distance between them.
What's the relationship between force and energy?
You can think of this as potential energy.
You can think of this as
a potential energy between the two protons.
The derivative of the energy.
So, the derivative of the energy,
the energy has a gradient in here.
Force always pushes you toward decreased energy.
And so this effectively creates
an attraction between the two protons.
That attraction is a kind of covalent bond.
It's a kind of force between the two of them,
which is due to the sharing of an electron,
or to the fact that the electron
can be in a superposition of quantum states
in the two wells,
in the two potentials of these two things here.
Now, does that mean that a proton and another proton
with an electron between them,
which has this attractive force, will bind together?
Not quite, because there's another force around.
What's the other force around?
The electrostatic force.
The system doesn't have zero charge altogether,
and so there's a repulsion force,
and the repulsion force can overwhelm the attraction force,
but nevertheless, there is a force between two protons,
if there is an electron around,
which is due, in a sense, to
the jumping back and forth of the electron,
or to the diminishing of the energy,
by the wave function sort of adjusting a little bit,
a little bit better than it would if
you just added the two wave functions together.
As I said, that's the origin of covalent bonds,
sharing of electrons,
and in this case, you can think of it,
you can draw a picture.
Now, the picture may or
may not do anything for you.
You have a proton over here,
that's the world line of a proton,
another world line of a proton,
and the electron might start
out being bound to this proton,
hop across to this proton,
hop back across to this proton.
You shouldn't take this too literally,
because if you stood in the middle, as I said,
you would disrupt the process.
But it's a description of the quantum mechanical state
of the electron between the two protons.
What it does, this possibility of
the electron jumping back and forth,
lowers the energy relative to
if you just had one proton
and just one electron in the bound state there.
That means that there is an effective force,
and you know, you can picture it.
This picture is a very,
is like any analogy, it's often very, very misleading.
But the presence of the
electron in between the two protons
creates an attractive force.
It's called particle exchange.
It's called particle exchange, or electron exchange,
between the two protons.
Now, yeah?
Could you think of it as
being the electrons hopping back and forth
as reducing the effect of the electron?
Positive charge, would it?
No, I don't think that
that is quite the right picture.
It doesn't really depend on the electric charges.
It just depends on the fact that you can find,
by adding together two wave functions,
you can find a wave function
with a little bit lower energy
than either one separately.
Is this what Feynman referred to as light, light, light?
As what?
Feynman used to say light, light, light.
Light, light, light, I don't know.
No, no, no, no.
He was probably talking about the Bose statistics
that photons like to be in the same state.
I don't know what he was talking about.
He made the statement that
he said that light likes light.
Electrons like each other, photons...
No, no, electrons hate each other.
They don't like to be in the same state.
Photons like each other.
They love to be in the same state.
I think he was probably talking about the opposite
of the exclusion principle for photons,
the Bose statistics of them.
I don't know because I don't know.
Protons have a tendency to repel.
Protons?
Protons.
Yeah, that's because of their electric charge.
Right.
Now what happens is we put the electron between them.
Is that reducing the repulsion force?
It does a little bit, but not very much.
And in fact, the force due
to the electron jumping back and forth
is a much shorter range
force than the electrostatic attraction.
So this force would only
be important at relatively small distances,
whereas the Coulomb force would fall off much more slowly.
So the Coulomb force would be a longer range force.
But, you know, it is there.
It is there.
The places where it shows up
is if you have a neutral system.
I mean, it shows up better
if you have a neutral system.
If you have two electrons so that
the total charge of the system is zero,
then you have a neutral system.
Then, of course, you have the
possibility one electron orbiting around this proton,
a second electron orbiting around this proton here.
Now the two objects here,
they're called atoms, hydrogen atoms.
They're neutral.
There is no electrostatic force between them.
But you still have this
possibility of electrons jumping across.
Electrons can jump across or tunnel across,
and then it does create a force.
It does create an attractive force which
can bind an atom, bind a molecule.
But even so, it was a mistake
that H2 plus positive charge hydrogen is bound.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, it is bound.
But, hm?
Yeah, at small distances.
At small distances, it is
enough to overcome the Coulomb force.
That's right.
Yeah?
Is there a possibility that between the two protons,
it's creating some kind of tension,
that creates some third force that
the electrons kind of orbit around?
Well, it doesn't create a third force,
but it creates a sort of slightly
nonlinear effect due to the two forces.
But it's just the solution of the Schrodinger equation
in the presence of the two
forces does not have the energy
that it would have if it
was just one of those charges there.
But let's leave it at that.
There is this notion of the energy being lowered
by the possibility of
alternating between two quantum states.
Is this thing at all related to quantum entanglement?
Not so much quantum entanglement.
It's related to what are
called off-diagonal elements in the Hamiltonian,
but it's not too closely
related to entanglement, I would say.
For entanglement, normally you need two electrons.
You only need one electron for this.
For very hot, very, very high temperatures,
does the electron move between
the protons for much higher probability?
Well, at high temperatures,
of course it depends on the temperature,
at very, very high temperatures,
all that will happen is
the electron will get kicked out
and, you know, go to,
uh, Alpha Centauri.
And it won't even remember the
fact that there was a proton around
if it gets hit hard
enough by a very hot photon.
Um, but if the temperature is not that extreme,
what it can do is cause,
even if you only had a single atom,
it could cause the electron to occupy higher levels.
Now, higher levels have bigger wave functions,
so the overlap between the
higher wave functions could be larger,
and it would certainly have some effect on the force.
Uh, but, uh, that's a, uh, kind of special effect.
All right, we have, we have a concept,
uh, that we see in the classical electrodynamics
that the effect of having two charges
changes the energy in between relative
to what it would have been
if you only had one,
and it creates a force.
Similar kind of thing here.
If you have two force centers,
you have the possibility of the, of the, uh, electron
being in a superposition of states.
In other words, of the, um,
of the equilibrium being in a quantum superposition
of the two states, the two
states being over here or over here.
That also lowers the energy and creates a force.
Um, is there a way to
think about the Coulomb force here
in quantum mechanics
where it is in some sense similar
to this jumping back and forth of the electron?
Yeah, there is.
Um,
let's come back
to a single proton.
A single proton
is interacting with the electromagnetic field.
That means it's interacting
with the field whose quanta are photons.
Classically, we might just describe it
by solving the field equations
for the electric field
in the presence of a charged particle.
Quantum mechanically, we think about it differently.
Particularly in quantum field theory,
we think about it as
the emission and absorption of photons.
Alright?
That's what the Lagrangian of qua- of
electrodynamics tells us.
It tells us about the probability for the emitting
and absorbing, absorption of photons.
So, one way of thinking about the electron
is that the actual physical electron,
is a quantum mechanical superposition of states
in which, first of all, there are no photons.
A superposition of a state with no photons,
a superposition of states in
which a photon has been emitted,
and therefore there's a pro- a photon present.
So it's a charged particle
together with a photon around.
Two photons can be emitted,
the photon can be reabsorbed.
The net effect in the end
is some kind of equilibrium distribution,
quantum mechanical equilibrium distribution
of photons surrounding the electron.
And you can measure those photons.
I mean, they're a little bit different
than measuring free photons.
These photons are sort of trapped at the electron.
They're emitted and reabsorbed.
And if I have another electron over here,
it is also emitting and absorbing photons,
so there's an equilibrium.
But every so often,
now this should be thought of
in the language of Feynman diagrams,
every so often,
a photon which is emitted from here
gets absorbed over here.
And I always think about it as two jugglers
each juggling balls.
And every so often,
if they happen to be close enough together,
a mistake will be made
and Joe will grab Moe's juggling objects.
Okay?
Really, what you really want to do
is you really want to calculate the energy
due to the electromagnetic field
or due to the quantum
superposition of photons that are present,
you want to calculate that energy
as a function of the distance between the charged particles.
When they're very far apart,
the two energies just add.
You just get the sum of the energy
of one charged particle and another charged particle.
But as they get closer together,
the charges begin to influence each other,
or in the language of Feynman diagrams,
the emission of one photon by one particle
and the absorption of that same photon by another particle
creates a force,
creates an energy which is not exactly
the sum of the two energies.
And that energy is the Coulomb force
between the charged particles.
So we have two distinct languages.
Well, apart from just writing down the Coulomb force law,
we have two other ways of thinking about forces.
One of them is through classical field theory,
where you calculate the fields of objects and square them.
And the other way is through the exchange of particles.
Feynman diagrams where particles
are exchanged back and forth.
Any particle can be exchanged in some context or another.
So every kind of particle in
one way or another produces a force.
In molecular physics, it's the exchange of electrons
which create forces.
Um...
In electrodynamics, it's the exchange
of photons back and forth
which create forces.
So any particle...
Any particle is also connected with a force
when that particle can be exchanged
or jumped back and forth between two... something else.
We'll describe some more examples,
but I did want, before we move on,
to just discuss the relationship
between particles and forces.
So we more or less have a one-to-one-to-one correspondence.
Particles,
fields for which those particles are the quanta,
and forces which are associated with exchange processes
where that particular kind of particle
can bounce or jump back and forth.
That's an important theme.
So when people say that
there are four forces in nature,
no, there's a force for every possible kind of particle.
And we will discuss some
of them as we go along.
Okay, I think it's time
now to start naming the particles,
listing them, listing their properties,
and discussing what they can do,
what kind of processes they can engage in.
And I could write down a big
long list of all the element particles
and then give you a test next week
to see whether you remember or not,
to see whether you memorized it or not.
That wouldn't be fun at all.
I think it's probably better to
divide them up into small groups.
Groups which are in some
ways simply related to each other.
Get familiar with them a little
bit and what they can do
before we try to write down the
whole damn standard model of particle physics,
which is a monstrosity.
It's not my fault, certainly not my fault,
that the standard model of elementary particle physics
is an ugly, monstrous mess.
It's not Steve Weinberg's fault.
It's nobody's fault.
Or if it is somebody's fault, that person,
well, he may be in the
room, but he's a little bit diffuse.
Frankly, we don't understand why
the particles are what they are.
We don't understand why there
is an electron and no electron,
and no particle whose name slips my mind
because nobody's ever named it because it doesn't exist,
but nevertheless, why some particles exist
and why other kinds of particles don't exist,
we largely, by and large, don't know.
We do understand some relationships between particles.
If this one and that one and that one exist,
then there's got to be another
one to match up with them
in some appropriate way.
But in the end of the day,
there are many more parameters,
many more different types of particles
than there are known relationships between them
which cut down the size of the problem.
Okay, the mathematics and the relationships
cut down the size of the problem somewhat,
factor of two, factor of three, or something like that,
but there are hundreds of particles.
So it is honestly a mess.
If you want to understand what people are holding back,
what they're hoping for in the next round of experiments
and so forth,
you have to understand some of that mess
and what the puzzles are about it.
So let's begin.
Let's name the particles.
We begin with the most obvious ones.
Let's make a table.
Let's see, we need some columns.
We can put the name of the particle over here.
I'll put the symbol for the particle over here.
I'll put the particle type over here.
Now what do I mean by type?
I simply mean whether it's a fermion or boson.
I'll put the electric charge over here.
There's another quantity which characterizes particles.
We'll call it the baryon number.
I'll tell you what it is.
It's a number.
I'll tell you what it is as we go along.
And there are other properties.
At the moment I'm not listing them.
And we'll put the mass over here.
All right.
The first one, of course,
and I'm not listing them in any particular order.
As it happens, I am
writing down the lightest one first.
The lightest one is, of course, the photon.
The standard symbol for a photon is a gamma,
like for a gamma ray.
It has a field associated with it.
The gamma particle is the quantum of a field.
In most cases, or many cases,
the field carries the same symbol as the particle itself.
But for the photon, the field is called A,
and it's really the vector
potential of the electromagnetic field.
You could use electric or magnetic fields,
but you can also use the vector potential,
which is another way
of describing the electromagnetic field.
It has, it's a boson.
I didn't write down the spin,
but the spin is one unit of spin.
The electric charge is zero.
The baryon number, whatever that is, is zero.
And the mass is zero.
So that's the first particle.
Next particle of interest is the electron.
Now, the electron is a particle which has an antiparticle.
It has an electric charge.
If it has an electric charge,
it must have an antiparticle of the opposite charge.
And it is a convention,
whether we think of the particle as the electron
and the antiparticle as the positron,
or whether we think of the positron as the particle
and the electron as the antiparticle.
The relation between them is mutual.
All right, so when I write the electron,
I really mean the electron and positron.
And so we could write E here plus minus.
Standing, E minus is the electron,
E plus is the positron.
The field of the electron is usually psi,
and maybe you could put a little E downstairs
to indicate that it stands for the electron.
It's made up out of creation and annihilation,
and annihilation operators for electrons.
Electrons are fermions.
It's charged, okay?
It's charged in what units now?
Well, the standard particle physics
or quantum mechanical unit for electric charge,
believe it or not,
is the electric charge of an electron.
It's a good unit to work in terms of.
You can go look it up in coulombs.
It's 10 to the minus, what?
23 coulombs.
10 to the minus 19th coulombs or, yeah.
It's some very small charge.
But it's not useful to think about it in coulombs.
All particles in nature have electric charges
which are integer multiples of the electron charge.
This is not true of quarks,
but quarks are not observable particles.
All right.
So the charge we'll just write
as minus 1 for the electron
and plus 1 for the positron.
So since we typically think
of the electron as a particle
and the positron as the antiparticle,
let's just call it minus 1
and remember that the positron has the opposite charge.
Baryon number is 0, and it's mass.
Now we have to decide on units for mass.
Units for mass are the same as units for energy.
E equals mc squared.
So we can either describe the
mass as our mass in kilograms
or in energy in joules,
or we can simply invent a new unit
which is more appropriate to
microscopic physics, to atomic physics.
In fact, the unit that we use
comes originally historically out of atomic physics.
It is the unit in which the ionization energy
of an electron in a hydrogen atom is what?
13.5 electron volts.
An electron volt is how much energy
you get if you pass an electron
across a capacitor plate of one volt.
It's a very, very small amount of
energy, some tiny fraction of a joule.
But one electron volt is the
amount of energy that you get
if you pass an electron across
a capacitor plate of one volt.
So the electron volt is the standard
unit that came historically out of atomic physics,
the theory of electrons and so forth.
It's going to wind up being
too small a unit for us.
Particle physics energies are
larger than atomic physics energies,
but for historical reasons, we have the
electron volt as our unit of energy,
and the mass of an electron measured in electron volts
is one MeV.
In fact, it's a half an electron volt.
Not exactly.
I think it's 0.51 MeV,
and MeV stands for millions of electron volts.
An MeV will be too small
a unit for many other purposes.
As I said, particle physics is a mess,
and the masses of particles extend all over the map,
and so in trying to search for a useful unit,
you're always frustrated.
The useful unit will always
be too small for the next...
Shouldn't it be exactly a half?
No, why?
No, it's exactly 0.51.
No, it's not.
What's that?
I mean pi 3.
Pi 3.
Pi equals 3.
Pi equals 3, right.
Okay, now, we can start...
Quantum electrodynamics is the theory of electrons,
and photons,
and we've talked about it a little bit,
more than a little bit,
and I just...
We could also write down over here
a table of the various...
We won't make it a table.
We'll just make a...
We'll just draw some pictures.
The basic elementary process
that takes place in quantum electrodynamics,
photons and electrons,
is the emission of a photon by an electron.
Okay.
Electron, electron, photon,
and as I've showed you several times,
you can rearrange the legs of this diagram
so that this could represent
not the emission of a photon,
but the absorption of a photon.
A photon comes in from the past,
or...
Whoops, sorry.
You can even flip the electron legs around
so that it looks like this.
Electron going backward in time.
Well, what does that mean?
That really means a positron emitting a photon.
So the basic...
building block for building up processes and interactions
is this vertex with two electrons,
electron, positron, whatever coming...
One going in, one going out,
and a photon coming out of it,
or going into it.
Out of that,
you build up
all of the various processes
of quantum electrodynamics,
but in particular,
the process or the phenomena
that corresponds to the force between charges,
and in the language of particle exchange,
it's the photon bouncing back and forth
between charged particles,
which...
which creates that force.
Yet another way to describe
what's going on here
is in terms of a Lagrangian
or a terminal Lagrangian,
the Lagrangian describing this process here
describes one electron in,
one electron out,
and one photon out,
and so you build that
out of the field operators.
One electron in
is psi electron.
It creates...
It has the creation and annihilation operators in it.
An electron out
is psi dagger
of the electron,
and a photon emitted in it.
And a photon out
is the field operator for the photon.
And if you plug in
all the creation and annihilation operators,
you will find in here,
buried in here,
terms where a photon is emitted,
an electron absorbed,
another electron emitted,
and so forth.
And this codifies,
this describes
all of the various basic processes
that can happen in quantum electrodynamics.
Now, there's a parameter in the Lagrangian
that appears,
appears the electric charge of the electron,
and that, roughly speaking,
is associated with the amplitude
for a electron to emit a photon.
An electron,
let's say you hit the electron,
or whatever,
the electron plows into the side of a x-ray machine.
What's the probability that a photon will be emitted?
Well, the amplitude is the electric charge,
and the probability is proportional
to the square of the electric charge.
So all of this here
is a way of describing
all of these basic processes,
and when they're combined together,
they produce forces,
they produce processes where photons are emitted,
the whole world of quantum electrodynamics
flows out of this,
basically, one expression here.
We won't try to go through that again now.
But let's start adding a
little bit to our particle list.
The next particles of interest,
these are, of course, familiar to you, I'm sure.
Now, if this were 1960,
when I, well, I was,
1962, when I went to graduate school,
probably the next particles I might write down
would be protons and neutrons.
Protons and neutrons are now subsumed
by quarks.
It is widely believed that in some sense,
protons and neutrons are composites of quarks,
although we will, remind me to come back
to this issue of the difference
or what it means to be composite versus elementary.
It's a very interesting story.
But naively, quarks are smaller than protons and neutrons,
and so protons and neutrons,
which are big fat globs,
are made up out of quarks.
So, next thing are quarks.
There's a lot of quarks.
We won't even get to all of them tonight
or the whole set of distinctions between them.
I don't think we will.
But there's more than one type of quark.
There are six types of quarks,
six distinct particles,
all of which are very similar
to each other in some respects,
very different from each other in other respects.
So let's list them.
There are...
They go under... They have names, all right?
Well, why are they called what they are?
They're called what they are just historically,
randomly people assigned silly names to them,
and there's no logic to what they're called,
no logic at all.
There's first of all the up quark,
and that's called U.
The symbol is U.
Well, let's see. We should
write there are quarks here. Quarks.
And I suppose the symbol for quarks is Q.
All quarks are fermions.
We'll write down their charge later.
They have all baryon number of one-third.
Now, why one-third?
Well, the reason is very simple.
The baryon number is basically the counting
of the number of protons and neutrons.
Each proton is counted
as having one unit of baryon number.
Each neutron is counted as having one unit of baryon.
Baryon is just a word for protons and neutrons
and a somewhat generalization of protons and neutrons.
Nucleon is a word for protons and neutrons.
There are other particles which we'll come to
which are very similar to protons and neutrons.
They're also called baryons.
The prefix bary, I think, means heavy.
And baryons, we'll call baryons because
they're a lot heavier than electrons.
But counting up the number of protons and neutrons,
what do you call the number
of protons plus neutrons in an atom?
The atomic weight.
Yeah, the atomic weight.
The atomic weight is equal, approximately equal,
to the total number of protons and neutrons.
And the total number of protons and neutrons is
equal to the total number of protons and neutrons.
So the number of protons and
neutrons in nuclear physics never changes.
Protons can turn into neutrons.
Neutrons can turn into protons plus other things.
But the number of protons plus neutrons never changes.
You have isotopes.
You do have isotopes.
But still, the number of
protons plus neutrons doesn't change.
The number of protons can change.
How can the number of protons change?
No, no, I'm just saying that
different isotopes have different numbers of neutrons.
Oh, yeah, indeed they do.
But are there processes where the
number of protons and neutrons change?
Protons, not plus neutrons, but
protons and or neutrons change?
Beta decay, radioactivity.
In radioactivity, one form of radioactivity,
a neutron decays into a proton
plus an electron and an antineutrino.
Okay, so in that process, the
number of protons changes by one,
the number of neutrons changes by one,
but the number of protons plus neutrons doesn't change.
There's a generalization of that in
all of nuclear physics and particle physics.
There's a certain quantity
which, for ordinary nuclear physics,
is just the number of protons plus neutrons,
and that number is sometimes called the baryon number.
We'll have to generalize it a
little bit beyond protons and neutrons.
It's the baryon number, and it could have
been defined to be two for the protons,
or seven for the protons, or pi for the protons,
but whatever it is, it has to be
defined as twice as much for two protons,
three times as much for three protons.
So it's a convention that you say
the baryon number of the proton is one.
Incidentally, what's the baryon number of the antiproton?
Minus one.
Proton has baryon number plus
one, antiproton, baryon number minus one.
Neutron, baryon number minus one.
Antineutron, baryon number minus one.
But clearly there's an element of
convention in exactly what you call them.
But once it was fixed that the
baryon number of a proton was one,
then the baryon number of a quark was a third,
because three quarks make a proton.
So it's just a historical glitch that the baryon
number of the most fundamental thing in nuclear physics
is one third and not one.
What about an antiquark?
There are antiquarks.
Baryon number is minus a third.
So I won't write that down separately.
The number of quarks is conserved?
Number of quarks minus the
number of antiquarks is conserved.
Now, whether or not that is an absolute conservation law,
it is not believed to be an absolute conservation law.
What do I mean by absolute conservation law?
Can a proton disappear?
It can't completely disappear.
Its energy has to go someplace.
Are there processes in nature where a proton might disappear
and become something that is
neither a proton nor a neutron
or anything else that you would call a baryon?
For example, without violating charge conservation,
a proton could become a positron and a photon.
So a proton could decay
into a positron and a photon.
Does it?
Well, you can wait.
If you have a single proton
and you sit there and wait,
you will wait a long,
long time before that proton decays.
Its half-life to decay that way is at least
10 to the 33 or 10 to the 34 years.
So this is not something that happens very regularly.
Does it happen at all?
The thinking is yes, it does,
but this is one of the
very, very interesting questions of particle physics
of whether the proton can decay.
And when you say can it decay,
you mean decay into something that
does not carry a baryon number.
And it is widely believed that the answer is yes,
but it has never been demonstrated.
Incidentally, how do you wait around for 10
to the 34 years for a proton to decay?
You get 10 to the 34 protons
and you wait around for one of them
and you see one.
Now 10 to the 34
protons is a lot of protons.
If you have protons and antiprotons together.
No, that's not that.
That's zero baryon number because
it goes to zero baryon number.
A proton has baryon number one.
An antiproton has baryon number minus one.
So that's not a baryon.
We call them baryon-violating processes,
processes in which the baryon number is not conserved.
Nobody has ever witnessed such a process
in the laboratory or any place else.
Can they happen?
There does not seem to be
any reason why they cannot happen
built into the mathematics of what we know.
So we leave this as an open question,
but empirically and at least
to a very, very high precision,
baryon number is conserved and quarks by
definition have one third of a unit.
One third of a unit.
That's the number one,
minus a third for antiquarks.
But in order to fill in the rest of this,
in particular electric charge and mass,
we have to label which
kind of quark we're talking about.
And there are lots of different kinds of quarks.
So let's put in the
list of different kinds of quarks.
This is not new particles, which are not quarks.
This is just a subheading
here, quarks and then things underneath.
There are up quarks, down quarks.
Why are they up and
down and not up and down?
There's nothing up and down about them.
What direction?
Up and down?
Up and down means in the Earth's gravitational field.
There's nothing upy or downy about them.
Then it gets worse.
There are strange quarks, which
are no stranger than non-strange quarks.
It gets more silly.
There are charm quarks, which are charming, I suppose.
I don't know.
Then there are, now this is, if you don't,
if you're squeamish or very,
bottom quarks, bottom quarks.
Bottom quarks and then top quarks.
The symbols are, of course, exactly the same.
I just didn't feel like writing the words.
Up, down, strange, charm, bottom, top.
Isn't there a beauty and truth?
Same as bottom and top.
I got a little pretentious beauty
and truth, so bottom and top.
Strange and charm.
How and under what circumstances these
things were named is not interesting.
I don't know.
I do know, but never mind.
They're all fermions.
Okay, the symbols are just what I wrote here.
What's the field symbol?
Sometimes Q, sometimes Psi Q, sometimes capital Q.
Sometimes, depending if you're talking
about the individual types of them,
you'll just use U, D, S, C, B, or T.
Use the same names for the
fields as you use for the particles.
And there's no completely coherent
convention that everybody sticks to.
All right, they're all fermions.
The whole lot of them are fermions.
As I said.
But now comes the charges.
So it's useful to divide them into groups of two.
These groups of two are
sort of repetitions of each other.
This group of two, in
many ways, is isomorphic, not exactly,
to this group of two, which
is the same as, not the same,
but which follows the same
pattern, the pattern of these two.
It's similar to the pattern of these two.
Similar, oh, I got them upside down.
Excuse me, wait.
If I want to keep the pattern, let me see.
I think I want to put down, up.
Down, up, strange, down, up, strange, charm, bottom, top.
Yeah.
All right.
So the down, up system is
very similar to the strange, charm system,
is very similar to the bottom, top system.
So let's write down what the electric charges are,
and you can see them.
You can see this similarity.
The down, up system has charge
minus a third and two thirds.
That's the first example of
particles in nature which have charges
which are not integer multiples of
the electric charge of the electron.
Okay.
However, quarks by themselves do not exist freely in nature.
They're always bound into other
structures, protons, neutrons, and so forth.
And those particles do have integer charges.
Okay.
The strange and the charm, exactly the
same thing, minus a third and two thirds.
Bottom and top, exactly the same,
minus a third and two thirds.
Can that be read?
They're just repetitions of the same thing.
What about the antiparticles?
If I were to list the antiparticles over here,
they would just have exactly the same
charges as the particles except opposite sign.
So this is simply replication
for some reason that nobody understands.
Nobody even has any idea
why nature replicated itself this way.
Are they still all bearing out a number one third?
Yeah.
They're all bearing out a number one third.
Right.
Okay.
And then the masses.
The masses are not similar to each other.
The masses wildly vary.
I'm going to put down estimates
for them because the precise value,
well, there are precise values of the masses,
but you can go look them
up on Google or wherever you want.
The down quark is about 10 MeV.
So it's 50 times heavier than the electron.
A lot lighter than the proton.
Incidentally, what's the proton mass?
About 1,800 times the electron mass.
In other words, about 940 MeV.
This is a lot lighter than a proton.
The up quark, about 5
MeV, less than the down quark.
And protons are made only out
of up quarks and down quarks.
So it doesn't look like
there's nearly enough mass in quarks
to be the mass of a proton or neutron.
We'll come back to that.
The point is, of course, there's more
in a proton than just its quarks.
Strange and charm.
Strange is roughly order of magnitude 100 MeV.
That's strange.
And charm is a little over about 1,000 MeV.
Now notice that the down quark
is heavier than the up quark.
But the strange quark, which
is analogous to the down quark,
is lighter than the charm quark.
So there's some pattern of inversion here.
Of the masses.
Again, nobody understands at all why that's true.
Charm is about 1,000 MeV.
Yeah, charm is about 1,000 MeV.
12, a little more than that.
You were about 100 MeV.
The right hand side was about 0.
Oh, sorry. 100. Missed the 0.
Decimal creep.
We come out better on the film that way.
Okay. 1,000 MeV.
And the bottom quark is about 5,000.
Oh, this is called a GeV.
Giga electron volt.
The bottom quark, see we keep changing units.
That's about 5 GeV.
And the top quark is about 170 GeV.
So how much heavier is the
top quark than the up quark?
Can anybody do that calculation?
Oh.
مرحبا
How much? 30,000? A lot. A lot.
So on the one hand, these
particles are extremely similar to each other.
They do the same things, they have the same properties,
and yet they have masses
which wander all over the map.
Does anybody understand why? No.
Are there any ideas? Yes.
Do any of them work? No.
We don't even have a clue about why there's...
First of all, we don't even understand,
of course, why there's even one of them.
One family. These are called families.
Why is there one family? Well, we don't
know, but for sure, if there wasn't one family,
we wouldn't be here because there
would be no protons and neutrons.
But given that there's this one
family of up quarks and down quarks,
why are there strange quarks and charm
quarks, or top quarks and bottom quarks?
Nobody has a clue.
Can I ask you a stupid question? Yeah.
When these quarks were found, the story goes
that they were looking in a certain place
because the math said the
mass should be a certain amount.
You know something about this?
In other words, they said
that they went through the calculations
and they knew that this is
where it was going to be,
that it was going to
be somewhere around so many GeVs,
and they knew that they were going to find it.
Oh, the top quark in particular.
Yeah, and they predicted that it would be
there before they went and looked for it.
Yeah, but not on the basis of abstract theory,
but on the basis of how the top
quark would work its way into other particles, properties.
I was just saying, because
you just said that the numbers,
and nobody knows why, and they're all over the ballpark,
but yet they seem to
know that that's where it is.
Yeah, but not because there was any basic underlying reason
why the top quark had that mass.
What you could do is you could say,
supposing the top quark had a certain mass,
and then calculate various Feynman diagrams
involving the top quark in various ways.
Feynman diagrams involving ordinary
particles, not the top quark,
but which had top quark in the top quark,
and then you could say, well, there's top
quarks running around in the interior of diagrams.
You calculate those diagrams.
Those diagrams have an effect on processes
involving other particles that you know very well,
and then you say, what does the
mass of this top quark have to be
in order that it does the
right thing for these other particles?
So it was not in any sense a deep understanding
of what it was.
It was simply an observation
that you needed that particular value
of the top quark mass in
order that it be consistent with...
Yeah, right.
So you can't observe a quark, but
you can predict how it will disappear.
What will happen if there is one?
What kind of showers and directions
and energies of particles will be included?
Go ahead.
You're asking or you're saying?
Yeah, if that's how it would detect the quark.
To say that you can't detect
a quark becomes, to a certain extent,
a matter of definition, what
it means to detect a quark.
You can certainly detect evidence of quarks.
What you can't do is create an
isolated quark in isolation from other things
and then examine it.
But we'll come.
We're going to come to the question.
I think you're probably remarking about jets produced...
Well, I don't know what you're talking about.
Yeah, we can talk about jets.
Let's come back to it
after we've talked more about quarks.
Does the fact that some quarks
have twice the charge and absolute values
on Earth, is that from theory
or is that just a bookkeeping concept?
Semi-theory.
Yeah, to some extent that is understood.
I'm not going to explain it.
I'm not going to explain it now,
but now I'm telling you the facts.
We can talk about how much of this
is explained and how much of the pattern is...
The right question is how
much of this pattern is required
for theoretical, mathematical consistency.
But we haven't gotten there yet.
Some of this pattern is required.
Yeah, some of this pattern is
required, but not much of it.
Very little of it is required by mathematical consistency.
Question?
No.
Is the relative abundance of the six kinds of quarks...
Relative abundance in where?
What do you mean by relative abundance?
You mean in the world?
In the universe, yeah.
There are very...
Neutrons are unstable, they decay.
Protons are stable, they exist
in intergalactic space and everything else.
They're all...
Oh yeah, the only thing
that has any appreciable abundance...
All the...
All right, first of all, the only quarks which
have any degree of stability are ups and downs.
The rest of these decay to these.
So the real abundance of real particles
in the universe are all ups and downs.
Okay?
Now, what's the relative abundance of ups and downs?
That's determined by how many quarks of
each type there are in a proton.
There are no neutrons.
Oh, sorry, of course there are neutrons.
There are neutrons in atoms, in nuclei.
So you have to know the relative abundance of
protons and neutrons to know the relative abundance of...
But that's all it is,
relative abundance of protons and neutrons.
Okay, so what do we know?
What is a proton and what
is a neutron in this language?
And let's come over here.
A proton is three quarks.
And a neutron is three quarks.
Now, as I said, I'm now in the
business of telling you facts about these particles,
not at this point trying to
understand why these are the facts.
We can't do everything at once.
A neutron...
is two down quarks and an up quark.
Let's just check that.
An up quark has charge two thirds.
And a down quark has charge minus a third.
So two thirds minus a third minus another third.
This is electrically neutral.
Charge equals zero.
That's good.
Neutron has charge zero.
Proton.
Proton is exactly the same as a neutron,
except with an interchange of up quarks and down quarks.
Two up quarks and a down quark.
Okay.
Now, up quarks and down quarks are a lot alike,
except for their electric charge.
The electric charge has to
do with the interaction with photons.
Let's forget photons.
Let's forget about the existence of photons for the moment
and just talk about quarks and the other particles,
which are important inside the nucleus and so forth.
Then it would almost seem that a
neutron and a proton are the same thing,
except for an interchange of the
up label and the down label.
You might then surmise that they are...
that their properties are almost exact...
are exactly the same,
if for some reason the electric charge is unimportant.
In other words, supposing we don't have
to worry about the interaction with photons.
Just forget photons.
Then it would seem that
protons and neutrons should be identical,
because what's the difference?
You just replaced up quarks by down quarks.
But it's not quite true,
because up quarks and down quarks
don't have exactly the same mass.
They don't have exactly the same mass.
Now, 10 MeV, by comparison with
the mass of a proton, is small.
It's almost negligible.
It is very small,
but it's almost negligible in nuclear physics,
or in particle physics.
And so to some precision,
to the extent that you can
ignore the masses of the quarks,
which are, after all, smaller by far
than the masses of protons and neutrons,
neutrons and protons are a good deal alike.
The only difference is the slight difference in
mass between the up quarks and the down quarks.
Which one is going to be
heavier, the neutron or the proton?
And of course it's going to
be the one with more down quarks,
because down quarks are a bit heavier than up quarks.
Down quarks are a bit heavier than up quarks,
and so it's likely that the neutron
is heavier than the proton, and it is.
Neutron is a little bit heavier than the proton,
and it's largely attributed to the fact
that the neutron has more down quarks.
Now, that's not all there is
to the difference between protons and neutrons.
If the down quarks and the
up quarks had exactly the same mass,
but you accounted for electromagnetism,
in other words, the photon,
you say, okay, the photon is not completely unimportant,
then which would be heavier, the proton or the neutron?
Why?
Yes, because it has some
electrostatic self-energy, because it's charged.
Okay?
So the proton would be a little bit heavier,
because of the electric, the
self-energy of the electromagnetic field,
the electric field, one would expect the
proton to be a little bit heavier.
In fact, the neutron is a little bit heavier,
and the reason is because the down quark
is a little bit heavier than the up quark.
Okay, but other than that...
Can you give us the masses?
Of which?
Neutrons and protons.
Yeah.
Neutron is about, what, 938 MeV,
and proton is about 939 MeV, or...
What is it, about 1.4 MeV difference between them?
Something like about 1.4 MeV difference between them.
There's enough energy between them,
there's enough energy separating them,
that the neutron can afford
a little bit of energy to,
when it decays into a proton,
plus an electron, plus a neutrino.
There's a little bit of excess energy
in the neutrino, which allows it to decay.
And allows it, in particular, to
decay with an electron, through an electron.
Okay, so that's the very, very
rough story of protons and neutrons.
We'll come back to it.
But, now, there are also these strange quarks.
Let's forget charmed quarks for a moment.
There's an interesting question.
Can you replace...
Notice that, in every respect, the down quarks
and the strange quarks are similar to each other,
except for the fact that the mass is different.
So you might ask, can you construct
an analog of the proton and neutron,
where you pull out a down quark
and replace it by a strange quark?
Or, perhaps two strange quarks.
Pull out a down quark and
replace it by a strange quark.
The answer is yes.
Of course you can, because, in every respect, the
up quarks and the down quarks are the same.
It's sort of almost like an isotope.
You pull out a proton and put it in a neutron,
and it sort of sticks together sort of the same way.
But it's even better here.
So you can construct another kind of analog.
These are called strange baryons.
Strange baryons, I forget their names.
Lambdas and Xi's.
They've got all kinds of names.
And...
It's been so long since I worked on
these things that I can't even remember their names.
They have symbols like this associated
with them, like this, and lambdas.
I don't remember which one is which.
Not important.
But, for example, you can create...
I don't know what its name is.
Pull out a down quark and create
a strange and a down and an up.
What's the mass of this one over here?
Sorry, not the mass.
What is the charge of this one?
Well, it's exactly the same as a neutron because
you pulled out a down and put in an S.
And the S and the down have the same charge.
All right.
So this is also electrically neutral, but it has a
strange quark in it, and it's called a strange baryon.
They're not stable.
They can decay.
We're going to discuss the decay processes later.
But they're not completely stable, so they evaporate.
And this one will turn into that one.
But, yes, they do exist.
Likewise, you can put in two
strange quarks and an up quark.
What is the charge of that one?
Same thing.
Charge neutral again.
And likewise, for the proton, you can
replace it by up, up, and strange.
So there are all these strange baryons.
When they decay, when those decay, what kind of...
What kind of what?
Products do you have?
Oh, protons and neutrons.
Only protons and neutrons?
Yeah.
Well, no, no.
You get some baryons and other
things like electrons and other things.
Of course, you can't just get protons.
You have to get some energy out.
And you also only substituted strangers for downs.
Yeah.
And you can't just get them out.
No, you can't.
No.
Well, the rules of what you
can exchange are a little bit complicated.
But at the moment, you can always exchange
one for a similar one of the same charge.
All right?
Now, you can also...
Oh, incidentally, these strange particles are a
little bit heavier than the protons and neutrons
because of this extra 90 MeV of...
Well, no.
Yeah, an extra 90 MeV.
90 MeV isn't much.
All right?
So they're somewhat heavier than
the ordinary protons and neutrons.
But in every respect, they're similar.
The main difference of importance is because they're
heavier, they can decay to the protons and neutrons.
And so they're not found
in the universe in any abundance.
Oh.
All those that you put up there
so far can be constructed with antiparts also?
Oh, yes.
Yeah, you'll have to take every
particle and replace it by its antiparticle.
Then it becomes the antineutron,
the antiproton, and the anti-question mark.
Excuse me.
You call these strange, Barrett's last name?
The strangeness is just another word
for saying they have a strange core.
Oh.
But what if you put a bottom quark in it?
Okay, then they become bottom.
Then they're bottom quarks.
Then they're bottom baryons.
Strange baryons is if you put an S in it.
Yeah.
Strange.
Are they strange?
Well, I don't know.
They were called strange because people became
familiar with protons and neutrons by the 1950s.
And then when they discovered these
other things, they said, oh, that's strange.
And unexpected things.
Yeah.
Where's the missing mass from the proton and the neutron?
Missing mass?
Well, if you add the mass of the…
Oh, you mean if you just
added up the mass of the quarks.
Right.
Yeah.
That's right.
There's a lot missing.
So there must be something
else in the proton and neutron.
No, no.
They're gluons.
Yeah.
No, no.
No attempt here to be dramatic.
But the gluons don't carry
any interesting charge, baryon number.
Do they carry mass?
Well, they carry energy.
They carry energy.
So…
Going back to what you
were saying there, it's binding energy.
It's a form of binding energy, yeah.
That's right.
It's binding energy.
Energies don't add.
Not relativistically.
I mean, well, masses don't add.
The mass of an object is
not necessarily the mass of its constituents.
Well, it's what you were saying
about the prevailing bond type thing.
Mm-hmm.
Right.
Here's the…
You know, these…
Yeah…
So…
As I was saying earlier, you're using
the language of particles here to describe these
composite particles.
It seems more complicated to use the language of fields.
Like, how do you combine
a down field and up field?
It seems like you would combine
everywhere and not be a particle.
So do you, I mean I don't think…
A field…
Do you want to know whether you
can construct a field describing a proton?
Yeah, you're using down and
up as if there were two?
Down and up?
Yeah, I mean you're using electron.
You're using down and up as if they're particles.
But if you think of
them as fields, then they're everywhere,
and the modes of the field
are combining to form these composite particles.
Well, in thinking about this particular aspect of things,
it's much easier to think about particles than fields.
We could think about it in
terms of fields, but it's much harder.
Question about the binding energies.
Yeah.
So if this difference between the quark energies
and the proton energy were binding energy,
that's a big positive energy.
No, it's not an integer.
It's not an integer.
No, it's a big positive energy.
Energy! Oh, I thought you said integer, yeah.
And usually when you think of things like that,
it's usually negative.
Right. Not true here.
Well, yeah, I mean, we'll
come to it, but yeah, sure.
Can we talk about the 3Ds or 3Ds?
Yes, yes, there is.
Yes, there is, but not yet.
Let's talk first about mesons.
Mesons are simply quarks.
Now, why, you know, you could raise the question,
why do three quarks bind together to form something?
Why don't two quarks bind together to form something?
In the early days of
quarkology, this was a complete mystery.
Why quarks?
Oh, you could say, oh, it's
in order to make the charge
an integer multiple of the electron.
Well, that's a stupid answer.
And it turned out not to be that stupid,
but at this stage, it's a stupid answer.
But yet, that is the pattern.
That is the pattern that they combine together in forms
in which this is not the only rule,
but this is one of the rules of nature.
We do understand it, and we
do understand where it comes from,
but a rule, a rule
of thumb at the present time
is the way things bind, they always bind into combinations
which have integer multiple of the electron charge.
Okay.
So, we're going to have
to work on the working rule
temporarily until we have a deeper understanding of it.
All right.
Mesons are also particles, composite particles,
which also have the property
that their charge is integer multiple
of the electron charge,
but they have zero baryon number.
They do not have baryon number,
which means that they must be made,
they're combinations of quarks.
They must be made of quarks and anti-quarks.
In fact, they are quarks, a quark and an anti-quark.
They're a quark and an anti-quark,
and so let's write down.
They are first of all
the ones that you can make
only out of ups and down quarks.
Ups and down quarks are special,
not in any deep sense,
but they're special because they're much lighter
than the other particles.
They don't decay,
or they don't decay as rapidly if they do decay.
They're abundant in nature,
and more than that,
it doesn't take much energy and collisions to make them,
so of course they were
the first particles to be discovered,
things made up of only up quarks and down quarks.
The up quarks and down quarks are pretty light,
and the mesons are typically pretty light.
They're an up quark and a down quark,
or a quark and an anti-quark,
and then you can start
thinking about the different combinations.
There's an up bar quark and a down quark.
There's an up quark and a down bar quark.
There's an up bar and an up quark,
and there's a down bar and a down quark.
I think I got them all.
Any quarks have the opposite spin?
No, you can't do that.
Don't they have to be the opposite kind
because it's one-third of two-thirds?
No.
Okay, let's work out what their electric charges are.
The electric charge of an up quark is minus two-thirds,
and this one is minus one-third.
This has charge minus one, right?
Minus a third, minus two-thirds.
That's fine.
Charge minus one is like an electron.
What about this one?
This is the anti-particle of this.
This one's not.
This one is just the anti-particle of this.
Oh, yes, right.
These two are anti-particles of each other
because they are related
by changing particles into anti-particles.
Down bar into down, up bar into up.
And this has charge plus one.
So these are anti-particles of each other.
Up bar up, that's electrically neutral, obviously.
And charge equals zero.
Now, in fact, neither one of these two by themselves
correspond to distinct particles.
Remember, we're doing quantum mechanics.
Each one of these states can
be thought of as a quantum state.
Think of it as a quantum state.
A quantum state consisting of an
anti-up quark and an up quark.
anti-down quark and a down quark.
One of the things you can do in quantum mechanics
is to superpose states.
If you have states, you can add them.
You can superpose them.
Superposing them means making combinations
that have a probability for being
either this one or this one.
There are two combinations of these two.
I'll tell you what they are.
They are up bar up plus down bar down.
And what would I put in front of
it to make it have total probability one?
One over square root of two.
This is a quantum state.
And this is the orthogonal quantum state.
Up bar up minus down bar down.
You know what this is?
This is an entangled pair of quarks.
Not entangled through their spin,
but entangled through their upness or downness.
If you thought of upness and downness
as being similar, analogous to
the spin direction of a particle
up or down,
and that's where this terminology came from,
then these would be two entangled states.
Entangled not through their spin,
but through their isospin.
Through their upness and downness.
We haven't used the word isospin.
Maybe I'll tell you what it means,
but not right now.
It is just this analogy between the spin directions
and the upness or downness quantum number.
These two things individually are well-defined particles.
This one over here goes together with these two.
And they are called the pions.
They go together for a good reason,
a good mathematical reason,
but they go together
Do I have the right ones? Yeah.
They go together because their mass
is very close to each other.
It is believed they would be exactly the same mass
if the up quark and down
quark had the same exact mass,
if the masses were the same.
All three of these are virtually indistinguishable
except for a small difference in their mass,
and they have different charges.
So, we have two different kinds of particles,
one called pi-on, plus one and minus one.
This is called the pi-on multiplet,
pi plus, minus and zero.
Three independent kinds of particles called pi-ons.
And as I said,
and we can discuss why
nature chose these particular combinations
to be analogous to each other,
but now I'm telling you facts and not mathematics.
So, pi-on over here,
and this is called the eta.
So, there's the pi plus,
the four states here really define the three pi-ons,
pi plus, minus and zero,
and the eta meson.
The eta meson is similar
to a pi-on in many ways,
but it's heavier.
Why is it heavier?
That is a complicated story.
It's not an elementary story.
It's a complicated story.
Maybe we'll come to it, maybe we won't.
But, as a matter of fact,
its mass, okay, what are the masses of the pi-ons?
The masses of the pi-ons are about 140 MeV.
The mass of a pi-on,
mass of pi-on,
m pi,
is about 140 MeV.
So, in other words, it's not too different,
from,
question?
Yeah, it's about 140 MeV.
So, it's somewhere in this range in here,
not this heavy,
and the mass of the eta
is about three times heavier or something like that.
The mass of the eta is about 500 MeV.
I don't remember the precise number,
but that's about right.
Why that is, why the
eta sticks out as being different,
was a puzzle for a long time.
It's not obvious.
Not obvious.
Even today, it's a rather abstract mathematical fact,
but it is understood.
Isn't it also true that they're relatively long, half-lives?
Not very long.
How do you compare it to most of them?
The numbers of orders of magnitude difference?
Uh,
they don't decay by strong interactions,
they decay by weak and electromagnetic interactions,
so they're longer-lived than many of these other particles.
Yes, that is true.
They are long-lived.
Okay, that, those are the mesons.
Did you give a name to
the up bar, down down bar?
No, they don't have names by themselves.
They're a linear combination,
which are the sum and differences of them,
and have definite values.
Oh, I see.
Yes, those are...
Is that similar to...
Is that something like the neutrino oscillations?
Well, in the sense that it's
related to quantum superpositions of states, yes,
but it's got more to do
with spin combinations of two half-spin particles.
There are two ways that you can entangle...
Well, we'll come to it next time.
The last thing I simply want to tell you
is that you can make strange objects.
You can make strange mesons.
You can take any d-quark and
replace it by a strange quark,
strange bar quark, and so forth.
That makes new mesons, which are called strange mesons,
or what's the other name for them?
K mesons.
K mesons are mesons containing
a strange or an anti-strange quark,
replacing a down quark.
Okay?
There are four of them.
Up bar strange,
up strange bar,
down bar strange,
down strange bar.
These two have charge zero.
Charge zero.
And these have charge plus one and minus one.
These two are called the charged K mesons.
These two are called the neutral mesons.
The neutral K mesons.
So there are three kinds of pions,
one kind of eta,
and four kinds of...
How many does that make altogether?
Let's see.
Three pions,
four K mesons,
and an eta.
Yeah.
There's more.
Did we leave something out?
Yeah.
We left out one.
We left out some.
Yeah.
We left out s bar s.
There's nine.
Right.
Nine.
Nine altogether.
The reason it's nine is simple.
There are three kinds of quarks,
three kinds of anti-quarks.
Three times three is nine.
Yeah.
Right.
Okay.
For more, please visit us at stanford.edu.