Stanford University
Before we start, we're going
to talk about quantum chromodynamics today.
Quantum chromodynamics, and we're not going to talk about
the deep mathematics of it and go into it.
We have basically one lecture to do
quantum chromodynamics, which is a huge subject.
It's a subject which easily takes a quarter.
But I'll stick with the highlights and
tell you what the basic intuitive picture is.
Quantum chromodynamics is
similar to quantum electrodynamics.
Quantum electrodynamics is the
theory of electrons and photons.
It's also the theory of the Coulomb force,
the quantum mechanical theory of the Coulomb force.
If applied,
to the problem of atoms in which you do not
worry about the motion or the nature of the nucleus,
the structure of the nucleus,
you simply think of the nucleus as
a fixed point creating an electric field,
then quantum electrodynamics is also the theory of atoms.
In the same sense, quantum chromodynamics
is the theory of quarks and gluons
and the theory, and the things that go with them.
The things that quarks and gluons make.
The things that quarks and gluons make are called hadrons.
H-A-D-R-O-N-S
Hadrons or hadrons.
And they consist of things like
protons and neutrons, which are called baryons,
which have a net quark
number or a net baryon number.
That means an imbalance of quarks and anti-quarks.
Three quarks for the proton,
three quarks for the neutron,
three quarks for the neutron.
And mesons, which are quark-anti-quark pairs.
And all of them are full of gluons.
Gluons are the electrically neutral stuff,
which is the glue and the binding
stuff that holds the quarks and gluons together,
much the same way that
the electromagnetic field or Coulomb field
is the binding agent that holds atoms together.
Atoms, other electrostatically bound objects.
Alright, but before we go into it,
I want to remind you a
little bit about the mathematics of spin.
Because, first of all, that particular
mathematics will come up in another guise,
but also a simply related mathematics to it
will also come up,
in the guise of a quantity called color,
or a concept called color.
We're not going to do group theory in this class.
Alright, we'll try to finesse it.
But the basic mathematics of what
we're talking about is group theory.
As I said, I'm not going to use group theory,
or at least not call it
group theory as we use it.
For spin, the theory of spin
is the theory of a group.
A group, if you don't know
what a group is, just ignore it.
Alright, but the group is
the group of rotations of space.
The theory of spin is also
the theory of the symmetry of physics
with respect to rotations of space.
But, uh,
we finesse that by not
talking about the theory of rotations,
but by talking about the theory of angular momentum.
I'll just remind you very quickly
that we derived everything about angular momentum
from some basic commutation relations,
which were of the form Lx with Ly
equals I times Lz.
I think there's an h-bar in there, but, uh, yeah,
there is an h-bar in there.
Well, those are the components of angular momentum.
We worked that out last quarter,
and we found some rather surprising and interesting things.
Oh, of course, there are three other relations like this,
which are gotten by permuting x to y,
y to z, and z back to x.
I won't write them down.
But when we, um,
worked out the consequences of this,
first of all,
we broke the symmetry.
Now, when I say we broke the symmetry,
I'm not talking about something, uh,
some symmetry breaking in nature.
Just we broke the symmetry in our mathematical description.
The symmetry being the symmetry of rotation,
or the symmetry, uh, which interchanges
x, y, and z, and so forth.
We broke it in our heads,
maybe not in the real physics,
but just by focusing on the z component of spin,
or on the z component of angular momentum.
We basically focused on it.
We cannot measure all three components simultaneously.
They don't commute with each other.
Here they are. They don't commute with each other.
At most, one of them commutes with itself.
Well, of course it commutes with itself.
And no two of them commute.
So at most, you can
talk about one of them, uh,
or measuring one at a time,
and we arbitrarily chose Lz.
When we did that and used these commutation relations,
what we found was, first of all,
that L is quantized.
And the difference between neighboring values of L
was always one unit in units of h-bar.
Number one.
Number two, we focused on spin.
And we described different,
different spin possibilities.
The first set of spin possibilities
were the half-spin objects,
or the things which we call fermions.
Those were the objects whose spin
was centered about zero
in such a way that the first level,
the first z component of spin was a half,
and the first one in the opposite direction
was minus a half.
Three halves, minus three halves, and so forth.
Those were fermions, but right now,
the main point was that the mathematics of spin,
or angular momentum,
gave rise to some multiplets.
There was first the spin half multiplet.
That was the multiplet with a spin minus a half
and a spin plus a half,
like the spin of the electron.
That was associated with half-spin particles and fermions.
Bosons, which for our purposes now,
just think integer spin,
the first one was just spin zero.
There are particles with spin zero,
they have no spin, that's all,
they just have no spin at all.
Then, there are particles with spin one.
The photon is a spin one particle.
There are other spin one particles.
There are nuclei and atoms of spin one.
And they have three states.
Plus one, minus one,
in units of h bar,
and zero.
And then, the next interesting family
has spin three halves.
Spin three halves again goes on the half-spin column here,
and that has one half, minus one half,
three halves, minus three halves.
There are particles with spin three halves.
There are certainly nuclei with spin three halves,
and atoms with spin three halves.
So these things also exist.
Likewise, what comes after spin one?
Spin two.
Spin two, spin zero, spin one,
spin minus one, or the z component of spin one,
minus one, two, and minus two.
These labels here are the z components of the spin.
Now, when you speak about an object of spin L,
L is the notation that
denotes the height of the spin.
The highest value of z component of spin.
So this would be, or M, you can use M.
Ordinarily, it's used M.
M or L, it doesn't matter.
Let's use L.
L is a little bit different than M.
When you speak of spin L,
you're speaking about an object whose maximum spin
along the z axis is L.
So this would be spin a half,
L equals a half.
This one would be L equals one,
and so forth.
How many states are there?
How many independent states are there
for a spin, a particle with spin L?
2L plus one.
For example, for spin a half,
twice L is one, plus one is two.
Two states.
If L is one,
twice one is two.
Add one more, that's three.
Three states.
And so 2L plus one is the number of states
is the number of independent
spin states
for a given value of,
for a given value
of L.
So that's something I want you to remember.
Now, another thing.
If you have more than one particle,
such as an electron,
then you have two spins.
Spins can be combined.
Let's consider what you can make
in the way of spin
by combining together the spins of two electrons.
Let's forget the fact that electrons
can orbit around each other.
Let's ignore what's usually called
orbital angular momentum
and just concentrate on the spin angular momentum.
What kind of angular momentum can you make
for two half-spin particles?
Well, the maximum value
of the z component of spin
is what?
One.
In units of h-bar.
Let's forget h-bar now.
When I say unit,
in maximum spin,
I mean in units of h-bar.
The maximum spin you can have
along the z-axis is one.
That's when both spins are pointing
along the same,
when both spins are pointing upward
along the z-axis.
That axis is the z-axis.
So you can have angular momentum one.
You can have angular momentum minus one.
And you can also have angular momentum
or z component of angular momentum zero.
But in fact, you can have two states
where the z component of angular momentum is zero.
This one and that one.
So there are two states,
two independent states,
whose z component of angular momentum is zero.
How many states are there for a spin one object?
Three.
Two L plus one.
Okay.
So there must be a spin one combination
because we can make total spin up equal to one.
That's the maximum.
So there must be somewhere there,
some combination must correspond to spin one.
What does a spin one have?
It has spin one along the axis,
spin minus one along the axis,
and spin zero.
But there are two states with spin zero,
with z component of spin equal to zero.
They can't both be part of the spin one multiplet.
What could the extra one be?
It's got to be,
either spin zero,
spin one,
spin two,
spin three,
spin four,
spin a half,
spin minus,
spin three halves.
So here's what we found.
Let's write them down.
As both spins up,
or both z components of spin,
I'm going to stop saying z components.
Both spins up,
that's got z component equal to one.
Both spins down,
That's got z component equal to minus one.
And then there seem to be two
with z component equal to zero.
But if I look at spin one,
all it has is plus,
minus,
and zero.
There are only three of them.
So this cannot be a multiplet.
These four states cannot all correspond
to spin one.
What else could be there besides spin one?
Spin zero.
Can't be spin two,
because spin two has to have five states.
The only other thing is spin zero.
So there must be quantum states here,
three quantum states corresponding to spin one,
and one,
when you put the spins together,
and you ask what kind of angular momentum
you make,
you can make spin one and spin zero.
The only combination,
the only question is what combination,
what quantum mechanical combination
of these two correspond to spin zero,
and what combination correspond to spin one,
to the missing spin one combination.
And I will tell you right now,
the answer is that the symmetric combination
with a plus sign,
is the same as the symmetric combination
with a plus sign.
Incidentally, this state over here is symmetric
between interchange,
you can think of it if you like,
as one spin over here,
one spin over here.
They're labeled.
There's one over here and one over here.
The spin states, if they're both up,
is symmetric.
That means the spin state is the same
if you interchange the two spins.
Obviously, they're both up.
This one is also symmetric.
Up down by itself is not symmetric.
If you interchange spin,
you can change the two of them.
This one goes to this one,
and this one goes to this one.
They swap.
But there's one linear combination,
one quantum mechanical combination,
which is symmetric under the interchange of the two.
Plus minus, plus minus plus.
This is the symmetric state.
What should you do to it
to make it have total probability equal to one?
Divide it by the square root of two.
So you get one over here.
That's one over here.
And so you get one over here.
The other one goes to this one.
This one goes to this one.
It's called symmetric.
It's symmetric.
And so,
what you do is you have to
divide that by the square root of two.
That's one over here.
And so,
one over here.
That's one over here.
And so,
now we can do this.
What we can do,
and I'm going to do this again,
is we can take all the three states,
which together form zero, one, and minus one.
If you rotate the axes,
they transform into each other.
This is a spin one up.
This is a spin one down.
Where's the ones with spin one
Okay, so this is the spin one
multiplet, and what about the other one?
We're missing a state.
There were four all together.
Here we have three linear combinations.
What's the other linear combination?
The other orthogonal linear combination?
With a minus one.
So there's another one here
with up down minus down up
minus square root of two.
This one, this is, these
three correspond to L equals one.
This one corresponds to L equals zero.
So these are the ways that you can put
two spin halves together to make the two possible
combinations.
This combination L equals zero, what is
it like with respect to its angular momentum?
The answer is it doesn't have any.
It's a thing without angular momentum.
As far as angular momentum goes, it's like a nothing.
I mean, it may have some energy, it
may have other things, charge, whatever, but as far
as angular momentum goes, it's like empty space.
It's got none.
You might ask, can a up spin and
a down spin come together and annihilate and disappear?
Well, there's all kinds of
reasons why electrons can't disappear.
But just for pure angular momentum reasons,
if we're just worried about conservation of
angular momentum and nothing else, then
which of these combinations can just disappear?
As I said, if we're worried about
nothing but angular momentum conservation, can this
disappear?
No, because it has two units of angular momentum up.
How about down?
How about this one?
Yes or no?
Let's take a vote.
How many think yes?
How many think no?
Okay, the no's win, because this
one is not without angular momentum.
It looks like it has no z
component of angular momentum, and it doesn't.
But the angular momentum about the x and
y axis of this is not equal to zero.
It does not have L equals
zero, it has L equals one.
This is the missing thing that allows
you to rotate the angular momentum into other
directions.
What about this one?
Yeah, that one has angular momentum zero,
and if the only consideration was angular
momentum conservation, it could decay.
It could just disappear.
Now one way of thinking about it is
you could say, well, yeah, that's good enough.
That's close enough.
This one here can disappear.
Okay.
So if you were to measure the angular momentum
of the symmetric one with respect to z, you'd
get one or minus one.
Yeah.
But where?
In which case?
In the symmetric case.
No, you get what I, along the z
axis, you would get zero in either case.
Zero.
Yeah, along the z axis.
But if you measure the angular momentum along
some other axis, you would get one or minus
one.
All right, so that's the theory of angular momentum.
Now, why am I bringing that up now?
Or the theory of spin.
In particular, spin a half.
Spin a half and how you
build out of it other spins.
Oh, incidentally, let's try to build spin three halves.
Let's ask what happens if you put together...
Three spins.
Well, if they're all pointing upward in
the same direction, what's the...and that would
be the maximum, what would you get?
Three halves.
How many states are there with spin three halves?
Oh, incidentally, how many states are there
altogether of three spins, each with spin
a half?
Eight.
Two times two times two.
Okay?
So there are eight states altogether.
How many states are there
for a spin three halves object?
Four.
So how many are left over?
What can those other four be?
Could they be another spin three halves object?
No, why not?
Let's go through it again.
If you have a spin three halves multiplet,
there will be one state which has z component
of spin three halves and one with minus three halves.
We've already used those up.
When we said there were four states
which formed the spin three halves multiplet, we
used them up.
Now all that's left now is spins whose
maximum value is plus or minus a half.
Okay, so what can be there?
What in addition can be there?
Only spin, only spin...
Spin one half. Anything else?
No, there can't be spin zero because making
three spin a halves can never make spin zero.
All it can make is spin three halves and spin
one half. But we seem to have four states left over.
The implication is there are two
distinct ways to make spin one half.
So there are combinations which correspond to the
spin three halves. The easiest ones are all three
spins.
So there are two ways to make spin one
half, which all together adds up to four states.
All right, so when you
take three spins, three half spins,
you get spin three halves and you get spin
one half twice. Two distinct ways of doing it.
Let's keep that in mind.
Okay, now why am I talking about
spin now? What I really want to
talk about is a concept called isospin,
isotopic spin. Isotopic spin was the first
internal symmetry group that, or
the first internal quantum number,
the first analog of a spin which occurred
in particle physics that did not have to do
with the rotation of space, but it had to do
with the rotation of an imaginary space or an internal
space, or if you like, an internal space. So, if
you want to talk about spin, you can do that.
So, if you want to talk
about spin, you can do that.
It just gave rise to
another set of quantum mechanical variables,
which were basically isomorphic, completely similar to
spin, to spin a half, to spin.
But it didn't have to do with spin. It
didn't have to do with the rotation of space.
You could imagine, if you like, that it had
to do with the rotation of some internal directions,
internal directions, imaginary directions
of space, mathematical directions.
Then you could imagine that it
was a complicated kind of sequence,
and that it discovered that motion and
and that can be applied
to a system of Professor Pfeiffer's
The natural mass scale for Hadron physics
is somewhere as is hundreds of MeVs.
The mass of a typical meson
is a couple of hundred MeVs.
The binding energy of particles is MeVs
million, sorry, hundreds of MeVs, not MeVs, hundreds
of MeVs.
What object in nature has binding
energies of order a few MeVs?
Nuclei.
Things that hold protons and neutrons together.
But what holds a neutron together as three
quarks has a binding energy of a few hundred
MeVs.
Alright, so the natural energy scale is a
few hundred MeVs, and there were only two
quarks which were very light, or whose
masses were very light by comparison with that.
And they were the up quark and the down quark.
The other quarks are heavy.
And to make particles out of
them, there's a cost in energy.
And so for the lightest objects, the
most stable, typically heavier objects will decay
the lighter ones.
The light objects of nuclear physics, the
lightest objects and the ones which are stable,
are the ones made of up and down quarks.
Now up and down quarks have almost the same mass.
Of course the down quark is about
twice as heavy as the up quark.
But they both have very small mass by comparison.
So if you look at the up quark and the
down quark, you can see that they have no mass
by comparison with the hundreds of MeVs of nuclear physics.
So in some first approximation, you can say
that the up quark and the down quark have
no mass.
More important, their masses are close to being equal.
That's asymmetry.
What does that mean?
down quarks, everything would be pretty similar.
Now of course the up quark is
slightly more massive than the down quark.
No, the down quark is slightly more
massive than the up quark. So typically
things made of down quarks will be a
little more heavy than the things made
of the corresponding up quarks, but the
difference is small. For example, two up
quarks and a down quark make a proton.
Two down quarks and an up quark
make a neutron. The mass difference between a
neutron and a proton is very small.
Okay, so that's an example of the almost
symmetry between up quarks and down
quarks. So in first approximation you just
forget the difference. Up quarks and
down quarks are symmetric with respect to
each other in the same way, or in
the mathematically the same way, that a spin
up and a spin down are symmetric.
In the case of spin it really has
to do with the symmetry of space rotating the
axes. In the case of up quarks
and down quarks, it's just a mathematical
manufactured space that you can imagine where
you take an up quark to a down
quark by flipping some direction in some
imaginary direction in your head, but all
you're doing is interchanging up quarks
and down quarks. Thinking of up quarks
and down quarks as mathematically the
same or mathematically isomorphic to up
spins and down spins, you come to
the concept of isotopic spin. Isotopic spin is
the analog of spin, but not up and
down in the sense of the z-axis and flipping
spin, but up and down in the sense
of up quarks and down quarks, because there's
nothing really up or down about it.
It's just the interchange of two labels,
up quarks and down quarks. And so we
invents the concept of isotopic spin,
and for all mathematical purposes the
replacement of up quarks and down
quarks is very analogous to the replacement
of an up spin by a down spin.
Okay, so for spin we have two states, up
and down.
And that defines spin.
For quarks we have up
and down, and that defines isospin.
Incidentally, what does the iso come from?
Isotope.
We're going to see in a moment that isotopic
spin interchanges, when you interchange up quarks and down quarks,
you interchange proton and neutron.
Of course, if you interchange proton and neutron in
a nucleus, you'll wind up making an isotope of something.
So it comes from the word isotope, isotopic spin.
But what it is, is in nuclear physics in
the old days it was just a replacement of the
interchange of a proton by a neutron, and
thinking of the proton and neutron as a spin
multiplet in a mathematical spin space.
It was traced eventually just to the fact that
there were two quarks, up quarks and down quarks.
That was the origin of it.
Yeah?
Did isotope spin predate quarks?
Oh yeah.
That's due to Heisenberg.
Yeah.
Well, something has to provide the end good charge or...
Okay, so isotopic spin is
not a precise symmetry of nature.
It's not a precise symmetry of
nature, in that first of all,
the up quark and down quark
don't have exactly the same mass.
But even if they did, there would
still be a distinction, a physical distinction, which
would make them different, and
that is their electric charge.
Electric forces within the nucleus, except for
a big nucleus, when a nucleus gets big,
electric forces become strong.
But for small nuclei, and especially for
protons and neutrons and helium, they're not strong.
They're not strong enough to be a force.
But for neutrons and hadrons, electromagnetic
forces are negligible by comparison with the
other forces holding protons and neutrons together.
So an approximation.
Ignore the mass difference between protons
and neutrons, or ignore the mass difference
between up quarks and down quarks, and ignore
the fact that they have electric charge altogether,
and concentrate on the other forces of
nature, in particular the strong interaction forces,
which we'll come to.
And then there is a precise symmetry relating
up quarks to down quarks, and that symmetry
is very much like ordinary spin symmetry.
It is analogous to spin symmetry.
Okay, let's talk about what you can make.
Supposing one quark by itself, we will come
to understand, is not a physical object that
we can examine in the lab.
So what can we do?
We can do a little bit of a study.
The simplest object that we can examine
in the laboratory is three quarks, and that's
a proton or a neutron.
That's like having three spins.
What can you make out of three spins?
What you can make out of three spins is
either spin three halves or spin one half, and you
can make the spin one half in two distinct ways.
But let's forget the two ways, let's just
say we can make spin three halves and spin
one half.
In the same way, taking three quarks, we can
make an object of isotopic spin one half or
an object of isotopic spin three halves.
Let's first concentrate on the
object of isotopic spin one half.
An object of isotopic spin one
half, how many states should it have?
Just by pure mathematical analogy with ordinary spin.
Two.
A spin a half object has two states.
An isospin state of one
half also would have two states.
What are those two states?
Proton and neutron.
So let's write down what the
proton and neutron are in quark language.
Now, let's imagine that we've labeled the quarks.
By labeled the quarks, you get the proton and neutron.
So let's imagine they're really located
at three distinct spots inside the proton.
This of course is not really
true, but I mean they move around,
but let's just simplify the story
and say there are three distinct quarks
and we're going to label them with three distinct labels.
Here's a down quark and here's two up quarks.
Alright, the down quark might
be the quark at position one.
Alright, so let's call it at position one.
The up quark might be at position two,
and the other up quark might be at position three.
Is there anything wrong with this state?
Quarks are fermions, right?
Quarks are fermions.
Because quarks are fermions,
their states should be anti-symmetric.
Their states should be anti-symmetric.
Now, that suggests that maybe the
right combination for the U quarks
is to anti-symmetrize it, and that would be correct.
That's not an important issue for us right now,
but I'm just being very precise.
That down quark and two up quarks,
and an anti-symmetric state is a proton.
An anti-symmetric state of two spins makes spin zero.
So this is an isospin zero
object times an isospin a half object
that has isospin a half.
But never mind.
This is a bit of mathematics.
It's a little too fancy.
We don't need to worry about it.
This is the proton.
It has charge plus one.
Two half, sorry, two thirds
plus two thirds is four thirds,
and minus a third makes charge one.
So that's the proton,
and it is the combination of three quarks,
which makes an isospin a half state.
Same as three spins making a spin a half state.
So the proton is also a member of a spin,
isospin a half object.
And the other one is gotten
by simply interchanging ups and downs.
And that's up, down, down.
Let me not belabor this point about the symmetry here.
And that's the neutron.
The proton and the neutron, in this language,
are symmetric with respect to each other,
and they form an isotopic spin a half doublet.
Okay.
In the same sense,
that you can put three spins
together to make a spin a half.
And there are only two such states.
So isotopic spin invades the theory of protons and neutrons,
and in this language just gives us another,
just like the quark has isotopic spin a half,
so does the neutron and proton.
Okay.
There's another object,
which is very similar to a
proton and neutron in many ways.
It's also made of three quarks.
But it's the combination...
Oh, incidentally,
what is the spin of the proton and neutron?
Actual spin.
One half.
Okay.
So you've taken three quarks with the same spin,
sorry,
three quarks with spin,
and three quarks with isospin,
and you've made a spin a half,
and an isospin a half.
Okay.
Now,
there's another object,
which has three quarks in it,
which has spin three halves,
and isospin three halves.
If you like,
the three ordinary spins are lined up in it,
in the same direction,
and the three isospins are lined up.
So what kind of thing are they?
Well,
if the three isospins are lined up,
that must mean that there
are objects with three up quarks.
Three up quarks,
three down quarks,
also,
the three spins are aligned,
just the ordinary spins.
The three spins are also aligned
to form spin three halves,
or down, or whatever.
Three quarks up,
three quarks,
three up quarks,
or three down quarks.
This is not a neutron.
This doesn't,
this is not a neutron or a proton.
This is a new object,
which is a little bit more
massive than a proton or neutron.
It has a name.
It's called the delta.
It has isospin three halves,
and it has spin three halves.
So it's sometimes called the delta three halves.
It has both isospin and spin three halves.
Let's forget it's spin.
Its spins are just aligned.
If we line them up all along the z-axis,
then they're all aligned.
Let's forget that.
What about this?
Can this be all there is
to an isospin three halves state?
How many states does a spin three halves object have?
Four, right?
So there must be two more,
and there are two more.
There are two more delta three halves states,
two more of them,
and the two more are U
U D and U D D.
Four states,
four objects,
all of which are related by symmetries.
They all have very close to the same mass.
The only thing which distinguishes their mass
is the little small difference between
masses of up and down quarks,
and they're all very similar to each other.
I'm telling you this for a reason.
This played an important historical role
that I'm going to tell you about in a moment.
These four states are called the delta three halves.
What's their charges?
Let's go through their charges.
What's the charge of this one?
Excuse me, what's the difference between
U U D and D U U?
All right, let's work out the charges.
Pardon?
Let's work.
The third one down,
what's the difference between that and a proton?
Ah, the spin.
Spin.
That's spin three halves, not spin one half.
Oh, okay.
The isospin is...
The z component...
No, no.
It's part of the multiplet,
which is an isospin three halves object.
Okay, right.
Isospin three halves.
So it's both spin and isospin three halves.
But by looking at these two, you couldn't tell that.
You have to know a bit more
about the nature of the way they're combined.
But the bottom two are
isospin one half, are they not?
No, they have a component of isospin,
just as the analog of the z component
of spin would be one half,
but the full isotopic spin would be three halves.
Yeah.
Remember, every object which has a spin three halves
comes in four states.
Four states.
Here they are.
One half, one half, minus three halves, minus three halves.
Okay.
Same is true for isospin.
Okay, but let's concentrate on spin for a moment.
These two states, they...
That's these two.
And the ones of maximum
and minimum spin, that's these two.
So there's got to be four of them,
but we're going to do it in a minute.
So, let's do it in a minute.
So, there's got to be four of them.
We know that a thing with
spin three halves has four states.
The z component of isospin can
be one half and minus one half.
But, by analogy with ordinary spin,
there will have to be four of them.
Okay, but let's come to the important point.
Let's first of all label their charges.
This one has three charge two-thirds object.
It has charge two.
This one has charge minus one.
And UUD has charge plus one and charge...
What is this one?
Zero.
So, the charges...
The charges are different...
Well, these two do have the same charges...
Sorry, did I get this right?
UUD, no.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
These two happen to have the
same charge as proton and neutron.
But these are different.
Okay.
All four of these objects have to
within a small discrepancy the same mass.
Just as the proton and neutron have the same mass,
these have the same mass,
but that mass is not the
same as the proton and neutron.
All right.
Proton and neutron, the mass is
about 940 in units of MeVs,
millions of electron volts.
This is the mass of the proton and neutron.
With the neutron being slightly heavier, not by much.
Okay.
The mass of the delta is about 1200 MeV.
The delta can decay.
It can decay into a
proton and neutron and a pion.
Let's just see how that would work.
Let's take the easy ones.
The easy ones have all three quarks the same.
Up, up, up.
So here we have three up quarks moving along.
And how can that decay?
What is it going to decay into?
It's going to decay into a
proton or neutron and a meson.
A meson is a quark-anti-quark pair.
Let me just draw for you how this happens.
This would be up, up, up.
The two up quarks go off.
This up quark also goes off.
But this up quark goes off.
But quarks can't separate like that.
Quark and an anti-quark appear in between.
Like that.
The quark and the anti-quark in between could
either be a down quark or an up quark.
So one possibility is that this is another up quark.
And then this would be an anti-up
quark and this would be an up quark.
An up quark and an anti-up quark have zero charge.
This would be the decay of the delta three halves.
What do we have here?
This one, no, this one can't happen.
This one actually can't decay.
Not possible.
We have to put a down quark here.
There's just not enough energy for it to happen.
This would be an anti-down quark and an up quark.
So what would this thing be?
Up, up, and down.
That would be a proton.
The proton is lighter than the delta.
So there's enough left over energy.
How much energy is left over?
Let's see, 260 MeV about, right?
Something like that. 300 MeV roughly.
300 MeV.
What's the mass of a pion?
About 140.
About 140 MeV.
So there's enough energy for this to happen and still
leave over some kinetic energy for the pion to fly away.
What kind of pion is this?
With an up and a down bar.
What's its charge?
Two thirds and one third.
So this is a pi plus and a proton.
Total charge two.
This is the object with charge two.
So these delta objects are not stable.
They all can decay into a
proton or neutron and a pion.
And they're very short-lived.
Their lifetime, oh, we could work out the numerical,
I'll tell you what their lifetime is, order of magnitude.
Order of magnitude, it's the time that
light would take to cross the proton.
So you can figure out that the proton
is about 10 to the minus 13 centimeters.
What's the speed of light?
10 to the 10th centimeters per second.
So 10 to the minus 23rd seconds or something.
They don't last long.
But they do last long enough to
be identifiable as distinct objects when they're produced.
These deltas.
These deltas and collisions,
particle collisions, deltas are produced.
And they're real objects.
But they're very, very short-lived.
Excuse me.
As a matter of notation, does it make
any difference which order you put u's and v's?
No, not for purposes here.
No.
Question about fermions.
You have the, where you have the proton, you have
the down quarks, then you have the two up quarks.
You have the up quarks, then the fermions.
They're fermions, but they can't be the same.
Okay, that's exactly what we have to come to now.
Alright, there's something wrong here.
Something's rotten in the state of Denmark.
What is it?
Well, we have three up quarks whose
spins are all in the same direction.
We could put those spins, we could if
we like, choose those spins to be all up
and make a delta three halves with it.
It's spin, ordinary spin up with all three in
the same direction, and they'd all be three up quarks.
You're not allowed to put
two fermions in the same state.
If you could fiddle around with a spin, maybe you could do
something with a spin, but all the three spins are the same.
Why are they the same?
Because it has spin three halves.
Three quarks with spin three halves have the same spin.
They also have the same isospin.
Namely, they're all up quarks.
So, we seem to have found an
object which consists of three identical up quarks.
That's a violation of the principle that you
cannot put two fermions into the same state.
This was the clue that led to the question,
eventually, to what is called quantum chromodynamics.
It was realized that quarks have to have another property.
They must have another property,
so that the three quarks in the delta
three halves can be different from each other.
The fermion statistics, the fermionic property
of them requires that they be different.
So, there must be a label.
Another label that was hidden from view for some reason,
which is there, but not apparent in experiments.
That label is called color.
Color is, again, a highly arbitrary term.
It has nothing whatever to do with ordinary color.
And it was just a label to...
to...
a name.
A name.
Different...
In different places, the three
colors of quarks are different.
In some places, they're red, white, and blue,
mostly in the southern parts of the United States.
Other places are red, green, and blue.
Red, green, and blue being the primary colors of light.
Opt that you see with your eyes.
I will use red, green, and blue.
I haven't heard red, white, and
blue being used for a long time.
Not for the last nine years or so.
But they're just labels.
They're just labels, and in no sense
are they physically different one from another
in any sort of interesting, measurable way.
The fact that there are three distinct ones,
and that they are not the same, is important.
They have exactly the same mass.
They have exactly the same properties.
So, let's now write down what
we know about the labeling of quarks.
All the various quarks we know about.
There are up quarks, down quarks.
That's the lightest one.
Then there are charmed quarks, strange quarks.
And after charm comes topical quarks.
Topical quarks.
Top quarks.
And bottom quarks.
They're not listed in order of mass.
The up is the lightest.
The down is next.
The charm is much heavier than the strange,
by a factor of about eight, or something like
that.
And the top is vastly heavier than the bottom.
But I've just put them in.
I've been perverse and put up on top of down.
I don't know why.
These are the six distinct types of quarks.
But now, for each type
of quark, there is another label.
So, quarks are labeled by two labels.
And the two labels are red, green, and blue.
As I said, I don't want anybody
to think they're really red, green, and blue.
But that's the label.
And where did that come from?
How did we know it was there?
Well, it's one of these things
where physicists simply followed their noses.
They simply said, look, there's
something wrong with this quark model.
You can't have three quarks all in the same state.
They must differ by something else.
Now, they could differ by position.
But it was known that, for one reason or
another, that it didn't have to do with the quark.
That it didn't have to do with position and momentum.
That was known to be irrelevant
for dynamical reasons, for energetic reasons.
So that was not the issue.
There were three quarks all in the same state.
They must have...
In fact, the situation was actually quite
similar to what happened in atomic physics.
Spin was discovered by Uhlenbeck and Goudsmit
because of the...
Because of atomic spectroscopy, helium had
two electrons in the same state.
No good.
Violates the Pauli principle.
Well, actually, the timing here, I
think, may be a little bit confused.
But it could have worked this way.
They could have said, well, Pauli tells us
that you can't put two things in that.
Maybe it did work that way.
I can't remember now.
I wasn't around.
I don't remember.
But the reason...
Or one of the reasons
that Goudsmit and Uhlenbeck might have,
since I don't know the history in detail,
might have invented spin
was because in the helium atom, there were
two electrons apparently in the same orbital state.
So you've got to attach
to the electron another quantum number,
another label.
And that worked.
That worked just fine.
It worked a second time.
History repeated itself.
And various people...
Nambu.
Nambu was the one who realized this.
Yoichiro Nambu.
Nambu, the Japanese American physicist, Nambu,
realized that this called for another quantum number.
And he said every quark has
to have another degree of freedom.
I don't think he called it color.
I suspect that was Gelman, but I'm not sure.
But a good deal later.
And then what he said is,
look, all that's going on here
is that you put three quarks together,
one red, one green, and one blue.
And now you're in business.
No more violation of the Heisenberg uncertainty principle.
The same trick, incidentally,
works for protons and neutrons.
That you can understand the proton
and neutron also as a red...
What are my colors again? Red, green, and blue.
Those are the primary colors, right?
Yeah.
A question.
So is there a physical property that can be measured,
or...?
No, no.
In every possible way, they are the same,
except we know there are three distinct ones.
So if you had one, you could tell the other...
Why?
I mean, how can you say that?
How can you say that maybe the, you know,
the principle doesn't apply?
Huh?
If you can't detect the difference, right?
You can...
If you have one, you
can tell the other one's different.
How? What are you measuring?
That's a little bit complicated.
And in collisions, you can
tell that if you have one...
If you have two of them, you
can tell that they can't be the same.
That you can tell.
Could you, in...
Aren't they conserved?
And the color conserved?
Yeah.
And in the action, you would have to find
if they're not in a different color or something?
Well, yeah, the color is
conserved, but it's also always zero.
It's not only conserved, but it's always zero.
So it's a little bit funny conservation law.
But look.
You could say the same thing about...
The solution doesn't quite tell you that you
need all three of the colors for a UUV.
Say it again?
UUV.
No.
But you do need something to distinguish the two U's.
Right.
Yeah.
But it gives you more
than you need in that case.
Yeah, it gives you more than you need.
That's why...
Oh.
That's why historically the delta
three halves played an important role.
It was looking at this guy here, which was unambiguous.
Three quarks, parallel spin, parallel...
Yeah.
...isospin, something's wrong.
It would have been possible to analyze the protons
and neutrons, but it would have been less convincing.
When the delta three halves was interpreted in terms
of quarks, that really hit you over the head.
So the ultimate resolution is...
And we now know, you know, really
experimentally extremely well that the three quarks...
That three different kinds of colors are really there.
You know, even with ordinary spin, what's the difference
between spin up this way and spin that way?
There's no difference.
They have exactly the same property.
All you have to do is turn your head over.
Or spin this way.
Unless you have another one to set
a direction or something to set a direction...
Then you can't tell the difference between them.
On the other hand, if you have some object which picks
out a direction and you bring a spin up to it,
you can tell whether the spin
is along a particular axis or not.
In the same way, if you have a
proton, a proton being different than a neutron,
and a proton and a neutron are
identifiable objects, I mean, in the laboratory,
if you have a proton, it picks
out a direction in this isospin space.
It's up in the isospin direction, not down.
And if you have another quark, you can discover whether that
quark has its isospin parallel to or anti-parallel to the proton.
So yes, you can tell...
Not its isospin.
You can tell whether it's...
I said something wrong.
But close enough.
If you have one object, it can provide a
kind of frame of reference for the other ones
and test whether they're the same or not.
But the mathematics of quantum chromodynamics simply
requires that you have these three different things.
You could say maybe it's
a violation of the Pauli principle.
You could.
There's no known mathematical framework for discussing that.
And there's no quantum field theory
that has anything but fermions and bosons.
So you'd have to invent something new.
Yeah, well, I thought these...
The Heisenberg attorney principle involves observable
and, you know, like, momentum and position.
Mm-hmm.
And you can make a case
that isospin is a kind of observable.
Absolutely.
But what would be the appropriate observable for Pauli?
Much, much more subtle.
Much more subtle.
Let's come back to it.
I'll tell you when we get there
after we've talked a little bit about...
I have a question.
It was known that quarks and fermions, mucosa,
they're spin of the proton which
is in the area of the quark.
Is that how they were known to be?
Mm-hmm.
Okay.
Yeah.
I guess I have the
same question in a different form.
If you have a down, up, up, a
proton, one of the three quarks is green.
And since the down, there's only
one of, I mean, the question is,
how can you really associate one
color with one of the quarks?
No, you have to think of quantum superpositions of states.
So you might write...
Let's take the case of the proton up, down, down.
This could be green, red, blue.
But we have to write all possibilities,
all ways of combining them,
and to make a real proton.
So we have to use some quantum mechanics
to symmetrize the wave functions and so forth,
symmetrize and anti-symmetrize them appropriately.
But the big advantage of this delta three
halves is you didn't have to do anything fancy.
Just three all in the same direction.
No.
Okay.
Sure, you could say, well, maybe there was
something wrong with our ideas about quantum field theory.
But by now,
we're going to be able to
do something about quantum field theory.
We're going to be able to
So,
the theory of quantum chromodynamics, which is exactly...
Chromo has to do with color.
Color is the important quantity in quantum chromodynamics,
just like charge is
the important quantity in electrodynamics.
This theory is a highly accurate description of
experimental data associated with the collision of hadrons.
And it's, you know, way
beyond what can be questioned now.
So,
the ultimate answer is that it works.
Okay, now let's talk about gluons.
The missing ingredient now,
we have the analog of electrons.
The quarks.
They're fermions.
They have some attributes.
They have some electric charge,
like electrons.
They stick together.
Not quite the way you
would expect them to stick together.
The way the electrons stick to a nucleus,
perhaps a little more the way electrons stick to positrons.
But they stick together somehow.
What's missing
is what sticks them together.
What sticks together atoms
is the electrostatic field.
The electrostatic field is associated with photons.
We can either think of it in field language,
that,
every electron creates a field around it,
or we can think of it in particle language,
that electrons emit and absorb photons.
The exchange of photons back
and forth between charged particles
creates the forces between them.
What about quarks?
What sticks them together?
Particles very, very similar to the photon.
At first it was a speculation.
Maybe such objects exist.
Then a theory was built,
a mathematical theory was built,
with quarks and gluons.
Gluons being the analog of photons.
They're very similar to photons.
They have spin one, just like the photon,
which means they have the same kind of polarization states.
They're massless, like photons.
Very similar,
but with one big difference that we'll come to.
And they jump back and forth.
Well, on the one hand,
a quark is a source of the field
that's associated with gluons,
the gluon field,
in the same sense that the electron is the source
of the electromagnetic field.
On the other hand,
not the other hand, but a similar hand,
the quarks can emit and absorb gluons.
What are gluons like?
What quantities do gluons have?
Photons are pretty,
in a certain sense, uninteresting,
except for the fact that they have a polarization.
They have a spin.
They have a polarization.
They have a momentum,
and they have a polarization.
And that's about all.
They don't have any charge.
By itself, a photon,
if it collides with another photon,
there are no forces.
Now, that's not exactly true.
There are forces between photons,
but they're secondary effects.
They're not electrostatic forces
because the photon is charged.
They're secondary effects,
which come from quantum electrodynamics
and loops of quantum complicated
Feynman diagrams involving electrons.
But the primordial interaction between photons
is there is none.
They move freely past each other.
And that's why a beam
of light moving in one direction
will pass through a beam of light
moving in the other direction with no interaction,
unless you're in some material.
OK, so photons are not very interesting.
And in the sense that
they don't interact with each other,
they are interesting from the point of view
of their interaction with electrons.
And basically, all of quantum electrodynamics
is summarized by one diagram.
And that diagram, which we've drawn several times,
is the emission of a photon from an electron.
Electrons are drawn as having a directionality,
the direction along which the charge is moving.
You can flip lines around,
and every time you see an arrow going downward,
that indicates a positron.
But it's all one basic vertex.
That's it.
And out of that, you can build forces,
you can build collisions, everything else.
All right.
Just for the purposes of bookkeeping,
think of a photon as having the same charge
as an electron and a positron.
In fact, a photon, if it's given a hit
and given a little extra energy,
can decay into an electron and a positron.
It's not that in any sense a photon
is made of an electron and a positron.
That's not the point.
But it happens to have the same properties
as an electron and a positron.
In particular, its electric charge.
It also has an angular momentum.
It has a spin, a spin of one.
And with an electron and positron,
if you line up their spins,
you can also make a spin of one.
So in many ways, a photon is similar
to an electron and a positron.
That's sometimes indicated by drawing,
by thinking of the photon,
as a fictitious composite
of an electron and a positron.
And then this diagram,
this diagram of the emission of a photon,
can be drawn just by saying
the electron comes along,
becomes an electron over here.
The electron over here
was really a positron moving backward,
which turned around.
Now there's no content in this
other than to say
without losing any electric charge,
you can emit a photon
and you can see it directly.
You certainly don't need this
to see that an electron can emit a photon
and that there's no violation of charge conservation.
That's totally obvious
that an electron can emit an electrically neutral thing.
But nevertheless,
let's just draw the emission of a photon,
by thinking of the photon
as a composite of an electron and positron.
It's not useful for electrodynamics.
The analog is quite useful
for quantum chromodynamics.
Okay, now let's come to quarks.
Electrons, we're finished with.
And the important thing in quantum chromodynamics
is the color.
So let's begin with quarks.
Quarks can be red,
green, or blue.
Let's make a column vector out of them
and use the language of quantum mechanics.
A quark can either be in the red state,
the green state, or the blue state.
And make a column out of it.
Okay.
An anti-quark,
let's represent anti-quarks
by red bar,
green bar,
and blue bar.
Okay.
And blue bar.
A gluon,
first of all,
a gluon is an object
that can be emitted by a quark.
If this is a quark,
and a quark goes off,
a gluon can be emitted.
But the interesting thing is,
the gluon behaves in some respects
like a quark and an anti-quark.
It's not a quark and an anti-quark.
I'll tell you precisely in what sense
it behaves like a quark and an anti-quark.
But let's think of the gluon
as a quark and an anti-quark in the same way.
So how do we label,
if we label each quark
by a color,
this now becomes a quark and an anti-quark.
A quark and an anti-quark.
How many different kinds of quarks and anti-quarks
are there?
What?
Did I hear nine?
Yeah.
You're almost right.
Right.
The logic was what I was looking for.
I wanted you to say nine.
There's a subtlety,
there's a subtlety which we'll come to.
There are really only eight.
But let's say nine to begin with.
What are those nine quarks?
Well, sorry, what are those nine gluons?
They're the nine combinations
that you can make
by taking a quark and an anti-quark.
In other words, they make a matrix.
If quarks are like a column,
then, and we might think of,
just for fun, we might think of
anti-quarks as making a row.
Red bar, green bar, blue bar.
Then gluons
would fill out a matrix.
All right?
In other words, to label a gluon,
you would label it with two indices,
two colors, and what would they be?
They would be red, red bar,
red, green bar,
red, blue bar,
green, red bar,
green, green bar,
green, blue bar.
What else?
B, R bar, B, G bar, B, B bar.
So the diagonals are indistinguishable.
Say that again?
The diagonal elements are indistinguishable.
Well, the diagonal elements
are not really indistinguishable,
but the point is that the sum
of the diagonal elements is
is not an independent quantum state.
All right, so it would seem like
there are nine gluons.
Later on, we will talk about
a particular subtlety
which tells us the quantum mechanical
superposition of red, red bar
plus green, green bar
plus blue, blue bar
is a nothing.
It doesn't exist.
But for now, for our purposes right now,
let's neglect that.
There are really only eight gluons,
but it really does look,
from this pattern here,
that there should be nine.
So let's play with it
as if there were nine.
Then what kind of Feynman diagrams
can exist?
Well, a quark can become
another kind of quark
and emit a gluon.
All right, so let's draw
the diagram for that.
Let's take the case of a red quark
becoming a green quark
and emitting a gluon.
What kind of gluon gets emitted?
Red, green bar.
Where's red, green bar here?
Right here.
Red, green bar.
And if you like,
you can draw that
with a neat notation.
The notation is just a bookkeeping device, really.
And here it's useful.
Here it really is useful.
Just think of the red
going through
and the green also is going through,
except when you flip the green line over,
it becomes an anti-green and a red.
So the gluon that's emitted
is as if the red just went through
and the green annihilated a green bar.
That's the basic vertex
of quantum chromodynamics.
There's not just one of them.
There are nine of them,
or actually only eight.
But the pattern is quark
goes to another kind of quark
and a gluon is emitted.
If a red quark goes to a red quark,
then it's a red, red bar.
If a red quark goes to a blue quark,
then it's a red, blue bar,
and so forth and so on.
Okay.
Now, that's, as I said,
the basic,
the basic phenomenon
or the basic primitive building block
of quantum chromodynamics.
You can build all sorts of,
sorry, that's half,
that's one of the building blocks.
There is another building block
that isn't there for quantum electrodynamics.
As I said,
photons don't interact with each other.
In particular,
a photon can't emit a photon
and another photon.
Electron can emit a photon
and stay an electron.
Photons don't emit photons.
So photons don't interact with each other
in any way except in materials.
Yeah.
Gluons are only emitted
with a change of quark.
No, they can,
no, they can have,
they don't have to change the quark.
I mean,
about this process.
Whether it changes
or whether it does not change,
nevertheless,
this is the only method,
the way in which one emits a gluon.
That's right.
This is the only way
in which gluons are emitted.
But there is something new
that makes quantum chromodynamics,
first of all,
far more complicated
and far more interesting
than electrodynamics.
Let's take a gluon moving along.
Here's a gluon.
Let's see.
Let's take that gluon to be a
red-blue bar gluon.
That's a red-blue bar gluon.
Okay.
Now, can this happen?
I'm going to show you something
that, yes,
is really part of quantum chromodynamics.
It's a very simple thing.
You can't just draw it.
Maybe it's not too surprising
once I draw it.
This is not really a quark,
but just imagine it's a fictitious quark
making up the gluon.
All right?
Fictitious quark goes off.
Well, if it's a fictitious quark,
it better not really go off,
but we'll see in a moment
what happens to it,
and the blue bar keeps going.
But now,
if these really were quarks,
a quark and an anti-quark could form.
What kind of quark and anti-quark
would you like to put there?
like to put there? Green? Let's put green
there. This would be green going this way,
and this would be anti-green going this way,
and this would be red. So red goes
through, blue bar goes through, and
green becomes anti-green going that way. Well,
what do we have now? Now we have
a basic vertex in which three gluons come
together. Let's draw gluons as wavy lines
similar to the photons. We now have a
vertex in which a red-blue bar becomes
a red-green bar and a green-blue bar. We
don't really have to remember what
combinations are possible. All we have to
do is figure out which diagrams we can draw
one by one.
So, remember the governance of
these elements in terms of uh,
where to
go accurately, to recognize the
identity of these elements and then,
what variance to take to see whether they are南
between them. Gluons can exchange gluons between
them. So now let's come to forces.
The gluon behaves in a way which
is similar to the photon and does something
which is similar to what the photon
does. It can be exchanged. Here's a diagram.
It's easy to draw diagrams where quarks
interact with each other. All right, let's
let's draw a diagram in which
an anti-quark interacts with a quark.
All right, here's a blue bar anti-quark
which emits a blue bar green gluon,
becomes a green gluon, and now the
green gluon is a blue bar. So now if you look at the diagram, you can see that this
is a blue bar green gluon which emits a blue bar green gluon becomes a green gluon and now the
green gluon becomes a green gluon and now the
green gluon, the green, sorry, let's
see, this would be a green bar.
This would be a blue green bar gluon.
His green bar is blue, but let's
say that blue goes right through like that.
And what do we have here?
We have here now an exchange of a gluon between a
blue bar and a blue, making a green bar and a green.
That's a kind of force between quarks.
That creates a force between quarks in very much
the same way that photons exchanged between electrons create forces.
You might want to make a force
between a blue bar and a blue bar.
Supposing we want...
Supposing we wanted a force between a blue bar and
a blue, then we would make this blue bar here.
All right, so we can make
all sorts of forces this way.
But what about forces between gluons?
All we have to do to this
diagram is add an extra two lines.
What did I have this originally?
Blue bar, let's make it blue bar.
Blue bar.
Green bar up here.
Green up here.
Let's put another line in here.
It's not another quark now.
It's really going to be representing a gluon.
And this one, let's take to be red.
Red goes right through.
Let's put another line over here.
I don't know, what did
I take that one to be?
I think I took that one to be blue bar.
Blue bar.
This is now a diagram which represents
the exchange of a gluon between two gluons.
This is really something new.
This is something very, very different than electrodynamics.
What does it lead to?
It leads to forces between gluons.
Quarks can bind together because of
the exchange of gluons and make hadrons.
But gluons can bind together and make objects.
There are objects in quantum
chromodynamics which contain no quarks.
There are no bound objects.
There are no bound states, composite objects in
quantum electrodynamics just made up out of photons.
There are objects which are
just made up out of gluons.
And how do they happen?
They happen because gluons can
exchange gluons back and forth.
We could just summarize this by saying,
there's a force due to
the exchange of gluons between gluons.
This would also mean, for example, that if you
had two waves of gluons going past each other,
they would interact with each other.
They would deform each other.
They wouldn't just go through each
other just like two electromagnetic waves.
In fact, even if you had
a single gluon wave moving along,
the different parts of it would exert forces on each other
and cause it to deform or do whatever it might do.
So, the watchword is that
the dynamics of gluons is non-linear.
Yeah?
Do we have to have the same
number of reds, greens, and blues with the...
You just have to make sure
the lines follow through the diagram.
On each side.
Interrupted.
We have to have the conservation of colors.
Well, that's what following the lines means.
Okay, well, we have to...
Where? Did I draw this
wrong? I might have drawn the...
Oh, sorry, this should be green bar.
This should be green bar, green, green bar.
Yeah, sorry.
The rule is, follow the lines.
When a line turns around in time
like that, change it to an antiparticle.
And...
That's basically the only rule of quantum chromodynamics,
that there are interactions between quarks and gluons,
and they satisfy the... let's call
it the follow the line rule.
Alright?
And there are interactions between gluons and
gluons, and they also follow the line rule.
We still have an anti-color problem with Rg.
Let's see where.
Rg bar...
Oh, sorry, Rg.
That's...
Rb bar, this should be b bar.
And that should be g.
No, this should be b bar.
Going this way.
This one should be g, and
this one should be g bar.
Okay, let's draw, let's do it over.
Yeah, yeah.
I messed it up badly enough, but I...
Yeah.
I should do it over.
This is a good chance to do it over.
Okay.
This should be...
Okay, so I think I had blue bar over here.
Red, if I remember.
I don't remember.
Red goes through, so it stays red.
Blue bar goes over here, and then
turns around, so this must be blue.
Okay.
This one was blue bar.
It has to be a quark and an anti-quark.
Blue bar straight through.
Blue bar here.
And now we have our choice
what we want to put over here.
So I think I put green going this way.
Green, green, green bar.
Green goes right through the diagram.
Okay.
I think it makes sense.
Every line just goes straight through.
Red goes straight through that way.
Blue bar goes straight through this way.
Well, we can put the arrow
the other way to indicate anti-particle.
So assuming that the intermediate chain
part would be a quark anti-quark?
Yeah.
Now, gluons always have the properties of quark anti-quarks.
Earlier, by analogy with the photon,
you said the gluons were massless.
Yeah.
Are these diagrams with
all these still convincingly massless?
They are massless.
We're going to come to what the meaning of
the mass of a quark and a gluon are.
All right?
in a technical and special sense.
I'll tell you right now what the special sense is.
We're going to quit in a
minute or two, in fact, right now.
I'll give you an example.
We're going to come, we're going
to study this theory one more week,
and we're going to talk about the confinement of quarks,
and we're going to talk about
the structure of hadrons and so forth.
But let me just tell you in what sense a
quark or a gluon does or does not have a mass,
or does or does not have
the mass that we ascribe to it.
So let me imagine that I have an object
of mass m, a small object of mass m,
and the small object of mass m has attached
to it a, I don't know what it is,
it's whatever.
I don't know what you want it to be.
Some sort of wiggly, soft piece of
chewing gum or something that dangles off it.
Now I want to move this object.
If I move the object with a very small force,
the force being so small that it doesn't deform,
that the acceleration is so slow
that the whole thing moves off together.
What kind of mass does it have?
The answer is it has the
mass of whatever you put here,
plus the mass of the wad of
chewing gum or whatever it happens to be.
We're thinking now purely non-relativistically,
just to give you an analogy.
On the other hand, supposing I shake
this thing with a very high frequency,
and I ask,
what are the properties?
What are the properties of the motion
of the core of it over here,
when it's been subjected to a very,
very high frequency force of some sort?
What kind of mass does it have over here?
Just the mass of this object alone, right?
The rest of it doesn't have
time to adjust to the forces.
It just stands still.
Now maybe this sends out a wave all right,
but the very rapid oscillation here,
the response of this end here,
will be the same as
would be the response of an object of mass m.
So what is the mass of it?
Is it the mass of the sum of them,
or is it the mass
of the thing at the end?
The answer is ill-defined.
The answer depends on the frequency of
the force that you exert on it.
Masses of objects are frequency dependent,
or,
well, in this sense,
in this sense,
the mass of this object,
the observed mass of it that it would respond with,
would depend on the frequency of the motion.
In the same sense,
the mass of a quark is frequency dependent.
If you shake,
a quark is some kind of object inside a hadron,
there are three of them,
and there's a bunch of mushy
gluon stuff in there holding them together.
Okay?
If you were to try
to move the quark by itself,
if you were to try to move the quark slowly,
if you grabbed the whole of that quark,
if you could do so,
and you moved it very slowly,
the whole thing would drag along,
and what would be the mass of it?
What would be the mass you would experience?
The mass of the whole thing,
which could be the mass of the proton,
which is 930-something-or-others.
What about if you were to,
to exert a very high frequency force on it?
Well, I'm not going to tell you what,
well, the answer would be
what we normally call the mass of the quark.
That's this 5 or 10 MeV
for an up or down quark.
So the mass of the quark,
when it's subjected to a very, very high frequency,
or when it's hit very hard,
and you try to see how it flies off,
dragging this other stuff behind it,
the initial impulse that it gets,
and the initial velocity that it goes off with,
will be sensitive to the,
to one value of the mass.
On the other hand, if you hit it very slowly
with a very gentle, low frequency force,
the whole thing would move off.
So the concept of what
is the mass of a quark
is somewhat ambiguous,
and to keep the discussion simple,
let's say the mass that we usually ascribe
to the floor, to the quark,
are these high frequency responses,
analogous to the mass at the end
of the wall of chewing gum here.
Isn't that a restatement of delta x delta t?
Not really.
This is a completely,
in this case, this is a completely classical phenomenon
that you have a small little nut
at the end of a wiggly something or other,
you shake it very rapidly,
you see it accelerates with one kind of acceleration,
you accelerate it with a low frequency,
it accelerates differently.
That's a classical phenomenon.
It does not have to do with the...
In the last lecture,
you described the electric charge,
the charge of the electron.
Yeah.
But it's similar.
Yes. Yes. Yes.
Lesson, that's exactly right.
The lesson is the parameters
that we describe particles with
are dependent on the mass.
They're dependent on frequencies and wavelengths
of the interactions that they engage in.
They're called running constants.
So we say the charge of a quark is plus,
you say minus one-third.
Yeah.
Is that,
the same story applies as the case of the electron?
It does. It does.
We have to sort out exactly what we mean
by the charge of a quark,
but let's just put it this way.
It's one-third the charge of a proton,
but yes, you're right.
We do have to define it carefully.
And that's a whole story unto itself.
Yeah.
Yes.
Why do you always have to have a quark
and an antiviral quark?
Why can't two quarks form a part?
That's a good question.
Next.
No, no, no, no.
That's what we're going to talk about.
We're going, that's next.
Right.
Yeah.
Just might be to not have the right time
for this question,
but this,
all this stuff with quarks here,
it's so odd with the fractional charges and color.
And my question is,
and because you can't look at individual quarks,
how do people figure this out?
Well, that took time.
Yeah.
Well, there was a number of clues.
There were a number of clues.
Um,
By the time I came into physics,
the idea of quarks was already established.
I mean, by 19,
I was a graduate student in 1963
when Murray Gilman announced the idea of quarks.
So, and I do know how he came to it,
but the,
there were clues.
There were a lot of clues.
Um,
there were a lot of clues,
but there were also a lot of inconsistencies.
Um,
so,
it was a pattern of suggestive facts
together with apparent inconsistencies,
such as the violation of Fermi statistics.
And there was another fact which was very peculiar.
The other fact we'll come to next time
had to do with the fact that
quarks are never produced in the laboratory,
that they're always permanently
confined inside protons, neutrons, mesons.
That was another fact.
And, uh,
it wasn't one person who put it together.
It was a whole variety of
people who put the whole thing together.
Nambu had the right idea in the early 60s.
He had the right idea.
But the whole thing got put
together and, you know, nailed in place.
And the whole structure was put
together over a period of ten years.
Can you explain why there's only eight gluons?
Yeah, we will talk about that.
Yeah.
From the start, this whole theory is ignoring electrons.
Yes, this theory is ignoring electrons now.
Just like in quantum electrodynamics, we ignore quarks.
Then we have to put them together.
We have to put them together
into some coherent thing in which
quarks and electrons and photons and
all of them form one bigger structure.
Some of which has been done
and some of it has not been.
So, yeah, it is a process of isolating.
I mean, physics always works that way.
You isolate, you divide and conquer.
And then you have to put it all together.
Okay, good.
Let's...
For more, please visit us at stanford.edu.