Stanford University.
Alright, let's talk about rotations
of space in this language.
Rotations of space are asymmetry, and
they can act on various things,
but one of the things
they can act on is vectors.
Those vectors might be a vector field, or
they might just be some vector in space,
a velocity vector, whatever.
Rotations act on vectors, and they
rotate vectors from one vector to another.
Let's see if we can put this up.
Rotations can be combined.
You can take an object, rotate it
about an axis by a certain angle,
and then rotate it by another axis about an angle,
and the result is an overall rotation
about some vector field.
You can rotate it from
other axis by some other angle.
So in an abstract sense,
the rotations do form a group.
Let's just think about it for a minute.
Do the rotation operations have a group structure?
Imagine taking a set of coordinates.
Incidentally, how do we parameterize rotations?
Rotations can be parameterized as vectors.
We won't worry about the fact that rotating by
more than 2 pi brings you back to this.
Supposing you don't worry about that for a moment.
Rotations can be, first of all, they have an axis.
They're rotations about an axis.
Let's take all rotations to always be right-handed.
In other words, rotations right-handed.
What happens if we have a rotation which is left-handed?
We can either think of it as a vector,
we can either think of it as a rotation,
a right-handed rotation by negative angle,
or we can think of it as
a right-handed rotation by the opposite axis.
Doesn't matter, you get the same thing.
Alright, so rotation has an axis.
Let's call that a unit vector n.
And it has an angle that you rotate by, theta.
How many parameters does it
take to describe a unit vector?
It takes two parameters to describe a unit vector.
Longitude and latitude on the sphere.
Unit vector is an arrow pointing to a unit sphere.
So that's two angles.
And another angle for how much you rotate about.
That's three angles, or three
parameters, to describe a rotation.
It's a three parameter family of objects.
Now, when you rotate an object, if
you rotate an object, a rigid object,
imagine you have a rigid object,
and you rotate it about some axis,
and then you rotate it about some other axis,
the result is always equivalent to a rotation
by yet some other axis and some other angle.
So the product of two
rotations, one that's done sequentially,
one and then another, is always another rotation.
So the answer is yes, there
is a product structure to rotations.
Number one.
There is an identity operation.
There is no rotation for rotations.
There's just no rotation at all.
There is an inverse.
Any rotation about any axis,
the inverse of it is just the rotation
by the opposite angle about the same axis,
or you can, if you like, think of
it the same rotation about the opposite axis,
but let's not get into that.
There's always, for any rotation about any axis,
there's always exactly the opposite one which undoes it.
So there's an inverse structure.
Sorry, there's an inverse structure.
What else do we need for a group?
Associative.
And it also happens to be associative.
Yeah, it happens to be associative.
That's a true fact.
It's not quite as obvious.
Okay, so rotations are a group.
Have we failed to say anything about rotations?
No.
Oh, good.
It's non-abelian.
This is the fact that a rotation of a group,
a rotation about the x-axis followed
by a rotation about the y-axis,
is not the same as
interchanging the two orders of rotation.
Go home and do that
if you haven't done it before.
Rotate about the x-axis, then the y-axis,
and then do it in the opposite order.
You won't get back to the same thing.
The smaller the rotations are, the
closer it is to being an abelian.
Yes.
These are sequential rotations, not simultaneous?
No, no, sequential, one after another.
Yeah, group action always
corresponds to sequential rotation.
Sequential, right.
Yeah, right.
That is correct.
The smaller the rotations, in a certain sense,
the closer it is to commuting.
But the group is definitely
a non-commutative or a non-abelian group.
It's our first non-abelian group.
Let's talk about its representations.
Where we're going, incidentally,
is, if we get to it tonight,
is the study of color.
Color is a symmetry group,
and it's represented as a symmetry.
The color of, I'm talking now
not about the color of your shirt,
I'm talking about the color of quarks,
the red, green, and blue.
It's not up and down, it's not a two-state system,
it's a three-state system.
And the operations which are interesting
are the ones which mix
up the different colors of quarks.
But so much of physics has that pattern
of group symmetries that we need
to understand it before we go on.
Okay, rotations.
Rotations, how do we construct a representation,
a matrix representation of rotations?
And the easiest way to do it
is to take the components of a vector.
Let the basic objects be the components of a vector.
Let the basic objects be
the components of an ordinary vector.
Call a vector v, and it has
components v, x, y, and z, or vi.
Let's call them vi.
i can equal 1, 2, and 3,
or x, y, and z, and so forth.
Now, when you rotate either, you
can either think of rotating the axes,
or rotating physically the vector about some direction.
Of course, the components v, x,
and v, y, and v, z change,
and they change by being multiplied by a rotation matrix.
All right, so for every rotation,
about any angle, about any axis,
there is a rotation matrix.
The rotation matrix depends on the
angle of rotation and the axis,
and it is a matrix, i, j.
How do you find the new resulting set of components?
You multiply the matrix by v, j, and
you get, let's call it v prime i.
Again, summed over j.
This is matrix times vector gives transformed vector.
All right, well, these are rotation matrices.
Now, do you know the definition?
Do you know the definition?
Do you know the properties of rotation matrices?
I believe we've gone through them,
but I will go through them again.
Invariant length.
Yeah, let's just see what that says.
Yeah, let's work out the properties of rotation matrices.
This is another group, of course.
Another group and another representation.
This is a three-dimensional
representation of the rotation group.
It is not the only representation of the rotation group.
There's many of them, but this is the
three-dimensional, three-by-three matrix representation of the rotation group,
and it's easy to think about because you can just visualize it
in terms of the components of a three vector, of a spatial vector.
All right.
If R rotates v and gives v prime,
and R is truly a rotation of a vector,
then it doesn't change the length of the vector.
That's the property of a rotation.
It changes nobody's length.
Incidentally, we take the components of the
vector to be real numbers for the moment.
Real numbers.
And the matrices, R, are
also composed out of real elements.
Okay.
So, what is the condition?
The condition is, the condition for
this to be a rotation is that,
for every possible v and v prime,
v prime being the result of rotation,
that vi, vi, this means the sum,
vx squared plus vy squared plus vz squared,
the length, the square of the length of v should be
the same as the square of the length of v prime.
So, let's work that out.
Let's see what that says.
We can work that out in detail.
This is Rij, let's put vj here.
It doesn't matter.
We're summing.
It doesn't matter what we call it, vj.
Same thing.
Okay.
Rij vj is equal to v prime i, right?
Oh, I don't know.
Maybe I want that i here.
It doesn't matter.
This is v prime i, right?
Let's write the same equation again.
Rik vk equals v prime i.
I've changed, you never, this dummy index, the summation
index, I don't want to conflate with this one here.
But this one is the same as this one.
Now, what I want to do is I
want to form v prime i, v prime i.
So, I want to multiply this by this.
And sum over i.
And what will I get?
I will get v prime i, v prime i equals
Rij vj Rik vk with every repeated index summed over.
Or equivalently, just write it a
little differently, Rij Rik vj vk.
This should be the same as what?
This should be the same as vi vi.
That's this over here is equal to this over here.
What is the condition that this is
equal to this for every possible v?
Right.
All right.
Let's write it in two steps.
It is that Rij Rik is equal to delta jk.
In other words, if this were true, that
Rij Rik summed over i was the Kronecker delta,
then it would tell you to set j equal
to k, and this would just become v squared.
So, that's the condition for a rotation matrix.
And it can be written in a different way.
It can be written that the transpose,
R times its transpose is equal to 1.
This is the unit operator, and this
is the representation for R times its transpose.
So, a rotation matrix satisfies, let's write it over
here, that R transpose times R is equal to 1.
Does everybody remember what transpose is?
Transpose is just interchanging rows and columns.
R transpose R is equal to 1.
Now, actually, we immediately now know what
the inverse of any rotation matrix is.
It's just a transpose.
Okay?
The rotation group has this property.
That's basically its defining property.
R trans...
That's the defining property.
That's the property of the matrices, of rotation matrices.
If you construct for every rotation such
a matrix, and you multiply the matrices,
you will find the matrix representation
of the multiplication table of rotations.
I'm just doing this as an example.
So, there are 3 by 3 representations.
Okay?
There are 3 by 3 representations,
3-dimensional representations of the rotation group.
Can we think of the 3-dimensional representations of the rotation group
as in any way being related to the quantum states of something?
Well, we've studied spin.
Spin describes the angular momentum
of a particle and so forth.
You can rotate the spin of a particle.
You can take a particle and you can rotate it.
You can put it in a magnetic field, rotate
the magnetic field, and it'll mix up the states.
It'll mix up the states.
We discovered that there were various
angular momentum possibilities for the spin.
There was spin 1⁄2, spin 1, spin 3⁄2.
There was also spin 0.
Spin 0, spin 1⁄2, spin 1.
How many states does a spin have?
How many states does a spin 1 particle have?
Three.
What happens when you take the state of a spin?
What does that mean?
That means that a spin 1 particle, just the
spin of it, nothing but the spin of it,
can be described by a column vector with three entries representing
the amplitude for any one of the three states of the spin.
Suppose you want to rotate that spin.
Well?
Well, in order to rotate that spin, you must multiply it
by some kind of rotation, some sort of operator that rotates it.
Rotate the spin state.
It's got three states.
The rotation matrices or the rotation operators which act on the state vector to
mix up the components must also be a three-dimensional representation of the rotation group.
In fact, it's just that rotation.
It's just that.
So it's often one speaks about
spin 1 particles being vector particles.
What that means is that the three states can be thought of
as being in one-to-one correspondence with the three components of a vector.
And they mix up among themselves the same way as
the components of the quantum states of a spin 1 particle.
All right.
But I want to, I'm interested
now in a spin 1⁄2 particle.
Well, I have a spin 1⁄2 particle.
And I want to know how the
state, anybody want to take a rest?
Let's take a little rest.
We've gone through a lot of material.
I've tried to keep it
as simple as I possibly can.
Incidentally, we've encountered two
different kinds of groups.
Discrete groups and continuous groups.
The group of...
Composed of 1 and p has only two elements.
Only two elements to the group.
And it's sort of discrete.
You can either flip or not flip.
That's all there is.
The rotation group or the multiplication by
e to the i phi is continuous.
Phi can be a continuous variable.
So there's a continuous infinity of elements.
And of course in the rotation group,
there are also a continuous infinity of elements.
So the kind of transformations and the kind of symmetries that
we can think about in physics break up into two kinds.
The discrete symmetries and the continuous symmetries.
Rotation being a continuous symmetry.
Reflection being a discrete symmetry.
The groups that are associated with
continuous symmetries are usually called Lie groups.
L-R-E.
They were first studied in
mathematics by a mathematician named Lie.
L-R-E.
A German mathematician, I guess in the 19th century.
Right.
Arm interests will mainly be in continuous groups.
Although now and then we
might think of a discrete group.
Okay.
Where were we?
Yeah.
I said that for a spin
one particle, which has three states,
the mathematics of rotating around those states is just
the mathematics of the three-dimensional representation of the rotation group.
But then you can ask,
what about spin a half particles?
Well, first of all, what about spin zero particles?
What happens to a spin zero when you rotate it?
Nothing.
There's all that.
So the symmetry group as a whole,
symmetry group as applied to a
spin zero particle, the rotation group,
really only has one element, and
it's the unit element and nothing else.
And its representation is just completely represented
by nothing more than the unit operator.
It's a completely trivial system, the spin zero particle.
The spin a half particle also already has two states.
Now, given a state of the spin a half particle,
what does it mean to be given a state?
It means...
One zero, that's to be identified with up,
and zero one is to be identified with down,
and a general quantum state has a complex number here.
Let's see.
Let's call it alpha one and alpha two.
Two complex numbers.
What do we specify about them?
We specify nothing more than that the
sums of the squared magnitude of them,
alpha one star alpha one plus alpha two
star alpha two should be equal to one.
That's all.
Other than that, it's free to
choose alpha one and alpha two.
If we choose alpha one equal one
and alpha two equal to zero,
then we are talking about a
spin pointing in the up direction.
Now, up of course is relative
to some definition of an axis,
but let's pick our axis, vertical, z-axis.
Then this state represents an up spin.
This state represents a down spin.
And in general, this combination here
represents a spin state in some direction,
a spin oriented in some direction,
which is determined by alpha one and alpha two.
Now, we're not going to do
the algebra figuring all that out,
but we can ask, what if
we take a given spin state,
alpha one and alpha two,
and we rotate it?
Or do we just rotate our coordinates?
Or we physically rotate all the spin states?
We physically rotate the spin
to another axis,
or just whatever the configuration was,
we rotate it.
What do we get?
Well, we have to operate
on this to get something new.
Alpha one prime, alpha two prime.
What do we operate on?
States?
To get new states, we operate with operators,
or with matrices again.
Matrices and the matrix representation.
So, this is going to be some element,
let's call it U, U one one, U one two,
U two one, U two two.
Every rotation can be represented
as a two by two matrix
acting on spinners, on half spin states.
Let's...
see what the properties of such a matrix...
Now, this is just another
representation of the rotation group,
and it's a two by two representation.
There's a subtlety about this, which
I'm not going to get into,
but about some of you may know it,
that the two valuedness of these representations,
not important.
This is going to represent a rotation of
the components of a spinner, of a half spin particle,
when you rotate the directions of space.
Alright, so what's the first thing that's important?
Well, first of all,
when you act on a state,
you should get another state.
If a state is characterized by the
sums of the squares of the elements
being equal to one,
alright, what does that mean?
That means alpha one star alpha one,
plus alpha two star alpha two,
equals one,
then the same should be true after rotation.
So this should equal, well, first
of all, it should be equal one,
but it should also equal alpha
one prime star alpha one prime,
plus dot dot dot, plus the same thing for two.
Well, it's very much, or similar in pattern,
to the fact that the sums of
the squares of the components of a vector
should be conserved under this.
So, if you're going to do a rotation,
the only differences here, we're
dealing with complex numbers here.
The half spin system is described
in terms of complex components here.
Incidentally, let's count components.
Um, if, uh, yeah.
How many components does it take to pick a direction?
Two, right?
How many independent, uh, components are there here?
Four.
They're complex numbers, and they each, uh, pair of them.
But we always know we don't
care about the phase of these things.
The phase of them doesn't matter.
So, dividing through by the phase
and forgetting by the overall phase,
that cuts it down to three.
There are only really
three independent numbers describing, uh,
such a, uh, spinner.
But what else do we require?
Alpha 1 star, alpha 1 plus, and that's one equation.
So, really, there are only two independent things here.
Two independent, uh, things, even
though there are four complex numbers.
One of the, uh, parameters doesn't matter.
The overall phase, it never affects anything.
And the other is the length of the vector,
the sums of the squares
of the, of the, of them,
are always set equal to one.
So, given any pair of components,
or given any spinner like this,
there's always some direction that it's polarized in,
that it's along, that it's,
uh, that its axis is along.
But how do you, what are the rotation,
what are the rotation operators U?
Well, they, first of all, the most important thing,
and the only important thing, really,
is that they have to preserve
the length of any given vector.
Not the length in three-dimensional space,
but the length meaning the total probability here.
That gives rise to a very, very similar condition
to this over here.
It gives rise to a condition which is
very similar to R transpose times R equals one.
I'm not gonna work it out now.
You can work it out yourselves.
It's the condition that U transpose complex conjugate
times U is equal to one.
It's just an extra little complex conjugate,
conjugate,
because when we sum things, we sum them
multiplying by their complex conjugate.
This combination here, the transpose complex conjugated,
is called the Hermitian conjugate.
And it's represented by U dagger.
So we've seen that before.
U dagger, U dagger,
is equal to the transpose complex conjugated.
Transpose means you flip things about the main diagonal.
Complex conjugate, you just complex conjugate every element.
U dagger is equal to U transpose,
I wrote it here, I
don't need to write it again.
So U dagger times U,
is equal to one.
And in fact, that's all we're really gonna need.
There is a two by
two representation of rotations in space.
They're complex matrices, and they're unitary.
This is the condition for a unitary matrix.
How many components does a unitary matrix have?
Can you figure that out?
Well, every, every matrix has a unitary matrix.
Well, every, every, it's a complex matrix.
Eight real components, right?
Eight real components, four complex components.
But no, not quite.
I mean, now there's a bunch of relationships here.
Now, how many relationships is this?
I heard the right answer.
Four.
Why is it four?
Because this is a matrix equation.
And there's a, and there's
a separate equation for each component.
There are four components.
This is four real equations here.
Four real, yeah, four real equations.
And so there are four real equations among eight unknowns.
There are four independent parameters of
a unitary two by two matrix.
Now, that's one too many,
because we've already found that rotations,
how many parameters characterize the rotation?
Three.
The unit vector, which is
two, and the angle was three.
So there's one too many components here.
One too many degrees of freedom
to actually describe the rotation group.
But there was an obvious candidate
for a, for one too many components,
for one more, well, I
don't know how obvious it is,
but there was a candidate for one more
restriction that we can put on these unitary matrices,
which will cut the number of parameters by one more.
And that is to set the
determinant of them equal to one.
Okay.
Why the determinant?
Well, first of all, you can see that,
okay,
the determinant of the product of two
matrices is just the product of the determinants.
Determinant of A times determinant of B
is the determinant of A times B.
So if we were to set the
determinant of every U equal to one,
then at least that would be consistent,
because when we multiply two
U's together to get another U,
we would still have the determinant equal to one.
So it is actually a theorem.
This is very easy to prove.
You can prove this, this is a one-liner basically,
that if you were to take only the matrices,
the unitary matrices,
which have determinant one,
that they form a closed group.
Setting the determinant equal to one
does not destroy the group property,
simply because, first of all,
the unit operator has determinant one,
and since the product of determinants
is the determinant of the product,
there still is a product structure.
So the unit operator is the component of the group.
So one additional equation that one
can impose without destroying the group property,
let's just write it as determinant of U,
determinant I'll indicate by a pair of brackets like that,
is equal to one.
It's also true that the determinant
of U dagger is equal to one.
They're complex conjugates of each other.
So the group of unitary matrices,
two by two unitary matrices,
with the property that every determinant is equal to one,
is first of all a three parameter group.
It has the same number
of parameters as the rotation group.
In fact, it is the rotation group.
There's a subtlety there which I won't get into.
It is the rotation group.
It has the same multiplication table as the rotation group.
But it doesn't act on,
it doesn't act on the vectors.
It acts on the states of a spin-half system.
So we've discovered something.
We've discovered that there are two
by two representations of the rotation group.
I have a question.
Yeah.
The determinant of the U
dagger is the same as the...
No, it's a complex conjugate
of it if it's not one.
If U is not one, it's a complex conjugate.
Yeah.
But if you have the
equation U dagger U equals I,
then, I mean, ignoring the determinant condition...
That says the determinant of U times
the determinant of U dagger is one.
That says the determinant of U dagger...
It has to be one or minus one?
No.
It has to be, it can be e to
the i theta and e to the minus i theta.
Okay.
Yeah.
Okay, but now we have fixed it.
We have fixed it so that
the determinant is equal to one.
All right.
The group,
definition,
the group of n by n
unitary matrices is called U .
A special case is one by one unitary matrices.
That's U .
That's that thing up there.
All right.
The group of unitary matrices with determinant
one is called the special unitary group.
S, U, n.
Special unitary group.
It plays an enormous role in physics.
S, U, n.
Special unitary n by n matrices.
Okay.
So this group here, which acts on the
two components of a spinner, is S U 2.
That's S U 2.
Let's go one step further before we turn to quarks.
One step further.
Is everybody happy with this?
Yeah.
I was just wondering where the spin matrices
that we discussed last semester would come in.
The spin matrices, the sigmas.
You're talking about the sigmas.
S, X commuted with S, Y equals I, S, Z.
Yeah.
That is a good question.
I will tell you.
I'll tell you right now then.
Okay.
Good.
Let's do that right now.
All right.
There were the matrices S, 1, 2, and 3,
and they were actually just half the Pauli matrices.
I'll assume you're right.
I'm sorry.
I don't even remember what the Pauli matrices are.
Okay.
Think about group elements which
are very close to the identity.
That means rotations by very small angles.
Rotations by very, very small angles.
The operators or the matrices should be
very close to the unit operator, right?
So we should be able to write those.
The special case of small rotations.
small rotations, we should be able to write them
as having unitary matrices which are close to 1.
1 plus something small, and then to
indicate small, let's put an epsilon there.
Epsilon times some matrix, okay?
Epsilon times some matrix.
Let's first ask what is the condition that, yeah, now
we want to know what's the condition that U is unitary.
Alright, so let's find out.
Let's multiply U times U dagger.
U dagger, this is not V, this is U dagger.
Let's multiply it by U dagger.
1 plus epsilon M dagger.
The Hermitian conjugate of 1.
1 is just 1.
I'm taking epsilon, well, let's see, we'll
take epsilon to be real for the moment.
Let it be, it's just a small number.
It's just a small number to indicate smallness.
Anything complex can go into these M's here.
And this is going to be 1 plus M dagger.
And this should be equal to 1.
Alright, when we multiply this out, I'll
only keep things to linear order in epsilon.
We're going to drop things to quadratic order in epsilon.
And that says that epsilon M
plus M dagger is equal to 0.
We have 1 times 1
over here, which cancels this 1.
Quadratic things we don't care about.
We have epsilon M plus M dagger
is equal to 0, since the 1's cancelled.
In other words, what it says is that
whatever M is, it should be minus M.
Minus its Hermitian conjugate.
Okay.
Now if we, this is called anti-Hermitian.
The thing which has this property is called anti-Hermitian.
Can we make something Hermitian
out of something that's anti-Hermitian?
Just multiply it by I.
Let's think about putting an I in here.
Let's go from the beginning
and put an I in here.
What do we do over here?
Minus I.
Hermitian conjugation always involves...
Complex conjugation among other things.
If we did that, then we would get M
minus M dagger equals 0, because of this relative
minus sign.
And then we would find that M equals M dagger.
In other words, if we incorporated an I
into the definition here, then M would be Hermitian.
M is a Hermitian 2 by 2 matrix, right?
It's a Hermitian 2 by 2 matrix.
How many Hermitian 2 by 2 matrices are there?
How do you make a Hermitian 2 by 2 matrix?
Oh, something else.
What about the determinant?
What's the condition that the determinant is equal to 1?
This is a little trickier.
Yeah, what is the condition?
Oh, oh, oh, I know.
Mm-hmm.
Okay, yeah.
Let's just write this in the following way.
It's 1 plus I.
I.
M.
And then order epsilon squared.
So let's forget order epsilon squared.
This is the determinant of 1 plus a small matrix.
Do you know what the determinant
of 1 plus a small matrix is?
Anybody know?
It is 1 plus a small number.
The question is, why is that?
The question is what is the small number?
E to something, could you approximate that?
Well you could, you could do
that. It's easier than that though.
Yeah, let's look at it. Let's do it.
1, 1, and then a small matrix, plus
m11, plus m12, m21, and 1 plus m22.
I haven't put the epsilon in, but
we'll just treat m as a small thing.
Let m be a small thing.
Alright, what's the determinant?
The determinant is this times this minus this times this.
This times this is quadratic in small numbers.
It doesn't matter.
m11 times m22 is quadratic in small numbers,
but there is a piece here which
is 1 times m22 plus m11 times 1.
What is that? That's m11 plus m22.
Trace.
Trace. The trace of m.
The trace of m.
So the determinant of 1 plus a small matrix
is m12 plus m22.
So m12 plus m22 is basically
just a trace of the small matrix.
So, yeah, the m's have to, the bottom
line is the m's have to be traceless.
Yeah, the bottom line is
the m's have to be traceless.
That's, that's, that we can prove.
Alright, so we have, we have
to construct a Hermitian small matrix,
which is traceless.
Alright.
That's exactly what these sigmas are.
They are the traceless 2 by 2 Hermitian matrices.
Any traceless 2 by 2 Hermitian matrix can
be written as a sum of sigma matrices.
So these m's here are
simply linear combinations of the sigmas.
The particular linear combination that you choose
will depend on the axis of rotation.
If you want to make a small rotation
about the x-axis, you'll put sigma x here.
If you want to make a small rotation about
the y-axis, you'll put sigma y there, and so forth.
the linear combination of the x and y axes,
in other words, the 45
degrees, you'll put the linear combination.
That's the connection between the
sigmas and the rotation matrices.
They're the representations of the small rotations.
Okay, the last thing is
how to write a small matrix.
The last thing is how to combine.
You know what?
I think I'm going to wait until next week
to talk about combining representations and just jump to quarks.
Let's get off the mathematics for a moment or two.
We only have a moment or two.
So let's talk about quarks.
Now, we're not interested in the spin of quarks.
Well, we are interested in the spin of quarks.
It's a spin and a half, but
that's not what we're talking about now.
I'm interested in the color of quarks.
And the color of quarks is described
by a three-state system, red, green, or blue.
So if I had a single quark, that
quark could be in one of three states.
Just as a spin could be in one of two
states, the quark color can either be red, green, or blue.
And so we could describe the
state of a quark by three entries.
The three entries will correspond to red, green, and blue.
But, you know, an alpha one,
an alpha two, an alpha three.
And the sum, the squares of alphas will just be the probability
that it's a red quark, a green quark, or a blue quark.
And what are the possible symmetries?
Oh, and another thing we can say.
Let me just go one step further and
say we could also think of the three fields.
The field operator for a red quark, the field operator for
a green quark, and the field operator for a blue quark.
And assemble them also in a vector like this.
What kind of symmetries can
we imagine among the three quarks?
We can imagine, first of all, certain discrete symmetries.
We can imagine the
discrete symmetries which interchange them.
Interchange red and green, or interchange
green and blue, or so forth.
But we can imagine a larger family that includes that.
Incidentally, these rotation matrices here
happen to include the matrix .
This matrix here is a special unitary matrix.
So among these rotation matrices is a matrix.
This is a matrix which interchanges up and down.
This means that the interchange group is
a subgroup of the full rotation group.
It happens to be a rotation group.
Yeah, determinant though.
I think we have to put an
i in there some ways, don't we?
Yeah, we have to put an i in to...
Yeah.
That's right.
Yeah, to give it a determinant one.
So the permutation of two things
is a special case of rotations.
It's not the...
All right.
Is there anything more complicated that we could do?
Yeah, there is.
The more complicated thing we can imagine is unitary...
No, it's not unitary.
It's not unitary.
It's unitary.
Now, it's not obvious that there
is such a symmetry in nature.
Well, I'll tell you there
And in fact, it's the whole point of
having color here, is that it adds another symmetry
to physics.
An important symmetry, that symmetry will play
a very important role in the properties
of quantum chromodynamics.
But the symmetry is the multiplication of
the three components, red, green, and blue,
by special unitary 3x3 matrices.
Same mathematics as appeared here,
except the mathematics involves 3x3 matrices.
I won't fill in all the components,
but, you know, it's U11 dot dot
dot dot dot dot dot dot dot.
3x3 matrices.
Special unitary matrices.
Determinant 1, again.
The special, that's called SU3.
This is the group SU3.
Now, I'll tell you right now from the start,
it is believed, in
fact, it's mathematically absolutely required
that physics is invariant under this SU3 operation.
In other words, it's a kind
of mixing up of the quarks,
which, of the colors of the quarks,
which is analogous to the mixing up
of the components of up and down,
which is also analogous to
the mixing up of the directions,
the three directions of space.
But this is not ordinary rotations.
This is special unitary matrices.
How many special unitary,
let's count the number of special unitary matrices.
Let's count the number of parameters.
How many parameters to describe
a special unitary 3x3 matrix?
Okay, right.
18 minus 9 minus 1.
Okay, why 18?
You've got 9 elements,
9 complex elements, that's 18.
Okay.
You have the equations
U dagger U equals 1.
There are 9 such equations,
1 for each entry in the matrix here.
So that's 18 minus 9.
And then we set the determinant equal to 1.
18 minus 9 minus 1 is 8.
Indepth.
independent, it's an eight parameter group, just like
the rotation group is a three parameter group.
So there's an eight parameter
family of rotations.
I bet you're wondering what that eight has to do
with the fact that there are eight gluons, aren't you?
Yeah, it's the same fact. Yeah.
Yeah, it's the same fact,
but we will come to it.
All right, why aren't there nine gluons? Because we threw away the
determinant. That doesn't make any sense at all, but it's true anyway.
Yep, it is true.
Yeah, so special unitary three by three
matrices are a particular representation of SU , but SU
is the symmetry group, the basic symmetry group of quantum
chromodynamics. And
just like
quantum
electrodynamics
was invariant under this operation
here, and that told us that
only the only in the Lagrangian,
only things with the same number of
psi's and psi daggers can enter.
The idea that the Lagrangian is
invariant under SU also has profound
consequences for the structure, for
the symmetries, for the conservation laws.
And so the rule is every
possible term in the Lagrangian of quantum chromodynamics, of
quark physics, should be invariant under this group here.
We'll come back and we'll start to talk
about how you construct quantum chromodynamics a little bit.
I
think we're probably finished
for tonight. I'm certainly finished.
I had intended to go a little bit further tonight and tell
you a little more, but I think that was quite a lot.
I think that was quite a lot.
And I don't know how many of you followed, how many of you didn't follow,
but I hope you at least get the flavor, if not the color of what the...
All right, okay.
We'll go a little bit further with this, but then we'll get
back to some things that can be understood without too much mathematics.
For more, please visit us at stanford.edu.