Stanford University
Let's get back to SU3 and SU2.
SU3 was QCD, and it's the
symmetry which acted vertically on our table.
It took us from one color, red,
green, and blue, and mixed them up.
Let's just remind ourselves about that.
So we made ourselves a table.
This is a table not of all elementary particles, obviously,
but it's a table of all the fermions,
yeah, it's a table of all
of the fermions in the Standard Model,
and not so much because they're fermions,
but just it happens that they're kind of the constituents,
the constituent particles of the atom and the nucleus.
So let's just write them down again.
There were the six different families of quarks.
The families refer to, well, I'll
tell you what they refer to.
There's the quarks.
Up and down.
That's called a family.
That's called the up-down family.
Then there is up, down, charm, strange.
I guess you can call it
the charm or the strange family.
And then there's the top and the bottom.
That's the horizontal structure.
And then we have red, green, and blue.
And we have a quark
in each one of these slots.
Let's take this bar away here.
Take this bar away and
take this one over here away.
We have a quark in each one of these slots.
And the color symmetry, the SU symmetry,
color which is associated with quantum chromodynamics,
is the symmetry group which acts on this triplet here
and mixes them up into each other.
That symmetry group has generators.
Those generators correspond to
the infinitely small transformations,
but it also corresponds to the gluons.
The symmetry group which takes red to green to blue
is associated with the existence of gluons,
which is the existence of the blue,
the existence of gluons,
and the gluons, when they're
emitted from one quark to another,
for example, from red to green,
you create a red, sorry, red-green bar gluon.
This transformation from red to green
is simply one of the generators of SU .
So the generators of SU , the transformations,
are in one-to-one correspondence with
the emission of a gluon.
You can think of an emission
of a gluon as a physical act,
which, a physical phenomenon,
which does the same thing as the symmetry group
which mixes the particles into each other.
That's the character of gauge bosons.
Gauge bosons are a sort of manifestation
of the symmetry group in which
the emission of a gauge boson
really does change a particle from one thing to another
in exactly the same pattern as the symmetry group
would change one thing to another.
Alright, so that's red, green, and blue.
And when you perform one of these transformations,
you do it on all of the quarks simultaneously.
You don't do it just on the up quarks,
or just the up-down family.
If you want the symmetry to be correct,
if you want it to be
a real symmetry of the theory,
then you must do it
simultaneously on all of the quarks,
and that corresponds to the statement
that exactly the same gluon,
let's say this is from up to up,
up quark to up quark.
Incidentally, the gluon emission does not change
horizontally, it only changes vertically.
So, for example, the same gluon,
which would be involved in emitting,
or which would be emitted,
when a red up quark becomes a green up quark,
that's exactly the same gluon
as would be emitted when,
let's say, when a top red quark
would be a top blue.
So, the same gluon,
green quark,
red, green bar, gluon.
So, the symmetry takes whole rows
and mixes them into each other.
Then, there is a second symmetry,
by now it's actually a third symmetry,
we've talked about electrodynamics
and what it does to the,
what the emission of a photon,
or what the symmetry associated with electrodynamics,
is,
but now we're encountering another symmetry,
which is usually called flavor symmetry.
Flavor symmetry, or,
I guess, family symmetry, somehow, sometimes,
it takes ups to downs
at the same time that it takes charm to strange,
at the same time that it takes top to bottom,
keeping the color unchanged.
All right?
So, for example,
there will be processes
in which an up quark,
let's say, of the blue variety,
emits a W plus boson,
W plus,
and it becomes a down quark,
also of the blue variety.
So, what has this W boson done?
It's a physical manifestation of the transformation
which takes you horizontally back and forth.
Exactly the same W plus
would mediate, or would be emitted,
the same kind of W plus,
would be emitted when a green,
let's say, charm quark
becomes a green strange quark.
Same W plus.
وما
إلى
ذلك
the gluons never move you horizontally
the W bosons never move you vertically
and that is also the character
of the symmetry groups, the symmetry groups
move you horizontally, that's SU
it doesn't move you from here to here
or from here to here
it just
moves you between up and down, down and up
or at the same time charm and
strange, strange to charm and so forth
that's the mathematical structure
of SU cross SU
if you add
the photon
the photon emission is associated with the symmetry
which changes the phase of every charge carrying field
which I explained that to you last time
every charge carrying field
transforms with a phase
under U1
and if you add those three together
you have the basic ingredients
of SU cross SU cross U1
cross simply means
that it's a product structure
where the SU don't mix up the colors
and the SU don't mix up the upness and downness
it's a product structure
and that's where the terminology of the term
is going to be used in the future
that's where the
uh
I guess you would call it terminology
that the standard model
is a gauge theory based on the gauge group
SU3
cross SU2
cross U1
now it is actually a little
bit more complicated than I'm saying
we're going to sort out the complications
but roughly speaking
SU3 for color
SU2 for the W emission
and U1 for electrodynamics
now this is going to
get slightly more complicated than that
because what I'm saying is not 100% consistent
for reasons that will become clear
but not yet
alright the emission of a W boson
incidentally of course W bosons are only discovered
right now in the world of physics
relatively late in the game
and they were postulated
sometime in the 60s
but it really only achieved some
real traction in the 70s
the W bosons
but the theory of weak interactions
or some aspects of the theory of weak interactions
goes back much earlier than that
I suppose to the 30s
the Fermi theory of weak interactions
and we'll discuss the relationship soon enough
okay what about the coupling constants
that are involved in these various interactions
the U1 coupling constant here
that's associated with the emission of a photon
and the coupling constant is simply the electric charge
the reason that the emission
or the reason that the probability
of the emission of a photon
is the fine structure constant
is because this is the amplitude
for the emission of a photon
you have to square it
to find the probability for the
for the photon to be present
so E squared
is basically the fine structure constant
it has some pi's and things that's not important
but E squared is basically the fine structure constant
and it's also the coupling constant
or the emission
the quantum mechanical amplitude
for the emission of a photon
either the virtual emission of a photon
which means that the photon is going to be reabsorbed
before it gets very far
or if the electron is jerked out of the way
then the real emission of a photon
the amplitude for that is this constant
called the electric charge
and it's a pure number
and it's a number
well, the fine structure constant itself
the square of this number
is as I told you about 1 over 137
okay, so it's a small number here
the SU coupling constant
that's usually called G
or we can call it G strong
G sub S
that of course is associated with the
emission of a gluon
and that's also a number
that number is close to 1
well, not close, that's a little
1 is a little bit too big
the corresponding thing corresponding
to the fine structure constant
would be more like about a fifth
a fifth is a lot
bigger than a 1 over 137
so the emission of a gluon
is a much much more probable
event
when a quark smacks into something
it basically emits a gluon
with a probability close to 1
almost always emits a gluon
whereas the photon almost never emits a photon
now you might think
in view of the fact that the weak interactions
are called weak interactions
and in fact
from the fact that the decay rates
are very much lower
associated with weak interactions
the weak interactions are indeed
in many many ways
very much weaker than either
the gluonic interaction
or the electromagnetic interaction
but it's not because the coupling constant is smaller
the coupling constant of the weak interactions
is closely related
to the coupling constant
for quantum electrodynamics
it's about the same order of magnitude
are
related
it's related by some
some simple numerical factor
but not
not very different
and so that raises the question
what is it about
these processes involving W bosons
that makes it so improbable
so unlikely
that a weak interaction will take place
and it is unlikely
after all
it takes the neutron 12 minutes to decay
it must be a very unlikely process
so that's the next question
let's think about the decay of the neutron
the decay of the neutron
originates from
a down quark
inside the neutron
down quark
emitting a W minus
and becoming an up quark
so let's add in the other quarks
there's another down quark
and an up quark
alright
this is a neutron
sorry
an up
and two downs
and this is a proton
two ups and a down
and a W goes off
alright
let's
W minus
but then
the W
can also become
W minus can become an electron
an electron
and an anti-neutrino
ah
let's go back to this table here
let me remind you
there are more particles
more fermions
the additional fermions are the leptons
the leptons come in
basically the same pattern
up down
charm strange
top bottom
but
they do not carry color
the meaning of that is they don't participate at all
in the color interactions
now you're perfectly free
to ask me why
and I'm perfectly free to say I don't know
so
ah
however
there's a pattern
and the pattern is not
it does have some structure to it
but I'll tell you what
not tonight
but at some point
maybe we'll understand this pattern better
almost as though it were a fourth color
are the leptons
so
I'll just
now the leptons do not have the same charges
as
the quarks
let me just remind you
these
this column
would be the quarks with charge two thirds
and this column would be the
quarks with charge minus a third
and notice
that this one has one more unit of charge
than this one
the difference of charge is one unit
all right
down in this lepton
on rho over here, the same is true over
here of course, two thirds minus one third, two
thirds minus one third.
Now the emission of a W
only cares about the difference of charge.
In other words, a W can be emitted
if the difference of charge is the right thing.
Alright, W plus or W minus has a definite
charge and to emit it, the difference of charge
of the initial and final fermion must be correct.
Alright, so if the W can be emitted when
a neutrino becomes an electron or when an electron
becomes a neutrino, the charge difference must be the same.
Okay?
In fact, what goes down here would be the neutrino.
The neutrino, the electron neutrino, and the electron.
The charge difference is the same.
This has charge minus one, this has charge zero.
So the charge difference is the same and
it is mathematically consistent to say that a
W boson, the same W boson, can
be emitted when a neutrino becomes an electron.
In the next class, we
will discuss the difference of charge.
So, in the last column, under the
CHARM strange column, comes the neutrino associated with
the muon and the muon.
The muon is in every respect, at least as
far as we know, essentially the same as the
electron except its mass is about 200 times larger.
Again, no rhyme, no reason
for that at the present time.
And then, under the top-bottom column, the
heaviest of the quarks is matched with the
heaviest of the leptons.
Incidentally, we don't know the details of
the masses of the neutrinos very well.
All right, there's the neutrino associated with
the tau lepton and the tau lepton.
And the tau lepton is quite
a bit heavier than any other lepton.
So, we're going to look at the neutrinos.
We're going to look at the neutrinos.
So, let's look at the neutrinos.
Leptons, I understand.
What is it?
I don't remember right now what
the word lep in Greek stands for.
What is it?
Light.
Not heavy.
Right.
Oh, and baryons stand for heavy.
Yeah.
And mesons stand for something in the middle.
That's right.
Meson.
Okay.
The terminology historically was a little bit confused.
Mesons meant something in the middle.
Baryons meant something heavy like protons and neutrons.
And leptons meant something light.
Well, because of that, the muon was called
the mu meson because it was sort of midway
between the proton and the electron.
That terminology went away when it was realized
just how different the muon was from the pion,
which has a comparable mass to it.
It was much more like the
electron than it was like the pion.
And so mesons are now reserved
for quark-anti-quark pairs, and they're always bosons.
And mesons are now reserved for
quark-anti-quark pairs, and they're always bosons.
And the muon is no
longer ever called the mu meson.
So that's just a historical note.
Okay.
Now, what is the probability of this process?
It's a Feynman diagram.
Every Feynman diagram has some parts to it.
And the parts consist, first
of all, of vertices and propagators.
Propagators are the elements which have to
do with the motion of a particle.
A particle from one point to another.
In this particular case, the motion of
the W from the point where it's emitted
to the point where the electron
neutrino or electron anti-neutrino are created.
So this process has two main ingredients that
we can isolate from the rest of it.
One of them is two powers.
Let's give the coupling constant a name.
The coupling constant is a function of the muon.
we call it Mgu, we call
it OK like we call it.
It's a relação constante of the muon.
ift
But it's also an interaction coupling
constant for the emission of a W.
Let's call it Nhw.
hhjhthht Ahhhonce
Ahhthhthhh36
rht ç
I
The strong interaction coupling constant for
emitting a gluon we called G strong.
This one is G weak.
enormously small. It's not the smallness
of this coupling constant which accounts for
the improbable nature of weak interactions. So first
of all, we get two powers g weak
squared. That's analogous to the two powers
of electron charge if we exchange a photon.
This is expected to be a number of about
1 over 100. It's not exactly the fine structure
constant. It's within a factor of 3 or
something. It's close to the fine structure constant
order of magnitude. That's what this is.
But then there's something else. There is the
propagator of the W boson. So we have
to know a little bit about propagators in quantum
field theory. They are the factors which
are inserted into a Feynman diagram to account
for the motion of a
particle from one point to another.
As such, they are simply functions of
the spacetime difference or the spacetime distance
between the emission and absorption. They're functions,
if you like, of the magnitude or
the proper time along between this event and
that event. But in any case, they're functions
that propagator. Let's call it
delta. Delta for distance between.
The two points. It's a function of
the spacetime distance between those points. Function of
distance. And it has the following property. It
depends crucially on the mass of the particle
that's being exchanged. It depends on the following
way. If we were to plot it, if we
were to plot it as a function of distance.
Now, if we went through all the mathematics
of quantum field theory and worked out the
propagator, we would find that it's got a
lot of stuff in it. It's got Bessel functions.
It's a complicated function, but not that
complicated. But the important aspect of it
is that it is large at small distances. It
falls or it grows like one over the distance
to some power.
One over the distance squared between the two
points. So it's very large at small distances.
But then at the end, if the particle had
no mass, it would just continue on its way with
the same power law fall off. It would
just fall off gradually with one universal behavior,
which would go like one over the
square of the distance between the points.
That's the way it would behave.
But, the mass of this particle introduces
a new ingredient. It introduces an ingredient
which causes the propagator to decrease
suddenly like that. It decreases exponentially fast.
Exponentially fast. In other words, the power
law gives rise to an exponential. And the
interesting question is…..
that happen? Where does that happen? At
what value of distance does the mass
suddenly manifest itself and tell the
particle, hey, you're out there and you
shouldn't be out there because you're carrying
off mass and there's no mass to
carry off. I mean you're carrying off some
mass from a, from, and there just is
none, you've got to get back there. That's,
but you don't have to think about it in
terms of a story. The propagator
has an exponential decrease. Where does it
happen? And the answer is just
dimensional analysis. In units in which C
equals h bar equals 1, pick such units,
mass, mass has the same, sorry, mass has
the same units. Now when I write M
equals, I simply mean units. What's the usual
notation for units? To put
a square bracket around the quantity?
Okay, the standard notation for the units
of an object that to put a bracket
around it, a mass has the same units
as an energy, well why is that? That's
because E equals MC squared and if C is
equal to 1, etc, etc, but they also have
the same units as inverse length, length.
Mass has the same units as inverse
length. Or, oh incidentally, there's a third quantity
which has the same units of
mass and energy. What is it?
Momentum. Same as momentum. Now, what about
momentum times distance? What are the units
of momentum times distance?
No?
M.
Uncertainty?
Uncertainty.
Think uncertainty principle. Think
uncertainty principle. Momentum times distance
is h bar. But h bar is dimensionless
in these units. So momentum and distance simply have
inverse units to each other. Okay? So
therefore, length has inverse distance to both mass,
energy and also momentum.
Therefore, we can say that,
or we can write it differently.
we can write that length has units of inverse mass.
Yeah, one over mass.
Well, that tells us the
horizontal axis here was distance, d.
The mass of the particle is m,
and that tells us that the distance
at which it falls off like this, the
only way that we can make a distance
using the mass of the particle,
occurs at a distance of one over
the mass of the particle.
Now that's really the Compton wavelength of the particle.
If we put back some c's
and h-bars, what would it be?
h-bar over mc.
Let's put back the h-bars and h-bar over mc.
Distance at a distance of order h-bar over mc.
The propagator suddenly dives down as an exponential.
Excuse me, what is the vertical axis of the particle?
The vertical axis is the size of delta.
Delta.
And what it is, is its
square of the propagator is the probability
that the particle can go that far before it emits.
So what this is saying is
that there's a sudden sharp turn off
of the probability for the
particle to go a given distance
before converting like this, which is controlled by the mass
of the particle.
In particular, the heavier the mass of the particle,
the less the distance it can go
before it has to give up its energy,
which is the probability in this form.
All right, now, usually what's prescribed in an experiment
is not the two points where these events take place.
What's prescribed in an experiment
is the momenta of the particles.
You measure the momentum of the particles.
You measure the momentum of the incident particle,
p of the proton.
No, this is the neutron down here.
Neutron.
You measure the momentum of the proton.
And what do you know?
You know the momentum of the W boson.
The momentum of the W boson
is the difference of the momentum
of the proton and neutron.
So you know the momentum of the W boson.
And of course, that tells you
the momentum of the electron and neutrino
by momentum conservation.
You don't, as a rule, certainly
not in these kind of experiments,
actually know the difference.
You know the distance between those two points.
You know the momentum.
But there's a relationship between functions of momentum
and functions of position, or functions of distance.
And that relationship is Fourier transform.
You can think of the propagator either
as a function of positions or momentum.
You can think of it as
a function of either position or momentum.
The position, distance between here and here,
or the Fourier transform of this function,
the Fourier transform of it,
is the amplitude for emitting
a W with a given momentum.
So the question is, what does the Fourier transform
of a function like this look like?
I'm not going to work it out.
This is something you can go and study for yourself.
So, if you have a
function which has a power law
and then a sudden decrease like that,
I will simply tell you what
the Fourier transform of the propagator is.
The Fourier transform is a function of the
square of the momentum of the W boson,
and also, parametrically, it depends on
the mass of the W boson.
Let's call it
twiddle.
Twiddle stands for Fourier transform.
And it's a function,
what should we call the momentum of the W?
Let's call it k.
And what does it look like? It's very simple.
1 divided by k squared plus
the mass of the W squared.
That's it.
That's the factor.
That's the factor that you put in,
and you know the momentum of the W.
And how would you know it?
By measuring the initial and final
momentum of the proton and neutron.
You measure the momentum of the W,
and then you insert this factor
in as one of the factors into
the amplitude for the emission of the W.
That's the rule.
That's Feynman's rules.
And that's it.
The addition,
oh, first of all, let's talk about a photon.
If we emit a photon, it has no mass.
And it's just 1 over k squared.
Typically, when you emit a photon,
in ordinary quantum electrodynamics,
the momentum of the photon is
pretty low by particle physics standards.
It's typically, you know, a few
hundred electron volts or something like that.
It's a very small k.
And so, the propagator for emitting the photon
at low momentum is rather large.
At low momentum, this is a
big number as k goes to 0.
The weak interactions,
we know that the probability
of emission is much, much smaller.
As I said, it is not the coupling constant there.
So the only thing it can be
is the mass of the W boson.
If the mass of the W boson is very large,
for whatever reason,
then this is always going to be small.
In fact, the biggest it will ever be
is what happens when k is equal to 0.
When k is equal to 0,
this propagator here is equal
to just 1 over mw squared,
and it's never bigger than that.
That's as big as it gets.
So the most likely thing to happen
is to emit a low momentum W.
And if you do,
it costs you a probability amplitude
equal to 1 divided by
the mass of the W squared.
This is standard quantum field theory.
In addition, there are the coupling constants.
So the net result
is that the probability, or the amplitude,
not the probability,
the amplitude for emitting,
emitting a W
and having it convert to an electron neutrino
is gw squared
divided by mw squared.
The mw squared is the factor in this Feynman diagram
for the W to go from here to here.
Or at least that's the biggest it can get.
Yeah.
Richard?
So in the other propagators,
the k squared part has minus signs in it.
k0 squared minus k1 squared.
Well, yes, this is true.
This is true.
Where...
Okay, so there we have
to get a little more technical.
And that mostly comes into play, yeah.
The...
Very little energy is emitted in a situation like this,
more momentum than energy.
So it's mostly space-like,
which means it's positive.
The reaction...
You would have to worry about this
if the momentum of this was time-like,
but it's not in these kind of processes.
But still, the main thing is that it's always small.
Why is it small?
A proton becomes...
In a beta decay,
the amount of momentum that's
transferred from the proton to the...
Or from the neutron to the proton
is minuscule by comparison with
the mass of the W boson.
Minuscule.
So it doesn't even matter whether it's positive or negative,
the k squared.
It's tiny by comparison with the...
With the mass of the W.
So the net result is that...
The weak interactions are made weak
because of the large mass of the W.
How large is it?
About a hundred times the mass of a proton.
So that means that the amplitude...
The amplitude for this process
is going to have a factor...
A relatively small factor from GW squared.
Roughly the fine structure constant.
And then a one over MW squared,
which is a tiny fraction squared.
The mass of the W is
a hundred times the proton mass.
That's a factor of ten thousand.
But that's just the amplitude.
We have to square the whole thing
to find the probability for the reaction to happen.
So what does that mean?
That means something like GW to the fourth
divided by MW to the fourth.
That's a very small number.
That's a very small number
if the mass of the W is large.
That's why weak interactions are small.
Not because the primordial coupling constant is small,
but because the mass of the W,
for whatever reasons,
happens to be large
in nuclear physics
or in proton-neutron type mass units.
And the usual units of nuclear physics
or old particle physics,
the mass of the W is large.
Are you just saying that's one in a million
or one in a billion?
One in a billion.
GW squared is about ten
to the minus three or something.
And then the mass of the
W is a hundred in proton units.
So that's ten to the four millions at least.
How do we know what
the mass of the W is?
From the weakness of the weak interactions.
Right.
So, right.
So, originally,
all that was known from experiment
was this combination.
What was known was that combination.
And it was called capital G Fermi.
Experimentally, what you measure
is neither...
By now, of course, there are fancier experiments,
but the experiments in the old days
where you never had enough momentum
to make this denominator vary very much.
You didn't get to see that the denominator
was varying with momentum.
All you saw was this numerical constant.
And it was always the same W boson in there.
It didn't change from one reaction to another.
It was always the W boson.
It was always Mw squared.
And so experimentally,
all you knew was this number G Fermi,
which is a small number.
A very small number.
Whatever its numerical value is.
It carries dimensions.
So if I told you what it is in some...
What should I tell you?
In units of light years per unit?
Whatever.
It's a small number.
Right.
So that's what was known historically.
Sometimes,
in 19...
Must be in the 1950s,
various theorists,
Julian Schwinger,
other people began to suspect,
look,
maybe the weak interactions
are similar to other interactions
and mediated by some sort of particle.
I don't know where the terminology W came from.
Probably stood for weak.
And I don't know if it was Schwinger or not
who first used it.
But,
I don't know.
the idea of a particle
heavy enough
that it would make this a small number
was introduced sometime, I think, in the 50s.
But it was recognized
pretty much from the beginning
that it would take a pretty heavy particle,
a hundred times the mass of the proton.
And so it wasn't until accelerators came into being
where you could generate that much energy.
Mid 70s, late 70s,
where accelerators,
which could create enough energy to generate a W particle,
actually detected it and actually measured it.
So yeah, the W particle really exists.
It can be produced.
So at the beginning of the class today,
you talked about the effect of the binding energy,
which seems to me in this picture
is the presence of the field of a nearby proton
that suppresses this,
this whole process.
What's suppressing it?
The presence of the field of
the nearby proton in the uterine.
In other words,
It only suppresses it because of energy conservation.
Nothing else.
A thing can't happen
if there isn't a better
energy available for it to happen.
So that's another thing which controls rates.
Yeah, okay.
Rates are controlled by three things.
Or,
well,
three things.
Coupling constants,
masses of particles,
and energy.
So,
you have particles in intermediate states like this,
and also available energy.
Available energy has to do with the energy
of the initial state and the final state.
There are three different features.
Coupling constants,
masses or propagators if you like,
the structure of propagators and
how they depend on momentum.
And finally,
a thing can't happen if there isn't enough energy.
So,
you have to have a very small
probability if the energy available is small enough.
So,
you need the initial state to have as much energy
as the final state in order for the process to happen.
And it's the last of the ingredients
there that had to do with the
suppression of the deuteron decay.
Three separate things.
Yeah.
These coupling constants,
are they really constant?
Or do they vary a little bit?
They vary a little bit.
We will come to that with momentum,
with distance scale.
Yeah.
So,
the W boson has a lot of energy,
right?
A lot of mass.
Well,
a real W boson in the
laboratory has a lot of mass.
Now,
when it degrades into an electron and a muon,
whatever,
right?
What happens to that energy?
The electron,
the energy of the final state must be
the same as the energy of the initial state.
That means there isn't really enough
energy to create the W boson.
There really isn't enough energy to create the W boson.
That's why there is no real process
in where a W boson goes flying off.
There simply isn't enough energy for that.
Well,
so what does happen?
The W boson is produced virtually.
According to the rules of quantum mechanics,
a violation of energy can take place as long
as it takes place for a short enough time.
If the amount of extra energy that's in here,
let's call it delta E,
energy time uncertainty principle,
says,
among other things,
that an apparent,
an apparent violation of the W boson,
of energy conservation,
delta E,
can only last for a time delta T,
which cannot be bigger than,
which must be smaller than in this case,
Planck's constant.
You cannot have an apparent violation
of energy in an intermediate state
that lasts for a time
longer than
delta E delta T,
of order h bar.
Let me give you another
example of this sort of thing.
If you have a potential,
ordinary potential energy,
this potential energy could be the potential
energy of an alpha particle in a nucleus.
An alpha particle is stuck in the nucleus.
It can't get out.
Why not?
It doesn't have enough energy to get out.
It has to go over a bump to get out.
So the alpha particle normally sits in the nucleus.
The beta particle normally sits over here.
But,
it can tunnel out.
Quantum mechanically,
Now,
the kinetic energy of a particle is always positive,
right?
In here it has a certain amount of energy.
It has a much higher potential energy over here.
This is a potential,
an ordinary potential function.
The potential energy is up here.
The particle started at rest.
It had no kinetic energy.
And had this much potential energy.
It has the same amount of potential energy over here.
And the same,
and also when it comes out over here,
it also comes out at rest.
Comes out over here at rest.
It was at rest over here.
Same potential energy, same potential energy.
So, it can happen.
On the other hand,
if you look at it in between,
it seems that it had a large potential energy,
much larger than it had over here.
And it can't have less kinetic
energy than it had over here.
The kinetic energy was over,
it was zero over here.
The meaning of that is
that it temporarily,
apparently violated energy conservation.
Now,
if you went and measured the particle in here,
and checked whether it was in here or not,
you would destroy the phenomena of tunneling.
But,
if you just look on the outside,
you will have to say,
somehow,
in the intermediate state here,
the electron had more energy than it was,
the alpha particle,
had more energy than it was supposed to have.
There was a violation of energy conservation,
an apparent one.
How long can the alpha particle last
under this barrier here?
The answer is it can't last long.
And the rule is,
if the violation of energy conservation,
this over here,
delta E,
then it had better get out from under there
in a time,
delta T,
which is less than H bar over delta E.
So this is a kind of familiar thing
from elementary quantum mechanics,
that apparent violations of energy conservation
can take place as long as they last
sufficiently short time.
Same thing over here.
There is,
the W boson is a very heavy particle.
There is simply,
not enough energy
in the neutron,
proton, neutron,
or anything else
to create a W boson,
let alone have enough energy
for the final particle.
That cannot happen.
What can happen is that temporarily,
for a very, very short time period,
the neutron can emit the W,
W minus,
become a proton,
but then it is as if
the alpha particle were under the barrier here,
the W boson says,
I can't last that long,
I better get rid of all that energy,
and it can do it a number of ways.
One way it can do
it is just by getting reabsorbed.
Okay?
The other way it can do it
is by becoming the electron,
which has a small energy,
and the anti-neutrino,
which also has a small energy.
So, the intermediate state here
of a very, very heavy W boson
is very much like the intermediate state
in which the alpha particle
is under the barrier here,
and it can only last a short time.
Yeah?
No, no, no, no.
And even energy conservation
from initial times
to final state is always exact.
It's just an apparent of our mission.
It would appear as though
the reabsorption is what happens all the time.
Basically, the W comes out and goes back,
and goes out and goes back.
Most of the times that can happen.
Every once in a while,
every once in a billion tries,
it goes out far enough
to decay itself.
That's correct.
Most of the time,
it's going to decay.
Do we have a separator
that's powerful enough
to make real W bosons?
Yeah.
How long?
Now, the Ws will decay
to electrons and neutrinos,
but if you make a W with enough energy,
all right, there's a certain lifetime
for a real W to decay.
It's not this uncertainty time here.
There is a certain lifetime,
so the W, when it's produced,
will eventually decay,
but the faster the W is,
the more time dilation
will cause the W to decay
later and later.
So real Ws are produced,
and the meaning of real Ws
is that you produce things
which, whose decay probability
is controlled by their velocity
and the standard relativity way.
What's the proper time
for it to decay?
Oh, boy.
Okay.
Very short.
The W...
Three times sin .
Three times sin to the 25th second.
Three times ten to the 27th?
Is that true?
I'll have to think about it.
You've described the Kovling constant
as the...
You've said the Kovling constant
is the probability
of the impact diagram
of the W.
Well, okay.
How does that translate
into a rate
or a time
for the decay?
The rate...
Right.
This...
I don't know.
This is...
This is the amplitude...
All right.
This is the amplitude
for the process.
The square of the amplitude
is a probability.
That's this.
And it's a probability
per unit time.
It's a probability
per unit time,
and so its inverse
is related...
Is related to the lifetime.
Its inverse is related
to the lifetime,
and that's why
this is a very small number.
The lifetime
unusually large in particle physics
units. So weak lifetimes, particles which
can only decay for one reason
or another by weak interactions have anomalously
long lifetimes. And where do you trace it to?
You trace it to the mass of the W. Now
if a process, remember what this really
was, it was k squared plus Mw squared,
well, right, if you have enough energy and
enough momentum, you can detect the fact eventually
that these rates here will be momentum
dependent. In other words, the effective constant here
won't be constant, it will depend on k.
And that, of course, has been seen with great
precision.
So
For the tunneling process, there's a delta T
which implies a kind of velocity. Is there
a?
Yeah, but if you went in there and
tried to detect the velocity, you'd destroy the process.
So if you take the this end and that end
and figure out the delta T, you know, the distance
you inferred.
You can construct something you can call a
velocity. It would be misleading to, you know,
think of it as the velocity of a
real signal, though. It's not a signal velocity.
Can we usually get any understanding of the
lifetime of a real 3W from looking at the
I think that's a good question. I think
the velocity is probably a little bit more
than that. I think the velocity is a little
bit more than that. I think the velocity is
Mm-hmm.
That's exactly the way you would calculate it.
Because the shot is so short.
The W boson, for example, it
has a number of ways of decaying,
but one way it can decay, literally
decay, is into an electron in an anti-neutrino.
And you can calculate the Feynman diagram
describing it has this factor G in it.
W minus a factor G and electron in anti-neutrino.
And you can calculate that.
And yes, you can compute the lifetime of the W.
It comes out to be 10 minus 20.
Whatever it is.
Same twist on the question.
In the case where in the
laboratory you produce a W boson,
Right.
what happens to that energy?
Because electron has very little energy.
No, no, no.
The W, when a real W decays,
it produces an electron in
a neutrino with enormous kinetic energy.
Very relativistic.
Right.
A W boson at rest will become,
and there are other decay modes.
I mean, this is not the only decay mode.
It can do a muon in a
neutrino, a number of different decay modes.
But if it decayed to an electron in a neutrino,
they would be very, very
relativistic electrons and neutrinos now.
I'm a little confused with exactly what is
the distinction between a real and a virtual particle.
Is there a clear definition?
Is there a greater definition?
Real and virtual, real particles are
simply the ones in the created initially,
well, the particles which came in and particles
which went out of a small interaction region.
The virtual particles are mathematical constructs
which are the internal particles in a Feynman diagram.
You don't observe them.
If you went into the, if
you suddenly tried to observe that particle,
how would you observe that particle?
The only way you could observe it
would be send something else into the system.
Okay, let's talk about trying
to observe particles of this nature.
So even before that, what about trying
to observe what's happening to an alpha particle
as it moves under there?
Well, obviously you have only a
very short time to observe it.
So if you want to observe, if you want
to know whether there was a particle under here,
you would have to interact with it
on a very, very short time scale.
Right?
A very short time scale to get in.
If you wanted to find out, for
example, by looking at it with a photon,
you would have to send in
a very, very short wavelength photon pulse.
In particular, the energy of that photon
pulse would have to be about that big.
That's what this energy time uncertainty principle says.
The same energy time uncertainty principle
gives you information about the wavelength
energy of a photon that you would need if
you wanted to have a time resolution good enough
to see what was going on in there.
So if you wanted to actually see the
motion of the alpha particle from here to here,
which lasts a time delta t, you would have to
hit it with a photon whose energy was big enough
that it actually would knock
the alpha particle into this region.
Into this region here.
So you're supplying the energy, but...
You're supplying the energy, and it's
one of these quantum mechanical complementarity things
that you think something is impossible,
and so you try to detect it.
And you find out in order to detect it,
you have to do to the system exactly that thing
which you were trying to prove does not happen.
Right?
This is always the same story.
And the same would be true of virtual particles.
Virtual particles last a small time.
If you wanted to get into the system and
detect one, you would have to hit it with something
with enough energy that it
would actually create that particle.
If you wanted to see the virtual
W here, how much time do you have?
Very short.
So you hit it with a photon.
A photon of sufficiently small wavelength that guess what?
It's got enough energy to actually knock a W out
of the system so that you actually see a W.
All right.
That's sort of unsatisfying and frustrating.
You were trying to prove one thing, and you found
out that you had to do something to the system
which did to it exactly what
you were trying to prove didn't happen.
Always that way.
That's quantum mechanics in a nutshell.
It's true that in a particle physics
experiment, you never see directly the W.
You never, on a scattering
experiment, you never see a W.
Not true.
If you're trying to see, for example, okay,
so let's first talk about something slightly different.
Do you ever get to see the
virtual photons that are present in an electron?
Well, yeah.
If you hit the electron
hard enough, you'll knock it out.
You'll knock the electron out, and
the photon will be left over.
So you do get to see them in that sense.
You do get to see the virtual photons if you do
exactly the experiment which puts in enough energy to see those virtual.
Let's come back to the W.
Same thing is true.
If you have a proton, that proton
can emit a W and become a neutron.
And of course, if there's nothing else around and it doesn't
decay, then the W will have to come back and be reabsorbed.
And so you can think of a proton as a sort of
equilibrium between a proton and a neutron with a W boson around it.
Constantly going back and forth between the two of them,
between the two things, with a very, very, very fast oscillation.
An enormously fast oscillation between the two.
You want to see that W?
All you have to do is hit it hard enough with a photon that has a frequency
which is large enough that it can resolve the short times that the W is out there.
And guess what?
If you do hit a proton with a high
energy photon, yes, you will knock out a W.
So in that sense, you get to see them.
But then, of course, it becomes a different process.
It becomes a process in which the W
is a final particle, not an intermediate one.
Is there any sense in saying that there's
a difference between a neutron and a proton?
A proton goes to neutron goes to proton.
You can also have neutron goes to
proton goes to neutron with a W.
The difference is that this one would be a
W plus and this one would be a W minus.
Yes?
Does it make any sense to say that when you did that experiment that
you knocked the W particle out as opposed to you created the W particle?
No, you can say it either way.
Language is one thing.
Facts are another thing.
The fact is at the end of the
day, there will be a W flying out.
Do you want to interpret that as a
W that was there beforehand that you knocked out?
Or was it a newly created W?
Well, the mathematics says that there will be a W.
One picture of it is that the W was there and you
jerked the neutron out before the W had a chance to get back.
And the mathematics supports that.
I mean, there is a way of thinking
about the mathematics that says that's what happens.
On the other hand, is this true?
All you ever get by
putting in enough energy is W?
You don't get so much energy.
You don't get enough?
Well, if I put in enough energy to
get a W particle, I get a W particle.
What if I put in twice that energy?
You still get W particles.
So does that imply somewhere in existence
the W because you always get W's?
Well, you don't always get W's.
Sometimes you get W's.
Sometimes you might get three W's.
When you hit a particle hard
enough, you get all sorts of junk.
When you hit a particle really hard, this is
what I was trying to tell you the other night.
When you try to think about what is
elementary and what's not elementary, it gets very confusing.
Because if you take what you thought was a
very elementary particle and you hit it really hard enough,
all kinds of junk comes out.
And among the junk that comes
out might be chairs and tables.
Well, you'd need a hell of
a lot of energy for that.
But you hit an electron hard enough with a photon, really, really, really hard, meaning to say with
much, much more energy than, for example, the mass of a proton, mass of a thousand protons, for example.
And guess what?
Out of it will come
protons, electrons, all sorts of things.
Every once in a while, one of
those electrons will stick to a proton.
And so you will discover that inside an
electron or inside a proton, there's a proton.
electron or inside a proton, there's a hydrogen atom.
The lesson is don't try to...
Your mental picture of what comes out of a system is
necessarily what was in there beforehand is a little bit defective.
Does this have anything to do with vacuum energy?
This in itself doesn't.
It really has to do with diagrams
which are disconnected from the rest of...
They're just there in the vacuum.
But the presence of vacuum diagrams like this...
Okay, so a vacuum diagram is
something which also apparently violates energy conservation.
Let's suppose this were an
electron, an electron, and a photon.
Two electrons necessarily have a
certain minimum amount of energy.
The vacuum has no energy.
Okay?
And so there's a certain violation of energy in there.
That means that that pair can
only last for a short time.
And I say, okay, I
would like to see that pair.
So you send in some very high frequency photon or
a pair of very high frequency photons from opposite sides.
And guess what?
You sometimes make electron-positron pairs
with an extra photon in them.
So you knock the hell out of that
vacuum fluctuation and you discover pairs of particles.
Yeah?
What are these reactions?
Are they independent of temperature or dependent on...
Oh, no, they're not dependent on temperature.
They are dependent on the particles that
you're colliding having a lot of energy.
All right, so it's a good question.
Let's say what it has to do with temperature.
When you have a system at high temperature,
it simply means that you
have a lot of particles around
with high energy.
So that means that typically at high temperatures,
there are enough high energy particles
to cause these things to happen.
But just think of high temperatures as just
having a lot of high energy particles around.
If you have a very
small number of high energy particles,
you won't think of that as temperature.
You'll just say, I have
some particles with large kinetic energy.
Right?
An example of what temperature
can do is if you have...
The alpha particle bound inside the nucleus like that,
and then you put it into a temperature bath.
Now, I don't mean your bath water temperature bath.
I mean temperatures which are many MeVs high,
which is zillions and zillions of degrees high.
But the effect of putting it into temperature,
you can either think of it
as particles coming in and colliding,
or you can just think of it as thermal...
vibrations causing this alpha particle to jiggle around
and give it enough temperature,
and sure enough, it'll jiggle over the top sometimes.
So yes, these virtual processes
can be induced by temperature.
But temperature is another way of just saying
there's a lot of high energy particles around.
Did you say that the vacuum could not
be attributed to the generation of W plus,
the...
The vacuum could not be attributed...
I don't think I ever said
the vacuum was attributed to anything.
No, I...
You were talking about the...
Vacuum fluctuations.
Yeah, vacuum fluctuations.
The W plus is some kind of a fluctuation too.
Well, the W is a particle.
The W is a particle.
I know, but the...
But isn't there a relationship between that and...
The W in this diagram is a fluctuation,
but it's not a fluctuation of the vacuum.
It's a fluctuation of the protein.
It's a fluctuation of the proton.
The proton sometimes fluctuates and
makes a W and a neutron.
That's, you know, a relative of,
but not the same thing as saying
an electron,
an antineutrino,
and a W, let's see,
that would be a W plus,
can sometimes form a vacuum fluctuation.
It's another process where there really
isn't enough energy for it to happen,
so it happens in this virtual
sense for a short period of time,
and in that sense it's
similar to this, but it's different.
But the same rules apply to it.
It can only last for a short time.
So if you want to
get into it and observe it,
you have to do it with
something which has very high energy
because of the uncertainty principle,
and the result is the energy is always enough.
If the energy is high enough to see in there,
it'll also be high enough to create those particles.
You'll have enough energy to actually release them.
The antineutrino is necessary for conservation.
Say it again.
The antineutrino is necessary there for conservation.
Yeah.
But another way of saying it is that
the basic interaction is always
one between electron, neutrino, and W.
Right. But yes, it is.
Right.
I was thinking that you could
turn a coffee bean into a cake.
Coffee bean into a cake, chocolate cake,
by basically adding energy.
You put in enough energy
to incinerate the coffee bean and add a chocolate cake.
Mm-hmm.
One cake is the probability.
Just one chocolate?
Why only one chocolate cake?
Okay, so how much, what's
the weight of a chocolate cake?
Weight of a chocolate cake is,
if it's really good chocolate cake, dense,
it weighs a kilogram, right?
A kilogram is a thousand grams,
which is 10 to the eighth Planck masses.
Okay.
10 to the eighth Planck masses.
Good.
If you could accelerate a pair of particles
to 10 to the eighth Planck masses
with a very, very, very small probability,
you might get a chocolate cake out.
Yeah.
Dream on, Michael.
Or anything else that weighs a kilogram.
What's that?
Right.
If you could put a,
I mean, if you could
make a delta T small enough
Mm-hmm.
to do your chair analogy,
you could get electrons turning into chair and anti-chair.
Right.
Now, if you take that to an extreme,
as short as possible time,
what is the mass that,
like a Planck, you know, Planck time,
what would the mass be equivalent to that?
Of a Planck time?
Yeah.
The Planck mass,
which is about 10 to the minus five grams.
So wouldn't that be the limit to how?
No.
The Planck mass is not the heaviest mass.
Obviously not.
I mean, a lot of Planck mass is.
But if you're going to explain chairs and anti-chairs,
shorter time, you could take planets and anti-planets
and galaxies and the like.
Right.
If you collide particles at energies much larger
than the Planck mass,
what you get,
I was going to say 99 times out of 100,
but let's make it 99.999999
endlessly out of whatever it is,
you'll get a black hole.
Okay?
But every once in a while,
with a probability which is exponentially small
in the entropy of the black hole,
that black hole will emit a chair.
Instead.
Right.
How do I know that?
I know that because the process of
a chair falling into a black hole
is possible.
And therefore, by time reversals,
you can get a black hole.
And so,
therefore, by time reversal invariance,
the process of a black hole
emitting a chair must be possible.
So yes, every once in a while,
the black hole,
or when I say every once in a while,
I mean a very rare percentage of the times
that you do this experiment,
the black hole will behave
in a statistically extremely unlikely way.
But all that entropy is, is statistics.
And basically anything that can happen will happen.
Eventually.
And so, yes, everything can
come out of a black hole
if you do the process enough times.
So, um, above,
so all of this above the Planck energy scale
has to do with the properties
of emission from a black hole.
The virtual photons and W particles are bosons.
So will they interact with the
other bosons in the close body
and tend to fall off?
Okay, which which photons?
Virtual photons and virtual...
Will they interact with which?
Any other virtual photon.
Okay, the virtual, let's first ask,
does the W interact with the photon?
Well, say there's another W close by,
the virtual W,
if they were,
will they call out the same statements as the bosons?
You want to know whether
Ws will interact with each other.
Do you have a question?
Well, photons fall in the same place.
They don't really interact with each other.
You know, all these are...
Photons do interact with each other a little bit.
You know how they interact with each other?
Through virtual pair production,
but you're talking about due
to the fact that they're bosons.
The fact that they're bosons is not what says
that they don't interact with each other.
Bosons, fermions, they all interact.
No difference in that respect.
Okay.
The reason that the photon
doesn't seem to interact with other photons,
let's see if we can trace it down.
Photons can scatter.
Now, ordinarily in the laboratory,
two light beams won't scatter each other.
But two photons can do the following.
A photon can come in,
another photon can come in,
and they can create an electron-positron pair.
Electron, E minus, E plus.
Electron-positron pair.
Well, if that can happen,
then the opposite can happen.
An electron-positron pair can become a pair of photons.
And in fact, it can happen as a virtual process.
As a virtual process,
a pair of photons can come in and go out,
but scatter by means of a virtual process.
By means of an intermediate state,
which is an electron-positron pair.
Okay.
Now, why doesn't it happen
in the laboratory with ordinary photons?
And the answer is,
it takes a certain amount of energy
to create the electron-positron pairs.
Right?
Each electron has a mass of,
what is it, half an MeV?
Right.
So these together take an MeV of energy.
If the pair of photons
has energy very, very much lower than that,
then there is not enough energy
for the real creation of an electron-positron pair.
But still, it can happen virtually.
But when it happens virtually,
there are propagators in here,
and it's the same sort of deal
as what happened here.
When you have to supply extra energy
for the process to happen,
there is always a cost
and probability.
Typically, the cost and probability
is somehow inverse to the amount of energy
that you need to make the process happen.
Okay?
So this process doesn't happen in the laboratory
because in the laboratory,
photon energies are always vastly smaller
than the mass of an electron.
Photon energies are what?
An electron volt?
Typical photon, optical photons,
are...
are an electron volt or two.
The mass of an electron is
of order a million electron volts.
And so typically, the photons
don't have nearly enough energy
for this process to happen.
And when a process,
when an intermediate process happens,
which has to happen very fast,
it comes and goes,
it's always at a cost of probability.
So this process, the scattering,
is a very low probability process
at low energies.
On the other hand,
if the photons hit with enough energy
to be able to create an electron-positron pair,
they really do interact with each other.
Now, I forgot what the original question was.
It had to do with W bosons.
But the same thing...
Same thing is true.
W bosons do interact with each other.
I wasn't talking about that type of interaction.
I was talking about their statistical interaction
because they're both...
Oh, they are bosons, yes.
Don't think...
It's not an interaction.
It's just the effect of Bosa statistics.
Well, let's put it this way.
The effects of the statistics,
fermion versus boson,
is only interesting
when you have a situation
where you create more than one particle.
So more than one particle
pretty much near each other,
pretty much in the same state.
In most particle physics experiments,
you create the particles going off,
flying off in every direction,
and it's very rare that you have two particles
of the same type going off
in pretty much the same direction
in such a way that it matters very much
whether they're fermions or bosons.
But yes, I mean, they do interact statistically
the same way photons do.
W bosons will prefer to be in the same state,
in the same sense that photons prefer to...
In principle, you could make a laser out of them.
Don't...
Not likely, but...
In principle,
you could make a system laze W bosons.
Can you tell whether...
You should call it a laser.
Can you tell what color...
Can you tell what color the proton or neutron is?
What color it is.
Does it matter? Red, green?
No, it's always three quarks,
one red, one green, and one blue,
which makes it white.
Or colorless.
Black or white, I'm not sure,
but I guess white.
But it...
There should be superpositions
of red, green, and black.
Somehow.
But a proton is always
one red, one green, one blue.
Is this a place to bring in
what happens at the other end of the energy spectrum
like the boson kind condensate?
Well...
Is that...
I'm just asking the question,
is this a place to fit it
in, or will we get to it?
Yeah, we will get to it,
and we'll get to it in the context
of the Higgs boson.
Okay.
Yeah.
The Higgs boson is the place
where something like
boson condensation happens.
Um...
All right, I did have one...
All right, um...
Nobody has asked me,
so let me bring it up myself.
What kind of group structure could we imagine
which would mix the up quark and the down quark?
Well, the up quark and the down quark...
The charm quark and the strange quark,
just forget them.
Just up quark and down quark,
they go into each other by W emission.
What group could we be talking about?
Now, it's obvious.
We're talking about SU .
There are two elements here,
and one can go to the other.
That's the symmetry of the system.
We're talking about SU .
But how many generators does SU have?
Good.
It has three generators.
Each generator,
the gauge bosons are in one-to-one correspondence
with the generators of the group.
That's the way it works.
The eight gauge bosons,
the eight gluons,
there's one for each generator of SU .
We only have two gauge bosons,
W plus and W minus,
but we're trying to postulate
that this is a theory
based on the symmetry SU .
We're missing something.
And indeed we are.
We're missing one gauge boson.
It is not the photon.
It is...
It is closely related to
the particle called the Z boson,
a third member of the W family,
W plus, W minus, and Z.
We'll come to it next time.
Please remind me if I forget to talk about
the relationship between electric charge,
Z boson, SU and so forth.
We've got to come to that.
But I wasn't...
I was going to talk about it,
but it's getting too late for now.
In fact, it's getting too late to do almost anything.
The other thing I had intended to talk about tonight
was spontaneous symmetry breaking.
Let's talk a little bit about spontaneous symmetry breaking,
just qualitatively,
and we won't try to do anything quantitative tonight.
Just qualitatively.
What is spontaneous symmetry breaking?
I think the best way to
describe it is by illustrating it.
There's a famous illustration,
which is in a sense spontaneous symmetry breaking,
but it's a famous illustration.
It's a famous illustration,
but it's a famous illustration,
it's not really a symmetry breaking,
but if it helps you, okay.
It's actually somewhat correct.
The famous example is people sit down to dinner
around a large table,
and each person has to
the left of them a fork
and to the right of them a fork.
Next person, left of them
and right of them a fork.
And nobody knows whether to go for the left fork,
for the left fork,
or the right fork.
And they sit there, and they sit there,
and they sit there,
and they can't decide what to do,
until all of a sudden,
one of them makes a
little motion toward the right fork,
and then they all go for the right fork.
There was nothing asymmetric to begin with,
but there was a kind of instability.
There was a kind of instability,
two possibilities in instability,
and the instability being such
that when the instability is kicked in,
when it's kicked off,
the whole universe, so to speak,
suddenly goes one way instead of the other way.
So, I will give you an example,
a mathematical example.
A ferromagnet is an example
of spontaneous symmetry breaking.
But let's think, let's start with a very simple example.
The simple example is,
a bunch of spins,
and the spins can either be all up or all,
sorry, the spins can either be up or down.
For the moment, it's not even important
that we're talking about quantum mechanics.
These could be coins, classical coins.
And the coins can either be up or down.
They're laid out on a table,
in a lattice.
Here they are.
And there's an interaction energy
between neighboring coins.
The interaction energy is such
that if the coins, if the neighbors are opposite,
for example, a heads and a tails,
that costs energy.
In other words, there's some kind of force
between the particles, or the spins,
or the coins,
so that if they're opposite,
that costs some energy.
If they're parallel, it costs less energy.
So they like to be parallel.
Energetically, they like to be parallel.
But parallel can mean this way or this way.
Anti-parallel can mean this way or this way.
Anti-parallel costs more energy than parallel.
Now think about the state of lowest energy.
What is the state of lowest energy?
The state of lowest energy
is obviously,
all heads or all tails.
There are two states of lowest energy.
All heads or all tails.
Which one is the ground state?
They're both ground states.
But now, supposing way far away,
off a hundred miles away,
one of the spins is known to be heads.
That one is asymmetric.
Well, normally, under most circumstances,
you would say that one degree of freedom,
very, very far away,
has no effect
on what the properties of the ground state are
far away from that degree of freedom.
That's a typical expectation.
It's usually true.
It's almost always true, ordinarily.
But, in this case,
that one head
will cause the ground state energy
to be different if they're all heads
than if they're all tails.
If they're all heads,
then you'll save one unit of energy,
and so, in seeking its ground state,
this system will tend to all heads
rather than all tails.
Once it's all heads,
then you can forget,
you can, once it's all heads,
then you can start over again,
and say, look,
the lowest energy state of this system is all heads,
it will cost me some energy
to put a tail in there
because it has four neighbors
which are trying to make it a head.
So, the result is
that this kind of system,
although it started with a symmetry,
it started with a symmetry,
heads goes to tails,
asymptotically very, very far away,
boundary conditions,
or just a very, very distant degree of freedom,
will tip off a instability
and put the system into one of the many possible,
in this case, only two possible ground states,
and once it's in that ground state,
then the properties of what goes on in here
are determined by that ground state.
In particular,
a tail will cost you energy
because of the presence of all the heads.
This is the simple,
and the most primitive example
of a spontaneous symmetry breaking.
How is it different
than just an ordinary symmetry breaking?
What would an ordinary symmetry breaking mean?
An ordinary symmetry breaking,
or what we can call an explicit symmetry breaking,
would be a symmetry breaking
if heads had a different energy than tails.
Not pairwise energies,
but just one head by itself.
Supposing that one head by itself
had less energy than a tail,
then of course it would be completely obvious
that the system would,
in its lowest energy state,
be all heads.
And so it would be also the case,
all heads,
but there would be no second ground state
in which they were all tails.
It would be biased by the energy,
or be biased by the energy,
not the one extra point,
or the particle infinitely far away,
but by the local things going on nearby.
So that would be a biased situation
where heads and tails
were not equivalent to each other,
were not energetically the same,
and it's not a spontaneous symmetry breaking,
it's just no symmetry to begin with,
or an explicit symmetry breaking.
Is there any difference
between explicit symmetry breaking
and spontaneous symmetry breaking?
Yes, there is.
There is one phenomena that can happen
when there's spontaneous symmetry breaking
that will not happen
if there's explicit symmetry breaking.
The phenomena is called domain walls.
A domain wall is what happens
if far away out here,
very, very far away,
you insist along this line here
that everybody is heads,
and way out here,
you assume that everybody is tails.
What then is the state of lowest energy?
And then the state of lowest energy
is everybody on this side, tails,
everybody on this side, heads,
and a boundary in between
where heads go from,
where tails go from the boundary,
where you go from tails to heads,
called domain wall.
So the presence of domain wall,
and this would not be the case
if you had explicit symmetry breaking.
If you had explicit symmetry breaking,
then the state of lowest energy
would just be all heads, period.
Wouldn't care that,
wouldn't care very much
that you did this thing over here.
So spontaneous symmetry breaking,
in this case,
the signal of it
is the existence under certain circumstances,
certain kinds of experimental setups,
would lead to the existence of domain walls,
where on one side you had one thing,
on the other side you had the other thing.
And so it would be the presence of domain walls
which would be the signal
that there was a spontaneous symmetry breaking.
All right, so this is the basic idea
of spontaneous symmetry breaking,
a symmetry of the system,
but with an instability,
or an instability
that you can kick off
by going very far away
and just fiddling with something very far away,
and that will fix everything.
As I said, the signal or the signature of it
is the existence of domain walls.
Next time we'll talk about other kinds
of spontaneous symmetry breaking
and come to the Higgs phenomenon.
The Higgs phenomenon is a phenomenon
of spontaneous symmetry breaking,
and we'll talk about it next time.
So,
just keep this example in mind.
For more, please visit us at stanford.edu.