Stanford University
You think I don't know, don't you?
No, as a matter of fact I do know
and that's what we're going to talk about tonight
and it's called the phenomena.
What is the... Higgs! Higgs!
I think you started to cover
this last week and I didn't really...
You described what you were talking
about as giving mass to the photon
Yes, that's what we're going to talk about tonight.
We don't actually give mass
to the photon, so what's different...
No, no, no, that's right. The real photon, the
symmetry group associated with it, is not spontaneously broken.
Tonight we're going to talk about how,
if the symmetry group associated with the photon
were broken spontaneously, how it
would give the photon a mass.
Now, there's a lot of information about this.
Now, the reason we're doing that is because exactly that
phenomena happens with the Z boson and the W bosons.
The photon is a little bit simpler.
Indeed, it might have had a mass.
The fact that it doesn't have a
mass is perhaps an accident of nature.
The absence of an appropriate Higgs field.
We're going to talk about what the
Higgs field is to give it mass.
So, that's what we want to talk about tonight.
How gauge bosons, like the photon,
get a mass when spontaneous symmetry breaking...
What is the symmetry, incidentally, when
I say associated with the photon?
There's a conserved quantity, which is the charge.
Conserved quantities always go with symmetries.
What's the symmetry that's connected
with the conservation of electric charge?
U1.
It's the thing which multiplies the charge.
It's the thing which multiplies
the charge fields by a phase.
It is a kind of rotation
in the complex plane, the complex field.
So, I'm going to explain to you tonight how spontaneous
symmetry breaking of that symmetry induces a mass for the photon.
Now, there is a situation in nature
where the photon does get a mass,
and the symmetry of U1 symmetry is spontaneously broken.
Does anybody know what it is?
A condensed matter.
It is a condensed matter, yes.
Okay, the answer is in a superconductor.
In a superconductor, photons propagate with a mass.
Now, that's in the superconductor.
When they leave the superconductor, they're photons again.
When they're in the superconductor, they
behave as if they had a mass.
Okay, so that's an example of the Higgs phenomena.
And we can talk about it.
Would that also be the case when the
photon is traveling through something other than a vacuum?
Well, the superconductivity only happens when the photon
is traveling through something other than the vacuum.
No, no.
Superconductivity or the photon, no, no, no.
The photon does not propagate with a mass.
It does not propagate with a mass in a prism.
Its velocity is slower than the speed of light,
but it's still true that at zero
momentum, meaning infinite wavelength, its frequency is zero.
Okay, let's talk about the difference.
That's an interesting difference.
Might as well talk about it.
The relevant issue is the shape
of a certain curve.
The curve is either energy versus momentum,
or for waves, what corresponds to momentum for waves,
either inverse wavelength or wave number, k.
Everybody remember k?
k is basically the inverse of the wavelength,
and vertically what do we have instead of energy?
k is like this.
Now, k is like this.
k is like p.
Vertical, here was energy.
Frequency, frequency, omega.
Right?
Remember, e equals h bar omega,
and p equals h bar k.
Alright, so k is wave number,
the number of waves that fit
into a given, into a unit distance.
Alright, so this, these two planes are the
same except for a factor of h bar.
Alright, what does, what does omega versus k look like
for an electromagnetic wave in empty space?
Well, what's the connection between omega and k?
Omega equals c times k.
That's it. Omega equals c times k.
Now, the same relationship incidentally
is true of sound waves.
Waves on a long string and
so forth are approximately the same relationship.
The difference, of course, is
they have different velocities of propagation.
But notice that omega is zero when k is zero.
That means on this side over here,
that the energy of a quantum or wave,
the energy is zero when the momentum is zero.
What do we call a
particle when its energy is zero,
when the energy is zero, if its mass is zero?
We call it, well, we call it
photons, yes, but we call it massless.
Alright, so any wave which has the
property that omega goes smoothly to zero
as k goes to zero, we call massless.
And typically, the shape of the curve looks like that.
k can be positive or negative corresponding to
a wave going to the left or the right.
Let's forget going to the left.
Okay.
The frequency goes to zero
when the wavelength becomes infinite.
That's massless.
And all that happens in
a prism is that c changes.
c changes. Okay.
Now, what about, um,
what about a particle with mass?
For a particle of mass, its energy
is equal to the square root
of p squared plus m squared.
Now, there's some c's there.
I think there's a c to the fourth, no,
c squared, c squared,
c squared p squared
plus m squared c to the fourth, right?
But if we set c equal to one, it's
just square root of p squared plus m squared.
What does that look like?
That's a curve which looks like this.
It's a hyperbola.
In fact, if we square this, we get e squared.
Let's set c squared to one.
e squared minus p squared equals m squared.
That's a hyperbola.
You see the difference.
In this case, when p goes to zero,
the energy is not zero.
That's the rest mass.
Or just the mass, if you like.
The rest mass is the value of
the energy when the momentum goes to zero.
All right?
So, two different situations.
One, the velocity of light
may be different in a prism
than it is in empty space,
but that just changes the slope of this curve
and does not change the fact that
the energy is zero at the origin here.
The other situation is that the
energy is not zero at the origin
and has this hyperbolic shape.
That's called having a mass.
And notice that there's a frequency.
Same thing here.
That a wave with infinite wavelength has a finite frequency.
What does infinite wavelength mean?
It means you disturb the field every place the same.
You rigidly, you make the field absolutely homogeneous.
Homogeneous means it's everywhere is the same.
You shift the field everywhere and you let it go.
What happens is everywhere as
it starts to oscillate simultaneously,
that's the phenomena over here.
Infinite wavelength, zero wave
vector, the whole field oscillates.
All right?
Also corresponds to particles at
rest oscillating because they have mass.
Okay.
All right.
So that's what the important
thing to keep in mind is
that oscillations of a field when it's homogeneous,
when it has infinite wavelength,
those are the things we call mass.
Does that answer the question?
Does that answer the question about the...
Yeah, okay.
Is it the wave number that
changes when it's moving through a solid?
Is that right?
Well, you can have any wave number.
I mean, if you took a ray
and run it into a piece of glass,
it's not the omega that changes.
That's right.
If you have a wave of a given
frequency and it shines on a piece of glass,
the frequency doesn't change when it goes into the...
into the material.
But, as I think you're foreseeing,
two different materials might have a different slope here.
So at the same value of frequency,
you would jump from one...
you could jump from one wave number to another.
And that's what happens.
At this situation where the entire field shifts,
would that be equivalent to the concept of entanglement?
No, no, no, no.
It's really the entanglement.
This is a perfectly classical way of thinking.
It's a perfectly classical wayfield phenomenon.
I understand that.
But what I'm saying is entanglement
says that this particle over here
and this particle over here respond instantaneously.
And by the entire field shifting, wouldn't that count for...
No, no, no, no, no, no.
Entanglement is a situation where you have two particles
in two different states which are entangled with each other.
A over here, B over here,
or A over here, B over here.
They have to be in...
There has to be two different states.
Spin up and spin down, spin down and spin up.
A classical field is when all of
the particles are in the same state.
It's quite different.
So on the curve that you drew,
that looks more like the...
That one, yeah.
What does that represent?
This is called...
The relationship between omega and k,
between frequency and wave number,
is called the dispersion relation.
You say there's no dispersion
when omega is a linear function of k.
When omega is a linear...
Incidentally, the slope of this curve is the velocity.
The omega dk is...
Yeah, the omega dk is the velocity of the wave.
Okay?
So if the slope of this is constant,
everywhere,
then all waves move in the same direction.
All waves move with the same velocity.
All right? That's light.
All waves move with the same light,
the same velocity.
If the slope varies from place to place,
for example, as it would if there was a mass,
then different wavelengths
propagate with different velocities.
In that case, the wave will disperse.
So it's called the dispersion relation.
Let's name it now.
Omega as a function of k,
that relationship is called the
dispersion relation of the wave.
So the words go that a massless excitation
is one with a linear dispersion relation.
A massive particle is one with a dispersion relation
that does not go to
zero as k goes to zero,
but has a curvature and a shape like that.
And the mass is nothing
but the energy of the quantum
when the momentum is zero.
So that's m.
Energy of a quantum as a function of the momentum
when the momentum goes to zero is the mass.
All right. So that's the notion of mass.
And it is connected with the curvature
of the potential energy of the field
at the...
or the curvature of the potential energy
at the equilibrium point,
wherever the equilibrium point happens to be.
Why?
Because if you shift the
field away from the equilibrium point,
let's say everywhere, it's homogeneously,
everywhere is the same,
what happens is it starts to oscillate about there.
It's pulled toward lower energy.
It overshoots, goes up and goes back.
And that corresponds to omega not being zero
at k equals zero.
k equals zero means you shift the field
everywhere simultaneously, homogeneously.
All right. So we take the field
and we shift it everywhere simultaneously.
And the frequency at that point is the mass.
If the frequency is zero,
and the only way the frequency will be zero
is if the potential energy is flat
as a function of the field.
If the potential energy happens to be flat
and you shift the field away from the minimum here,
it's not a minimum anymore.
It's just a flat direction.
It's called a flat direction.
Of all things, it's called a flat direction.
If you shift the field along a flat direction,
it won't respond.
It'll just sit there.
So that corresponds to the homogeneous field,
k equals zero, having no energy,
no frequency, frequency zero.
All right. So you spot a massless object
when there's a direction,
a flat direction of the potential energy.
Here, the flat direction of the potential
is going around the rim.
On the other hand,
if you excite the field perpendicular to that,
it oscillates.
And so this kind of field
has two distinct kinds of quanta associated with it,
one massless, one massive.
What's the massive one called
in the context of the standard model, incidentally?
Massive.
The Higgs boson.
Okay.
So oscillating this way,
we would call the Higgs boson,
and it has a mass.
What about oscillating this way?
That's the Goldstone boson.
It's massless,
but there is no massless Goldstone boson in nature.
So something happened to it.
In the parlance of high-energy physics,
the Goldstone boson got eaten
by the gauge boson,
resulting in giving the Higgs boson a mass.
So that's the phenomenon that we want to do
mathematically tonight.
The Goldstone boson eaten by the gauge boson,
resulting in a mass for the Higgs boson.
Remember, the Goldstone boson
is the one associated with a motion around here.
The Higgs boson is the
one associated with this over here.
Okay.
So let's go through it.
There's mathematics to this.
If I could do it without mathematics,
I would, but I can't.
So we're going to do it with mathematics.
And we've already set up the ingredients.
We've already set up the basic ingredients for it.
All we have to do is combine them together.
So that means in a standard model,
there's only one spontaneous symmetry breaking,
and that's the Higgs field.
As far as it's known.
It's not a simple U1 symmetry.
It's this SU symmetry of the weak interactions
that take ups to downs and neutrinos to electrons.
So it's a little more intricate
than just the U1 symmetry breaking.
I've always, well, maybe I misheard,
but I always thought I heard that
the Higgs was giving mass to everything,
including...
Including itself.
Yeah?
Is that right?
Yes?
Well, no, no, no, no, no.
Yes and no.
Okay.
So let me tell you what the point is.
There are a collection of particles in the system,
in the standard model,
which for one mathematical reason or another
cannot have any mass
unless the symmetry is spontaneously broken.
Now we're going to go through those reasons.
We're going to go through them for various particles
and see what the reasons are
why mass is disallowed
by the standard model
without spontaneous symmetry breaking.
Then when spontaneous symmetry breaking happens,
all of those particles get mass
and they become the masses of the standard model particles.
Now you might ask,
what about particles that didn't require
a spontaneous symmetry breaking to get a mass?
Are there any particles that don't require
And the answer is yes, there can be.
Those particles are all the particles
that we don't see in life.
They're all the particles that
we don't see in a laboratory.
Why would it be that we would see those
which symmetry breaking gives a mass
and we don't see those
that symmetry breaking doesn't give a mass?
Any speculations of why that might be?
Yeah.
The natural mass might be
way up at the Planck scale.
The natural masses of particles may be very much larger,
leaving over a bunch of particles
which don't have masses
for what you're calling natural reasons.
And those particles only get mass
from spontaneous symmetry breaking.
Those particles are the light ones.
Those are the ones we see in the laboratory.
We have every reason to believe,
and in fact I think we practically know by now,
that there are additional particles in nature.
For example, the dark matter particles.
We don't know with absolute certainty
what the dark matter particles are,
but it seems very likely that the dark matter particles
are particles a thousand times heavier than a proton,
for example.
Why is it that those particles have large mass
and the other ones don't?
And the answer is in the mathematics of the theory,
those particles which have large mass
don't require the phenomena of spontaneous symmetry breaking
to get a mass.
So we're going to go through that.
That's my goal for tonight.
And if we don't make
it through it entirely next time,
the Higgs phenomena and what the words mean,
the Higgs particle gives such and such a mass.
The first class of particles which cannot have a mass
unless there's spontaneous symmetry breaking
are the analogs of the photons,
the gauge bosons.
So tonight I'm going to try to show you
how the photon gets a mass
from spontaneous symmetry breaking.
Let's begin with a boson field phi.
We did this last time,
but since it's a subtle and difficult concept,
let's do it again.
And phi is a complex field.
That means there's a phi
star to go along with phi,
and we can write phi in two ways.
Phi real plus I phi imaginary.
What does it correspond to?
It corresponds to what I drew before,
phi real, phi imaginary.
Or we can write it as phi
equals rho e to the i alpha,
where rho is the distance along here.
It's not a real distance in space.
It's a distance in field space.
And alpha is the angle.
Two different ways, polar coordinates
and Cartesian coordinates for the field.
Now, incidentally, phi star is, of course,
phi real minus I phi imaginary.
And it's also equal, this one here,
is also equal to rho
e to the minus I alpha.
Rho and alpha are functions of position.
This is a field.
So these are functions of position.
And as you can see, in either case,
there are two fields,
the real field and the imaginary field,
or the radial field and the angular field.
You might begin to guess
about the connection between
rho, alpha, and the two kinds of motions
that can take place here.
Alpha corresponds to exciting the angular modes.
If you vary alpha from place to place,
it's like varying around the circle.
If you vary rho,
it's like moving radially back and forth.
Which one do you think gets a mass?
Rho.
Which one doesn't get a mass?
Alpha.
Which one is the Higgs boson?
Rho.
Which one is the Goldstone boson?
Alpha.
Good.
You got it.
I hardly have to go through the mathematics now.
No, no, really.
That's the way the mathematics is.
Now, the trick in going through the mathematics
is to write the Lagrangian for this field.
It's derivative of phi star times the derivative of phi.
This, of course, means,
time derivative squared minus space derivative squared,
but I'll just write it that way.
Derivative of phi with respect to space and time
as four vectors dotted into each other.
That's the gradient terms in the energy.
And you can work them out
in terms of phi and phi star.
I'll tell you what they are.
This becomes derivative of phi real squared
plus derivative of phi imaginary.
In other words, it just behaves
as if there were two independent fields,
real and imaginary.
Or we can write it
in terms of rho and alpha.
And this would become,
I'll write it down for you.
You can work it out yourself.
Derivative of rho squared
and then,
plus rho squared
times the derivative of alpha squared.
Rho is the magnitude of the field,
alpha is the angle,
but each of these are fields.
And this is what Lagrangian is.
You can either think of it
in one way or the other.
No problem.
Now let's add in a potential energy.
The potential energy,
I'm going to assume,
is symmetric.
Symmetric with respect to rotations in this plane.
In other words, that it
really does have a U1 symmetry.
For a potential energy to have a U1 symmetry,
it means it's only a function of rho.
Equivalently, it's only a function of phi star phi.
It does not depend on the angle.
So let's write that.
Plus V of rho.
That also corresponds, well, okay,
V of rho.
Let's take, actually,
potential always comes in with
a minus sign in the Lagrangian,
so let's put it in with a minus sign.
A simple case would be rho squared,
an energy which increases
quadratically away from the origin.
That's a possibility.
Let's think about that possibility.
Rho squared.
It's not really what I,
it's a possible expression.
What would that correspond to?
What would that correspond to in
terms of phi real and phi imaginary?
Just rho squared.
It's phi real squared plus phi imaginary squared.
That's the Pythagorean theorem.
Rho squared is phi real squared plus phi imaginary squared.
So if the potential was
the very simple form of quadratic,
we would add here phi real squared,
or minus subtract, not important,
phi real squared,
plus phi imaginary squared.
Notice the Lagrangian would actually
be the sum of two terms,
one for phi real and one for phi imaginary,
and both of them would have a mass term.
There could be a coefficient here,
m squared over two, let's say.
Then you would have this
situation which I drew over here,
where both directions of oscillation correspond to a mass.
And they're quite independent of each other.
They don't even couple to each other.
They don't even talk to each other.
Just two separate fields,
one that I labeled phi real,
the other one I labeled phi imaginary.
Now there could be more complicated
things here which would couple them together,
but this is the basic picture
if the potential looks like this.
But what if the potential looks like this?
That's also a function of rho,
but it would be inconvenient to represent it
in terms of phi real and phi imaginary,
especially since the minimum,
is stuck out here away from the origin.
The coordinates phi real and phi imaginary
are not obviously the best
coordinates when you're stuck out here.
Better coordinates are the angular
coordinate and the radial coordinate.
Why?
Because they correspond to
two different kinds of oscillations
with two different frequencies.
In other words, just think of this
as a function of rho and alpha.
Now this potential energy doesn't depend on alpha at all.
But it does depend on rho.
It depends on rho in a way which is minimized
when rho is equal to f.
And in fact it takes a good deal
of energy to displace it away from f.
So it's natural to write that rho
is equal to f
plus a bit of fluctuation.
In other words, the minimum energy
is when rho is stuck at f.
Anywhere along here, rho is stuck at f.
But you can displace it a little bit,
and let's represent that displacement away from f
by a letter of the alphabet.
And I'm going to choose
the next letter of the
alphabet after f, which is h.
H for what?
H for Higgs.
Okay?
All right.
So the Higgs field is just
a displacement of the radial direction
or the radial part of
the field away from its equilibrium.
All right.
Now, it costs a good deal
of energy to excite this Higgs field.
Why?
Because it's got a potential, and
that potential might be rather sharp.
In fact, it is rather sharp.
So,
to some approximation,
some rather good approximation,
we might say
that the low energy behavior
is as if rho were frozen at value f.
Now, this is a very common thing in physics
to say
that there are low energy excitations,
low energy oscillations of a system,
low frequency oscillations,
and high frequency oscillations,
and ignore the fact that,
if we were to ignore the high frequency oscillations,
that would be equivalent to ignoring H here.
Just saying rho is equal to f
plus something that takes too much
energy for us to worry about today.
We'll worry about it another day
when our accelerators have more energy.
Okay?
What would this look like then?
Well,
rho is stuck at f.
We might as well ignore its derivative.
Okay?
Furthermore, what about V of rho?
V of rho is just V of f.
So, V is stuck at the minimum.
If it's stuck at the minimum,
it doesn't vary from place to place.
This and this
are irrelevant
to the dynamics of the angular field.
Furthermore,
since it costs so much energy
to make a bit of H,
we can just approximately say
that rho is equal to f,
and we find that for the low energies,
for the small energy excitations,
that the Lagrangian is just f squared, a number,
times the derivative of alpha squared.
There is no potential energy associated with alpha.
Why is there no potential energy associated with alpha?
For the obvious reason
that we don't gain any potential energy
when we go around the angular direction.
All right?
We, uh,
this is a little bit less familiar
because it has this f in it,
but we could redefine the field.
We could redefine the field by inventing a new field.
Call it beta.
Beta is equal to f times alpha.
It's just a rescaling of the field.
All right?
Just a redefinition.
And then,
we would rewrite this as just d alpha,
sorry, d beta squared.
No mass term.
No mass term because it doesn't cost any energy
to displace the field homogeneously everywhere.
All right?
No mass term,
and so alpha or beta,
depending on which you want to write,
is a massless field.
It is the Goldstone boson.
And as I said,
what its energy corresponds to
is slow variations of the field.
As you vary the field from place to place,
slowly,
you get a little bit of energy.
If you vary it slowly enough,
you get a little bit of energy
from the derivative terms here,
but no potential energy.
So that's the hallmark of a massless particle,
and it's the Goldstone boson.
Goldstone bosons
are the massless particles
which are the consequences
of the spontaneous symmetry breaking
of a continuous symmetry.
Okay? That's the buzzwords.
Now,
that's half the story.
That's the spontaneous symmetry breaking half
together with the Goldstone boson phenomenon.
The other half of the story,
which also has to do
with varying the phase of a field
from point to point,
is the gauge invariance.
So I want to spend a little bit of time.
I'm going to give you
a break for a few minutes.
Then we're going to review again
what I told you last time about gauge invariance.
That should take us another 15, 20 minutes,
or 10 minutes, I'm not sure.
And then put the two of them together
and see what comes out.
Okay?
And what will come out will be
that the Goldstone boson is eaten by the gauge boson,
giving the Higgs boson a mass.
No, giving the Higgs boson a mass
and also giving the gauge boson a mass.
Yeah?
I'm confused whether rho is the radius
in the complex plane,
or is the field value at a radius
in the complex plane?
The field is a point in the complex plane.
The value that a field takes on
is a point in the complex plane.
At every point in space,
the field has a value
which is a complex point in the plane.
In other words, at one point in space,
the field is 3 plus i times 6.
At another point in the plane,
it's pi plus i times 6.
That's the value of the field at a point
times the e.
Someplace else,
it's the Euler-Macaroni number
plus i times the Shmulevitz number.
We haven't specified where in the complex plane that is,
except we've said that it's radially symmetric.
Hmm?
Except we've said that it's radially symmetric.
What's radially symmetric?
The value of the field at any...
No, the value of the field at a point
is not radially symmetric.
The value of the field at a point
is the value of the field at a point.
It's not radially symmetric.
It's the point on the complex plane.
What's radially symmetric is the potential energy.
The potential energy
is only a function
of this squared plus this squared.
The field at some point has the value over there.
At some other point in space,
the field takes on a value over here.
At some other point,
it takes on a value over here.
The potential energy
is only a function of the sums of the squares.
But 3 plus i, 6
is the value of the field,
and it doesn't say anything about
where in the complex plane that occurs.
3 is a function of the...
The value of the field
at x plus i, y is...
No, it's not the value of
the field at x plus i, y.
The value of the field is...
x and y are not positions of space.
This is not the field
at the point x and y.
This is the field whose value
is a point in the complex plane.
It's an abstract idea.
Fields can be complex.
They can be real.
They can be multi-component.
You can assemble them together
if they have two components into a complex variable.
So the field itself is a complex variable.
It's a complex variable
where as you move around in space,
the field takes on different values
on this complex plane.
Get used to that idea.
Fields don't just have to be numbers.
They can be complex numbers.
They can be multi-component objects.
Yeah.
Question.
In the sombrero picture there,
going in the mass fold direction,
if you give it a big enough displacement,
it'll go into the other equilibrium point.
What does that mean in terms of...
Yeah.
If you give it a hard enough kick,
it'll go all the way up.
It'll swing around.
Does that manifest itself in some kind of particle?
Well, the problem is that the amount of energy
that would be involved for the Higgs field
is way beyond the energy
that even a big accelerator can...
So it's out of the ballpark from even the LHC.
But yes, I mean, in principle,
you could give the field a big enough knock
to knock it over the top.
Not everywhere simultaneously in space.
That would be an enormous amount of energy,
but in some region, yeah.
But if that's exactly in
line with the peak of the...
Very unlikely.
It would go off and wind up all over.
Right.
So it's very unlikely.
That's right.
Yeah, it would make a monstrous splash of some kind
going off and on.
Let's take a 10-minute break.
Okay.
Let's go through again...
Yeah.
...what we mean by a
field as a function of space
and what this idea of a
field which is a complex variable is.
Just to make it clear once more.
We have space, x, y, and z, right?
Now we can have fields in space.
Let's say scalar fields.
You can have a scalar field in space which...
Now what characterizes it as being a scalar?
It means it doesn't change when you rotate coordinates.
That's all it means.
It doesn't change...
Not when you rotate the
coordinates we're talking about here.
When you rotate the coordinates of real space,
it doesn't change.
That's what a scalar field is.
Now you can have several scalar fields.
Let's say in particular you can have two scalar fields.
Let's give them names.
Let's call them phi i and phi r.
They're two scalar fields.
You can then assemble them if you like.
This is totally a matter of convention.
It's totally a choice.
It's a useful choice.
It's one of these things in mathematics
which sometimes are really just useful conventions.
And this is one of them.
In fact, the whole idea of
complex numbers is a useful convention.
It's a useful convention for representing pairs of numbers.
That's all.
And the pairs of numbers are called the real numbers.
They're real and imaginary parts of the numbers.
X...
Not...
Better not call them X.
X stands for space.
Okay?
But just real and imaginary components are just
ways of speaking about pairs of real numbers.
Now it is a little
more than pairs of real numbers.
There's more structure that goes into the complex numbers.
But, you know, fundamentally it's a
way of talking about pairs of numbers.
You can plot pairs of numbers on the Cartesian plane.
The Cartesian plane is not real space.
It's just the Cartesian plane in which you've
plotted the real and imaginary parts of complex numbers.
If I had two fields, two scalar fields, one
of which I called phi real and the other...
That's its name.
Phi real and phi imaginary.
I can assemble them together into a complex field.
Okay?
Yeah.
A complex field.
And at each point of space, there would
be a phi real and a phi imaginary.
Okay?
At each point of space, I could go and
plot the value of the field on the complex plane.
Keep in mind, the complex plane is not space.
It's just an auxiliary construction.
An auxiliary construction which is
useful in replacing two real fields
by one complex symbol.
That's all it is.
It's a trick for representing...
for cutting down the number of equations that you write.
Cutting it in half, basically, by
writing them as equations for complex variables.
Okay?
So, in that language, you
would say that the scalar field...
the complex scalar field phi is that... just that.
It's a complex scalar field.
And at every point in space,
real space, it has a value.
That value is not a single number.
It's a pair of numbers.
Why?
Because it's a pair of fields to begin with.
That pair of numbers can be plotted.
So, at this point of space
over here, the field is over here.
At that point of space, the field is over here.
At that point, it's over here.
And so forth.
That's the idea of a complex scalar field.
Sometimes, the real and imaginary parts of a complex field
are called the real and imaginary components of the field.
But don't get those confused with
the components of a vector field
or a tensor field or
the components of the gravitational field.
Those components have to do
with projections onto real space-time coordinates.
This has to do with the
projections onto this fictitious two-dimensional plane
that's useful for writing pairs of numbers.
Now, once you realize that you can write...
the field as a complex variable
and plot it on the two-dimensional plane like that,
then it becomes a possible symmetry of nature
or a possible symmetry of mathematics
to rotate the field.
In other words, there might be a
symmetry which says that you can relabel
or redefine phi i and phi r by rotation.
And that happens when...
when we have Lagrangians like this,
which don't change when you do what?
When you multiply phi by e
to the i times a phase.
These are the class of Lagrangians
which don't change when you rotate
the field simultaneously everywhere in space.
When you rotate it in this fictitious plane.
In other words, take the
field at every point of space
and you rotate its value.
You give a new value to the field,
which is related to the old,
and you rotate it in this way,
changing the angle here,
rigidly everywhere in space,
then this Lagrangian does not change.
We went through that last time,
and that's the basic idea of
a complex field with a symmetry,
with a symmetry of...
called U1 symmetry.
It's a global symmetry.
That's called a global symmetry.
A global symmetry is one where you're
not allowed to change the phase angle
in space.
It's rotated everywhere.
So you can see that symmetry just
by looking at what's a function of rho?
Yeah.
Well, you can look at
it in a number of ways.
You can see that since this has
real squared plus imaginary squared things in it,
whenever a thing is a function of real squared plus...
And the other term was...
This one?
And the other term was a Pythagorean zero.
Yeah.
Right.
So this is a function of rho also.
You can see it here.
And incidentally, what does the symmetry
operation do on rho and alpha?
Rho stays the same.
And alpha?
It's not the same.
You shift it by a constant, namely
the angle that you're rotating the field by.
Well, shifting alpha by a
constant doesn't change its derivatives.
Yeah, that's why I was saying that the potential
is the only part where the derivative doesn't come in.
That's correct.
Right.
So...
All right.
So I think we have the basic idea.
Now let's go through again...
All right.
Now, yes.
Let's go through the idea of a gauge transformation.
We went through it last time,
so I'm just going to remind you.
We're not going to spend
a lot of time on it.
We're going to do it as fast
as we can, but please ask questions.
It is not a symmetry of
this Lagrangian to multiply the field phi...
by an arbitrary function of position, by an arbitrary phase.
This is called a phase.
e to the i times this times phi of x.
This is not a symmetry.
We went through this last time.
We rewrote that Lagrangian in terms of phi prime
and found out that it didn't have the same form.
In other words, the Lagrangian written up there, in particular,
the term derivative of phi star times the derivative of phi...
I don't have to put in the indices mu here.
You know about that.
That is not the same as the derivative
of phi prime star derivative of phi prime.
Not the same.
And therefore, it is not a symmetry.
Okay?
This is not a symmetry.
Why?
That's because when the derivatives act, they act not
only on phi, but they act on theta here.
They act on theta if theta is variable.
If theta didn't vary in space,
then this would be a symmetry.
But if theta varies in space, it's not.
We worked that out in detail last time, and
I'll show you in a moment what we found.
But to make it a symmetry, you have
to add another field, a kind of compensating field.
A compensating field that will compensate for the changes in
the Lagrangian when you shift the phase of the field.
Keep in mind, it's useful to remember that shifting the
phase of the field is just adding a function to alpha.
Okay?
Shifting the phase of the field is
adding a function, theta of x, to alpha.
It changes the phase angle everywheres by amount theta.
All right?
If theta is a constant, it's a symmetry.
If theta is not a constant, it's not a symmetry.
In order to make it a
symmetry, you have to add another field.
And the other field is called the vector potential.
All right?
It's a four vector.
It has an index mu.
It's also a function of position.
Out of it, you build the electromagnetic field,
E and B, or electric and magnetic field.
The transformation property, when you do a
gauge transformation, this is called a gauge transformation.
When you do a gauge transformation, you'll have
to do something to A at the same time.
In fact, you have to take A prime of x
and set it equal to A of x plus or minus.
I always get confused by the signs here.
I think it's plus the derivative.
This is A mu of theta.
In other words, you add to A
the gradient, the space-time gradient of theta.
If you do these two operations together
and you construct the right kind of Lagrangian,
it will be invariant under this operation.
If it's invariant, it's a symmetry.
So let me remind you how it works.
Incidentally, that's good enough.
You have a minus there.
You had a minus there last time.
Oh, last time I had minus?
I think the idea is that A
goes to A prime plus d mu.
Theta, d mu is theta.
I'm just saying if you write it with an arrow notation of the transformation going
from starting with A mu and going to what, then you have a minus sign.
If you write the transformation as A mu goes to A
mu plus d mu, then when you write it with A...
Okay, yeah, yeah.
I was just reading it the other way.
Then you have a minus.
Yeah, right.
But this is the transformation that you make.
These are the prime variables.
These are the unprime.
And I may have written
it the opposite way last time.
I don't remember.
But I will compensate for any mistakes.
Not any mistakes.
Not any change of notation
by changing it consistently everywhere.
From one week to another,
I don't remember the precise notation.
But both of them, you know,
you can do it either way.
You wrote that d equals del plus
IA and d star equals del minus IA.
I may have changed.
I may have inadvertently changed notation.
But as long as you
do it consistently everywhere, it's fine.
Okay.
So let's now...
We've seen that the ordinary derivative of phi prime
is not simply related to the ordinary derivative of phi.
Let's write out the relationship.
Let's take the derivative of phi prime.
Derivative with respect to any axis.
I'll stop writing mus and nus.
The derivative of phi prime is first of all equal to e to
the i theta, which is a function of x, times the derivative of phi.
If that's all there was, and we did multiply the derivative
of the complex conjugate of phi by the derivative of phi,
the e to the i thetas would cancel out, right?
All right.
So if that's all there
was, we'd be in fine shape.
We would say there's a symmetry.
But there's another term.
And the other term is phi times the derivative i times
the derivative of theta all times also e to the i theta.
It's this term here which is the nuisance.
If all there was was something which carried an e...
If theta only entered through e to the i theta here,
it would cancel out when we multiplied this by the complex conjugate.
But theta comes in through its derivative over here.
That's the problem.
All right.
To fix that problem, why
should you want to fix it?
Well, it's a fact of
nature that there are gauge symmetries.
It's also an interesting fact of
mathematics that such symmetries are possible.
To make it possible, you replace the
ordinary derivative by what's called the covariant derivative.
This is a mathematical concept that
comes from the theory of fiber bundles.
But I think it was...
I don't know whether the theory of fiber bundles was
invented before or after the notion of gauge invariance in physics.
I have a feeling it
was invented afterwards, but somewhat independently.
Gauge invariance was really vile when you tried to...
Right.
...to generate the electricity.
I think so, yeah.
Right.
I don't know who...
But I don't know whether mathematicians
invented it completely independently through the...
But I really don't know.
In any case, it is both
a mathematical and a physical concept.
And in order to make the Lagrangian gauge
invariant, you invent a new kind of derivative.
It's called the covariant derivative.
With respect to...
Again, with respect to each invariant,
you have to make the covariant derivative.
And you have to make the covariant derivative.
Again, with respect to each direction of space or time,
you write that this is equal to the ordinary derivative.
I think it's plus...
Now I'm going to get myself confused.
I'll try plus.
If it doesn't work, we'll change it.
Plus i times a times phi.
Now, there is an implicit index in here.
Once more, I will write it.
Just...
Remember, a is a vector.
Derivative plus multiplying by a.
Sometimes this is indicated by saying that
derivative is replaced by derivative plus i a.
But it only makes sense if you
apply it to a complex field like phi.
So this is the definition of the covariant derivative.
And if I were to write the covariant derivative...
Of phi star, it is
by definition just a complex conjugate.
So it's equal to d mu phi
star minus i a mu phi star.
Okay.
Now I assert, easy to check, easy to check...
That...
The relationship...
Between the covariant derivative of phi and the
covariant derivative of phi prime is very simple.
All you have to do
is evaluate the covariant derivative of...
What is the co...
This is the covariant derivative of phi.
Let's write down what the
covariant derivative of phi prime is.
Well, it's exactly the same,
except you stick primes everywhere.
d mu phi prime is
just equal to d mu phi.
So you have phi plus i a prime times phi.
phi prime, thank you.
phi prime everywhere is phi prime.
phi prime.
Okay, if you stick phi prime over here, you're
going to wind up with this extra term over here.
That is, if I evaluate d mu phi prime...
Let me write it better.
d mu phi prime...
Here it is.
Let's see, is this right?
No.
What did I do here?
This was d mu phi prime, right?
Well, you used a capital phi.
Hm?
Phi, phi, they're all phi.
No, it...
No, no, no.
d phi prime.
Okay.
Yeah, no, no, there's no difference between...
Well...
Capital and not capital.
No, here it is.
So regular phi's are actually lowercase.
And when you use the bars, they are lowercase.
Okay.
So you can write it down.
When you use the bars, they are uppercase.
Sorry?
When you don't use the bars, they are lowercase.
What bars?
Phi's are case.
If you don't have the i bars on
the top and the bottom, phi is lowercase.
Sorry, where's i bar?
You know, those bars that you write on the top.
Yeah, like those things.
What's uppercase phi?
Yeah, that's an uppercase.
Yeah, I'm just telling you, there's no
distinction in my notation between uppercase and lowercase.
Sometimes, I like to write uppercase and lowercase.
I like to put those little things there when
I'm feeling in a good mood, I put these things
on.
When I'm not feeling in a
good mood, I leave them out.
I see.
That's it.
In most of the books, they use lowercase.
Yeah.
But then for special cases, they will...
No, no, no.
Okay.
Phi is phi.
Phi is phi, and I did
not mean to distinguish uppercase from lowercase.
That's right?
Phi is a number.
level over there.
No, no.
Power bar.
Point.
Speed bar.
Yeah.
That's right.
It's like an infinite number, say like a circle.
Yeah.
Exactly.
It's a Setting scale, but theeeeeeeeeeeeeeeee acá之
right?
No I mean, I'm saving.
How terrible.
Okay, so this angle right here.
Yeah.
I want it to align.
Okay.
Yeah, what's really meant by
d mu phi star d mu
Is one a conjugate?
Is one a conjugate and the other a conjugate?
No, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, they
are the, okay, so let's, if you have a four vector,
an arbitrary four vector, v mu, you can multiply
it by g mu nu, that's the metric, and get
v mu, v nu.
The meaning of this symbol for ordinary
special relativity is that the time components of
these two are the same in
sign and the space components are opposite.
Alright, so, right, the meaning of this is it
should be taken to be the upper, the lower,
the covariant vector times the, right, but I
don't want to write that every time over
and over.
So I just write an
abstract symbol derivative times derivative.
Okay.
Yeah.
I think you have to have the lowering operator there.
Hmm?
You have lower on the left, upper on the right.
Sorry, you're right.
Thank you.
Okay.
Right.
But we've already gone through special relativity a
number of times, and so I don't feel the
need to be so careful about relativity in that.
Right.
So I won't even bother
writing them for the most part.
I keep saying I'm not going to
write them, and I keep writing them.
Okay.
Good.
Now, here, I, right, if I plug in d
mu phi prime, I will get this unwanted, nasty piece
over here.
Right.
Okay.
So if I also plug in a
prime times phi, where is a prime?
Let me write a prime over here.
A prime equals a, it's either
plus or minus d mu theta.
Then they will cancel.
They will cancel.
There will be a term di d mu
theta times phi, you know what I mean.
Right.
So if I, the two.
The two d mu thetas will cancel each other.
One from calculating the derivative here,
and the other from the explicit difference
between a prime and a.
So, what will I find?
Well, I'll tell you exactly what I will find.
I will find that d mu phi prime, this one
over here, is equal, not quite to just d mu phi.
What am I missing?
This.
This is equal to d
mu phi prime d mu phi.
Okay.
And the other two, this is
equal to e to the i theta.
e to the i theta.
Overall, e to the i theta.
So you say, well, I didn't get anywhere.
d mu of phi prime is
not the same as d mu phi.
It's not gage invariant.
True enough.
But it only differs from being gage invariant
by an outside overall factor of e to the
i theta, which will disappear when
you multiply this by its conjugate.
Notice that in this formula here
the derivative of theta does not appear.
You have the covariant derivative of phi prime
is equal to the covariant derivative of phi
up to this overall factor of e to the
r theta, which will cancel when you multiply this by
d mu of phi star prime.
That will be equal to e to the
minus i theta times d mu of phi star.
So when you multiply these two together,
the unwanted unpleasant things that have derivatives
of theta in them disappear.
What is the cost?
The cost is you had to introduce a new field.
It's transformed in this way over here.
Once you allow yourself that freedom to introduce
a new field, the vector potential, then this
Lagrangian over here becomes
invariant under gauge transformations.
Later on we'll write it out in some more detail.
One more point before we jump to the question.
I'm sorry.
I'm going to go back to the conclusion.
And that's the electromagnetic part of the Lagrangian.
This field is a charge-carrying field.
It's not the electron because the electron is
not a boson, but it could be some charged
boson of some sort.
Some charged boson of some sort.
And there are charged bosons.
A helium nucleus is a charged boson.
So, five.
Five.
Five represents some charged boson.
A represents the vector potential.
And the electromagnetic field is
also governed by a Lagrangian.
The Lagrangian is defined F mu nu to equal
d mu A nu minus d nu A mu.
The mixed space-time component is the electric field.
The space-space component are the magnetic fields.
And the square of F. Now that,
there are some signs that go into it.
F mu nu, F mu nu.
That's E squared minus B squared.
That's the Lagrangian of the electromagnetic field.
The important thing for us
is that this is gauge invariant.
This does not change when you make a gauge transformation.
What happens to A?
A changes by the gradient of theta.
So what happens to this?
F prime becomes F plus d mu d
nu theta minus d nu d mu theta.
These two terms cancel.
So F is itself gauge invariant.
And when you add F squared, it's still gauge invariant.
So the whole upshot is, oh, one more thing.
One more thing you can add that's gauge invariant.
That's a potential which depends only on phi star phi.
A potential which depends only on phi star phi.
So the full Lagrangian of a simple gauge theory involving
the interaction of electromagnetism
with a charged scalar field would look like this.
It would have d mu phi d mu,
let's just put d phi d phi star.
It would have v of phi star
phi, which is just v of rho,
if you remember, and then plus F
squared, plus E squared minus B squared.
And it would be fully
gauge invariant, no change in it
when you make a gauge transformation.
That's the simplest gauge theory in a nutshell.
And that's basically it.
That's basically the structure of all gauge theories.
They have a structure similar to this.
Now let's ask, what happens when
the symmetry of rotation of phi
is spontaneously broken?
When does that happen?
It happens when the potential has this upside down sombrero.
I guess it's not an upside down sombrero.
When it has that shape, so that
the ground state of phi breaks the symmetry,
what happens?
What new thing happens?
Oh, before we do that, let's
just remember that this potential is such
that the angular direction is a Goldstone boson, no mass.
The radial direction, which we call
the Higgs boson, has a mass.
And furthermore, the photon does not have a mass.
How do I know the photon doesn't have a mass?
The reason is simple.
The F is only a function
of the derivatives of the vector potential.
That means if you were to
shift the vector potential everywhere simultaneously,
there would be no change in energy.
Shift the vector potential everywheres
together, no change in energy,
that means a massless particle.
So there are two massless particles.
There are two apparent massless
particles floating around in this theory.
One is the Goldstone boson,
and the other is the photon.
And now, watch what happens.
Let's take...
Oh, what would a mass term for
the photon look like if you had one?
Well, the mass term is always
something which is quadratic in the field.
For example, the mass of phi, if it existed,
would be phi star phi, or phi squared,
phi real squared plus phi imaginary squared.
Or the photon mass B, it
would be something proportional to a squared,
to the vector potential squared.
If you allowed yourself to put
the vector potential squared into the Lagrangian,
you would have a mass for the photon.
That would not be gauge invariant.
Look at it.
Here's a squared, which means...
This means a mu, a mu.
If you put that into the Lagrangian, what
would happen when you make a gauge transformation?
It would shift to a
plus the gradient of theta squared.
But that's not the same as a squared.
A squared is not the same
as a plus derivative of theta squared.
So a squared, just a squared,
a squared would not be gauge invariant.
Would not be gauge invariant.
Okay?
So a mass term is not allowed by gauge invariance.
Gauge invariance is a symmetry which
prohibits the photon from having a mass.
Or does it?
Well, let's look at this Lagrangian a little more closely.
And in particular, let's look at this term over here.
In fact...
Let's concentrate on the Goldstone boson piece of it.
And we can do that by writing that
phi is F times E to the I...
Ah, no.
Let's not.
Let's just...
Let's go for it.
Here's the term in the Lagrangian.
All right.
So what's in here?
d phi is derivative of phi plus...
Is it plus IA times phi?
Is that right?
Yes.
Okay.
It's what you wrote.
It's what I wrote.
d phi star is derivative
of phi minus IA phi star.
All right?
Now let's suppose that we're looking at the
ground state when the field is right over here.
When phi is equal to F.
Okay.
Let's say just the real value.
The real value of phi is equal to F.
Let's...
For simplicity, let's say the
imaginary part of phi is zero.
So the field is sitting right over here.
Let's look at the various terms.
First of all...
Well, the most important term is this one here.
A times phi times phi star.
But phi times phi star is...
I say...
is stuck at the minimum here.
It's stuck at the minimum because
it takes a lot of energy
to shift phi away from the minimum.
So as long as we
don't excite a lot of energy,
there's an effective term in the Lagrangian
which is just a squared times phi star phi,
which is just equal to f squared times a squared.
Somebody said, hmm.
Why'd you say, hmm?
Because you immediately see that this is behaving
like a mass term for the photon.
This is behaving exactly like
a mass term for the photon.
What's the mass?
The mass is basically just f, actually twice f,
well, squared of two times f.
But this factor, this numerical factor here,
is playing the role, forget this,
it's playing the role of a squared,
times f squared, which would
be a mass for the photon.
It would be an energy that you get
when you shift the field homogeneously.
So what have we learned?
We've learned that when
you spontaneously break the symmetry,
when you study the theory in the neighborhood
of the minimum over here,
the effect of one of the terms in the Lagrangian
is just to make a mass for the photon.
Isn't that interesting?
When the photon propagates in this world
where the symmetry is spontaneously broken,
it behaves as if it had a mass.
And it does have a mass for all practical purposes.
So we've gotten around the statement that says
photons can't have mass.
Now real photons, of course, don't have mass.
But there's photons in this world
where the spontaneously broken symmetry do have mass.
The second thing is the Goldstone boson disappears.
Why does the Goldstone boson disappear?
Well, let's remember what the Goldstone boson is.
It's this angle alpha,
the angle of the field on the complex plane.
What does a gauge transform a...
Well, first of all, what is the Goldstone boson?
The Goldstone boson is simply a slowly varying
or a varying value of alpha.
Alpha is a field.
It can vary in space.
If it couldn't vary in space, it wouldn't be interesting.
Alpha can vary in space.
So it's a very interesting thing.
But you can make alpha vary another way.
You can make it vary by doing a gauge transformation,
adding a little bit of theta, of x.
So you can make alpha vary from place to place,
and you might think that that makes a Goldstone boson.
But it doesn't because this is a symmetry.
A symmetry means that you don't change the energy.
It means that the system
seems to be in a state
that stays in the ground state.
This is not a real change.
It's a gauge transformation.
So the Goldstone boson completely disappears.
It completely disappears.
It just becomes a gauge transformation,
no real energy associated with it.
And at the same time,
the vector potential gains a mass.
So it's a sort of zero-sum game.
You get rid of one mass...
No, it's not a zero-sum game.
Yes, you can make it work.
So what you're going to do is you're going to
remove the массeless Goldstone boson
and remove the massless photon,
replacing the massless photon by a massive photon,
and at the same time,
the Higgs boson now has a mass
because it oscillates about here.
That's the Higgs phenomenon.
by plugging in the value of the Higgs field
or the value of phi at the minimum here, we
generated a mass term for the photon, and
where did it come from? It came from this
covariant derivative. That's all. It
just came from the covariant derivative.
Could you rewrite the whole Lagrangian in those terms?
Yes you can. And if you can, you can
rewrite the Lagrangian in those terms, you can do
a gauge transformation and basically completely
remove this angular degree of freedom. Completely
remove the angle from the... I'll show you
a simple baby version of that. If you completely
forgot the radial degree of freedom,
just completely froze it, just completely froze
it, you would find that the Lagrangian, let's see,
yeah, the covariant derivative of phi would
become F, I think, times the derivative of
alpha plus the vector potential itself, maybe times
E to the... let's see, phi is just equal
to F times E to the i alpha.
And so the derivative of phi is F, I alpha, sorry,
F, I, F derivative of alpha times E to the i alpha.
So there would be an E to
the i alpha multiplying the whole thing.
This is just setting the magnitude
or the rho equal to F.
Okay.
I think F would come on the outside.
F would come on the outside here, wouldn't
it? F would come on the outside. This would
be the covariant derivative of phi and
it would contain the derivative of the angular
part. That's the important thing. It contains
the derivative of the angular part. What about
the derivative of phi star? That would be
the same thing, derivative of alpha, i here,
minus i A times E to the minus i
alpha F. I'm getting tired, so it's getting a little...
I'm getting tired.
Okay.
I'm getting a little bit late. That's what
you would get. Okay. When you multiply them
together, you would get exactly what you expect.
Okay. Now you also have F mu nu. You
have this times this in the Lagrangian and you
have F mu nu squared. Now let's make
a gauge transformation. This is a clever gauge transformation
which is designed to get rid of this
term altogether. How can you make a gauge transformation
that gets rid of this term? Just set
theta equal to minus alpha. Remember what happens
to the vector potential when you make a
gauge transformation. It just picks up a derivative
of theta. If you make your gauge
transformation using for the gauge function theta, alpha
itself, this just goes away completely. Or
sorry, it doesn't go away completely. It just
becomes A.
Okay.
And this term in the Lagrangian just becomes
A squared. So by design, you can construct
a gauge transformation which just removes this.
This times this gets rid of the alpha
dependence altogether and you just get F squared times
A squared. All you get is the mass term.
That's all that's left. And of course, you
still have F squared, but this is gauge invariant,
so it doesn't change.
So this is the Higgs momentum that's going
to change when you do the gauge transformation.
Net result, the angular degree of freedom
just sort of disappears. Some magic happened.
The angular degree of freedom disappeared. The
Goldstone boson is gone and the photon
has a mass. Meanwhile, the Higgs boson,
which is this radial oscillation, that's still there.
So this is the magic of the Higgs phenomena,
and it's the phenomenon of giving a mass to
the gauge bosons.
Well, it can't go anyways unless you have a programmer
Is it fair to say that the oscillations in alpha
are indistinguishable from just gauge oscillations?
From just
Yes, that's fair to say. It's only fair to
say that it's true. Now, I will tell you
right now that this is also the
physics of superconductors. In a superconductor, there
are charged bosons. The charge bosons are
bound pairs of electrons. They recover komm du
manch.
Boom وبطเฦ
zoals
charst
Cooper pairs. Cooper pairs are loosely bound
pairs of electrons, but they are bosons.
So there's a charged boson field in the
system, and the charged boson field gets shifted away
from the origin by some complicated dynamics
in the superconductor. It creates a condensate
of those charged pairs, and it's equivalent
to exactly this kind of spontaneous symmetry breaking,
where phi would be replaced by
the field describing the Cooper pairs.
So this is also the physics of a
superconductor, and in the superconductor, the photon also
behaves like a massive particle. One last thing.
How can you lose a degree of freedom?
How on earth can a degree of freedom disappear?
The angular degree of freedom. It
didn't disappear. What has happened, a massless
photon has two polarization states. Remember, polarization
is a little arrow that is perpendicular
to the motion of the photon. It's, if
you like, the direction of the electric field
oscillations. So every photon carries with it
a polarization vector. There are two of
the two orthogonal directions for the polariz- if
the photon is going that way, the polarization
can be that way or it can be that
way. So there are two polarization states. You can
also think of them as the states of
circular polarization of the photon. There is no state
in which the polarization vector of the
photon points along the direction of motion. Maxwell
theory doesn't allow that. Why is that consistent
if the photon is described as a vector? How
can it be that it only
has two components and not a third?
And the answer is very simple. The photon
moves at the speed of light. It can never
be brought to rest. Suppose it could be
brought to rest. Supposing the photon could be brought
to rest. If it could be brought to rest,
and you brought it to rest, it was going down
that way, and you brought it to rest, it
had a polarization along the x-axis, and you brought
it to rest. It would be a particle
at rest with a polarization along the x-axis.
Now you could accelerate it along the x-axis, and
all of a sudden it would become a particle
whose polarization was along its direction of
motion. So the answer is, if a particle
like the photon were to have mass, it
would have to have three directions of polarization.
You could bring it to rest, and once
it's at rest, there's no distinction between the
three directions. It would have to have
three directions of polarization, and then if you
sped it up along some axis, it
would have three directions of polarization. The massless
particle can never be brought to rest, and
it's perfectly consistent for it to only have
two directions of polarization, namely circular this
way or circular this way. Another way
of thinking about it is if you
take a particle circularly right-handed polarized, and you
brought it to rest, and then accelerated it
off in the opposite direction, it would all
of a sudden have left-handed polarization.
It would have left-handed polarization.
Left-handed, so, all right, it's also a way
to think about it. The point is that you
have not lost a degree of freedom. The
Goldstone boson has really become the other missing
polarization of the photon. Or another way of
saying it is you started with four degrees
of freedom, the two components for each photon,
the two components of the chain of the photon,
the two components of the charge scalar,
and the two components of polarization of the
photon. In the end, you were left,
again, with four degrees of freedom, three polarizations
of the photon, and the Higgs boson. So
you really haven't lost any degrees of freedom.
You've turned the Goldstone boson into
what's called the longitudinal degree of freedom
of the photon, the one in which the
vector potential or the field is pointing, the electric
field is pointing along the direction of the
photon. And the reason for that is because,
you know, the electron is pointing at the
direction of the electron, and the electron is pointing
at the direction of motion. That's
what's happened. But they all have mass.
Now the next time I will show you
the physics in a simplified context, the same context
of why the fermions, the electrons and the
quarks, get their mass from the Higgs phenomenon.
So far we haven't talked about the quarks
and the electrons. They also have mass. What
does their mass look like? Well, the
Higgs phenomenon is a very simple phenomenon. It's
a very simple phenomenon. It's a very simple
phenomenon. How do they get their mass? Well,
the Higgs phenomenon is a very simple phenomenon.
It's a very simple phenomenon. It's a very
simple phenomenon. It's a very simple phenomenon. What
does their mass have to do with the Higgs
phenomenon? That will be the next time. When we
finish that, we will have a set-up in which
all particles, including the Higgs boson, all
get their mass from the same place, namely
the spontaneous symmetry breaking. Then we can
start to talk about this very interesting
situation that all of the particles in nature
that we know, you know, that we've measured,
are the ones which would become massless
if there was no spontaneous symmetry breaking.
Boy, I've had enough of that.
Enough for tonight.
For more, please visit us at stanford.edu.