Stanford University.
I'll go over it again very quickly
and then tell you what the Higgs phenomenon
has to do with masses of quarks and leptons.
So far I've explained to you how the gauge bosons,
not the photon, but the z and the w boson,
how they obtain masses from this shift of
the field away from the most symmetric position.
Which field? The Higgs field.
But I went through it in a very simple context
where I made it look
very much like ordinary electrodynamics.
And I'll continue to do that, but keep
in mind we're not talking about the photon,
we're talking about other gauge particles.
So let's just go back to...
a little bit of time.
Let's go back to the first one.
Electrodynamics, which we're not really talking about,
but still, the mathematics is the same.
There are these gauge bosons, the analogs of photons.
The mathematics of them may be a little more complicated.
The symmetry group may not be
U1, it may be SU2 or SU3,
but that's not terribly important.
And there is a dynamics that leads to Maxwell's equations.
It's governed, in fact, as the
simplest way to encapsulate it is in
terms of a Lagrangian.
You begin with...
a good pen.
You begin with the field tensor.
Let me just remind you what it is.
It's in terms of...
the vector potential.
You begin with that.
You square it.
Let's just call it F squared.
You make the appropriate Lorentz invariant combination
of squares of components of electric and magnetic field.
And that's the Lagrangian.
And notice it only contains derivatives of A.
And therefore, the photon is massless.
To have a mass, you have to have...
you have to get an energy.
A mass corresponds to an energy.
A mass is a mass of
energy corresponding to shifting a field
homogeneously everywhere with no derivatives.
This has no energy or no energy associated
with a uniform shift of the vector potential
because only the derivatives come in.
And so the photon, by virtue of this, is massless.
It moves at the speed of light.
And this simply leads to Maxwell's equations.
Now you add something else.
You add this Higgs field.
The Higgs field...
The Higgs field is a
field which corresponds to charged particles.
Again, I emphasize we're not
talking about ordinary electric charge.
We're talking about the charges that
couple to the Z and W bosons,
the weak charges.
And we write this phi in the
form rho E to the i alpha.
It's a complex valued field.
Rho times E to the i alpha.
And we write down its Lagrangian.
We write its Lagrangian in terms of
these things that I called covariant derivatives.
d phi
is equal to the derivative of phi
plus, or I can't remember if it's plus or minus
i times vector potential times phi.
We write the Lagrangian in terms of those things.
And all of a sudden we have
an interesting interaction between the electromagnetic field
and the charge field. Here's the
source of the interaction right over here.
That would be,
basically that would be
electrodynamics, ordinary electrodynamics, but now
something new happens.
The something new that happens is the energetics,
the potential energy of phi,
favor something unusual,
namely that phi,
the minimum value of phi, sorry, the
minimum value of the potential energy is
not at phi equals zero,
but
at the bottom of this
Mexican hat potential somewhere, an arbitrary
position along there.
And so we write that phi, let's say
the radius of this circle here is F,
the magnitude of the field, the magnitude of
this, let's call it by its name, the
magnitude of this Higgs field,
is now F,
it's shifted away from the origin by amount F,
and it is also true
that the
curvature at the bottom here is very steep,
and so it costs a lot of energy
to shift the field away from the bottom here.
In some first approximation,
we can just say
that phi is simply equal to F, the numerical number,
times e to the i alpha of
x. Only alpha is allowed to vary,
and F is sort of frozen.
Frozen because it takes too much energy to shift it away
from the middle, and so it's a little bit more difficult.
So we write that phi is the derivative of x,
and that's the minimum,
but alpha, the angular variable, is still there.
We could write, let me tell
you what happens now, we could take
this form
for phi
and figure out what the covariant derivative of phi is,
given that phi has this frozen form
where only alpha varies.
I'll write it for you.
It's just equal, let's see, to
the derivative of phi, which is 0.5.
So we write the derivative of alpha
plus i a.
Now all of that gets multiplied
by F
times e to the i alpha.
That's the covariant derivative of phi.
The derivative of alpha,
sorry, I think it's i, no i here,
plus this, and maybe there's an overall,
yes, I think there's an overall i.
That's what you get when
you calculate the covariant derivative.
Now, next thing we're going to do
is multiply this by its complex conjugate
to compute the action, or the Lagrangian, for what?
For F? No, F is just a number.
We've already assumed that F can't vary very much.
The Lagrangian for alpha.
Let's see what we get.
We're going to get F squared,
the number F squared, that's a number.
And then we're going to get derivative of alpha,
that's the derivative of alpha
with respect to space or time,
plus the vector potential squared.
And e to the i alpha is going to cancel,
because we're multiplying it by its complex conjugate.
This is what you get.
For the Lagrangian of the Higgs field,
if you make the approximation that it's stuck,
where is it, that it's stuck
and can't move away from the minimum.
I may have blown the sign,
but did I blow the sign?
I don't think so.
No, there was also an i in this term,
because when you differentiate phi,
you get i times the derivative of alpha.
So both of them have an i
and I stuck it out over here.
No, I mean in the dp star.
Oh, oh, oh, oh, yeah, let's see.
Yeah, i times minus i is one.
Okay.
Yeah, i times minus i,
you scared me for a minute.
It's not i squared, it's i times minus i.
It just wasn't written, so I wasn't
quite sure what the complex conjugate was.
Well, the complex conjugate involves minus i.
Right.
Okay.
So what do we get?
We get this expression over here.
Now, do you remember what a gauge transformation looks like?
Gauge transformation, which is a symmetry,
which is supposed to do nothing to the physics.
Take any function.
Let's call it theta, which is
what I called it last time,
but it could be anything.
A gauge transformation is to take a
and shift it by the derivative of theta.
That's a gauge transformation.
Okay.
But look at this.
This is a plus the derivative of something.
This is a gauge transformation.
This is a gauge transformation where what
we have used for the gauge transformation
is not an arbitrary function theta, but this alpha function.
Okay.
This alpha field, this alpha field itself.
Now look what we have.
Let's redefine a plus the derivative of alpha.
It's just a gauge transformation of a.
Let's redefine it.
Let's give it a new name.
Let's call it a prime.
Okay.
This is f squared times a prime squared.
That's all this is.
What happens to f squared,
which originally involved a,
what happens to f if
we replace a by a prime?
It's completely unchanged because f is gauge invariant.
And so we can also
think of f squared or f.
There's this thing over here.
It doesn't make any difference.
And what do we find?
That the net upshot,
the net upshot of it all,
is to just replace the
original variables by prime variables.
And that's just renaming.
That's just a new name for something.
And to add a term in the Lagrangian
which is proportional to the square of the vector potential.
That was the net effect.
Just add a term for the Lagrangian
for the gauge field,
which is proportional to a squared.
No derivatives in it.
No derivatives in this term here.
It's just a prime squared.
That means that if you were
to shift a prime everywheres simultaneously,
you would get some energy from this term.
This term is a mass for the photon.
It's not the photon, of course.
It's the z and the w boson.
So here's an example of
how this shift of the field
from zero to value f
gives a mass to a particle
which you might have said
is not allowed to have a mass.
How did it happen?
The vacuum shifted to some new spontaneously broken vacuum.
And the excitations of the electromagnetic field
in that shifted vacuum have a mass.
So that's the Higgs phenomena.
And furthermore,
the alpha field is gone.
It's gone.
It's been absorbed into this thing we called A prime.
So there's no massless particle anymore.
The Goldstone boson has disappeared.
It has made a mass for the gauge boson.
And that's it.
Now, not quite it.
There is still this thing that we froze
in an approximation.
In an approximation, we said,
let's ignore the oscillations
of the field back and forth in this other direction.
If we're given the system enough energy,
if we really poke it hard enough,
we can start this Higgs field
oscillating in the radial direction.
Let's call it the radial direction.
It's not a radial direction in space.
It's this radial direction in field space.
Those oscillations also are quanta.
And they're massive quanta.
Why?
They have a lot of energy even at rest.
They oscillate back and forth.
Those are the Higgs bosons.
So we started with massless photons,
massless Goldstone bosons,
and massive Higgs bosons.
And we ended up with massive Higgs bosons,
no Goldstone boson,
and a massive photon.
That's the Higgs phenomenon.
All right.
Could you say again
why the A prime squared indicates a massive...
Yeah. Whenever you have a...
All right. First of all, what is a mass?
A mass is an energy from
a field theory point of view.
Mass, of course, is inertia of a particle or whatever.
But from a field theory...
Well, we'll go back a step.
A mass in special relativity
is just the energy of a system at rest.
If a system has no momentum,
if it's at rest in its own reference frame,
then it's...
The energy in that reference frame is the mass.
So that's the first step.
Energy at rest is called mass.
Now, what does being at rest mean?
Being at rest means having no momentum.
From a field theory point of view,
from the point of view of fields,
or from the point of view of quantum mechanics,
a particle at rest or a particle with zero momentum
corresponds to the quantum...
of a field of infinite wavelength.
Infinite wavelength means the field doesn't vary at all
from point to point.
And so a mass, what it corresponds to,
is an energy stored in a field
if you shift the field simultaneously everywheres.
With no derivative, no spatial derivative,
just shift the field everywheres simultaneously.
If you get some energy,
that energy is called the mass.
Okay?
Well, we started with a Lagrangian
and also an expression for energy
which only involves derivatives of a field.
If it only involves derivatives of a field,
it means that if we shift the field
everywheres simultaneously,
we won't get any energy.
So in that sense,
if this was all that there was for the photon,
then we would say the photon has no mass.
A uniform shift of the vector potential
would not create any energy.
We say the photon has no mass.
But now, once there's a term in here like this,
which doesn't involve derivatives,
does not involve the derivatives of a,
that means if we shift a simultaneously everywhere,
the response, the energy stored in this term,
is not zero.
We shifted a from zero,
where the energy was zero,
to something else,
and we got some energy.
That...
That energy is called the mass of the photon.
So it's energy stored in...
Does everybody know what I mean by homogeneous?
Homogeneous means everywhere is the same.
All right?
If you shift the photon field,
everywhere is the same,
and you get any energy from it,
that's the mass of the photon.
In fact, in particle physics
or in field theory in general,
you identify the mass of a particle
as an energy stored
in shifting the field simultaneously everywhere.
Okay?
It's not just in particle physics.
In all kinds of contexts.
I think I talked about them last time,
but let me just remember and remind you again.
A sound wave in a crystal.
A sound wave in a crystal
corresponds to a motion of the crystal lattice,
which you could think of as the response
to a shift of the position of the molecule.
If you shift the position of the molecules
in a variable way,
in other words, way down here,
you shift them to the left a centimeter,
and then halfway down there,
you shift them to the left a half a centimeter,
and then over here, you don't shift them at all,
and then over here,
a half a centimeter to the right, and so forth,
you make a long wavelength...
It's called a phonon.
A long wavelength phonon,
but it's a kind of wave in the crystal,
and it's a kind of wave in the crystal.
We're very slowly varying,
and there's energy stored in that.
You've deformed the crystal a little bit.
That energy is called the energy of a phonon.
Now, what happens if you shift the crystal
everywheres simultaneously by exactly the same amount?
We could call that a homogeneous shift.
Do we get any energy from that?
No.
So a homogeneous shift,
where everything is shifted simultaneously altogether,
that gives no energy,
and so you would say phonons are massless.
Phonons have no mass,
which means that a phonon
with zero momentum has no energy.
Phonons, photons, spinons...
Spinons are in magnets.
They have to do with the orientation
of the little fundamental magnets.
If you reorient the magnets in a variable way
from place to place,
you get a little bit of energy.
It's called a spin wave.
If you rotate all the magnets together
simultaneously everywhere,
it costs no energy.
You just rotated the magnet.
So that's another example of waves
which at infinite wavelength,
or homogeneous waves,
have no energy.
They're also massless.
I thought we started out this analysis
with a particle that was
vibrating a little bit in alpha.
Yeah, we did.
And that originally,
before we coupled it to A,
to the vector potential,
its energy was purely
rho squared,
d...
Well, let's call it f squared,
d alpha squared.
That's all there was.
It was just the square of this thing
where the vector potential was
completely absent from the problem.
Okay?
Now, because it only involves derivatives,
if we shift alpha everywheres simultaneously,
in other words,
everywheres in space,
we shift the angle...
instead of saying
the field has the value over here,
we put it over here.
Everywheres in space.
That costs no energy.
It costs no energy
because it didn't make any derivatives.
I'm not sure what the question was,
but does that answer it?
Well, by shifting it,
you're changing alpha.
You're changing alpha.
And that means...
But it's derivatives of alpha
which give you energy.
Oh, because you're not continuously moving it in alpha.
That's right.
You're not moving it,
you're not changing it from place to place.
If you change it from place to place,
that's the energy of the goldstone boson.
All right?
But if you shift it everywheres simultaneously,
then it costs no energy.
Why?
Because the energy only involves gradients.
Okay?
So that's the idea.
So keep that in mind.
That's a buzzword.
That mass stands for energy at rest,
but it also stands for energy
associated with uniform homogeneous shifts of fields.
Fields or whatever it is we're talking about.
There is an interesting example
to see, to get an
idea of how mass can happen.
I explained to you that if you have a crystal
and you move all the molecules simultaneously,
it doesn't cost any energy.
Now, supposing your crystal lattice
was composed of particles
which themselves had both plus,
some plus charges and some minus charges.
Okay?
So these are molecules,
ions, plus ions and minus ions.
Or they could just be atoms.
They could be the protons at the,
the nuclei at the center
and the electrons around them.
And supposing you did the following.
You shifted all of the electrons
to the left uniformly
and all the protons to the right uniformly.
That would be called a homogeneous shift.
Just a little bit.
Just a little separation between the electron cloud
and the nuclei.
Do you think that would cost any energy?
You bet, because you would have pulled the,
the plus charges away from the minus charges.
That would be a homogeneous shift of,
not fields, but locations,
which would cost energy.
What do you think would happen
if you made that shift,
the, the, the plus particles this way,
the minus particles this way?
What'll happen next?
It'll start to vibrate.
Okay?
It will not behave the way it would
if everything was moved simultaneously.
So moving everything simultaneously,
that's a zero momentum phonon.
Moving the plus charges relative to the minus charges,
what is that called?
Anybody know?
A plasmon.
Plasmons have mass.
Phonons do not.
Okay?
The derivatives there include a time component,
don't they?
The derivatives include what?
A time component.
Oh, yeah, absolutely.
Absolutely.
So when you're talking about shifting things,
is, doesn't the time component...
Yes, yes, yes, yes, yes.
What you're saying is right,
but I'm just imagining spatially shifting everything
and not inducing any time derivatives.
Yeah, but the shift...
Well, all right, we, good.
No, no, it's a good question.
No, no, no.
By shifting, I don't mean an actual process.
I just mean a mathematical change
in what you mean by the vacuum.
Right.
Or you do it extremely slowly,
very, very slowly,
move it from here to here.
Yes, you're right.
These, the actual energy contains time derivatives also,
but I was simply...
The same is true, incidentally, of the crystal lattice.
What are the time derivatives of the shifts?
Kinetic energy.
The kinetic energy, the velocities of the molecules.
So if you really give the crystal a shift,
which means it's moving off with a velocity,
then, of course, there's kinetic energy.
So when I said a shift,
I meant a shift in your imagination
where you shift everything simultaneously
and start it out at rest
compared to where it originally was also at rest.
Good.
But that's a good point.
Okay, let's talk now about fermions.
This means electrons, muons, and so forth.
And where do they come from?
Where do they get their mass from?
It turns out the real electron, muon, quarks
also get their mass from this Higgs phenomenon,
from this spontaneous symmetry breaking.
And let's discuss what we know about it.
The first thing we go back to
is the basics of the theory...
Not the theory, but actual experimental data
about weak interactions.
This could be beta decay,
the decay of a neutron to a proton,
but...
and an electron and an antineutrino.
Okay, here's what goes back to...
the 50s? The 50s.
No, earlier than the 50s, I think.
I don't remember exactly when.
The following fact was found
in the 1950s.
It was discovered.
First of all, reflection symmetry,
which means reflection of space,
left hand into right hand,
is not a good symmetry of nature.
It's an ancient fact from the 50s
that it was discovered that the reflection,
the mirror reflection of a process,
is not another possible process.
Now, in quantum electrodynamics,
the mirror image of any process
is another possible process.
That itself is a symmetry.
It's not a continuous symmetry.
It's a discrete symmetry.
You take everything and you reflect it.
You don't rotate it. You reflect it.
You take the left hand and the right hand.
There's no hand which is sort of midway...
There's no continuous way to go
from left hand to right hand.
So replacing every left hand by a right hand
or every left screw thread
with a right screw thread and so forth,
that's a symmetry of quantum electrodynamics.
And it's also a symmetry of quantum chromodynamics.
It is not a symmetry of the weak interactions.
Left and right are fundamentally different,
and as different as they can be.
So let me tell you what the experimental fact is,
that the decay of a neutron,
neutron,
which gives a proton
an electron,
and an antineutrino...
Well, let's first talk about the handedness of particles.
Is there any sense in which particles are handed,
have a handedness, like my hands?
Yes, there is. They have a spin.
They also have a direction of motion.
If the spin is along the direction of motion,
in other words, there are two possibilities.
The spin can be oriented along the direction
of motion, or it can be oriented opposite
to the direction of motion.
In quantum mechanics, of course,
if the spin is oriented in some other direction,
you can build it up out of superpositions
of the two states along the direction of motion
and opposite.
So an electron moving along with a high momentum,
for example, can either have its spin
along the direction of motion,
that means it's rotating with a right hand screw thread.
It's rotating or spinning with a right hand screw thread,
that's called a right-handed electron.
And an electron can also be a left-handed electron.
That simply means its spin is going...
is helically going in the opposite direction.
So there are two kinds of electrons,
right-handed and left-handed.
Now, what happens in a beta decay like this?
You might think you could either make
right-handed or left-handed electrons.
Right?
Right-handed and left-handed electrons
are as good as each other in every respect.
In quantum electrodynamics, there are no processes
which are not symmetric.
If you can make a right-handed electron in some process,
then there's a reflected process,
which is also a possible process
where you can make a left-handed electron.
If right is possible, left is possible.
Nevertheless, when the process of beta decay
became something where you could really do
with precision and study the handedness
of the electrons that come out,
they're always left-handed.
There was never a process...
It doesn't matter what orientation
the spin of the neutron has.
No matter what you do,
the electrons which come out are always left-handed.
This goes beyond the theory of beta decay.
Any weak interaction process...
In other words, any process
where a W boson, for example,
where a W boson interacts
and takes an electron into a neutrino,
or where you interchange,
where you flip these lines
to make different processes out of it,
it's always the left-handed electron
which interacts with the W boson.
Never a right-handed electron.
So, for example, you could imagine a process
where an electron scatters off something,
changes into a neutrino,
and there's something over here that it scatters off,
a proton or something else or another electron.
You'll always find that the left-handed electron
scatters and the right-handed electron doesn't.
This is a fact.
And the same thing is true of the neutrino incident.
It's always a left-handed neutrino.
It's questionable whether a
right-handed neutrino exists, incidentally.
This is a question which we've not answered.
We'll come back to it another time.
But there certainly exists both right-handed
and left-handed electrons.
We think there are also probably right-handed
and left-handed neutrinos.
All right, so electrons...
So there's something asymmetric,
left-right asymmetric, about the...
about the weak interactions.
And it is...
What is it?
It is that the left-handed electrons
are charged with respect to the W boson.
In other words, we could imagine a situation
in electrodynamics which would be similar.
It's an untrue situation.
Don't... Let me say it right now.
This is not correct. All right?
But we could imagine a world
where only left-handed electrons
are charged.
Left-handed electrons
could scatter off photons
or could produce photons
and become left-handed electrons
and which right-handed electrons could not.
We could imagine it. It's not true.
Let me say it over
and over. It is not true.
But imagine it.
Then you would say that the left-handed electron
has an electric charge
and the right-handed electron does not.
Now, that's bizarre. I mean, that's...
That's really bizarre. Okay?
And it's not true.
But with respect to the weak interactions,
not the emission of a photon,
but the emission of a W boson,
it is as if
the left-handed particles
carried charge
associated with the emission of a gauge boson
and the right-handed particles did not.
Okay?
That's a very strange fact.
It's, uh...
It's a very typical fact.
But it's also
a kind of quark.
What's that? It's also true of quarks.
It is also true of quarks.
Um...
We have to...
We're gonna modify the statement a little bit,
but at some deep level,
it's exactly true.
Okay, let's talk about
left-handed and right-handed particles,
uh, fermions.
And let's go back to the Dirac equation.
And I will tell you a little bit
about the connection between the Dirac equation
and the handedness of particles.
I'm not going to spend a lot of time.
I'm just gonna give you
the rough outlines of the idea.
Let's go back to the Dirac equation.
The Dirac equation looked something like this.
I d psi by dt.
This is the Dirac field,
which could correspond to the electron.
It could correspond to the muon.
It could be the field of the electron.
It could be the field for quarks.
They all have the same form, the Dirac equations.
The, uh, time derivative of the Dirac field,
and remember what the Dirac field is.
It's a four-component object
where the four components
correspond to,
let's say,
two different subdivisions.
The particles can have spin
along either axis.
That gives you two components,
upspin and downspin.
And the particles can have positive or negative energy.
Remember, Dirac particles can
have positive or negative energy.
Now, we've learned over and over again
that the negative energy particles
should be replaced by
antiparticles of positive energy.
But in the mathematics,
uh, the Dirac field
has four components,
upspin positive energy,
downspin positive energy,
upspin negative energy,
downspin negative energy.
And the positive energy
is the positive energy.
Or you can think of it as
upspin and downspin
of particle and antiparticle.
Okay, so there are four components
to the Dirac field,
and the components,
think of it as a four-component column vector.
There are matrices,
four-by-four matrices
called the Dirac matrices.
Dirac called them alpha.
Three alphas,
sorry, three alphas,
for the three directions of space.
Let's call them alpha i
for the three directions of space
times the derivative of the field
with respect to
x sub i.
This would be the Dirac equation
if
the particle had no mass.
Now, how can you see that?
You can see that because
the equation only involves
derivatives of the field.
If the field,
the whole dynamics
of the field only involves
derivatives of the field.
We've seen in previous situations
that when the dynamics of the field
only involves derivatives,
the field is massless.
There's no restoring force,
no tendency for the field to oscillate
unless it has a gradient.
No time derivative,
unless there's a space derivative.
So if you shift the field
psi everywhere simultaneously,
it does not create an oscillation,
does not create any energy.
What do you put
on the right-hand side if you want to have
a mass for the field?
Well, there was a fourth Dirac matrix
called beta.
You put the mass times
beta times psi.
That's the Dirac equation.
Now,
the electron could be moving along
with a momentum.
A momentum means there's a gradient
of the field psi.
It means a plane wave,
but that's not so important.
And the spin can either be
along the direction of motion
or opposite to the direction of motion.
Those two components,
we can think of that as the left-handed
components of the Dirac field
and the right-handed components.
So let me write these equations for you.
This is four equations,
and they're written for each component.
Let's write them for the left-
and right-handed components separately.
Here's what it looks like.
I times the derivative
of the right-handed
component of the Dirac field
describing right-handed electrons
plus
I alpha I
derivative
of the right-handed field
is equal to
Now, you might think
that the right thing to put here
is something involving the right-handed field.
But it turns out
this matrix beta
interchanges right-hand and left-hand.
So,
a mass term over here
corresponds
to a coupling
between right-handed
and left-handed.
And likewise,
here's the equation for the
left-handed component.
d psi left-handed by dt
turns out
it's minus I
alpha sub I
d psi left-handed
by dxi
is equal
to m
psi right-handed.
In other words,
it's a funny equation
in which the right-handed
and the left-handed components
are completely independent
if the mass is zero
and the left-handed
mixes them up.
Roughly speaking,
you can think of a Dirac electron
as one which, as it moves along,
oscillates between left and right.
And
the oscillation
is the mass term.
But let's not push that too hard.
It's not quite right.
The mass term couples together
the left-handed and right-handed
components.
This is
for a Dirac particle
what a mass term is.
It's a thing which couples together.
It's an energy
which is only there
if both the left-handed
and the right-handed
components are both excited.
Okay, now we can see
some odd things.
Let's suppose
that only the left-handed
Dirac particle had a charge,
which is true
with respect to the weakened
electron,
but not true with respect
to the electromagnetic.
But let's just pretend
only the left-handed
electron has a charge.
The right-handed electron
has no charge.
Okay?
A fictitious world.
Is this equation
allowable then?
Well, it's not.
Because the meaning of this equation
is that
a charge
will turn into a left-handed particle.
I'll explain it another way in a second.
And a left-handed particle moving along
will turn into a right-handed particle.
What does this mean?
It means that charge conservation
would be violated.
A left- or right-handed field
becoming a left-handed field
would violate charge conservation.
Another way to say it
is to remember
that
a charged field
is multiplied by
e to the i theta.
If a field has charge,
it gets multiplied
under a gauge transformation
or under one of these U1 transformations.
It gets multiplied by
e to the i theta.
If it has no charge,
it does not get multiplied
by e to the i theta.
Now we look at this equation.
This equation,
if the right-handed field
is multiplied by e to the i theta,
nothing would happen
to the left-hand side,
but the right-hand side
would pick up a factor
of e to the i theta.
Likewise over here.
The left-hand side
would pick up a factor
of e to the i theta.
The right-hand side would not.
These equations cannot be symmetric
if only
psi left
is multiplied by e to the i theta
That's another way of saying
that charge conservation
would not permit
a mixing of left and right
like this
if only the left-handed electron
were charged.
Both of them are charged
in reality
and because both of them
carry the same charge,
you can go back and forth
from left to right
without violating charge conservation.
Yeah?
Are the charges on the alphas
are consistent?
Probably not.
No, they're probably not.
Oh, no, no, no, no,
I meant that they're, sorry.
No, you're right,
they're not consistent.
I pulled the whole i out on the outside.
You're right.
Yeah.
Okay.
So it's just basic charge conservation
would forbid
the possibility of a mass
if only left-handed electrons
had charge.
Or if only right-handed electrons
Fortunately for the real world,
that's not true.
Electrons, both right-handed and electron
and left-handed have charge.
The electron has a mass.
The world would be very different
if the electron didn't have a mass
and
chemistry wouldn't exist.
Yeah.
We wouldn't be in a happy world.
How would the world be different
if right-handed electrons
could be emitted from
weak interactions with both left-handed?
If both right-handed
and left-handed.
We'll come to it.
It would be very different,
but
we will come to it.
Okay.
So,
I'm going to
let's come to the weak interactions.
Question. You can
measure the spin of electrons vertically
unless they select the ones that are pointing upward.
And if you accelerate those
in that direction, do you say they have
a spin as the type that you're talking about?
The same thing. Okay.
There's an interesting question.
Is it possible
that there would only be one kind of electron,
namely only left-handed electrons?
Okay.
Yes, it is, but only if
they're massless.
So let me explain why.
Supposing there was only a left-handed electron,
that means it spins only to the left
when it moves,
it has a left-handed
helical kind of motion.
Now,
if the electron has a mass,
you could imagine
slowing it down and bringing it to rest.
Bringing it to rest
in a way that doesn't change its angular momentum.
You could
exert a force on it
which doesn't change its angular momentum.
So, in that case,
you would take this electron,
which is moving along, rotating
to the left with a left-handed motion,
bring it to rest,
and even go past that,
bring it back the other way.
Its rotation, sense of rotation,
hasn't changed.
That's just angular momentum conservation.
But its direction of velocity has changed.
It has turned into a right-handed electron.
So,
if I
I judge by my thumb,
if it's moving in that direction,
then the direction of my fingers is its handedness.
So,
if it's rotating that way
and moving that way,
it's left-handed.
But, if it's rotating that way
and moving that way,
it's right-handed.
So, if the particle has a mass,
you can always bring it to rest
and over-decelerate it
and you're guaranteed then that you've taken
a left-handed electron
and turned it into right-handed.
If it has a mass.
What if it has no mass?
Then you simply can't
bring it to rest.
You simply cannot do this process
of taking it, moving it in that direction,
slowing it down, bring it to rest.
What you can do is
rotate it around,
but that does not change.
I don't change my left hand to my right hand
when I rotate around.
But,
if I can bring it to rest,
then you can be sure that both kinds have to...
If I can bring it to rest,
I can be sure that both kinds
necessarily have to exist.
You can only bring an object to rest
if it has a mass.
So, there's another way of thinking about...
Yeah?
このまま仮面になる
A circularly polarized photon.
Right.
Okay, it changes its polarization.
If it's rotating that way
and it bounces off the mirror,
it will continue to rotate that way,
but it will go in the opposite direction.
That means it's changed
from circular polarization right-handed
to circular polarization left-handed.
So the photon is also...
But it never came to rest, right?
That's right, it never came to rest.
Right.
Right, okay.
If you had a particle
which only could have one helicity,
helicity means this handedness,
then you couldn't have a mirror that reflected it.
That's a good point.
You have an electron B.
Yeah.
Do you have all the electrons
in one stream or both streams?
Generally, you have both.
But because, okay, because real electrons have a mass,
it means the electron, the real electron,
is a mixture of both.
So you have all kinds of handedness.
But then what do you do with the focus?
Why would it be difficult to focus?
Because the spin...
Well, that doesn't make it hard to focus then.
Focusing doesn't have to do with the spin,
it has to do with the position.
Yeah, but the focus is on the place.
Mm-hmm.
So the spin changes.
I'm not sure with the focus.
Okay.
the left-handed and the right-handed. It could happen.
It depends on exactly what's focusing it. Now,
to a good approximation,
left-handed and right-handed
particles in an electric or magnetic field
behave the same way. They have the
same trajectories. Not quite,
because of the difference of the magnetic moment.
So, magnetic moments are small
of an electron.
And,
if you have a gradient of an electric
field or a gradient of a magnetic field,
well,
a magnetic field in general,
I think what you're saying is a
magnetic field will affect the left-handed and the
right-handed electrons differently.
Yeah, this is true.
Yeah, that's right.
That can happen.
Okay.
So, here we are.
We're in a world of...
Does this fact that
left-handed and right-handed are different,
is that just an accident of nature?
Is it what?
Is that just an accident of nature?
Probably not an accident of nature.
It's not an accident of nature.
But, for the moment,
I think that's a good thing.
For the moment, let's treat
it as an accident of nature,
an empirical fact that we know for the moment.
Okay?
All right.
If it's true that the mathematical Dirac equation,
if the left-handed particle and
the right-handed particle have different charge,
then the Dirac equation, or the symmetry of the system,
will not allow us to
mix right-handed and left-handed like that,
then the question is, how
might the electron get a charge?
Or get a mass, excuse me.
How might it get a mass in this fake world
in which left-handed and right-handed
electrons have different electric charge?
I use electric charge just because it's familiar,
and I want to make this about it's
really the weak interaction forces that we're interested in.
All right.
Let's imagine that there's another field.
Let's make it a boson field.
A boson field, phi.
And this boson field, phi, is also charged.
Let's say it has plus charge.
Boson field means it's quanta have positive charge.
Let's write down the rules
of transformation under these U1 symmetries.
First of all, all right, let's write them over here.
Under a U1 transformation, psi left
goes to e to the i theta,
and psi left.
Why?
Because left-handed electrons are charged.
What happens to psi right?
Somebody yell out.
It just goes to psi right.
It doesn't transform at all.
And what happens to phi?
It's charged, right?
It's charged by assumption,
and depending on the sign of the charge,
let's say it goes the same way as this one,
e to the i theta phi.
Okay, now let's come back
to the Dirac equation over here.
Clearly, the equation as it stands
is not invariant under this operation.
The left-hand side of the top equation does not transform.
The right-hand side does transform.
Same thing with the lower equation, except opposite.
But now let's play a trick.
Let's take this mass, throw
the mass out for the moment,
and put in here a constant, some unknown constant,
which we'll fix later, a numerical constant,
times phi, let's see, the left-handed one transforms,
times phi star,
and this one times phi.
Is this legal now?
This one doesn't transform at all, right?
What about this?
Psi left gets a phase,
but phi gets, or phi star gets the opposite phase.
So, we haven't violated the symmetry, the U1 symmetry.
How about this one?
No.
No what?
No, it's good, or no, it's bad?
No, it is good.
Let's see.
Psi right does not transform at all,
and I think psi left and
phi transform the same way, right?
So, phi right doesn't transform at all.
Psi left picks up the factor of e
to the i theta, but so does phi.
So, both of these equations
are now consistent with the symmetry.
This is a perfectly good alteration of the Dirac equation,
which does not violate charge conservation.
There's another way to think about it.
You can think about this picture as saying a right-handed,
the left-hand side represents the
propagation of a right-handed particle,
and the right-hand side represents
the splitting into a left-handed particle,
and the left-hand side represents
and I guess it's a phi particle, an anti-phi particle.
So, a neutral particle breaks
up into a left-handed particle,
which has charge, and a right-handed particle,
which has the opposite charge.
That's what this equation means.
Particle propagating along makes
a transition to two particles.
One is left-handed, and one
is of a phi star type.
Conserves charge.
And you can say the
same about this one over here.
A left-handed particle moves along and becomes a phi,
and a right-handed particle.
That also conserves charge.
So, that's the way you can think about this.
It just describes a new kind of process
in which lefts and rights can turn into each other,
but only at the cost of
emitting charged particles to compensate the charge.
What's the probability for emitting such a particle?
What's the strength of this interaction?
It's this constant G.
The G is called a coupling constant.
It's not the electromagnetic charge.
It's none of the coupling constants we've already described.
It's called a Yukawa coupling.
All right, now let's come back to phi.
Let's suppose phi is one of these magical Higgs fields.
Supposing phi is one of these magical Higgs fields.
Remember, the Higgs field, or the...
is also a charge-carrying field,
and let's suppose it has the form
rho e to the i alpha.
In addition,
something which is definitely not true of electrodynamics,
let's suppose this phi field has a spontaneous...
has rise to a spontaneous symmetry breaking,
so that, in fact, it has magnitude F.
Let's forget alpha for the moment.
What happened to alpha?
It got eaten by the Higgs phenomena
and disappeared out of the system,
but rho itself, or phi,
was just proportional to this F quantity.
What was F?
F was just the shift of
the field away from the origin.
Then what happens over here?
Right.
Phi is too rigid to get excited very easily,
and so it's just approximated to...
It's approximated by a constant.
This just becomes approximately
G F psi left.
This becomes approximately
G F psi right.
How do you separate G from F?
G is just a number.
So is F.
So they can't be separated, really?
Well, okay, here's how we separate them.
Remember what happened to the black?
Remember what happened to the photon in this fake world?
It got a mass equal to F.
So we look at the photon,
and we say the photon,
not the real photon,
I really mean the Z and the W.
We look at the Z and the W,
and that tells us what F is.
Then we look at the fermions,
and we see what G is.
All right?
But what is this combination?
This is the mass of the fermion.
The fermion is playing exactly the same role
as the original mass in the Dirac equation.
So another magical example
of how a shift in the Higgs field
gives rise to masses for particles.
The masses for particles simply mean
the coupling between left and right-handed.
Left goes to right-handed.
We identify that as the mass of a fermion,
and that's what happens.
So the mass of a fermion
is the mass of a particle.
It's not the mass of a particle that's broken,
but only if the symmetry is spontaneously broken.
So the Higgs phenomena has another role.
It gives the fermion's mass.
How big is the mass of the fermions?
The mass of a fermion is
equal to some G times F.
Now, there are different fermions in our world.
That only means that there are a collection
of different Gs in the world.
These Gs are called Yukawa couplings,
and there's one for each kind of fermion.
There's an electron Yukawa coupling.
Let's estimate.
How big is the electron Yukawa coupling?
Remember that the mass of the Z boson,
or the W boson, is essentially F.
Anybody know what the mass of a W boson is?
It's about 90.
It's about 900 GeV, right?
Did somebody say?
How much?
Sorry, 90 GeV, not 900.
Thank you.
Roughly 100 GeV.
What's the mass of an electron?
So we could be talking about electrons here.
This would be the Yukawa coupling for the electron.
Half an MeV, right?
So G electron here must be a very small number.
What is it?
It's the ratio of the
electron mass to the Z mass,
and that's 100 GeV versus half an MeV.
That's a big number.
Hundreds of thousands.
How much?
200 what?
That's 100 GeV versus half an MeV.
The difference between an MeV and a GeV
is a factor of 1,000,
so it's roughly a factor of 10 to...
This number is about 10 to the minus 5.
Very, very small number.
How do we know it?
We know it from knowing both
the mass of the W boson
and the mass of the electron.
Next.
What's the next one?
The next one is the muon, or the up quark,
or the down quark,
and there's a variety of different numbers.
What's the heaviest of the quarks?
The top quark.
The top quark, and what is that?
How much, what's its mass?
It's about a factor of 1 1⁄2 or 2 times,
somewhere between 1 1⁄2 and 2 times
the mass of the W.
So that means for the top quark,
this number here
is a number of order one.
So there's a whole spectrum
of these different Yukawa couplings
that nobody understands.
But one thing that's interesting is you,
and you say, so, okay, so all you've done
is fit a collection of numbers
to the masses of the fermions.
But now you can hope for an experimental
conservation, experimental confirmation
of these numbers.
Let's go back to the coupling
of the right-handed and the left-handed particles here.
And remember that F was simply
the frozen value of the Higgs field.
But the Higgs field is not really frozen.
It really can shift around.
What is the Higgs field?
The Higgs field is the fluctuation
away from this frozen value,
the real Higgs particle.
The real Higgs particle is the fluctuation
away from here.
So in fact, what we should really write,
if we're doing it correctly,
is F plus the Higgs field
times psi left.
What is this telling us?
This is telling us that, sorry,
this is right, this is right, I think.
No, left, yeah, left.
This is telling us that a process
can happen where a right-handed fermion
can turn into a left-handed fermion
and a Higgs particle, a real process.
Right-handed particle can become
a left-handed particle and a Higgs particle.
And what's the amplitude for that?
The same Yukawa coupling.
What is that word before coupling?
Yukawa.
Yukawa was a Japanese physicist.
Sorry. Yukawa.
Yukawa.
Yukawa was a Japanese physicist
in the 40s who,
among other things,
wrote down the mathematics
of the couplings between fermions
and bosons like this.
All right.
Won the Nobel Prize for this in the 1940s
for different physics,
for nuclear physics applications
of these ideas.
But in any case, the point is
that the same coupling constant
which appears in the mass of the fermions
also governs the process of a fermion
becoming a Higgs boson and another fermion.
I should draw these as solid lines.
Fermion left-handed becomes fermion right-handed
and a Higgs boson.
Now, we've not detected the Higgs bosons yet.
We've not detected them yet.
So it becomes a very, very important thing
once the Higgs boson is detected
to study the different processes
in which Higgs bosons are produced
to see that the relative probabilities
of producing a Higgs boson by an electron
and by a top quark or another kind of quark,
that they have the same ratios
as these constants here.
For example, it tells us
that in the decay of the Higgs boson,
this could be read as
the decay of a Higgs boson
into a pair of fermions,
that it prefers to have a fermion
that is supposed to decay into the heaviest fermions
if it has enough energy to do so.
It will preferentially decay to heavier fermions
rather than light fermions,
and that's a consequence of this
because the couplings here are larger.
So that's one of the things that will become important
in the LHC,
is to study the properties of Higgs bosons
and see if we can detect evidence
for these coupling constants.
So basically all the coupling constants,
regardless of where they come in,
are really probability numbers?
They're square roots of probability.
Sometimes they're fourth roots of probabilities.
It depends on how many times you have to square.
But yeah, right.
They're related to probabilities.
So there's an assumption here
that there's only one such Higgs boson
that everything couples?
I have made the assumption
that there's only one type of Higgs bosons.
In various more complicated theories
beyond the standard model,
there are often more than one.
And then much of what I have to say,
for example, there are Higgs bosons,
well, yeah, there are supersymmetric models,
there are usually two Higgs bosons,
but then you just modify it accordingly.
And of course much of what I say
has to be modified
because the weak interactions are SU2, not U1.
So what I'm doing is
giving you a kind of simplified version
of what the Higgs phenomena does.
But thus far, taking into account
all of the various gauge interactions,
here's an interesting fact.
All of the particles that are seen
in the standard model
could not have a mass
if it were not for this shift,
for this shift of the Higgs field.
The gauge bosons,
they normally do not have mass.
And the only way to give them the mass,
the only known way to give them mass,
is this phenomenon of spontaneous symmetry breaking
associated with the Higgs field.
Their mass is typically proportional
just to this F.
So the Z and W boson.
All of the fermions,
because of this peculiar property
that the weak interactions are purely left-handed,
the symmetries,
of the gauge theories,
do not allow you to just write down,
in other words, to postulate
a mathematical mass term for these fermions.
The only way that they get mass
is through this shift of the field.
To say it yet another way,
all of the masses of the known particles
are such that they are proportional
to this symmetry breaking parameter, F,
the shift of the Higgs field.
That's a curiosity which may be deep,
but may be important.
Question, if you have antiparticles
and they decay,
would the direction be the opposite?
Yes. That's a good point.
If an electron is purely left-handed,
then its antiparticle is purely right-handed.
But nevertheless, we continue to call it left-handed.
We call it...
We still say the electron is left-handed.
You say left-handed,
but is it left-handed anti-electron
or positron?
The positron would be right-handed.
The positron which interacts with the Z and W bosons
is right-handed.
So you'd call it biotent?
You'd call it biotent.
Biotent is not right-handed,
so it's antiparticle.
Uh, it's just a pure convention.
We have a lot more experience with electrons
than we do with positrons,
so we tend to name things
by the way we tend to say the electron,
meaning the full complex of objects
that go together with the electron
are called left-handed.
Nevertheless, the positron is right-handed.
So what do you do about the electrons and positrons?
What do you do about their...
Well, an electron and a positron,
if collided together,
can make, for example, a Z boson.
So I guess it would be a left-handed electron
and a right-handed positron,
could make a Z boson.
Right.
Okay.
Are all positrons created by the same thing?
No.
No, no, you can create positrons
in all kinds of ways.
Uh, you hit any particle hard enough with anything,
and it will make, among other things, positrons.
Right.
Certainly not all positrons in nature are made of, uh...
For example, you can make positrons, uh,
by just colliding an electron with a photon.
You hit an electron hard enough with a photon,
and you'll make...
The electron won't disappear,
but out will come an extra electron and a positron.
Okay, for example, let's see if we can work out
the Feynman diagram that describes that.
Okay, so the Feynman diagrams,
the basic Feynman diagram,
or the basic vertex,
is electron, electron, and photon.
But if we flip the lines around,
we can turn this into electron,
let's call this E minus,
E plus, that's positron,
and photon.
Or, better yet, let's see,
so what did I say?
We said electron collides with a photon
and makes an extra electron and positron.
Okay, so here's the, uh,
photon colliding with the electron.
Then another photon emitted,
and that photon turning into an electron and a positron.
All right, so that's a Feynman diagram,
a fairly complicated Feynman diagram,
uh, that would take an electron and a photon
and turn it into an electron,
two electrons and a positron.
So there's all kinds of processes that can make power.
On the linear accelerator,
can you select the speed of the electron?
Sure.
Well, you're asking in practice,
how much can you, uh, not that much.
So, yes, you can, you can, uh,
you can change the energy of the, uh,
varying the magnetic fields and so forth.
I had thought that one
of the last experiments I did
was with polarized electrons.
Polarized electrons, yeah.
It's hard to make polarized electrons,
but once you make them, you can accelerate them.
So the electrons are made in, uh,
slow electrons are made, which are polarized.
Don't ask me how they're polarized.
I don't remember, but, uh,
then they're accelerated as polarized electrons.
I do remember.
It's a very low-energy spin-orbit interaction
that's selected to get...
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah, but the details of how, I can't remember.
It's not easy to do.
You need big magnetic fields,
and it took a while for them to, uh,
to generate the technology to do, uh,
uh, polarized electrons.
Polarized electron beams.
Polarized means all the spins are in the same direction.
Yeah.
So what about neutrinos?
Okay, so neutrinos, all right,
so in the standard model
and in old-time physics of the, uh,
before recent years,
it was not known whether the neutrino...
It was thought that the neutrino was massless.
Now, the mass of the neutrino is very, very small.
Remember, there are several different neutrinos,
electron neutrinos, muon neutrinos.
Very small.
Within experimental error,
they move with the speed of light.
And that means that it's possible for them
to have only a single handedness.
All right?
In the standard model,
neutrinos all are left-handed.
The standard model does not even contain anything
that you could call right-handed neutrinos.
Uh, generalizations of the standard model
have right-handed neutrinos,
but those right-handed neutrinos typically
have a very large mass,
and, uh, it's a complicated story.
Maybe we'll come to it.
But in the simple standard model,
um,
neutrinos are massless.
Now, do we know, are they really massless?
They're not.
We know they're not.
We know they're not because of neutrino oscillations.
So we know they're not,
but their masses are very small,
10 to the minus 3 electron volts or even smaller.
And, uh, so, uh,
in, um,
approximately, they're very close to massless.
They're not quite.
What actually happens to neutrinos is really curious.
Remember, a mass term is a thing
which turns left-handed to right-handed.
All right?
So it's a process in which left-handed
can make a transition to right-handed.
Now, uh,
what happens with the neutrino?
There are left-handed neutrinos,
and of course they go along with right-handed antineutrinos.
If a neutrino is left-handed,
then the antineutrino is right-handed.
And one way of having a mass for the neutrino
is to have a left-handed neutrino
make transitions to right-handed antineutrinos.
Mass is always, for fermions,
it's always left hand turns into right hand
turns into left hand turns into right hand,
processes which involve that.
For neutrinos, curiously,
the right-handed particle,
which the neutrino can make a transition to,
uh, is the antiparticle of the left-handed neutrino.
So that's an interesting, um, fact.
Why could the electron, the real electron,
why could the real electron not get a mass
by mixing, by the left-handed electron
with the right-handed positron?
You'd be pretty, yeah, you'd be pretty amazed
to see a electron turn into a positron
because it violates charge conservation.
So that's not an option for the electron.
Why is it allowed for the neutrino?
Has no charge. Has no charge. Right.
Uh, the buzzword terminology for a particle
which gets a mass from a Dirac equation,
it's very curious, um,
the thing on the right-hand side here
is the antiparticle of the thing on the left-hand side
for a neutrino.
A particle which gets its
mass by mixing in this way
with its antiparticle is called a Majorana particle.
Majorana.
Was Majorana the, uh,
young Italian physicist?
I'm not even sure what year.
Uh...
Majorana.
Ettore Majorana,
who disappeared shortly after, uh,
inventing the Majorana particle
and never was heard of again.
I don't mean he wasn't academically heard of.
I mean he was never heard of again.
Nobody knows what happened to him.
Mafia doesn't...
Are you gonna be able to tell us
why we think the Higgs particle
is gonna be reached, the mass of it?
Yeah, we can, we can talk about...
Turns out the mass of the Higgs particle
is also generated by the Higgs particle
and is also ordered the same F,
so we more or less expect that the Higgs particle
will have the same order of magnitude mass
as the W and Z boson.
Somewhat heavier, but, uh,
but more or less the same.
But, okay, so let's think about now what we found.
This is somewhat striking.
All masses in the standard model
trace back to this parameter F.
If F were zero,
they would all be massless.
All right, all the particles of the standard model,
with the possible exception of the Higgs boson itself,
but all the particles of the standard model,
all the familiar guys there,
and even many of the unfamiliar ones,
Z and W and so forth,
top quarks, bottom quarks,
the whole works,
uh, all of their masses
are a response to this F.
They're all proportional to F
in the formulas of particle physics.
Why is that?
Why are there no particles in nature
whose masses, um,
might not be much, much larger than F?
Well, maybe there are particles
which masses are much larger than F.
We just haven't discovered them yet.
Why not? Because there are,
the limits of our energies
are roughly at about that level now.
This number F,
in order to agree with the mass of the particle,
the masses of Z and W bosons,
this number F, thought of as a mass,
is about 250 GeV.
If there were particles in nature
whose mass were much larger than 200 GeV or so,
we would not have discovered them.
All right? Supposing there were particles,
let me give you an example
of a particle in this context,
in this, uh, slightly fictitious,
but, uh, but still qualitatively correct,
context,
where a particle could get a mass
that was not due to the Higgs boson.
Suppose we had a particle
in this weak interaction context
where both the left-handed
and the right-handed components
both had the same charge
with respect to these weak interactions.
Suppose such a particle existed.
Then there would be no obstruction
to having a mass
which had nothing whatever to do with F.
It could have a mass
which would be arbitrarily big.
It could be much, much bigger than F.
It could be 10 to the 16th times bigger than,
or even bigger than F.
There would be no obstruction
to it having a mass
having nothing to do with this F.
Uh, there are other kinds of particles
that could have,
uh, masses which are not due to this F.
The thinking now
is that the natural mass scale
of elementary particle physics,
wherever it comes from,
we can talk about where it comes from,
is much, much bigger than F.
Any particle that can have a mass
will have a mass,
and that mass will be much, much bigger than F.
It is only those particles
for which there are symmetries,
which are, there are deep underlying reasons
why in the absence of spontaneous symmetry breaking,
they can't have mass.
The gauge bosons themselves,
the photon is one of them,
uh, these particles which are purely left-handed,
they are forbidden from having mass
unless there's a spontaneous symmetry breaking.
So maybe it's not so surprising
that all the particles
which have low enough energy to have been detected,
all are the ones
whose masses
are coming from the same origin,
namely a small amount
of spontaneous symmetry breaking.
All the other particles
which could have masses
independent of this F
simply apparently have masses
at some scale which is much larger.
That's the thinking.
Uh, so it's not, in that sense,
the particle spectrum as we know it
consists of the particles
which would have been massless
if the symmetry was not spontaneously broken.
They're all responses
to a small amount of spontaneous symmetry breaking.
Uh, that's the thinking in any case.
This may or may not be true.
Does that mean that they don't
play a large role in reality?
Well, um,
it definitely could mean that.
It depends, of course,
on what you mean by reality.
Which ones don't play a big role in reality?
The ones with the finite masses.
Oh, the ones which can have masses, uh...
Right.
They do not play much role in ordinary physics.
Now, one exception
is the possibility of dark matter.
The best guesses about theories of dark matter
is that the masses of them
are much significantly larger than this F,
possibly by a factor of 10,
larger than this F.
For such particles,
it's unreasonable for various reasons
to think that they get their mass in this way.
And so dark matter particles
may be the first indication
of a spectrum of particles
whose masses do not come from spontaneous symmetry breaking.
That's the theory.
Spontaneous symmetry breaking.
That's thinking in general.
At least this particular spontaneous symmetry breaking.
Uh, yeah?
What is the mass of cosmic rays?
Well, it depends.
Cosmic rays can be electrons,
they can be, uh, protons,
they can be photons.
What their mass is is the mass of those particles.
They're very high energy, though.
They're very high energy,
but mass means energy at rest.
Right.
All right, so you could ask me,
what is the energy of cosmic rays?
Well, basically anything up to
about 10 to the 21 electron volts.
So 10 to the 21,
what's 21 minus 9, 12?
Uh, 21 minus 9 is, uh, 12?
10 to the 12th GeV,
which is very, very high,
higher than any accelerator
that we're gonna build.
Uh, incidentally,
cosmic ray collisions,
in a certain sense,
will not be as high an energy probe
as,
as accelerator probes.
And the reason is because the cosmic ray
is banging into a particle at rest.
The Hadron Collider
will collide together two particles,
and it's, you may think
of it as twice the energy,
but it's much more potent than that.
We can come to why.
Uh, uh, hitting a particle at rest
with a high energy
is not typically as potent
as hitting two particles, uh, head-on
with a good deal lower energy.
So what will be measured in CERN
will be processes and energies,
uh, 10, um, no, still not as high,
still not as high as the highest cosmic rays.
Um,
not quite, no.
What is CERN?
You don't use,
or you're using frequently here,
is it inertia?
Is inertia and mass essentially the same thing?
Yeah, well, yes.
Yes, and now you can ask,
by what magic is it that inertia
and these expressions in, uh,
Dirac equations and so forth
correspond to the same physical idea,
and that's more complicated.
Um,
but you could go back to basic,
basic relativity,
and you could have asked,
special relativity,
and you could have asked
the same question there.
Definition, two different definitions of,
of mass.
One of them is inertia,
all right, how hard it is
to get a thing accelerating,
and the other is energy at rest.
Why is the energy of an object at rest
related to the inertia of how much,
how hard it is to accelerate it?
All right.
That is contained in the rules of special relativity,
but once you know that,
then you might as well focus on the definition
of mass as energy at rest.
All right, so the question does not have to do
with particle physics.
It doesn't have to do it.
It has to do with special relativity.
Yeah.
So, uh,
so once it,
it, it changes mass,
does it start to couple with the gravity field?
Exactly.
Well, it couples,
yeah, yes, this is,
that's right.
Um, good.
So,
that's correct.
Once it gets mass,
it starts to couple to the gravity field.
Now, that's a little bit,
um,
not quite accurate.
Photons don't have mass.
Photons do couple to the gravity field.
What is it about photons that,
what is it that really couples to the gravity field?
It's energy.
Energy.
Energy is the thing which really couples
to the gravitational field.
How do we know that photons couple
to the gravitational field?
They bend,
the trajectories of a photon are deflected
in a gravitational field.
Action equals reaction,
and so that means that the orbit of the sun
is slightly perturbed every time a photon goes past it,
but that's pretty negligible.
But just the fact that,
that photons are deflected when they go around the sun
means that,
that massless particles do couple to gravity.
But, um,
uh,
particles at rest,
their energy is still there.
It's simply their mass.
So if you have two
particles more or less at rest,
the gravitational interaction between them
is related to their mass.
Well, resistance to acceleration is
also related to total mass.
It's related to?
To energy,
to,
not just to energy,
not just to energy.
Indeed it is.
That's correct.
Uh,
the resistance to acceleration of a high energy particle
is,
um,
the mass of the particle at rest.
Yeah.
Uh,
the only,
the only subtlety
is that the resist,
let's call it the resistance,
the resistance to acceleration,
if a particle is moving down the z-axis,
then there's a different defective inertia of it
if you make a force along the z-axis
or if you make a force perpendicular to the z-axis.
So there's no universal concept of mass,
unique mass,
for a particle which is moving.
Depends on which way you push it,
what its inertia is.
That's why people stopped talking
about the mass of moving particles,
which mass,
and,
uh,
stopped talking about that
and defined mass to be the
energy of a thing at rest.
But yes,
um,
it is correct that the more energetic an object is,
the harder it is to deflect.
How do you know if an
electronic rest is left-handed or right-handed?
Well,
in a certain sense,
it's not left-handed or right-handed.
Um,
an electron at rest,
the handedness is the relationship between the momentum,
and it's particularly well defined for high momentum.
For high momentum,
the definition of a right-handed particle is
one whose spin is along its momentum,
and a left-handed particle is one whose spin is opposite.
So the answer is that there
is no definition of right-handed and left-handed
for a particle at rest.
It's mostly useful for high-energy particles,
the notion of handedness.
So if an electron is at rest,
can it not interact,
have a weak interaction?
Okay,
this,
this now you've really pushed me to the edge of,
uh,
okay,
so.
Uh,
w-
all right.
There's a subtlety,
which I haven't told you about,
and it's the difference between
what is called chirality and helicity,
and I,
I promised to tell you about it.
Uh,
I've,
uh,
been a little bit loose
in what I mean by handedness.
So,
let's come back to it.
Uh,
the idea of handedness as I've defined it,
is especially useful for high-energy particles,
particles whose momentum is very large.
When the particle is,
has a very small momentum,
the handedness of it,
uh,
is,
oh god,
it's,
I'm,
I'm losing my,
uh,
my,
it's getting too late for this.
We'll come back to it.
Yeah.
I will,
I will explain.
No,
F is of order 250 GeV.
The Higgs particle,
as there's good evidence that it's,
it's,
there's good evidence that it's
a good deal lighter than that.
Yeah,
but evidence is that,
is the question.
Oh,
um,
high precision,
uh,
experimental and theoretical,
comparison between,
uh,
the properties,
the masses of the Z and W bosons.
Uh,
they would have a little,
they would respond to changes in the mass
of the Higgs boson in a certain way,
and from experimental knowledge of the
masses of the Z and W boson,
uh,
I would say the bound on the Higgs
mass is probably that it's less than 160 GeV.
So that's less than this 250 GeV,
but not by an order of magnitude.
So,
I want to follow up on a question
I asked earlier about the possibility of multiple
minima.
And it occurs to me that if you
had particles which you didn't see in generations,
then that would,
that would get in the way of
having multiple minima in that potential function that,
so you'd have multiple F values from one potential function.
Yeah.
So if you had a particle that didn't exhibit generations,
then it wouldn't,
wouldn't make sense.
Let's,
let's,
let's come back to it.
We will talk maybe next quarter
a great deal about multiple minima and,
and what kind of different physics
can take place in different minima.
Um,
but,
simply stated,
you can have anything happen,
almost anything happen in another minimum of the potential.
So I,
I didn't want to get into that tonight.
I'm getting tired as you can see.
So ask me some more questions if,
if,
if the energy level that's
required to answer them is low,
I will do it.
But,
but,
what's the next lecture about?
I don't have a class yet.
How about,
we're going to have a class next week.
What's next week?
Next Monday,
I mean,
I'll be at the end of this course
or we're going to have another class next week.
What's the date?
It's the 9th.
9th.
This is the 9th lecture.
Well then I suppose we have another class.
I know I have to be away at some
point but I don't think that's till the 18th.
Um.
It was the message in the classroom,
it would be at the middle of the day.
Oh,
yeah.
You couldn't be there,
right.
Oh, yeah.
Yeah.
Well, we don't have to have two classes.
And we won't have two classes because
I'll be away for the 11th week.
But for the 10th week, where, which?
Yeah, let's meet.
Why not?
Sure.
Okay.
Yeah.
If I recover from tonight.
There are various scenarios for the
value of the Higgs boson mass.
And in some of them, the
range of energies is quite easy.
It's the rate and the things that things decay into.
Sometimes they decay into just invisible things.
So the Higgs boson will not
be the first thing discovered at LHC.
Of course, it may be the first thing.
It's the first thing that's
discovered if nothing else is discovered.
But there's a lot of room for
discovery before the Higgs boson, particularly if there's
super-synchronicity.
The photon and the gluon don't seem to have antiparticles.
Is that because they have zero mass?
No.
It does not have to do with their mass.
It has to do with their absence of
having any kind of charge to distinguish the particle
from the antiparticle.
Yeah.
So the photon is uncharged with respect to
any kind of charge that we know about.
It doesn't participate in weak interactions.
It's not electrically charged.
Neutrons have no charge.
They have antiparticles.
Neutrinos have no charge.
They must have weak charge.
Antineutrino.
一样
They also don't have any conserved charges.
But there are anti-neutrinos.
There are anti-neutrinos.
Oh, oh, oh, that's, well, are there anti-neutrinos?
You can't have all that.
Well, no, some people would say
there's only one kind of neutrino
and it's both left-handed and right-handed.
Other people would say there are neutrinos
and anti-neutrinos.
The point is the neutrinos can mix together
with the anti-neutrinos and form
a massive Majorana particle,
which is its own anti-particle.
Why?
Because it's a superposition of a particle
and an anti-particle.
So there's some subtle quantum mechanics there.
Make it stop.
Yeah.
Does the standard model,
I'm trying to explain my charges, is quantized?
No, well, yeah, yeah, yeah,
we can talk about that too.
It does.
But only, yeah, it does.
Remember the neutrino?
Neutrinos have weak charges.
They interact under the weak interactions.
And so the weak interactions provide
this collection of charges that we've been discussing.
And the neutrino is not uncharged
with respect to the weak interaction,
with respect to the Z and the W boson.
In particular, the neutrino and the anti-neutrino,
the anti-neutrino interact differently with the Z boson.
So you might say that
with respect to a Z boson,
the neutrino and anti-neutrino have opposite charge.
You can have pair production of an electron.
They also have lepton number,
which is another considered quantity.
Right, but I was going to mention that.
If you can have pair production of electron and neutrino,
and they have to be the same.
Yeah.
I mean, conserved lepton.
Unless the lepton number is not conserved.
But anyway, they have to have opposite weak .
OK, all right.
I'm nodding my head yes, but
I know deep in my heart
that the answer is no.
And the reason is that lepton number is not really
thought to be conserved.
Right.
And it's connected with this Majorana story
and the mass of neutrinos.
Neutrino oscillations can mix neutrino
with anti-neutrino and things like that.
For more, please visit us at stanford.edu.