Stanford University.
Today,
my main purpose is to
go through a very famous theorem.
And it's the theorem which is the
classical mechanical analog of the kind of
reversibility that we talked about in,
I think it was the very first lecture.
Remember?
Arrows pointing in,
arrows pointing out,
and some rules about
reversibility.
And I said at some point we
would get to the real thing as it
stands in classical mechanics and how it
is similar to what we talked about that
first lecture.
The theorem is called Lieville's theorem.
And so today at least
you'll get a sense of the potential of it.
And then I'll talk about it in the next lecture.
And for a good part of the lecture,
I will talk about Leoville's theorem.
But first I want to remind you about Hamilton's equations,
phase space,
Hamilton's equations,
and while I'm at it,
to show you how Hamilton's
equations lead to energy conservation.
That,
of course,
is an important thing.
We've seen how Lagrange's
equations lead to energy conservation.
And what was it?
It was conservation of the Hamiltonian.
So it will not be surprising
in any way that Hamilton's equations,
which are really just
a repackaging of Lagrange equations,
lead to energy conservation.
Incidentally,
even before I get started,
everybody asks over and over again where these equations
come from.
Why,
what,
and I can always tell you quantum
mechanics is at the root of them,
and of course
that's true.
But you might have asked a slightly different question.
If quantum mechanics is at the root of them,
what was Hamilton and Jacobi and Lagrange
and Poisson,
what were they all doing?
They didn't know about quantum mechanics.
They had no idea about quantum mechanics.
What were they doing playing with
this stuff and creating these houses of,
formal houses
of cards and structures on top of structures?
Very,
very beautiful,
extremely beautiful.
But where were they getting all of this from?
And as near as I can make out,
they were playing with the
equations and finding structure there
for its own sake.
To what extent they realized how deep
an aspect of nature these equations were,
I don't really
know.
And I really don't know what drove them
other than playing with the equations and finding
formalities.
I mean,
they were playing with the
equations and finding formal structures there.
So we're kind of working logically
backward from quantum mechanics to classical mechanics,
and starting with classical mechanics,
whereas the logic goes the other way.
But historically,
we're doing it the way it really happened historically.
And so it's very interesting what kind of
weird minds these people had that were putting
these things together in this
way and just creating formal structures,
formal meaning,
you know,
mathematical structures.
So I'm going to wrap up the talk with
just for the love of the beauty of the equations,
as far as I can tell.
And Hamilton's equations was one
of those structures that was discovered.
Lagrangian equations were an earlier one.
Newton's equations,
of course,
were even earlier.
Newton knew why he was doing his equations.
He was trying to explain the orbit of the moon,
the orbit of the Earth and all that
stuff.
What was Lagrange doing?
I think he just noticed the similarity
of the equations with the equations of Newton,
equations of optics or the least action,
the least action being similar to the,
or the
equations that come out of least action
being not too different than the equations that
would come out of least time.
So I think he's just playing with it.
And Hamilton even more
so was just taking the structures,
the mathematical structures that appeared and reassembling
them in all kinds of interesting ways.
Question?
Yeah.
You said that Newton didn't discuss kinetic energy.
No,
I don't think Newton had a concept of energy.
To my knowledge,
Newton did not talk about energy.
What was the first...
I'm not sure.
I don't know.
We can look it up.
It's something
we can look up on the internet.
I'm not sure.
Maybe somebody can look it up and tell us.
Okay.
I'm not even sure if it was a physicist.
Might have been a chemist or...
Heat,
from heat maybe?
No,
that would be...
Yeah.
Certainly by the time of Carnot,
there was a very clear concept of energy.
No,
I must know.
It was earlier than that.
It was true.
Leibniz had a concept of
what he called the least weevil,
which is twice the kinetic energy.
Leibniz.
Yeah,
Might be.
he may have been the one.
I don't know.
However,
we have it and we can use it.
Well,
heat was thought to be a substance.
What's that?
Heat was supposed to be a substance at that time.
Heat was thought to be a substance.
So you have a conservation of substance.
Right.
But the idea of transmutability of heat into
work and work into heat somehow was there.
Well,
that's why Felicitas left.
Yeah.
Because of these concepts.
Okay,
let's get started.
Let me write down Hamilton's equations for you again
and then just show you in a couple of lines.
They do imply the conservation of energy,
which means the conservation of the Hamiltonian itself.
All right,
so we suppose that we have some system characterized
by a bunch of Q's and a bunch of P's.
We'll put some little index under them
to indicate which one we're talking about.
For each Q,
there's a P.
For each P,
there's a Q.
And in Hamiltonian mechanics,
the laws or the law of nature or the collection of equations of motion
are packaged in the form of a Hamiltonian function of the Q's and P's.
H of Q and P.
I won't bother writing little indices unless I need them.
H of Q and P is
the basis of the Hamiltonian function.
It's the basic object of the theory.
And how is it connected to the equations of motion?
It's connected to the equations
of motion through Hamilton's equations.
Namely,
I always have to remember where the sign is.
P dot is equal to minus dH by dQ.
We'll put an index here.
The 15th P.
It's time derivative.
Is equal to the derivative of the
Hamiltonian with respect to the 15th Q.
Alright,
so they come in pairs.
And there's a Hamiltonian equation
like this one for each I.
And the other one is Q dot I
is equal to plus dH by dP sub I.
Now,
H can be a complicated function
of all the Q's and P's.
So each right hand side here does
not just depend on one label here.
All the I's appear in H.
And so this equation can say that
P1 dot is some function of P1,
P2,
P3,
all of them.
And likewise here.
Okay,
but the equations come in pairs.
Alright,
let's write down now the time derivative of the energy.
Which means the time derivative of the Hamiltonian.
And see if we can calculate it.
This is dH by dT.
This is the total derivative.
The complete explicit derivative.
Not the explicit.
The complete derivative of H with respect to T.
And H can vary because either P varies with time
or Q varies with time or both vary with time.
And so that's equal to the derivative of H
with respect to P times the time derivative of P.
Let's put an I in here.
The derivative of H with respect to QI.
QI dot.
H changes with time because H changes
with P and P changes with time.
And at the same time H changes with
respect to Q and Q changes with time.
That's what this means.
Alright,
now let's just plug in Hamilton's equations for
the P dot and the Q dot here.
Alright,
so let's put in here P dot.
This is equal.
There's a minus sign.
dH by dPi.
dH by dQI.
Oh,
sorry.
There is of course a summation here.
This means sum over all I.
So let's put the sum in.
I don't have room for the sum.
Put it in this way.
Okay.
Good.
I won't bother writing it again.
I mean,
I intend there to be
summations over I in these equations.
dH by dPi dH times Pi dot.
But Pi dot is minus dH by dQI.
So there's a minus sign.
dQI.
Then plus dH by dQI.
And now Q sub I dot.
Q sub I dot is dH by dPi sub I.
Nope,
no dot.
I.
Dot my I's,
not my Q's.
Does the H have a dependence on time?
Oh,
that's a good question.
If it does,
then there would be another.
Okay,
so let's not include it in the same color.
But let's just include it as it is.
So if the H has an additional possibility that H might depend
explicitly on time because some parameters of the problem are changing with time,
then there would be another term here,
the H by dt.
And this means the change in the Hamiltonian,
keeping P and Q fixed,
but the change with respect to time because
some parameters in the problem might change with time.
Okay,
so that's a good point.
But,
of course,
the essential point is that
the problem is changing with time.
And that if the system is
translationally invariant with respect to time,
which is another way of saying that the
parameters of the problem don't change with time,
for a closed system where
everything has been taken into account,
we expect that the parameters don't change with time,
then in that case this would be zero.
This red piece here.
And the black piece,
you'll just notice,
is just written the same thing twice,
once with a minus sign.
So it's just plain zero.
That was easy.
So in Hamiltonian form,
the conservation of energy is just
that this is equal to minus this.
You add them together,
it's all equal to zero.
Zero.
And if there is an
explicit time dependence in the Hamiltonian,
then,
of course,
the energy of the system would not be conserved.
As I've emphasized over and over,
the meaning of that is usually that
there's some other sense in the Hamiltonian form,
that there's a second system that is moving in such a way as
to share and exchange energy back and forth with the system you're talking about.
But let's not take that case now.
Let's just take the simple case where
the Hamiltonian does not depend explicitly on time.
Time translation invariant.
Then it's a one-step,
one-line thing to see that the energy is conserved.
And another way to say that is,
to say,
take the surfaces,
this is a space here of some number of dimensions.
If the number of q's is n,
then the total number of
dimensions in this space is 2n,
nq's and np's.
And write down the equation
that h is equal to e,
where e now is just a number.
It happens to be the energy of the system,
but let's just think of it as a number.
Then the solutions of this equation are,
these equations are just some contours,
some surfaces in the phase space.
The phase space is the pq space.
And surfaces of constant energy,
one equation in an n-dimensional space,
here's an n-dimensional space,
it's got to be even,
strictly speaking,
but I can't draw an even,
alright.
One equation among a collection of unknowns,
or a collection of variables,
gives you a surface of one less dimension,
if we have 2n dimensions
for the q's and the p's,
and I write down an equation like that,
it defines some surface in the space.
How many dimensions does the surface have?
One less than the total number of dimensions.
That's what writing one equation does.
So what this says,
is that the way the
system moves through the phase space,
the motion through the phase space,
stays on surfaces of constant h.
The trajectories through phase space
stick,
so to speak,
to surfaces of constant h.
There are many surfaces of constant h.
As I vary the value of h,
I make different surfaces through here.
I'm not going to try to
draw another surface on top of that.
But the point is,
once the energy is fixed,
the system will continue to travel on that surface.
It doesn't have to form,
it doesn't have to go
on a closed surface like this,
a closed loop,
it just will stick to that surface.
An example that we talked about was the harmonic oscillator.
For the harmonic oscillator,
the Hamiltonian was omega,
just a number,
times p squared plus q squared.
p squared plus q squared is a con-
or omega times p squared
plus q squared is a constant.
That's a circle.
Alright,
we start with a two-dimensional space,
p and q.
We write one equation,
p squared plus q squared is a constant.
That defines a circle,
which is one less dimension.
We have different circles
corresponding to different total energy.
And,
the way the system moves or behaves with time
is wherever you start the system,
it will stay on the same circle.
Just orbit around that,
around the origin.
So,
that's another idea that the surface...
Yes?
Okay.
You've got four equations there,
p squared plus...
Four equations.
What I'm saying is,
I'm trying to see...
So,
for p and for q,
you've got one equation each,
is that what you're saying,
or two equations?
The equations of motion are these.
There are two equations of motion.
It follows from these two equations of motion
that the time derivative of the energy is zero.
That says that the...
Or,
the time derivative of the Hamiltonian.
That says that the Hamiltonian is a constant in time.
So,
let's call that constant E.
Okay?
The constant,
of course,
is determined by the initial conditions.
Whatever the initial energy is,
that's what E is.
And each value of E corresponds
to a surface in the phase space
of one lower dimension.
The rule is the motion of the phase point,
let's call this the phase point,
through phase space,
stays on the same surface of constant energy.
That's one of the many consequences of these equations here,
that the motion is on a surface,
just like that.
Okay?
Excuse me.
The way you present this,
there's really no relationship between the P's and Q's.
This is just all very axiomatic.
Yeah.
Well,
it's not that there are no relations.
The relations between them are given by these equations.
That's right.
Right.
But...
Yeah.
No,
no,
that's right.
For example,
there's no automatic assumption
that P is equal to the mass times Q dot.
Right.
So,
you take whatever the Hamiltonian is,
and we'll work out some examples which are nonstandard,
but basically,
the Hamiltonian can be any function of Q and P.
In many cases,
you can write it as a kinetic term,
that's what P squared is,
plus a potential term,
but by the time we've gone this far,
we can write many,
many other kinds of Hamiltonians.
The only question is,
do they correspond to anything in nature?
The answer is often yes.
But now,
as you say,
I think you put the right word on it.
The axiomatic...
This is an axiomatic theory now of mechanics,
or a formal structure,
or whatever you want to call it,
and that defines it.
Okay,
so now let's...
move on to the idea
of a flow in phase space.
Let's go back to the harmonic oscillator for a minute.
And instead of taking a given initial condition
and a given starting point,
a particular starting point,
for example,
this point,
and then watching the phase
point move around in a circle,
let's imagine all possible starting points
and indicate them by points on this plane,
and in fact,
think of a sprinkling of them.
It's uniformly distributed through here.
Every one of them moves...
And in the back of my mind,
I'm thinking that
the sprinkling of points can
be thought of as a fluid.
Not a real fluid,
but an imaginary fluid
composed of a huge,
huge,
a huge dust.
Think of it as a dust,
but a fluid dust,
where all the particles of
the dust move in a way
which is dictated by these equations.
So wherever you happen to be,
you'll be at the next point a little bit later.
You'll move in some way,
and some way is dictated by what the Hamiltonian is.
And so you get a pattern,
a picture of a flow.
In this case,
for the harmonic oscillator,
the flow is very simple.
Just everything sort of rigidly moves around
on a carousel,
so to speak.
Everything's just rigidly moving around.
And so the fluid has
an extremely simple kind of motion.
And it's not important whether this is a fluid,
whether any real fluid could move like this.
This is a secondary question.
Just picture it as a fluid
or a collection of a dust moving around like that.
More generally,
for an arbitrary phase space,
always even dimensional,
but I can't draw it even,
even dimensional,
you can play exactly the same idea,
that the phase space is filled up with a dust.
The dust corresponds to every possible starting point,
and then just start the clock and let it go,
and the dust moves through the phase space
and defines a flow of a fluid,
a flow of an imaginary fluid.
We're interested in the fluid,
and we're interested in the properties of it.
But we're interested in one very specific property,
the property called,
having a divergence or a convergence of the flow,
divergence of the flow.
You said it's a rigid thing,
so you're implying that they all have the same period.
In this case,
in this case,
they all have the same...
Period.
Period?
Period,
yes,
that's exactly right.
And what is the period?
It's determined by this frequency.
Well,
harmonic,
this is a harmonic oscillator.
Harmonic oscillator,
no matter how far you displace the coordinate,
it oscillates back and forth
with exactly the same frequency.
So,
right,
so that translates into the statement
that everything moves around rigidly.
Right,
exactly so.
All right,
so now we come to
just a little bit about fluid,
about flow vectors.
Flow vectors and how they're connected to this
and the properties of those flow vectors.
A flow vector is a very,
very simple idea.
Incidentally,
we're imagining a flow
which is a kind of stationary flow,
points move,
points move.
Their motion,
what they're doing next
only depends on where they are on the phase space.
Where this particle moves next,
in other words,
what its velocity is.
Not the velocity q dot,
but the velocity in the period
q dot and p dot.
So,
what are the components of the velocity,
what are the components,
first of all,
of position in the q p space?
q and p.
Okay.
What are the components of the velocity in that space?
Not the real,
not the honest velocity of mechanics,
but the velocity in phase space.
q dot and p dot.
So,
we make a little vector out of them.
All the q dots and all the p dots.
q dots and line them up.
q one dot,
q two dot,
blah,
p one dot,
line them up.
And make a vector.
Make a thing whose components are the vector.
And then,
that velocity vector
can be thought of as
a vector in the phase space.
A vector in the phase
space showing the direction of flow.
What is the flow?
It's just these p dots and q dots.
This is the velocity vector.
And they're given entirely by known functions,
if we know the Hamiltonian,
known functions of position in that space.
The right-hand side are known functions of the position,
which are determined by the Hamiltonian.
And so,
it means whenever a point in
the flow gets to this point,
it always has the same velocity.
The velocity being determined by the value of h
and its derivatives at that point.
All right.
So,
that means that we can take this space
and fill it up with the same velocity.
With a vector field.
A vector field just means a vector at every position.
At every position in q and p space,
in phase space,
we draw a vector which is
just the velocity of the phase point
if it gets,
if it's at that point.
Kind of an ugly drawing I made,
isn't it?
Well,
okay.
Let's draw it for this guy over here,
for this system.
Is the velocity the same at every,
at every point?
The velocity is not the same at every point.
Even at a fixed radius,
the velocity is over here in this direction.
Do I have it right,
or is it,
is it clockwise or counterclockwise?
I told,
clockwise,
isn't it?
The velocity is this way here,
this way here,
and this way here.
But suppose you're moving closer.
Then the velocity is smaller.
The magnitude of the velocity is smaller.
It goes around in the same amount of time,
but it has a smaller distance to go around.
So the velocity,
this is not a very good circle around the origin.
Here's a circle around the origin.
The velocity is smaller here.
And if you go in even closer,
the velocity is even smaller.
And so we fill the space up.
With a velocity field.
Of course over here it's this way,
over here it's this way,
here it's this way,
and so forth.
And that's called the velocity field of a fluid.
Okay?
It's called the velocity field of a fluid.
And it's just a collection.
It's nothing but these guys over here.
P dot and Q dot.
Okay.
Now,
the question I want to ask about this fluid
is whether it's compressible or not.
Whether it's compressible or not.
Now,
what does compressible mean?
I'll tell you what compressible means
by starting with an example of a one-dimensional example.
Supposing I have a fluid,
which is a one-dimensional fluid.
In other words,
it's just a collection of points
moving along one-dimensional axis.
The fluid moves,
and what I want to know is
what is the velocity?
Well,
the velocity is whether the points of the fluid
get squeezed together and spread apart.
In other words,
whether the fluid is compressible.
If the fluid is strictly incompressible,
that means it has a constant density.
You cannot change the
distance between neighboring particles.
For example,
if the particles were little billiard balls,
well,
a one-dimensional billiard ball is a little weird,
but one-dimensional little billiard balls,
and they were up against each other,
and there was no room between them,
then you couldn't compress the fluid,
and let's assume you also
can't stretch the distance between them.
Then we would call that an incompressible fluid.
Now,
an incompressible fluid,
if we take the velocity field,
at every point there's a velocity,
and the velocity depends only on where you are.
Is it possible that the
velocity could vary along this axis?
Well,
if the velocity varied along this axis,
I think it's pretty apparent.
For example,
supposing the velocity was relatively small over here,
and then jumped to something big out here.
It's pretty clear that in the
region where the jump took place,
the points would have to be spreading apart.
Okay?
The points would have to be spreading apart.
So the only way to have
an incompressible fluid in one dimension
is for the velocity to be absolutely constant,
and independent of where you are.
It could depend on time,
but we're assuming explicitly that
the Hamiltonian doesn't depend on time.
And so an incompressible fluid would be one
for which the velocity vector had to be absolutely constant.
So one aspect of the incompressibility,
one aspect of the incompressibility
is that the velocity vector
is not going to be consistent with the velocity vector.
So what we're trying to
do is that if we look
at a little segment of the fluid here,
as much stuff comes in here as goes out here.
The number of molecules that come in from here
has to be the same as the
number of molecules that go out here.
Or better yet,
the volume of a fluid
in a small amount of time
that passes into this little region here
had better be the same volume of fluid
that passes into this little region here.
So that's the first aspect of the incompressibility.
The second aspect is that
the velocity vector is going to be
that passes into this little region here.
And so what we're trying to do is
to make sure that the velocity vector
is consistent with the velocity vector.
So that's the first aspect.
The third aspect is that
to get the same statement of it,
or we can stick with a body,
a piece of the fluid,
and follow the piece of the fluid.
And then to say it's incompressible
to think about it is
to stay fixed in the space,
not move with the fluid,
watch the
fluid move past you,
and say as much must come
in here as goes out here.
Both of those,
they're equivalent statements,
and to summarize them,
the fluid is incompressible.
But what
is the condition for incompressibility?
It's that the velocity has to be uniform right
across this line.
Or another way to write it
is that the derivative of the velocity
vector,
let's call it the velocity vector,
with respect to x,
this is x,
must be 0.
What
happens if the velocity vector,
if the vdx,
is positive?
Let's just think about that for
a moment.
If the vdx is positive,
that will mean that as you go to the right,
the velocities
are getting bigger and bigger.
I would say,
I want you to come up here.
I want you to come up here,
and I want you to
say that's decompressing,
the fluid is stretching out.
So if dv dx is positive,
it sounds like
it's the opposite of compression.
And if dv dx is negative,
that means that the velocity
over here is large,
smaller,
and maybe even turning negative and going
the other way if the dv dx is negative.
That's clear that's a compressional kind of situation.
dv dx being zero is the incompressible fluid.
Alright,
now we're going to need the concept
of an incompressible fluid for higher dimensions.
One dimension will not be enough for us,
so
supposing we have a fluid in,
well,
let's begin with three,
oh,
let's begin with two dimensions.
We have a fluid and 2ca in r.
You won't get any mike,
I'm not saying that,
but you do,
fluid in two dimensions,
and either we can follow the fluid,
take a little box in the
fluid,
follow it for a period of time,
its shape might change,
I don't know what it does,
but if it's incompressible,
the volume,
or in this case the
area of that piece of fluid
will stay the same,
or we can focus,
we can stand still and focus on a box here,
and the
condition of incompressibility is that as much fluid,
volume of fluid,
flows into this
region in a small interval of time as flows out.
For example,
it might be flowing in over
here,
and flowing out over here,
might even be flowing in over here,
but then it better
flow out over here,
and so forth.
That as much flows in as flows out.
Now,
I'm not going to work out the mathematics of this,
probably many of know it,
but I'll just tell you what the answer is.
Supposing we have,
in two dimensions here,
a flow vector which is Vx and Vy.
These are the components of the move vector,
they depend on where you are,
x and y.
What is the condition that fluid
does not build up in this region?
So,
first of all let's go back,
back to what we said before for the one-dimensional case.
If the fluid velocity is varying across
the x-axis here,
that's bad.
It means it's either compressing,
more fluid is coming in
one side than going out the other.
So we said that dv by dx better be zero.
But it's pretty
clear that dv by dx,
let's write the partial derivative
since we're now in multiple dimensions.
The partial derivative of the velocity,
and in particular the x component of the velocity,
this is how the x component of
velocity is varying as you change x.
So if the x component
of velocity is small here and big here,
then the fluid is stretching.
That's some measure
of how much the fluid is stretching in this direction.
But all we're interested in is
following the volume.
If the fluid is stretching in this direction,
then the fluid is stretching in this direction.
If it's stretching in that direction,
that's okay as long as it's compressing in the other
direction.
If it's stretching itself out in this direction,
it can still maintain its
volume and still not be compressed if
it's being compressed in the other direction.
Phase space,
phase space,
phase space.
Yes,
yes,
absolutely.
Absolutely.
This is a general statement about
a fluid in any number of dimensions,
that the condition
that it's incompressible is not that the derivative
of vx with respect to x is equal
to zero,
but that the sum of them,
derivative of vy with respect to y plus the derivative
of vz with respect to z is equal to zero.
The first term measures how much compression
there is along the x axis.
If the x component of,
incidentally,
as far as the x squeezing goes,
the y component of
velocity doesn't matter.
What's important is how much
the x component of velocity is
changing as you vary x.
And what these stand for is
the combined sum of the compression
along the x axis,
the y axis,
and the z axis.
Let's go,
let's get these three coordinates
now.
vx,
vz.
And that's the condition that
the flow of the fluid is,
um,
incompressible.
Now,
this symbol,
or this quantity,
the derivative of the component of a vector field,
the x
component of a field with respect to x,
plus the derivative of the y component of a field
with respect to y,
plus,
and so forth,
has a name.
Everybody know what the name of it
is?
Vector.
divergence of the vector field.
The divergence is a sort of
measure of how the vector field
is spreading out at any point.
This is the divergence and the symbol for it,
there's
a symbol for it which is del dot v.
The del stands for the derivatives,
the v stands for
the vector field,
and the dot product,
it looks like it's a dot product between a del
symbol and the v symbol,
but it doesn't matter.
This is what it is.
This is what it is,
the
sum of the various components of the
velocity field with respect to the same coordinate.
It's called the divergence of the flow.
It's the spreading out,
or the compression.
Now
having
the
,
talked about this flow,
and as I said,
it's an equivalent question to ask if you
stand at a point and require that the
total volume of fluid that flows into that region
is the same as the amount that flows out,
that's equivalent to following the fluid and
saying that in a chunk of fluid,
the volume doesn't change.
They're equivalent statements.
Okay.
Let's abandon the idea of the
del and the v and the dot.
Let's abandon this whole line of thought for
a moment and return to the very first lecture.
And remember what we said.
We had some kind of system,
which was characterized by some
sort of space of configurations.
Let's put another one over here.
That's a die with seven faces.
One,
two,
three,
four,
five,
six,
seven.
Yeah.
And we drew some
some arrows to indicate how the system moved.
The arrows are in some sense very,
very similar
to this idea of a flow in phase space.
They're telling you where to go next,
is what they're
doing.
We gave some examples of good laws of physics.
I'm not going to draw a good law
of physics,
but what is true of a good
law of physics is that at every point,
what flows
in must flow out.
That every point has an arrow
coming in and an arrow going out.
That
if you're at this point,
you know where you'll be next,
and you also know where you were
just before,
unambiguously.
Well,
that's somehow saying something that sounds a little bit
related.
If I take a little box around here,
as much
flow as I can.
It flows in as flows out.
One arrow in,
one arrow out.
We could even do something more
common.
Let's go to the six-sided case for a moment.
We had laws of physics,
for example,
which looked like this.
That was a particularly simple one.
We could take a couple of points,
and we could follow them.
Two points to two points.
They move around on the cycle here.
Two points
to two points.
Two points to two points.
The number of points,
if I start with two
points and follow them,
they stay two points.
They stay two points.
So in some sense,
if
we thought of the number of
points as a kind of volume,
the volume is conserved if we follow
the system around here.
Or we could say it the other way.
If we focus on a particular
node here,
the number of arrows in is the
same as the number of arrows out.
By contrast,
there are some bad laws.
Here's a bad law.
No matter where you start,
you go to the central
point.
No matter where you start,
you go to the central point.
That's an irreversible
law.
You may know where to go next,
wherever you start,
but if you find yourself over here,
you don't know where you came from.
If I draw a box around here,
I notice that it's not
true that as many arrows come in.
As many arrows come in as go out.
More arrows come in than go out.
That's the nature of
an irreversible law.
So it almost sounds like in this discrete,
simple-minded six-state
system or ten-state system,
this one has seven,
whatever it happens to be,
that the law of
reversibility sounds almost like something that's
going to be in the system.
It's just a simple law.
So it's like saying that the fluid is incompressible.
And in fact,
if the fluid is incompressible,
that sort of means that,
well,
it means something like this.
It means a continuous version of
the same idea,
as much in as out.
So the question then is,
is the flow of the fluid
in phase space dictated by Hamilton's
equations,
is it such that it's incompressible?
Another way of saying it is
if you start with a volume of,
in phase space,
a little volume
of phase space and follow it in time,
does it occupy the same volume afterwards?
Or does
it have an effect of getting squinched
up so that things which were clearly distinguishable
and different from each other get squished into
a smaller region where they can be less
distinguished?
That's the question.
So I'm going to show you now is Leoville's theorem.
Leoville's
theorem is the theorem that says that
the flow in phase space is incompressible.
And
it's the closest thing that we have,
closest analog that we have to this idea that,
well,
this idea that as many points come
in as go out of every point here.
Just to clarify,
are the V's are P dot and Q dot?
Yes,
the V's are P dots and Q dots.
Right.
So we line up all
the P dots and Q dots.
Let's think of our velocity vector.
Well,
I'll tell
you what,
let's start with just the case
with one P and one Q,
and then generalize it to
any number of P's and Q's.
So we have one P and one Q,
Q and P.
And what is the velocity
vector at every point?
The velocity vector?
Let's call it the velocity vector.
Let's call
it V sub P and V sub Q.
These are the components of the velocity vector.
And by definition,
V P is P dot
and V Q is Q dot.
Okay?
So this phase space here
is filled up with a velocity
flow where the components are P dot and Q dot.
Now let's calculate the divergence of
the flow.
The divergence of the flow is the derivative of
V P with respect to P plus the derivative
of V Q with respect to Q.
If you like,
this one is telling us
how much the fluid is bunching
up along the P X in the P direction,
and the other one is
telling us how much the fluid
is bunching up in the other direction.
If it's incompressible,
the sum of these should
be zero.
Okay.
Now we can work it out.
What is V P?
V P is P dot.
But that's minus the derivative
of H with respect to Q,
right?
Hamilton's first equation.
And Q dot is equal to plus
the H by DP.
So you just calculate them,
whatever they happen to be.
You calculate them,
their
functions of P and Q.
and they give you the components of
the velocity vector in the phase space.
Okay?
Any questions?
Good.
Now all we have to do is calculate.
The derivative of Vp with respect to P,
here's Vp right over here.
This is minus d by dP of dH by dQ.
And what's this one over here?
This is plus d by dQ of dH by dP.
Okay.
I think we must have mentioned
at some point about partial derivatives
that the process of partial derivatives is
independent of the order of the differentiation.
I think we,
I hope we mentioned that because if we didn't,
we'll mention it now.
If you have the second derivative of
a function with respect to two independent variables,
it doesn't matter which order you differentiate.
That's a little theorem.
It's a very simple theorem.
I can show you on the blackboard why it's true.
But I think we've,
did we do this in class?
Never?
Hmm?
Oh,
we didn't.
It's clear?
All right,
get up and prove it.
Let's prove it.
Let's label four points here.
A,
B,
C,
D.
And we have a whole bunch of them.
And we have a function of the four points.
All right.
Let,
and this direction is P and this direction is Q.
All right.
What's the derivative of the function
with respect to Q down here?
Well,
let's call it VC minus VD,
right?
We should put a little epsilon in the denominator.
But basically,
the derivative of some function,
whatever function,
it happens to be function.
The derivative of a function with respect to Q is
just the derivative as you move along the Q axis.
Okay?
Now,
what's the derivative with respect to Q up here?
That's F of B minus F of A.
Okay?
So,
now,
let's consider the derivative with respect to P.
That's differences going vertically of the
derivative of F with respect to Q.
D by DP.
That's just the difference of this and this,
right?
It's a difference of differences.
But the difference...
This one tells you to move vertically.
This one tells you to move horizontally.
So,
the difference between this expression and that
expression is just this mixed derivative here.
Let's write it down.
F of B minus F of A
minus F of C plus F of D.
F sub C,
F of D.
This minus this.
Okay?
Here's another way to write it.
It's F of B plus F of D
minus F of A minus F of C.
But that's neat.
Look what it says.
It's F of B plus F of D
minus F of A minus F of C.
So,
it's this one plus this one
minus this one minus this one.
That's for the second derivative.
Okay?
This one plus this one
minus that one plus that one.
But now,
think about the other order of differentiation.
D by DQ of DF by DP.
If you just spend one second doing it,
doing the same thing,
you'll find out it's exactly the same thing.
I'm not going to work it out.
It's the difference...
It's the horizontal difference of the vertical differences.
You know what I mean.
It's exactly the same expression.
So,
it doesn't matter when evaluating this combination here.
It doesn't matter whether you think of it as
differences going this way or differences going this way.
You know what I mean.
This takes too many words to express it.
This is an example here.
The second derivative with respect to P and Q of H is the
same as the second derivative with respect to Q and P of H.
So,
what's the net upshot?
This is zero.
Okay?
This is Leoville's theorem.
That the flow is without any compression or decompression.
That the divergence of the flow vector is zero.
And it's a consequence of Hamilton's equations.
What it says is in this phase space,
this two-dimensional phase space,
as you watch the fluid flow,
there's no buildup anywhere.
And there's no tendency for the fluid to compress,
to rarefy,
or to get more dense.
Now,
what about any number of Q's and P's?
No difference.
You just put an I in here.
I,
I.
Same deal.
Exactly.
It's just a multiple version of exactly
the same thing with any number of dimensions.
In each pair of directions,
in each pair of directions,
each Q and P,
the flow along one axis is compensated
by the flow along the other axis.
The way to say it then is that if
you take a piece of this fluid in phase space,
a collection of points,
and you either,
two ways to say it,
as I said.
Follow it,
the volume of it in the phase space doesn't change,
or stay at one point as
much comes in as goes out.
That ensures,
incidentally,
that points in the phase space cannot come together
and coalesce and lose memory of which point was which.
They maintain their integrity.
They don't stay there forever.
They're not the same distance apart,
but each one occupies a little
volume which is sort of sacred,
and the other ones can't penetrate it and,
and lose their,
lose their individuality,
so to speak.
Are you assuming a summation in the...
Yeah.
Absolutely.
Those cancel in pairs.
They cancel in pairs,
which is a special version of incompressibility.
It means in pairs,
in pairs of directions,
the compression in one direction and
the compression in the other direction.
Two removes or interfunctions and the
decompression in the other have to cancel,
so it's a special kind of incompressibility,
but it is incompressibility.
It's actually a stronger thing,
but-
It's a stronger kind of incompressibility.
It is a stronger,
it's stronger than incompressibility,
but it's not weaker than incompressibility,
and so it,
and as I said.
It is the closest thing that we have for the continuous world
to this idea that there's Beei's idea that there's no convergence of the,
of the trajectories in chronological order.ließlich
in the discrete world,
the loss of information.
I have a question.
So the expression that you've written for divergence,
that's the way divergence looks in Cartesian coordinates.
It is.
And I assume this result is going to carry over
to other kinds of coordinates?
No,
phase space is always thought of as Cartesian.
Phase space is thought of as Cartesian in this sense,
or it's thought of as called symplectic.
It's not really Cartesian,
but it's...
Cartesian is close enough to us.
Yeah?
With this...
I'm not trying to confuse things,
but would this hold for,
like,
the notion of expanding the
universe with a coordinate system?
Yes,
that's a good question.
And the answer is yes.
But even more simple,
let's talk about taking a box of gas and expand...
Oh,
incidentally,
this theorem
does not have a coordinate system.
It does not really depend on the Hamiltonian
not having any time dependence.
Time dependence,
it wouldn't matter.
It's still true,
the Leoville's theorem.
But okay,
so we take a box of gas,
and we expand the box of gas.
That's almost like the universe expanding.
What happens?
Well,
there,
the real fluid,
the ordinary sense of fluid,
the positions of the molecules in real space,
they're obviously...
They're actually spreading out from each other,
right?
So the fluid in ordinary space is not incompressible.
It's being rarefied in this case.
What that means is that in the P space,
the momentum space,
the points must be getting closer together.
The points must be getting
closer together in momentum space.
And that's true.
That's a correct statement that...
That if a fluid is expanding in ordinary Q space,
it means it's contracting in the P space.
The momenta are getting closer to each other.
Now,
let's think about that for a moment.
What does happen to the
momentum of particles in a gas
if you expand the gas?
It goes down,
right?
They get closer to zero.
And they all get closer to zero,
so the gas...
The gas is getting compressed in the P direction
while it's getting expanded in the X direction.
If you squeeze the gas,
exactly the opposite happens.
So yes,
it does...
It is an important aspect of expanding universes,
that the same thing happens.
So what if it's a sudden expansion,
so the particles...
Still.
It doesn't matter how fast the expansion is.
This theorem has no...
No assumption in it that the parameters
are not changing suddenly with time.
I know what you're thinking.
You're thinking about entropy,
but phase space volume is conserved.
Look.
And Mr.
Simon,
is a five particle system
five points in two-dimensional phase space
or ten-dimensional phase space?
Say it again.
If you have five particles.
Ten-dimensional phase space.
So those points there wouldn't run.
They represent individual particles.
They represent individual states.
They have.
Yes.
They represent individual states.
That's right.
They could of course repre...
They don't represent individual particles.
They represent states.
That's correct.
Well,
right.
The points represent states,
and then we imagine fictitious particles.
Fictitious particles are in this higher dimensional space.
That's right.
I have a question.
I think it's related to what you're talking about.
It seems pretty easy to see how
the Lubez's theorem follows from Hamilton's equations
for the phase space velocity field.
But I'm kind of fuzzy on what this fluid is.
What are all these...
What's the initial density?
Well,
all these points are different states of the system.
Yeah.
I don't think about the fluid at all,
it seems straightforward.
Yeah.
You don't have to think about the fluid.
Forget the fluid if you like.
The fluid is just to visualize.
And physicists always draw the fluid
because it's a useful trick to visualize.
But here's the statement.
Take a patch,
a region of the phase space.
Every point in this phase space goes
somewheres after a certain period of time.
Are you with that?
Yes.
Okay.
That means this patch will move.
The moves in a way which
preserves the volume in phase space.
The volume in phase space means
a product of P and Q.
The integral over P and Q of...
Or just the ordinary volume in the PQ space.
Just normal concept of volume.
Normal concept of volume,
but not spatial volume,
but volume of volume.
Volume in QP space.
Now,
it's an interesting question.
Supposing you change coordinates
in some very complicated way,
that will also entail a change
of the definition of the momenta.
Will,
if you re-parameterize everything
by some totally different coordinates,
will the theorem still be true?
And the answer is yes.
So,
the way you've drawn it also...
The theorem also implies a relationship of the movement,
that you don't have some
going up and some going down.
You might have some going up and some going down,
but then you're likely to have some
coming in and some going out to compensate.
Well,
I was thinking about the way you've...
You get a very complicated drawing if you have some
of those arrows going one way and some going the other.
Good.
So,
let's take an example.
Let's take an example.
I think what you're saying is that the
shape of a region of phase space can change.
And it can change in radically complicated ways.
Yeah,
this is a simple change,
but if you had some of those arrows
going this way and some going the other,
then it's very complicated.
It could be.
Let's construct an example.
I'll come back in a moment for a question.
Here's a Hamiltonian.
It may be a little bit unusual,
but it's a perfectly good Hamiltonian.
We can write it down and we can study it.
Not p squared plus q squared,
but just p times q.
Let's see what that one does.
Hamiltonian is p times q.
What is vp?
vp is the same as p dot,
and that is equal to partial...
Oh,
that's equal to the partial derivative.
I'm going to get rid of
some of the equations in a moment.
That's minus the partial derivative
of h with respect to q.
And what is that?
Minus p,
right?
Okay.
So the first equation is vp equals...
Let's write it as p dot.
I'm not going to call it vp.
Let's just call it p dot.
p dot equals minus p.
Supposing p is positive for a moment,
what happens to p as time goes on?
Do you get bigger or smaller?
Smaller.
Right.
What happens if p is negative?
What happens to it in time?
It gets bigger,
but in magnitude it also gets smaller.
In fact,
what's the solution of this equation?
p dot is equal to minus p.
It's an exponential,
but a negative,
a shrinking exponential.
So p shrinks.
Whatever p is,
it gets smaller with time.
In fact,
it exponentially gets smaller with time.
That sure sounds like the first thing you do.
The fluid is compressing along the p-axis,
and it is.
And it's compressing violently as time
goes on since it's being exponentially shrunk.
What about q dot?
q dot is equal to plus dh by dp.
And what's that equal to?
That's equal to q.
So what happens to the q motion of the fluid?
It exponentially expands.
So it's contracting in one direction
and expanding in the other direction.
That means if I were
to take a little square patch,
it would spread in the q
direction and shrink in the p direction.
It spreads in one direction by the same
factor that it shrinks in the other direction,
and the result is the area stays the same.
But the shape can change a lot.
So this was just a simple example of
a case where you can violently make the shape,
but the volume stays the same.
Just a second.
There's a question over here.
Before we do anything else,
let's just check that the
divergence of the velocity is zero.
Here's the velocity.
That's vp is minus p.
vq is q.
What's the divergence?
It's the derivative of vp with respect to p.
That's minus 1.
Plus the derivative of vq with respect to q.
That's plus 1.
If I add them,
I get zero.
So the divergence of the fluid is zero.
The two kinds of motion cancel each other.
Okay,
now a question.
So since pq is action,
is the Uville's theorem equivalent
to the conservation of action?
No.
No,
it's not the conservation of action.
It's the conservation of volume and phase space.
Why do you identify with action?
pq has units of action.
Oh,
it does have.
Indeed,
it does have units of action.
It's more closely related to
entropy than it is to action,
but there are circumstances in which
entropy and action are simply related.
pq is not the action,
but it does have units of the action.
It also has units of angular momentum,
but it's not the angular momentum either.
And you might begin to guess that it
has a lot to do with quantum mechanics,
because in quantum mechanics,
the basic rule of quantum
mechanics is that action is quantized.
And so these little areas in phase space might...
Well,
we'll get to it.
Let's not jump ahead.
You're touching on something important,
though,
when you point out that this is units of action.
But it is not the action.
It's not,
strictly speaking,
the action.
Yeah?
Do the rules allow you to break that up,
or is it...
Break what up?
Oh,
oh,
that's a wonderful point.
In other words,
the question is...
The answer is definitely not.
But the question is a good one.
The question is,
suppose you start with a
volume of phase space like this.
Could that volume go to this and then
pinch off and break up into two separate volumes?
The answer is no.
I'd have to think about proving it.
It's not too hard to prove.
I think that was the question,
was it?
Yeah.
No.
The other part of the theorem,
a little more complicated to prove,
I have to think about it,
is that the topology of a
region of phase space doesn't change.
And as I said,
that can be proved.
The way you prove it is by going
to the point where it's just barely touching.
And then you go to that point right over there,
and you say,
which way does that point go?
Does it go this way?
Or does it go that way?
It's the same point in phase space,
and the direction that it goes in is not ambiguous.
It is determined by the Hamiltonian,
and it only gets to go in one direction.
So because this point among all other,
and all other points are
completely deterministic where they go,
it can't split.
Politics,
they call it German Mandarin.
What's that?
Politics,
they call it German Mandarin.
Right.
But what it can do,
there's absolutely nothing that says that
it can't generate a very long,
long,
thin string like that.
So is that related to your
statement before that points can't coalesce?
Yeah.
But the important thing is that you can think
of each point as having a little volume that,
an integrity that doesn't allow
other ones to jam into it.
So to speak.
Like little incompressible particles
or billiard balls that the...
Question.
Is there an application for the
Louisville's theorem in terms of solving something?
Sure.
Oh,
yeah.
Yeah.
Take a gas and put it
in a box and expand it.
What happens to the,
what happens to the velocities?
Well,
basically the answer is if the expansion is,
if the expansion is,
if the expansion increases the volume of
ordinary space by a factor of two,
it will increase,
it will decrease the momenta by a factor of
two and as a result cool the gas a very,
very definite way.
Yeah.
In thermodynamics it is absolutely central to the,
to the conservation,
well,
to the concept of entropy and,
and it is the reason from this point of
view why when you expand the gas it cools.
Don't trajectories overlap for the solid pendulum,
for example?
No.
What's a solid pendulum?
A pendulum with a solid rod instead
of a string when it's standing straight up.
Clockwise versus counterclockwise.
Okay.
Yeah.
You're asking,
that's a good question.
Supposing you're at a point of unstable
equilibrium and you start right up here.
Yeah.
Then this point does indeed go in a different
direction than this point and that's exactly the situation
when you get these very,
very clean threads forming.
We're moving back to it.
What I wanted to talk about before doing that was
to talk about the kinds of systems that don't have Liebhold's,
yeah.
I'm just thinking that the thought thing is
that gives the illusion of two separate things.
Two separate entities,
but they're entangled.
Who?
When you take and do that,
stretch it.
This?
No,
the picture you drew there.
This?
But there's two things separated by
a great distance but still connected.
Would that be considered like giving the
illusion of two different things but entangled?
Not entangled.
Well,
connected.
they're not physically connected to each other.
This doesn't mean that they're physically connected to each
other and exerting forces on each other or anything.
It just means that...
I'm saying it's really one entity,
but...
Well,
it's one blob of phase space.
It's not an entity.
It's a blob of phase space that
you first drew and you followed it.
You just followed it.
Each point in here is a different initial condition.
It's diff...
Well,
it is.
That's what it is.
It's a different initial condition,
and now you follow the initial conditions in phase space,
and some of them separate,
some of them grow together in some directions,
but always in a way that conserves the volume.
Let's take an example of a system
that doesn't conserve the volume in phase space,
just to see what the difference is.
Now,
I've already proved that the
volume in phase space is conserved,
so how can I take a system
which doesn't conserve the volume in phase space?
Well,
I proved it by starting with Hamilton's equations of motion,
so I will have to take
a system which doesn't have a Hamiltonian,
which doesn't have a...
for that matter,
a Lagrangian,
and which therefore violates the rules.
Very simple system.
The damped harmonic...
The damped harmonic oscillator is a harmonic oscillator
where the bob of the oscillator,
or whatever you call it,
is moving through a viscous fluid.
What happens...
First of all,
what happens to the damped harmonic oscillator with time?
It just runs down,
right?
It starts to oscillate.
What happens to the position x?
It goes to zero with time.
What happens to...
What happens to the velocity v?
It goes to zero with time.
After a long,
long period of time,
you can't tell where it came from.
It doesn't seem to have this character of being...
Let's see exactly what happens.
Well,
let me...
Let's...
We could work out the equations.
Let's work out the equations.
The equations are m x double dot.
That's acceleration.
Is equal to force minus kx.
That's the harmonic oscillator,
the restoring force.
So far,
no problem.
And then I'm going to add something,
which is the viscous drag force
minus a constant times x dot.
That's a velocity-dependent viscosity term,
and it's a force which depends on
how fast you're moving through the fluid.
That's viscosity.
Viscosity cannot be derived from a Hamiltonian.
Where does it really come from?
It comes from the enormous number of particles colliding,
and it comes from the statistics of them,
and it comes from places that we're
not going to try to get into now.
But this is the equation of motion for a damped...
Not damned,
not D-A-M-N-E-D,
but damped.
D-A-M-P-E-D.
Damped harmonic oscillator.
Okay.
What does it do?
Well,
the ordinary harmonic oscillator...
And let's,
incidentally,
let's call m x dot,
let's call that p.
Even though there's no Lagrangian to derive it from,
the real definition of momentum
is the derivative of the
Lagrangian with respect to velocity.
In this case,
this is not a legitimate system
that comes from a Lagrangian.
Nevertheless,
since we're familiar with thinking of momentum
as mass times velocity,
let's call this the momentum.
All right,
then here's the phase space,
p this way,
x this way.
And what does the system do now?
If it wasn't for this damping term,
it would move in circles.
It would just move everlasting circles
that would just went around and around and around.
What really does happen
is the viscous drag force sucks energy out of it.
Remember that energy was just x squared plus p squared.
If energy is being sucked out of it,
it means the radius of the
orbit is getting smaller with time.
So if energy is being sucked out,
let's say slowly,
let's imagine this viscosity is small,
then it just spirals into,
and gets closer and closer to the origin.
You're right,
it should be clockwise.
Right?
And in fact,
it doesn't matter where you start.
You spiral into the origin.
After a long period of time,
you could start with a
patch of phase space that big,
follow every point,
and they all get shrunken down to a point,
to a little volume very,
very close to the center here.
So evidently,
this is a system
that doesn't have a Leaville theorem,
that the,
um,
that the volume in phase space is not conserved.
But let's check that by calculating the velocity field
and calculate its divergence.
Let's really do the calculator.
Let's do it.
All right.
So first of all,
you know what?
I'm going to get rid of
the mass and the spring constant
and the constant here.
And we're just going to simplify
the equation to the bare bones.
Bare bones,
then x dot is just equal to p.
Now what is p dot?
I'm sorry I did that.
x dot is p over m.
Or m x dot,
yeah,
p over m.
All right?
That's x dot.
That's the x component of the flow,
right?
Vx.
What about vp?
vp is p dot.
And what is p dot?
Well,
the left-hand side of the equation here is p dot,
right?
This is p dot.
d by dt of m x dot.
So here's p dot.
It's equal to minus kx
minus c times p over m.
So p dot,
so this is vp.
Here's vx.
And here's vp.
And that's minus kx minus cp over m,
right?
This is just force is equal
to restoring force plus viscous force.
Viscous force is proportional to velocity,
and velocity is proportional to momentum.
Okay,
now let's calculate the divergence of the fluid.
The derivative of vx with respect to x is what?
Zero.
There's no x on the right-hand side.
So the derivative of vx
with respect to x is zero.
Well,
what about the derivative of vp with respect to p?
Minus c over m.
So the divergence is not zero.
The divergence is not zero.
In fact,
the divergence is negative.
That means the flow vectors are kind of pointing inward.
They're not diverging.
They're converging.
And it's this over here,
which is,
so to speak,
the velocity divergence,
which is pushing everything into the origin.
So we find consistency.
The divergence of the fluid is
not zero if there's a viscous force.
The viscous force cannot be derived from a Hamiltonian.
And it violates the Hamiltonian.
It violates the theorem.
It violates the theorem,
of course.
It violates the statement,
the conditions of the theorem.
But it's a system where you really do lose information.
You start it going,
and after a while,
the phase points lose their integrity,
and they all get squished into the same small volume.
So it gets harder and harder
to distinguish the points of phase space.
It's basically a sink.
Yeah,
it's a sink.
There's a sink distributed throughout here.
And it's playing the same
role as this sink over here,
where all trajectories were leading into the same point.
It's playing the same role.
And it's the sort of system that cannot
be a consequence of the fundamental laws of motion.
Is it possible to have the divergence of zero
for a system without a Hamiltonian?
Is it possible to have a...
Oh!
That's a good question.
Yes.
Yes,
it certainly is.
It certainly is.
Yeah,
the question...
Okay,
so I think the question was,
is it possible to have the divergence zero,
but not have your equations come from a Hamiltonian?
And the answer is yes.
The answer is most certainly yes.
So...
The...
The Hamiltonian construction here is
not necessary and sufficient for...
for Leoville's...
for Leoville's condition,
let's say.
It's sufficient for it,
not necessary.
You can have system,
you can have...
Not mechanical systems.
I don't know of any
mechanical system that works that way.
But yes,
a fluid.
Let me give you a very simple example.
A fluid in three dimensions.
In other words,
a real incompressible fluid,
a genuine incompressible fluid moving in three dimensions.
It can't come from a Hamiltonian
because the phase space of a Hamiltonian system
is always even dimensional.
Right?
So it just can't.
Uh...
But still,
if the fluid was made out
of a lot of billiard balls
that were stuck together and,
uh,
incompressible,
even dimensional,
each billiard ball would have an
integrity and could not get lost,
and so it would have this character of being,
um...
Uh...of...of...
of not losing information,
if you like.
Yeah.
Um...
You said a number of times that the Hamiltonian,
uh...
development is sort of logically
the same way as a Lagrangian,
and that really is the same as Newton's equations,
but...
doesn't the damped harmonic oscillator,
isn't that described by Newton's equations?
Yes,
it's described by Newton's equations,
but it's not described by a force
which is the derivative of a potential energy.
No,
I...it is not correct.
Okay.
It is not correct that,
uh...
that the Lagrangian and Hamiltonian...
Okay,
let's...
are equivalent to Newton's equations.
That's incorrect.
They're not the same as F equals mA.
They're the same as F equals mA if the forces
are derived from a potential.
If the force is derived
as the derivative of a potential,
then they're the same.
So,
right,
so Newton...
Newton's equations are just F equals mA,
and it doesn't tell you what
the rules about the forces are.
It tells you some rules,
equal and opposite and so forth,
but it doesn't tell you
that they come from a potential.
Yeah.
Newton did not know about energy conservation.
No.
What did you say about a three-dimensional fluid?
Okay,
XYZ,
that's what you meant.
Yeah.
Okay,
but that...
In V space,
that's six dimensions.
No,
no,
no.
Just take a system...
a system of...
I think...
I think the question was,
supposing you have a fluid that's incompressible
with a set of coordinates,
does it follow that the equations of motion
for that fluid...
not...
Oh,
boy.
Okay.
So,
you're saying that the velocity vectors...
that the velocity vectors derive from differentiating
some kind of function of the P's and Q's.
The answer is no.
Example,
a three-dimensional fluid
with a velocity vector...
Forget about the fluid,
just a velocity vector.
A velocity vector in three dimensions
which corresponds to an incompressible fluid.
Okay.
Don't worry about it.
The answer is that the incompressibility
does not imply Hamilton's equations.
Hamilton's equations imply the
incompressibility of the fluid.
It's a one-way thing.
Yeah.
I want to go back to my last question.
I was going to pose a very simple system.
You have two particles.
They have zero momentum.
They're close together.
Total energy would be zero.
Now,
we take one particle and we move it out
13 billion light years.
Then,
all of a sudden,
it has an enormous momentum
because of the expansion of the universe.
Is that...
In other words,
it's a...
The momentum is a function of the distance,
x.
If you draw a phase space...
Okay.
Do you see what I'm saying?
I'm not sure if...
The...
Just the separation of the two particles
implies some kind of energy
because of the expansion.
I'm not sure if I'm articulating this very well.
But the coordinate system itself is expanding
where in normal space,
that doesn't happen.
There's no expansion.
Because you can...
The...
The Hubble constant,
you can have things,
you know,
separating faster than the speed of light.
Okay.
Which has nothing to do with this,
obviously.
Right.
But,
you know,
with a gas,
the larger it gets,
the smaller the momentum.
But just looking at the expansion of the universe,
the further the particles are separated,
the larger the momentum...
You're talking about a different phenomenon
which I could describe in a different way.
If you have an explosion...
Now,
this isn't expanding a gas by,
you know,
a controlled expansion.
You just take a gas and you explode it.
Particles don't even interact with each other.
They just go flying out.
It's not a surprise that
the ones which are furthest away
are the ones that are going fastest.
Why are they further away?
Because they were going faster.
So,
you know,
you can...
That's the expansion of the universe.
Why are the distant galaxies moving faster?
Why are they further away?
You ask me that?
Because they're moving away faster.
That is the way Hubble's law works.
That really is the way Hubble's law works,
that the things which are maximally far
are the ones which are moving away fastest.
Why?
Same reason.
So it's a different question.
Yeah.
The fastest horse wins the race.
Not surprising.
In this example with the damping
where you have this spiraling image...
Yes.
Aren't you really not losing information
if you have infinite position?
Okay,
so...
All right,
so that's...
What I'm telling you is
the closest thing that we have
to the discrete losing of
information or not losing information
is whether or not the divergence
of the velocity field is zero.
I think what you can say is,
what you can say in this case
is that each little cell of phase space
is not maintaining its integrity in the sense
that it is not maintaining
the same volume in phase space.
That's about all you can say.
You're right if you had infinite precision
and you knew exactly where that point was
and exactly what velocity it had with infinite precision,
you could reconstruct the past from the equations.
But in practice,
all of the phase points here are getting squished together
and losing their individuality.
You need a better and better microscope
to disentangle what's happening here.
There's a unit of size...
Well,
I don't want to get into quantum mechanics.
No quantum mechanics.
I don't want to talk about quantum mechanics tonight.
So you're right.
It is different than this very discrete situation
where no microscopes are necessary
and no enormous precision is necessary
to identify a point among six points here.
But it has a similarity,
and the similarity is as
many points flow into a point
as flow out of a point.
I think that's the bottom line.
That's as close as I can get to relating
the two concepts of reversibility that we talked about.
And of course,
in quantum mechanics,
where in a sense everything really is discrete,
the Liouville theorem becomes much,
much more similar
to this situation here.
The Liouville theorem is replaced by another theorem
which is much,
much more like this.
The connection is that in quantum mechanics,
there's a little unit of phase space,
a smallest unit of phase space.
The smallest area in phase space.
That's what's quantized.
It's the area unit in phase space.
And what quantum mechanics tells you is that
systems don't get bunched up
into smaller and smaller volumes.
But we'll have to come to that.
That's a ways in the future.
At the moment,
the theorem is that
volume in phase space is conserved.
Shape is not.
So think about it.
The other questions?
You started with a surface in phase space
as what is represented,
like the conservation of energy or the...
Yeah.
How does that relate to the flow?
Well,
of course,
among other things,
the flow is along these surfaces.
But that doesn't change the facts here.
Right.
That's...
Let's go back to the harmonic oscillator.
In the harmonic oscillator,
the surfaces are these circles.
So if you start on a circle,
you stay on a circle.
And that's a true statement.
The other true statement is if we
take a bunch of phase space here,
a little region of phase space here,
and we follow it,
it's not...
It's not a definite energy.
It's got just some little box with some volume.
And follow it,
it just moves around here
rigidly maintaining its volume.
Two different statements.
So they're not so much related.
They're not so much related.
Right.
You can take a little volume of phase space,
which includes several different energies,
and follow it,
and it will maintain its volume.
Notice in this case,
in this case,
the shape of the region also is conserved,
is maintained.
So in the x squared plus...
the p squared plus q squared case,
that's the harmonic oscillator,
it's not just that the volume of
a piece of phase space is conserved.
The shape is conserved.
In this other case over here,
the volume is conserved,
but things get stretched one
way and compressed the other way.
So this is...
the harmonic oscillator is special this way.
In Newton's world,
you can change energy by doing work.
Yes.
Do we have the equivalent...
How do we handle work?
Well,
work is energy that's exchanged with a system
that you're not accounting for.
In other words,
if I have a system
let's suppose it's this eraser here,
and the eraser is satisfying some equation of motion,
which has a gravitational force,
a kinetic energy,
and so forth,
and I am an external system
that's not being accounted for in the equations,
exerting forces on this,
then I can exchange energy with it,
or I can change its
energy by doing work on it,
but the work,
the energy that I give it,
is taken from me.
So I can exchange energy with it,
so work has to do with exchanging energy
between systems that you're accounting for everything
and other systems that are...
are acting as external agents on the system.
For example,
well,
yes,
the concept of work is useful
when you separate a system into the part
that you're going to describe,
and the part you're simply describing by external forces.
Where those external forces come from,
you don't care.
You don't care if they're described by a Lagrangian
or a Hamiltonian or anything else.
You just say there's an external force on a system,
and that external force on
the system does work on it.
It can just raise a weight.
Of course,
it changes the energy at the cost of
having to provide the energy from the external system,
which is doing the work.
So,
um,
but the concept of work
is not one which comes
up very much in modern physics,
so I don't...
We don't really need to think about it.
Energy conservation is the important idea,
and the idea that two systems can give energy
back and forth between them,
and that we sometimes call that work,
uh,
is sort of secondary.
Yeah.
Just looking for connections,
is there...
Louville's theorem preserved...
says we preserve topology of phase space.
Does it do anything...
Preserve what?
Topology.
It does,
yes.
Does it...
Is there any...
It doesn't preserve angles,
does it?
No,
no,
definitely not.
For example,
in this case,
PQ here,
if I took a cross like this,
and I evolved it,
it would become a cross like that.
No,
it definitely does not say angles are conserved.
Most definitely not.
The harmonic oscillator is probably the only case
where it's true.
And that's an unusual case.
Uh...
Right.
Yes?
Just to...
I listened to your lectures on the tape
from the previous series,
and you...
In the classical mechanics,
you talk about Legendre's theorem.
Oh,
yeah.
I decided to abandon...
Not to bother with it this time,
but the Legendre transformation.
Right.
Is it mostly mathematical,
or is it physically significant?
It's a trick.
It's a useful trick.
It's especially...
Um...
It's...
I decided it wasn't important enough
to worry about this time around.
And,
um...
Uh...
We didn't...
We didn't really need to think about it.
If I ever need it,
and we ever need it for anything,
I'll do it,
but...
It's...
Uh...
Right.
We used it over and over,
but I didn't call it that.
Okay.
Um...
I could go on for another few minutes,
or we can just stop here.
I want...
The next thing...
As I said,
a lot of this development
of classical mechanics,
which really did turn out
to become absolutely central
once quantum mechanics happened,
was playing around with the equations
and putting them in different forms
and finding different elegant,
uh...
representations
of the same set of equations.
And we're gonna do
at least one more version of mechanics,
or at least one other concept which
is closely related to the Hamiltonian version,
and it's called Poisson brackets.
It's again one of these very elegant
things when you look at it and say,
what the hell good is that
other than for just writing neat equations?
And the importance of it,
again,
quantum mechanics.
Maybe I will start the
subject of Poisson brackets right now.
At the beginning of the hour,
because you just cycled back to what you talked about,
the beginning of the hour.
The beginning of the hour was energy conservation.
No,
no,
the very beginning,
7 o'clock,
you were musing about the 19th century physicists.
And you said that you were speculating that
they had played with a lot of different
equations without realizing the
physical significance of them.
Well,
I don't know.
They may have realized the
physical significance within the context of
classical mechanics.
I mean,
for example,
Hamilton probably did realize
that the Hamiltonian was energy.
But what they were doing
was just playing with the equations,
I would say.
I don't think they understood.
They could not have understood how important it
was going to be 100 years from then.
There was no way that they could have.
They were,
among other things,
they were finding analogies between different kinds
of things.
For example,
the motion of light rays and mechanical systems.
Well,
once you know that the motion
of light rays is like mechanical systems,
you might
begin to wonder,
is there an analog in classical
mechanics of wave motion and so forth?
And the answer is yes,
there is.
But they were exploring all these
analogies and mathematical similarities between different
things,
trying to create structure.
And they were trying to create structures
where everything would fit into the same kind
of structure,
trying to make the equations as small as possible,
meaning as few as possible,
as elegant,
as neat as possible.
In my opinion,
it was not so much motivated
by individual phenomena as trying to unify
everything and packaging it into the same kind of package.
Formal structures,
creating formal structures.
But I wasn't there.
I didn't do it.
And I can only guess what was in their minds.
There were largely,
you know,
there was no difference in those days,
or not much difference
between a physicist and a mathematician.
And,
well,
I first heard this remark from my friend Dick Cronenberg.
Feynman many years ago,
that the difference between mathematicians and physicists is
the difference between masturbation and sex.
I think what he meant is
that physicists are interacting with a partner,
namely the physical
world.
Mathematicians are interacting...
I don't know what was on their mind.
I wouldn't have done what they did,
unfortunately.
All right,
let's talk a little bit about Poisson brackets,
just to set us up for the next time.
What is a Poisson bracket?
Well,
it starts out by saying,
supposing I have a function of P and Q,
the most general
thing I could be interested in,
you know,
the most general thing having to do with the
dynamics of a system is to know how a function
changes with time.
Now,
the function could just be Q,
in which case,
figuring out how the function changes
with time is just figuring
out how Q changes with time,
meaning how the position changes
with time.
It could be Q times P.
And you ask,
how does Q times P change with time?
I don't know why you would want to do that.
But,
well,
it could be the angular momentum,
R times P,
which is a kind of Q times P.
The
angular momentum,
if there's a torque on the system,
then the angular momentum changes
with time.
You might ask,
how does the angular momentum change with time?
So,
how does the general function F of
Q and P change as time goes on?
Let's explore that question,
just as an abstract.
Just an abstract question.
How does this change with time?
And again,
the number of tricks here is rather limited.
I'm interested in how this quantity changes with time.
Now,
why does it change with time?
It changes because Q changes and P changes.
As you follow the trajectory through the phase space,
F of Q and P changes just because Q
and P change.
So,
how do you calculate this?
Standard rule.
You differentiate.
We're going to do the same thing.
So,
we're going to divide Q by DQ,
sub I,
we're going to sum over I,
times Q sub I dot plus
the F by the P sub I,
oops,
P sub I dot.
Same thing.
We've done it before.
We'll probably do it again.
We differentiate something with respect to
time by differentiating it with respect to
the arguments.
the thing that the function depends on,
and then multiplying by how fast those things change.
But now we have something.
We have P dot and Q dot,
so I can substitute that in here.
And this is equal to summation.
Now,
somebody first did this calculation.
I don't know who it was.
Maybe it was Poisson.
But let's write it out.
The F by dQ sub i.
Now,
what's Q sub i dot?
Q sub i dot.
The H by dP sub i,
right?
Negative.
Minus?
Q?
No.
No,
that's right.
And then there's another term,
which is the F by dP sub i.
And then P sub i
dot that does have a negative.
So,
it's equal to dH by dQ sub i.
Two functions.
One of them is H,
the Hamiltonian.
The other is some general function.
Poisson did this calculation,
and he did it for the harmonic oscillator,
and he did it for this system,
and he did it for that system,
and he got tired of writing this down.
He wrote it down so
many times for two different functions,
that he decided to give this operation a name,
or to write a symbol for it.
And so he said,
given any two functions,
whatever they happen to be,
let's now take any two functions.
They don't have to be,
one of them does not
now have to be the Hamiltonian.
This is just a definition.
Let's,
uh,
let's replace it.
by some general function which we'll call g
may or may not be the Hamiltonian of the system
just two functions of phase space
this quantity
the derivative of one with respect to q
times the derivative of the other with respect to p
and then interchange
and subtract
and sum over i
that Poisson called the Poisson bracket
Poisson was not a modest man
it's called the Poisson bracket of f and g
and it's simply written
f comma g
we're gonna write this kind of thing down
now and then
and we're not gonna bother
writing all of this mess here
we're gonna write it's the
Poisson bracket of f and g
but now we have a
new way of writing Hamilton's equations
and everything about the system
and the new way of writing it
here it is
we'll go back now and call this h
let's call this h again
we have a new formulation of mechanics
in which the time derivative of anything
it could be q
it could be p
it could be anything
is given by the Poisson bracket
of f with what
with the Hamiltonian
that's all there is to the world
every time derivative of anything that you can think
of is a Poisson bracket of f and g
and that's what we're gonna think of
is just the Poisson bracket of that thing
with a Hamiltonian
of course you have to know what the Hamiltonian is
this is the most condensed
version of classical mechanics I know
I mean it is really condensed
this is everything that you could
I can condense it even more
I'll condense it even more
take this subtract it
square it
call this thing
say that it's zero
and then call this thing in here a
and then we only have one equation a equals zero
that's Susskind's equation
in fact you can write any equation
you can take all of
the equations of all of physics
take their squares add them all together
set it equal to zero
and that's uh...
but uh...
this is pretty neat though
the time derivative of anything is the Poisson bracket
of the anything
with the Hamiltonian
now if this was all there was to it
then Poisson brackets wouldn't be all that interesting
but it's not
we're gonna find out
that all kinds of equations of physics
can be expressed in terms of Poisson brackets
and that's the reason we're doing this now
symmetry is all sorts
of things that the Poisson
bracket is a very central thing
and we'll spend a little bit of time
I'm not gonna spend a lot of time
with that but uh...
I just wanted to show you how it works
okay um next time I'll tell you a little more
about Poisson brackets
and then what i want to go is angular momentum
angular momentum and how angular momentum works
angular momentum is extremely important in quantum mechanics
and throughout physics and we'll talk about that later
Spend some time learning about classical angular momentum.
For more,
please visit us at stanford.edu.