Stanford University.
We're going to start tonight and maybe
finish tonight with more about Poisson brackets.
But I think I will go back and we're
going to study angular momentum in the context of
Poisson brackets as a case of mechanics
being formulated through the use of Poisson brackets.
Okay,
so Poisson brackets and angular momentum tonight.
But let's go back.
I think I told you a
little bit about Poisson brackets last time.
And we began with a question,
if you have some function of the p's and q's.
You can think of it as just a function
that varies from one point of phase space to another,
but you can also think of it just as
a function of the positions and velocities of a point
moving through phase space.
And because the point is moving through phase space,
the p's and the q's vary.
And if the p's and the q's vary,
the function f of p and q will vary.
And we can ask the question,
along a given streamline,
we're really thinking about along
a given streamline now,
as the system wanders along that streamline,
what is the time derivative
of an arbitrary function of p and q?
Now when I say arbitrary,
I always mean smooth enough and differential enough.
And I'll tell you that the derivative of f
is going to be the derivative of f with respect
And what is that?
And we know what that is.
This is a quick review from last time.
It's the derivative of f with respect
to p times p dot along the trajectory.
Now if you like,
you can decorate this thing with
little indices i and sum over them.
I'm going to leave that out.
Just because I get tired of writing it.
But if you're interested,
you can go back to my course.
So the derivative of f with respect to p sub
i times p sub i dot plus derivative of f with
respect to q sub i times q sub
i dot all summed over all of the coordinates.
And as I said,
I will not bother being explicit about that sum.
There it is.
All right.
Now what is p dot?
p dot from Hamilton's equations is partial of h minus,
you know,
h times p dot,
and p
minus partial of H with respect to Q
and Q dot
oh,
minus,
right?
No
no,
partial of H
yes,
right,
minus,
right?
P dot is minus
P dot is minus dH dQ
right,
I know why I'm confused
the reason I'm confused is
I always write this one first
and I always have the minus sign second,
so
that's alright,
we'll just leave it
dF by dQ times P dot
dF by dQ times Q dot
which is dH by dP
so,
that's the question
I'm going to write it the other way because
I want to keep a consistent pattern
the F by dQ
dH by dP
minus the F by dP
dH by dQ
and as I said
well,
let me put it in
now that we finished the expression
we put in I,
I,
I
and sum over all I
this kind of expression
comes up over and over again in classical mechanics
not only in the context of time derivatives
but in the context of all kinds of situations
where you have two functions
of P's and Q's
one could be the Hamiltonian,
but it might not be
it might be anything else
and this particular combination of the two
this particular combination comes up all the time
and it's called the Poisson bracket
of F with H
and it's written with
curly script,
curly brackets
F
in this case,
H
more generally,
you take any two functions
it doesn't have to be,
let's make it more general now that we've done it
now that we've seen the reason why it comes up
at least in one context
and just generalize it
so that G could be anything
and F could be anything
this is called the Poisson bracket
and it's written this way
and it seems like a
rather arbitrary thing to write down
but as I said,
it does occur over and over
and we'll see some examples tonight
let me write this one more way
let me imagine time
has been broken up into little epsilon intervals
and then,
this of course is nothing but
the change in F,
the variation in F
when you change epsilon by one unit
this is nothing but the time derivative
the change in F with respect
to a small change in time
I'm just writing it this way
because it'll come up later
something like that
um,
yeah
that first part of the equation is no longer true
let's put G arbitrary in there,
right?
yeah,
absolutely right
once G is arbitrary
that's,
uh,
that's not F dot
this part of the equation is no longer true
only if G is the Hamiltonian is it true
but
the other part of the equation is definition
definition of the Poisson bracket
and
classical mechanics can be beautifully formulated
elegantly formulated
French formulated
in terms of Poisson brackets
there's an algebra of Poisson brackets
which if you know the algebra
you don't even really have
to remember what they came from
you can calculate anything you want
uh,
without
in other words,
a set of rules about Poisson brackets
and I'm gonna tell you what the set of rules
we'll write them over here
here's the definition of the Poisson bracket
let's put them over here
and now I'll tell you what the rules are
they're not,
they're not arbitrary rules
they follow from this definition
the first fact about Poisson brackets
is they're anti-symmetric
so let's take A and B
I'm now going to use A
and B for two arbitrary functions
the Poisson bracket of A and B
is equal to minus
the Poisson bracket of B with A
now you can see why that's true
uh,
if I interchange F and G
I simply interchange these two terms
and so the whole thing changes sign
if I replace F by G and G by F
it simply changes sign
and so whenever I
interchange the two things in a Poisson bracket
it changes sign
so that's rule number one
rule number two
if I add two functions
A,
let's call it B again now
and I take the Poisson
bracket of the sum of them
with a third thing
it's very simple
it's just equal to Poisson bracket of A with C
plus
Poisson bracket of B with C
you can see why that's true
if F happens to be the sum of two functions
then the derivatives are also sums of two terms
and the Poisson bracket just adds in that way
it's easy enough to get
Poisson bracket of C on the left
with A plus B on the right
just using the minus sign
alright,
a third rule
I didn't write this one down in my notes
but I suddenly just realized it
if you take the Poisson bracket
of A with B or C or whatever we use
and I multiply A by a number
in other words
the Poisson bracket
what's a notation for an arbitrary number?
C,
constant
constant times A
A
I see
by the end
no,
no
A
I'm absolutely Greek
lambda
with B
or C
it's just equal to lambda
times the Poisson bracket of A with B
that's easy
in fact this third one is a special
case of one that I'm about to write down
no,
that's,
that's a,
that's a case
alright,
number four
this is the only one
that's not completely absolutely transparent
I'm not going to work it out for you
I'm going to allow you
this is your homework
work it out
but it's very easy
it's that if I take
not the sum of A and B
but the product of A with B
Poisson with C
if I take that product
and feed it into here
and just use the rule for differentiating products
in other words
A times B here is now substituting for F
alright,
I have to differentiate F
for example with respect to Q over there
and with respect to P on the second term
use the product rule
for
differentiating a product
A times the derivative of B
plus B times the derivative of A
and you'll find out very quickly
that this thing here is equal
to A Poisson with C
times B
plus A
Poisson bracket with C
the order that I've written
doesn't matter here
in quantum mechanics it does matter
but in classical mechanics it doesn't matter
you can put the B on the left
you can put the B on the right
it just means ordinary multiplication
so when you see an expression like that
it consists of two terms
one of them is B times
the bracket of A with C
and then A bracket B with C
alright,
so that's pretty easy
those are the basic rules
about Poisson brackets
and then there are some special cases
once you know these special cases
and these rules
you can pretty much calculate the Poisson bracket
of any function of P and Q
with any other
you have to use these rules over and over again
several times
but here are the special cases
the Poisson bracket of any Q
Q is a function of itself of course
so any Poisson
the Poisson bracket of Q sub i
with any other Q
is equal to zero
now why is that?
let's look at it for a minute
if F is Q1 let's say
and G is sub i
and then this is the same
so when you do the same thing
and the answer is always going to be zero
because every term in here
involves differentiating with somebody with respect to P
so if there's nobody around
who depends on P
in fact you could write this more generally
any function of Q
with any other function of Q
gives zero
you've got to differentiate in the expression
with respect to both P and Q
and so this is zero
it is also equal
p sub i with p sub j.
i can equal j or not equal to j,
it's still equal to zero.
Any p with p or q
with q is always equal to zero.
Any function of p with a
function of p is zero.
Any function of q with
another function of q is zero.
The
things which are not zero are
Poisson brackets of functions of p with
functions of q,
for example.
In particular,
the simplest case is the
Poisson bracket of q sub i with p sub j.
If you look up on the top here,
let's see
what that would be.
The f is q sub i.
The only thing that you can differentiate q
sub i with respect to is q sub i itself.
In other words,
you can differentiate q sub i with
respect to q sub i and get
something,
namely 1.
But you can try to differentiate q sub i with
respect to q sub ii.
You won't get anything.
So the only contribution comes from
differentiating f with respect to q and
g with respect to p.
The only time you'll get a contribution
is if i is equal to j.
Why is that?
Because each term in the sum here
mates a q sub i with the same index i.
The only contributions mate the
indices together,
one with one,
two with two,
three with three,
and so forth.
So the
only time you can get something not zero,
and this is something that you work out,
is when i is equal to j.
Otherwise it's zero.
I can write,
well I'll write it out first.
Zero if i not equal to j,
if i equals j,
or to write it in fancy notation,
it's equal to the Kronecker delta symbol,
delta ij.
Let's use these rules to calculate,
let's use these rules without any reference
at all to anything but the rules,
but this set of algebraic rules over here.
Let's use them to calculate the
equations of motion for harmonic oscillator.
The equations of motion for harmonic oscillator begin,
let's do it over here,
with a Hamiltonian.
And now the Hamiltonian is
a function of p's and q's,
not q's and q dots,
but think of it as
a function of p and q.
And,
okay,
let's suppose the oscillator has a mass m.
So what's the kinetic energy term
in terms of m and p?
It's got a p squared in it.
What else?
Where does the m go?
Numerator or denominator?
Denominator.
It's 1 half mv squared in terms of velocities,
but momentum squared divided by 2m in terms of momentum.
p squared over 2m plus k over 2,
q squared.
Let's call it q squared.
I don't want to start mixing.
I want to start using the equations of p,
of x's and q's.
All right,
this is my Hamiltonian now,
h.
And I want to work out the equation of
motion for the p's and q's using only what's here.
No reference to Lagrangian.
In fact,
not even a reference to Hamilton's equations,
although Hamilton's equations went into the
rule that the time derivative of something,
let's write back,
let's go back to a little bit later,
but it's a reference to Hamilton's equations.
Yeah,
let's go back to the basic
rule that given anything of interest,
its time derivative is the Poisson
bracket of that thing with the Hamiltonian.
So that's the one thing I would
add to this set of rules here,
that the time derivative of the thing is the Poisson.
Now we don't care where it came from.
In fact,
we don't even need to know.
This contains,
certainly contains Hamilton's equations,
but let's forget it.
Let's just use this rule.
Okay,
so here we are.
h is p squared over 2m plus q squared,
k over 2.
And I want to calculate the equations of motion.
In particular,
let's start with p dot.
Well,
let's start with q dot.
q dot is the Poisson bracket of q with h.
So I could stick h in here now.
Let's put p squared over
2m plus k over 2q squared.
But q has zero Poisson
bracket with any function of q.
So I don't need to write that there.
When I keep being tempted to say commute with
because I tend to think in quantum mechanical language.
We need a verb for taking the Poisson bracket.
Anybody got a good verb for it?
Pubbing it.
Poissonate it.
Good,
good,
good.
Poissonate it.
All right.
So taking the Poisson bracket of f with a Hamiltonian,
we will call Poissonating it.
Poissonating q with a Hamiltonian requires only that
we Poissonate q with p squared over 2m
because q is a Poisson.
So if q Poissonates with q squared,
the Poissonate means to be zero.
Okay.
Well,
if two things Poissonate,
oh,
God.
Okay.
All right.
Does everybody see why I don't
have to write q squared here?
Yeah,
okay.
All right.
Now,
what do we do?
We say this is a product.
Well,
first of all,
we can take the 1 over 2m on the outside.
1 over 2m.
That's this rule.
That's one of these rules,
multiplication by a constant.
We take that on the outside.
And then we have q with p squared.
Now,
q with p squared,
we use,
sorry,
q with p squared,
we use the product rule.
The product rule,
and whose product?
The product is p squared.
Incidentally,
you could have written the same way the other way.
You could have switched this around.
Everybody would have just changed sign,
and the equation would still be true.
So if I put c Poissonated with a b,
then the orders would change,
but the equation would still be true.
Okay.
So what is the Poisson
bracket of q with p squared?
According to the rule,
that's p times the Poisson bracket of pq
plus p times the Poisson bracket of pq.
There are two terms.
p is p times p.
p squared is p times p.
And now there's two terms.
This one times p,
and this one times this p over here.
So what's the result?
The result is twice p times
the Poisson bracket of q with p.
But what's the Poisson bracket with q with p?
We just go down to our table over here.
It's 1.
Okay.
So our first equation of motion is
that q dot is p over here.
p over m.
Okay.
I think we've seen that before.
That's just a statement that the
momentum is m times the velocity.
Okay.
So that's the first equation.
And the second equation of motion,
same thing.
Oops,
sorry.
p dot is the Poisson
bracket of p with the Hamiltonian.
But now I can leave out the p squared
over 2m because Poissonating p with p squared gives 0.
Poissonating p with q squared has
a chance of not giving 0.
So we put here k over 2 q squared.
Let's take the k over 2 outside.
p dot equals.
Let's take the k dot
k over 2 on the outside.
And now we do the same thing.
It's twice,
equals twice q times the Poisson bracket
of p with q times k over 2.
q times q,
we get two terms.
That's where the 2 comes from.
Now what's the Poisson bracket of p with q?
It's not 1.
It's minus 1.
Minus 1 because you have to reverse them.
Okay.
So this is minus 1.
That is where the minus sign.
In this formalism,
that's where the minus sign comes from in Hamilton's,
in one of Hamilton's equations.
So the 2's cancel.
Put the k over here.
Minus sign because commutator,
Poisson bracket of p with q is minus 1.
All right,
so that's p dot.
And that's of course the standard Newtonian equation.
q dot is p over m.
p dot is minus kq.
These combine together to give Newton's equations which say that the
second derivative of q times the mass is equal to minus kq.
So these two together are Newton's equation for,
or Hooke's,
I don't know whose equation it is,
but the equation of motion for a harmonic oscillator.
And it's a simple example.
Okay,
any questions about Poisson brackets?
Yes?
In terms of a mathematical structure,
is this an algebra?
It's not a group.
It's not a what?
No,
it's not a group.
I think you would call it an algebra.
Does it have an interval?
No.
No,
there's no inverses.
You have product and addition.
Anything else?
Hmm.
So what's the connection to commutators?
Well,
the main connection is,
instead of drawing wiggly things,
you draw square ones.
And you put an i on the right hand side.
Let's not do it now.
Well,
okay.
Poisson.
Poisson bracket of two things in
classical mechanics is essentially the commutator of
the two of them times i,
Planck's constant.
But we'll get to that.
That's not for now.
Okay.
All right,
now we're going to study angular momentum.
This is not a separate lecture.
We're going to study angular momentum,
the equations of motion for rotating bodies and
things of that nature by using Poisson brackets.
We'll do the gyroscope by Poisson brackets.
Very efficient.
And,
um...
I seem to have lost one page of my notes,
but I'll try to do it on the fly.
Motion of a rigid body in space.
Poisson brackets are the way to think about it.
And here,
obviously,
it didn't help very much.
I mean,
it just did what Hamilton's equations did.
It's just a sort of redundant
way of thinking about Hamilton's equations.
Or Newton's equations.
But when you start thinking about angular momentum,
you start to see the power that
it has.
All right.
Now,
remember what angular momentum was.
Angular momentum was the conserved quantity
that's conserved because of rotational invariance.
Okay?
If we have a collection of...
Let's just take one particle and not try
to think about lots and lots of particles
for right now.
And let's just go through the little exercise.
Let me write over here on this blackboard,
on this part of the blackboard,
the quantity
Q is conserved if there's a symmetry.
In particular,
if the symmetry is such that it takes...
It's a constant.
And the Q's,
Q sub i equal to F
sub i of Q times epsilon,
where epsilon is any small
number.
If this is a symmetry which does not
change the Lagrangian in the case that we originally
studied,
today we're going to study Hamiltonians,
but this was a symmetry.
If that is a symmetry,
then there's always a conserved quantity.
And the conserved quantity...
The conserved quantity...
Is the sum over all the i's.
Remember what it is?
P sub i times F sub i,
oops,
not delta,
but F sub i of Q.
You know,
it wouldn't be that bad a deal if
I just erased the epsilon here and said,
you just track it through,
you don't ever have to worry about it.
It really is a symmetry.
It really is just P sub
i times F sub i of Q.
And you could also write this as sum over
i P sub i times delta of Q sub i.
I'm leaving out a factor of epsilon,
but the point is that if a thing is conserved,
so
is epsilon times it,
so it doesn't really matter whether
I put the epsilon there or
not.
But in any case,
this is the thing which is
conserved if there is a symmetry.
What was a symmetry?
A symmetry was an operation
that doesn't change the Lagrangian,
an active transformation
that doesn't change the Lagrangian.
So let's go back to angular momentum.
In the case of angular momentum,
the transformation we're talking about is a rotation.
So there's our particle.
It's located at point,
let's say,
.
Our Q's are now X and Y.
And we make an infinitesimal
rotation by the small angle epsilon.
And,
well,
that's it.
The point moves to a new X
plus delta X and Y plus delta Y.
So what happens to X?
Delta X is equal.
Now obviously if Y is positive,
as it is here,
and you rotate,
delta X will be negative.
You'll move slightly to the left here,
obviously.
So this must be minus.
And it's minus Y times epsilon.
And delta Y is equal to
plus X times the same epsilon.
Epsilon is a small angle.
Everybody remembers this.
And so now we can write down the conserved quantity.
And the conserved quantity is called angular
momentum and is labeled with an L.
In this case,
Q is being replaced by a
thing called L and its angular momentum.
So what happens?
So what is it?
It's the sum.
The sum over I now becomes the sum over the
two directions of space of P sub X times the
change in X,
which is minus Y,
plus P sub Y times X.
Let's see.
Do I want to write it that way?
Yes.
Like this.
Or just X P Y minus Y P X.
Same thing.
Let me just erase it and write it this way.
This is L.
Now this is the angular momentum
for a particle moving in two dimensions.
angular momentum is really a vector
what component of angular momentum is this
it's the Z component where Z is the
axis coming out of the blackboard the angular
momentum about the Z axis so let's call this
L sub Z now this is the Z component
of angular momentum X P Y minus Y P
X what about the X and Y components of
angular momentum they would be exactly
the same thing instead of rotating about
the Z axis you rotate about the Y
sorry instead of rotating about the Z axis you
rotate about the X axis and all you have
to do to find the components here is to
permute Z goes to X goes
to Y X goes to Y
goes to Z X Y Z x y z
x y z x y z X goes to Y,
Y goes to Z I'm never
consistent about about whether I use
a lowercase or an uppercase Z
forgive me for that minus Z P Y X Y y Z
y z X Y and then L sub Y is X Y
Z
py,
pz,
px,
minus y,
z,
x,
p,
z.
Sorry,
p,
z.
These are the three components of angular momentum,
and they're all conserved for an isolated system.
The conservation corresponds to the symmetry
of rotation about the three axes.
Suppose you want to rotate about some arbitrary axis,
incidentally,
not the x or the y or the z axis,
but the square root of 2 times
x plus square root of 2 times y.
You know,
some cattywampus angle.
You just take the axis that you want to rotate,
and you dot it as dot product into the,
you take the unit vector along
the axis you want to rotate by,
and you take the dot
product of L with that direction,
and that gives you the angular momentum,
which is the angular momentum conserved by
virtue of rotational invariance about that axis.
Okay?
The first thing I want
to do with the angular momentum,
which is an odd thing to do,
we could solve all kinds of problems,
we could study why your motorcycle flips up
in the air when you accelerate it or whatever,
but I want to do something different.
Okay?
Okay.
I want to study its Poisson brackets.
Oh,
let's write this in another form,
just remain needed some time in the future,
I don't know.
The angular momentum vector is the r
vector cross product with the p vector.
Same thing.
These are just the components of the cross product.
All right,
but before we do the Poisson brackets of angular momentum
with other components of the angular momentum,
I want to get to the Poisson brackets.
I want to get to that.
But let's just do the Poisson brackets
of the angular momentum with the coordinates x,
y,
and z.
All right?
So let's take L sub z,
let's take the Poisson bracket,
we're just still exploring now,
think of this in the spirit of exploration
of what the hell Poisson was talking about.
All right,
so let's take the Poisson bracket,
let's take the Poisson bracket of x with L z.
Let's begin with that.
And we'll also do y with L z and
also z with L z and see what we get.
All right,
so what is that Poisson bracket of x?
Now x is one of the q's.
x with L sub z,
which is x p y minus y p x.
It does.
Is there any contribution from
anything on the right hand side?
x with x,
that doesn't give you a Poisson bracket,
and the x with p y
don't give you a Poisson bracket.
Only q's with the same index,
give you a Poisson bracket with the corresponding p.
So x
x does not have a Poisson bracket with p sub
y and it does not have a Poisson bracket with x
It does have it does it
have a Poisson bracket with y?
No
But does it have a Poisson bracket with px?
The answer is yes
So here's where we get the non-zero contribution from
And what is it?
It's minus y times the
Poisson bracket of x with px
Which is?
You're right,
minus
Minus from here,
not from the Poisson bracket
So we get minus y
Anything interesting about that?
Yeah
That minus y is the same minus y as here
We'll see how it turns out
We'll get to that related in a moment
We'll recognize a set of equations which will be interesting
Which will make an interpretation for this
So x with L sub
z is equal to minus y
How about y with L sub z?
Okay,
so
Alright,
let's do this
Let's write it out
Equals y with,
same thing,
xpy minus ypx
Again,
which term contributes?
When we have x over here,
it was the last term which contributed
Now it's this term
Poisson bracket of y with p sub y is 1
Poisson bracket of y with p sub x is 0
So it's only this here
And that's just equal to x
That's x times the Poisson bracket of y with py,
but that's 1
So it's just x
Alright,
let's write that,
x
Oh,
I left out an equation here if I
want to think about this in three dimensions
What about delta z?
When I rotate about the z axis,
what happens to z?
Nothing
It just stays the same
If you rotate about the z axis,
z doesn't change
So this is 0
Oops,
equals
Alright,
let's calculate finally
z
z with L sub z
Okay,
same,
I erased,
I kept erasing it,
I shouldn't keep erasing it,
but nevertheless
z with L z
L z has nothing that involves a z in it
Or a p z
It has x,
y,
px,
py,
but nothing that has a Poisson bracket with z itself
So the answer is 0
It is not an accident that
you get the same expressions here
Everything gets multiplied by epsilon,
but
But apart from the factor of epsilon,
what we found is that taking the Poisson bracket of
With respect to L x gives you the small
change in a variable when you rotate a little bit
Let's try it for the p's
What happens,
what are the changes in px,
py,
and pz when you rotate axes?
Let's write them out here
The change in px
What happens to px when you
rotate the axes a little bit?
Exactly the same structure
p is a vector
p is a vector,
and the components,
this is just a way of talking about the way
the components of a vector change when you rotate axes
It doesn't matter whether it's the position vector,
the velocity vector,
the force vector,
the momentum vector
They all do the same thing
And so the change in px is minus py
And the change in py is equal to px
And the change in pz is 0
When you rotate coordinates
Whatever the momentum is,
when you rotate it,
it changes the same exact
way that any other vector does
So let's work that out
Let's calculate the Poisson bracket of px with lz
Where does it get a contribution from?
The only thing in lz that px
has a Poisson bracket with is x
Is x itself
So it's Poisson bracket of p with lz
For lz,
it's only this term which contributes
And what do you get?
You get py
Minus py,
ah sorry
Minus py
Minus,
yeah,
minus py
Here,
let's go through it
This is Poisson bracket of px with xpy
Okay,
the py we can take out
Put it over here
And the Poisson bracket of px with x is what?
Minus 1
Minus 1 because I've got these in the wrong order
Well,
not in the wrong order,
but then
So,
yes
Minus py
Same structure as this one
Except the vector now is p
Minus py
If I did the same with py lz
I would in fact get plus px
And how about the last one?
Pz with lz
The only thing that has a
Poisson bracket with z is pz
And pz doesn't appear in lz
So that's equal to 0
So,
what we've found here is a
special case of something very general
It really is almost a definition
But,
in the Hamiltonian language it's a definition
But we've already used
You've already seen it
The Poisson bracket of something with an angular momentum
Is just a change
The small change in that something
When you make a rotation
That's much more general
Now remember,
let's go back to the Hamiltonian
Where is it?
Hamilton's equations
Alright,
we've erased Hamilton
Here it is
Here's the Hamilton's equations
Taking the Poisson bracket of something with h
Gives you the small change in that something
When you change time a little bit
Remember what the Hamiltonian was
It was the constant of time
It was a conserved quantity
That was conserved by virtue of time translation invariance
In other words,
shifting time a little bit
We'll find exactly the same kind of equation here
That taking a Poisson bracket
of something with the angular momentum
Gives you the change in the something
When you do a small rotation
Taking the Poisson bracket with the Hamiltonian
Gives you something proportional to
the change in that something
When you shift the time a little bit
Let's do another case
You see the pattern
What Poisson brackets do
Is they generate by means of Poissonating with them
With a variable
They give you the small change
Under certain symmetry operations
Let's try it out
For another context
Let's see
Where do I want to go?
I always run out of blackboards
Alright,
we'll use the top blackboard
Um
I don't
I don't know
So it sounds like maybe
we ought to try commuting things
Or commuting Poissonating them with momentum
And see what we get
Do we get the small change in quantities
When you shift?
Alright
So what is the shift we're talking about?
In this case,
let's work with P and
Q rather than P and X
Alright
A small translation or a translation is just Q
Delta Q
Is just equal to epsilon
No function in front of us is equal to Q
So if you shift Q a little bit
In the direction
Whatever direction you're talking about
Whatever direction we're talking about
Only one variable for simplicity
Delta Q is epsilon
In other words
F is equal to one
If F is equal to one,
what's the conserved quantity?
It's P times delta Q
Or P times F
And that's just P
Alright
So the conserved quantity
Conserved by virtue of translation invariance
Of the single particle is just the momentum
Let's take the momentum
Let's take the Poisson bracket
Of any function of Q
Any function of Q
With P
Well before I do that
I will ask you
What's the small change in F of Q
If you shift Q a little bit?
If you shift Q?
It's the derivative of F with respect to Q
Right
The derivative of F with respect to Q
If I make a small change in Q
Then the change in F
Is epsilon times delta Q
So that's the small change in F of Q
Is the derivative of F by dQ
So now I have a question
When you take the Poisson bracket
Of F of Q with P
Do you get the F by dQ?
That's the suggestion that's hanging in the air now
If Poissonating with respect to an L
Gives you the small change when you rotate
And Poissonating with respect to H
Gives you the small change when
you shift time a little bit
Does Poissonating with respect to P
Give you the small change in a general thing
Let's be more general now
And take an arbitrary function of Q
And ask how it changes
Or what you get when you
Take a Poisson bracket with respect to P
How do we do this?
How are we going to do this?
I haven't told you any rule
For taking an arbitrary function of Q
But let's take a specific function of Q
Let's take Q to the n
Let's take for F of Q
Q to a power n
An integer power n
And let's try this first
The question is,
is this or is this not
The derivative of F with respect to Q?
Question mark means
Doesn't mean equals,
it means is it
Is it?
Alright,
Q to the n with P
Poisson bracket of that
Well,
Q to the n
Is Q times Q times Q times Q
N times
Dot dot dot,
n times
How do we calculate this?
We use the product rule
It's going to be a Q on the outside
Times
It's a Q on the outside
Times Poisson bracket of Q to the n minus 1
Times P
Can you see what the pattern is?
How do you prove this thing?
You prove it by induction
By mathematical induction
Let us suppose
That this is
Do I have that right?
I think I have it right
Yeah,
we'll do it for
No,
I just wanted to check what I'm doing
Q with Q to the n minus 1
That's Q to the n minus 1
Times P
Okay,
so
Oh,
oh,
I know what I'm doing
Yeah,
plus
Plus
Q to the n minus 1
Poisson bracket of Q with P
I have to write the full product rule
The product rule
Involves two terms
Okay,
so what is this?
Let us assume
When we prove something by induction
We assume it for n minus 1
And we see if we get it for
For n
So what's this Poisson bracket?
By assumption
By assumption it is
N minus 1 times Q to the n minus 2
By assumption
That's the induction hypothesis
That it's n minus 1
Q to the n minus 2
But then I multiply by another Q
And so that gives me n minus 1
Times Q to the n minus 1
Did I get that right?
Q squared
N minus 2
Just from this term
The hypothesis is that
This Poisson bracket
Is the derivative of Q to the n minus 1
With respect to Q
And that is
N minus 1
Times Q to the n minus 2
And then we multiply it by another Q
And that gives us
N minus 1 to the
Q to the n minus 1
But how about
This one over here
What's Q with P?
That's 1
So we just add one more
Q to the n minus 1
This just adds one more
And we get
N times Q to the n minus 1
This is the derivative of
Q to the n with respect to Q
What do you have to do
To complete the induction
Theorem,
the induction proof
You have to check it for n equals 1
If it's true for n equals 1
And it follows for
N from n minus 1
Then you've proved it
So is it true for
N equals 1
For that case
The derivative of Q
With respect to Q
Is just 1
So it's true for n equals 1
But
So we've just
We've discovered that for functions of the form
Q to the n
That the Poisson bracket
Of F
With P
Is equal to
DF by DQ
Now what about
For sums of
Two things
Q to the n
And you know a power series
A series of terms with different powers
And different coefficients
Well for that we use
The rules of Poisson brackets
Which allow you to add things
And multiply them by constants
And so forth
And those basic rules of Poisson brackets
Will allow you to take
Sums of different powers of Q
Times coefficients
And that way you can get
Basically any function
You can approximate any function
With a arbitrary polynomial
And
So it also follows
For an arbitrary function
Just by adding them together
That's the basic theorem
About Poisson brackets
But what does it say
It says that when you
Poissonate something with the momentum
It gives you the small change
In that something
When you translate Q
So in fact
We have
At least three examples
Of the Poisson
Of conservation laws
Being connected to Poisson brackets
Well conservation laws
Sorry not conservation
Symmetries
The symmetry operation
Is defined
Or is constructed
Symmetry operation
By taking the Poisson bracket
With the quantity which is expected
To be conserved by virtue of the symmetry
Is that a mouthful
For every symmetry we have
We take that thing
Which is conserved
And we take its Poisson brackets
With things and that gives us
The small change
Or in other words it tells us
What the transformation is
If I didn't know
What the transformation was
Associated with
The angular momentum
If I didn't know what the transformation was
The symmetry that was associated
With angular momentum
All I have to do is take the Poisson bracket
Of all the things in the theory
And that will tell me what the small changes are
That's the idea
That
That's the connection
So far we haven't talked about conservation
We've talked about symmetries
And how they're generated
The language is
That L sub Z
Is the generator of rotations
About the Z axis
It generates rotations about the Z axis
Or infinitesimal ones
By Poisson bracketing
Same thing for all the things in the theory
The generator of translations
Is momentum
The generator of time translations
Is the Hamiltonian
And to compute how something changes
Under a small shift of whatever it is you're doing
You take the Poisson bracket
Okay now let's
Before we study more
Let's look at
About angular momentum
Alright we're going to come back to angular momentum
In a minute
But just one observation
What is the connection
Between
Symmetries
And conservation laws
I've talked about connection between symmetries
And Poisson brackets
But now what's the connection with conservation laws
Can we see that through the method of Poisson brackets
Can I ask a question about
So what I take away from this is
That when you've got your
I mean maybe this is what you just said
When you have your conserved quantity
And you've got your various
So far we haven't discussed conservation laws
In this Poisson bracket framework
But you've got some conserved quantity
Then from
This computation
You can determine what the motion is
That provides for that conservation
No you can provide
You can say motion
In the sense of real motion
But
No no no no
You're finding what
Symmetry operation corresponds
That conservation law
For example
By using L sub z
You find out that
L sub z is conserved
As a consequence
Of invariance under
Rotation
That doesn't tell you that things move
In a rotational spiral
They move in straight lines for all you know
Or some other way
But what you're saying is
If you take as a given
Your L's
And you don't even know
How you have that
Those are sort of
Infinite equations of motion
No they're not equations of motion
They are
Symmetry transformations
The connection with
Equations of motion
Is if you use the Hamiltonian here
Okay
If you use the Hamiltonian
It's equations of motion
Otherwise it's just telling you some operation
It's telling you there is some
If L sub z is conserved
You should have in the back of your mind
Okay there must be some operation
Which is a symmetry
Let's find out what that operation is
Here's what the symmetry is
And you conclude
That it's rotation symmetry
That's not the same as saying
You know what the Hamiltonian is
Which is the thing which tells you
How things move
Okay now we come to the Hamiltonian
Let's give a name
To these various generators
L z
For rotation
P for translation
H for time translation
Let's call them generators
And call them g
All of them are generators
All of them are g
g for generators
They are functions of p's and q's
Everything in phase space is
a function of p and q
Alright
g generates some symmetry
Let's start with g being conserved
What does it say that g is conserved
Well
It says that the time derivative is zero
And the time derivative of it
Is the Poisson bracket of g with h
So if you have a time derivative
The Poisson bracket with anything with h
Is the time derivative of it
So if g is conserved
It says the Poisson bracket of g with h
Is equal to zero
That's one way to read this equation
It says that g is conserved
But let's turn the equation around
Let's turn it around
And have it write
That h Poisson bracket with g
Is equal to zero
Same equation
Except for a minus sign
But zero doesn't care about a minus sign
And what does this equation say
This equation says
That when you do the small transformation
Associated with g
h doesn't change
The top equation said
That g didn't change
As the system evolves
The bottom equation says
That h doesn't change
When you do a transformation
In other words
If
,
g was l sub z
It says that h doesn't change
When you rotate the system
If g was
Translation
That would mean just
P here
The conservation of momentum
Would also say that h doesn't change
When you translate the system
What does it mean to say that h doesn't change
When you rotate a system
Or you translate a system
it says that the Hamiltonian,
the structure of the Hamiltonian,
or the value of the Hamiltonian,
that every point in phase space
doesn't change if you rotate it coordinates,
that's saying there's a symmetry.
So on the one hand,
read this way,
the same equation says that G is conserved,
that same equation says that H doesn't change
under an operation which is generated by G.
For example,
if G was the angular momentum,
it would say that H doesn't
change when you rotate the coordinate frame.
In Hamiltonian or in Poisson bracket language,
this is the expression,
as I said,
I'll just emphasize it once more,
is the connection between conservation laws,
this,
and symmetries,
this.
So it's quite a beautiful packaging.
Of that connection.
Yes?
Does this mean that if you know what's conserved,
you can always figure out what the symmetry was?
That's what it means.
Just by taking...
Yes?
If you know something's conserved,
G.
And you want to figure out what the transformation is,
just Poisson bracket everything in sight with G,
and it will tell you how it transforms.
That's exactly what it says.
Any other questions?
So you see this,
it was not just a little game of defining something.
So that Mr.
Poisson could avoid writing down a complicated expression,
the thing has real power.
You've given us some examples of this.
Is there a general way to
write that statement that you just said?
Yeah.
That's saying that they're conserved.
I'm just saying...
No,
this is the conserved.
The G is conserved.
Okay.
This says that the Hamiltonian doesn't change when you do...
When you do a G transformation.
Right.
One says the fact that the
Hamiltonian doesn't change says there's a symmetry.
The fact that G doesn't change
with time says there's a conservation law.
This is the thing which is conserved,
but it's also the thing which generates a symmetry.
ありがとうございました
I'm looking over there where you're basically
taking a fossil and bribing it with the various pieces,
and then you're getting the same thing you get above.
And in that example,
and I'm looking
for the general statement of that,
that thing doesn't seem to say anything about conservation.
No,
it doesn't.
And that's what I'm asking.
Without bringing in conservation,
is there a general way to state that?
Yeah,
but at this level,
it's really a bit of a definition.
It's a bit of a definition.
The definition is given a quantity,
here is a transformation rule.
This transformation rule here.
And it doesn't say it's a symmetry.
It just says that with
every quantity that you can write
down,
every q,
whatever it was called,
or every g.
Sorry,
we're calling it g.
For every g that we write down,
we
can define an infinitesimal transformation.
That's all this says.
If that g is conserved,
it says this.
But if we write that around the other way,
it says that h doesn't change
when we do a g transformation.
So it relates conservation to symmetry.
Same equation.
OK.
Of course,
we could have done the
same thing with ly and lx
and discovered rotations about the other axes.
Now,
it's kind of interesting to
ask what happens when you take
Poisson brackets of components of the angular momentum
with other components of the angular momentum.
I don't know if you find it interesting,
but I think you will find it interesting.
By the time we're finished doing it and using it,
we will see real power
in solving problems by our power.
What does it mean?
It means that we find a nice
way to do a problem where we don't
have to go back to drag ourselves back
through the definition of angular momentum,
through the fact that the angular momentum is made up
out of lots of little particles.
But we just use some basic structures like this.
OK.
So let's ask now,
what is the Poisson bracket
of one component of the angular momentum with another?
Let's just fill out a set of ideas,
concentrate on angular momentum.
We don't need this anymore.
And in particular,
let's start with Poisson bracket of lx.
So we have x with lz.
I can guess what the answer is going to be.
Well,
I won't guess.
We'll write them out.
We'll write out the whole bloody thing and compute it.
And then I'll tell you what my guess would
have been after we compute it.
All right.
So lx is ypz minus zpy.
And lz,
I believe,
is xpy minus ypx.
Is that right?
Yes.
OK.
Now the question is,
what can give us a non-zero answer?
Let's begin.
Well,
let's take them one at a time.
How about this with this?
Yes.
pz and x,
nothing.
But y with py,
what is that?
So what you're going to wind up getting,
if you just use the rules,
is y with py is 1.
And the rest of the expression is pz times x.
So we'll first of all get pz times x.
That's coming from combining the y with the py here.
How about this one here?
The?
Well,
first let's go through them all together.
ypz with ypx,
does that give anything?
y,
you get nothing with y.
you get nothing with px.
And pz,
nothing with y and px.
Nothing.
Nothing there.
zpy with xpy,
nothing.
But the last term gives you plus.
Here we have py.
py with y.
So that gives us z times px.
And is it plus z times
px or minus z times px?
The last?
It's minus.
It's minus because when you
take the Poisson bracket of py
with y,
you get one more minus sign.
There's two minus signs here and then one more
because py with y is minus 1.
So altogether you get this.
And what is that?
Let's see.
That's lx with lz.
Is it plus or minus ly?
Minus ly.
So this is minus ly.
Now,
what would I have guessed?
I would have guessed minus ly,
but for entirely different
reasons.
l is a vector.
Whenever you have a vector,
you have a vector.
Whenever you Poissonate anything,
any component of a vector,
x,
y,
or z,
with lz,
you get minus
the y component.
Whenever you take the x component of
any vector and Poissonate it with lz,
you get minus the
corresponding component.
Same rule.
Lx with lz gives you minus ly.
Okay.
I'm going to,
let's see.
Ly with l.
Yeah.
We can find all the other ones by cycling,
x to y to z.
Okay.
So we have,
you know what I'm going to do first though?
I'm going to change the order.
I want to get rid of the minus sign.
The reason I want to get rid of the
minus sign is because I happen to remember it one
way.
Lz with lx.
Let's change the sign.
And what will that do?
That just takes the minus sign away.
All right.
The next one,
z goes to x,
x goes to y,
and y goes to z.
And lz,
x,
y,
z,
x.
All right.
I usually remember this in the form.
I remember the first one.
Okay.
So I do the first one.
Lx,
ly is equal to lz,
x,
y,
z,
and then I cycle them through.
Okay.
These are the basic Poisson brackets
between components of the angular momentum.
For those who know a little bit about quantum mechanics,
you'll recognize these equations
as the classical Poisson bracket analog
of the commutation relations of angular momentum.
But that's,
as I said,
we're not doing quantum mechanics,
but I'll just remind you.
Okay.
Just update this to be clear enough for us.
All right.
So if the order g is omega 1,
omega u0c2 over r cancels the room and
A tends to the room,
it leads to r2,
and then that away...
So it starts with r2,
but...
Yeah.
I'll do it instead of it.
Okay.
I have a less than one class on gradually increasing.
Yeah.
And then I will work out for you the rigid body
equations of motion for a torque-free rigid body moving in space.
I'm not going to study them in any detail.
I just want to show
you the power of Poisson brackets.
All right,
so we have a gyroscope.
And a gyroscope now means a
center where something is anchored to,
an axle,
and a wheel.
And the thing about the gyroscope is the flywheel is rotating so fast that the
only angular momentum that you have to worry about is the angular momentum about the axle.
Now,
the flywheel may move a little bit,
in which case there would
be other components of angular momentum.
But we'll assume that it's not.
We'll assume that they're much,
much smaller than the angular momentum about the axle,
about the direction of the axle.
So the angular momentum,
then,
is along the radial direction.
Here's the center of the wheel,
of the flywheel.
And the angular momentum,
by assumption,
is along that axis.
Okay.
What is the Hamiltonian of it?
Well,
it does have some energy by
virtue of the rotation around that axis.
And it's a large energy.
It's a large energy.
But I am going...
All right,
let's take it into account.
We'll take it into account.
What is it proportional to?
It's proportional to the square of
the angular momentum about that axis.
In fact,
it's proportional to the square
of the total angular momentum,
since we don't have to worry about
any angular momentum except the contribution around there.
Remember,
this thing is going to
be a little bit more complicated.
It's going to rotate,
or do whatever it does.
I don't know whether it'll rotate this way.
It's going to rotate somehow,
or move somehow.
But the magnitude of the
angular momentum doesn't change much.
So we'll assume that.
The magnitude of the angular momentum doesn't change.
It just changes direction.
What is the energy?
Well,
first of all,
there is a contribution,
which is just the square of the angular momentum.
Let's write that down.
S squared plus Ly squared plus Lz squared.
Just in other words,
the total spin angular momentum of the wheel sums
of the squares of the components of angular momentum.
And it has some coefficient in front of it.
What would you put for the coefficient?
I would put the moment of inertia divided by 2.
Number.
I over 2.
Everybody know what a moment of inertia is?
I have it wrong,
don't I?
What do I have wrong?
Yeah,
it's 1 over I.
Moment of inertia of the wheel.
And if you don't know
what a moment of inertia is,
it's just a number.
It's of course made up out of a
mass and a distribution of masses and so forth.
But it's just a number for everybody.
Not for everybody in the room.
For everybody.
It's a number.
So that's it.
That's the energy just by virtue
of the fact that it's rotating.
Let's take that alone.
I'm going to add another contribution.
The other contribution is going to be the potential energy.
Because we're going to assume the
whole thing is in a gravitational field.
But we'll take that into account in a moment.
But let's ignore it to begin with.
No gravity.
It's just in free space.
That means no torque on the...
Nothing pulling it down.
No torque.
It's just spinning about that axis.
I will tell you right now.
The angular momentum is conserved.
If there's no torque on this gyroscope,
it just will continue to point in the same direction.
But let's prove it.
Let's see what happens.
Let's calculate the time derivative
of any component.
I'll take the x component
of angular momentum.
And let's show that it's zero.
Alright.
Here's all we have to do.
We take the Poisson bracket
of Lx
with
1 over 2i
Lx squared
plus Ly squared
plus Lz squared.
What's the Poisson bracket
of Lx with Lx squared?
Did I tell you among these rules
is a rule
that says the Poisson bracket of
anything with itself is zero?
That's obvious.
Of course that's true.
Yeah.
Anything with itself is zero because it's anti-symmetric.
Okay.
Alright.
What about the Poisson bracket
of Lx with Lx squared?
That's zero because
it's going to have,
you know,
always you're going to be looking for
an Lx with Lx and that's zero.
So,
first condition,
you can throw this one away.
Now,
what about Lx with Ly squared?
What does that give?
Lx
with Ly squared,
you use the product rule.
It's Ly times Ly.
So it's twice Ly
times the Poisson bracket of
Lx with Ly.
Twice Ly
that gets rid of a 2 down here.
Alright.
And then Ly
Ly times
the Poisson bracket of Lx
with Ly.
That's equal to Lz.
Alright.
Lx with Ly
gives an Lz,
but there's an extra power of Ly
on the outside,
so it's Ly
times Lz.
What about Lx
Can you read that?
I'm going to rewrite it.
1 over I
L
L...
I've forgotten what it was.
right?
But now we have to do Lx with Lz squared.
For that,
we're going to have an Lz again.
And we're going to have
the Poisson bracket of Lx with Lz,
which is what?
I hope it's minus Ly.
I'm going to assume it's minus Ly.
And these cancel.
So the time derivative
of Lx
is zero.
A broader lesson is that
L commutes
commutes
has zero Poisson bracket
with the sums of the squares
of the angular momentum.
Lx squared plus Ly squared plus Lz squared
gives nothing
when you Poisson
bracket with one of the components
of angular momentum.
And of course the same exact thing
would be true for Ly and Lz.
All of the components of angular momentum
are conserved.
Good.
We knew that to begin with.
All the components of angular momentum are conserved.
But what happens now if
we impose a torque on this?
We impose a torque by pulling down
with some force
on here.
Then there's some potential
energy.
And the potential energy
let's forget torque,
let's just think about
Mg.
Let's think of the flywheel,
the center of the flywheel
is at this point over here.
The flywheel has mass M
and it has a gravitational
potential energy
Mg times
the height.
The mass of the thing times
acceleration due to gravity
times the height.
That's the potential energy
due to gravity.
And what is the height?
The height of this is going to be
proportional
to the
to the z component
of the angular momentum.
Why is it proportional
to the z component of the angular momentum?
It's proportional to the z component
of the angular momentum because the angular
momentum vector
is along the same axis as the radial
vector.
As you change the direction here
the angular momentum
also changes
and the height of this thing
changes exactly the same way as
the z component of the angular momentum
changes.
When it's down
at the bottom
the z component of angular momentum
is maximum and negative.
As it comes up
the z component of the angular momentum goes to
zero when it's horizontal
and changes sign
when it's above.
So the potential energy
is proportional to minus
the z component of the angular momentum.
Minus because the force is downward.
So I don't
there's some coefficient
some number
the potential energy
let's just call it v
is going to be proportional to minus
some constant
made up out of
the mass and
the little g
and whatever else we have to worry about
some constant
times
lz
again
when lz is big and positive
that means it's pointing upward
then the potential energy is large
when lz is down
then
the potential energy
is negative
and it changes the same way
as the height changes
Alright so we now know
something else.
We now know that there's another
contribution in the energy
which is proportional
to some constant
now it's not the moment
of inertia,
it's just some
constant minus c
times lz
Excuse me
lz is the
axis of rotation
Sorry,
l,
yeah
No,
z is not the axis of rotation
The axis of rotation is the radial direction
So z points out of the board
No,
it's down
Down
Sorry
The torque,
if I understand right,
the torque
here is
Don't worry about torque,
let's just calculate the potential energy
No,
but I mean that's why we have
the potential energy
Yeah,
but the torque,
the force is down
and the torque is into the board
The force is down,
the torque is into the board
but I've never heard of torque
Shouldn't you put a rest for it,
like a base
for it,
if you're,
for that
point which is resting on a surface
Is this axle a real axle?
It's attached to this point,
Olivia
Oh,
it's attached to that point
But doesn't that imply that the
other end of it is not
moving or not?
No,
no,
I'm sorry
It's a gyroscope,
it's free to
do whatever it wants
Only this length here is fixed
There's a vector here
and that vector is the position vector
of the center of this thing
Thank you
There's no real axle there
It's empty space axle
It's a real axle
Maybe if you label that axle L
L vector
Let's label it
Alright,
you want to label it L vector?
Good
Fine
Yeah,
the axle is along the L axis
Alright,
let's go back a step
In fact,
I'm not going to call this vector L
I'm going to call this the R vector
The position vector
of the center of the wheel
So this is R
That's the R vector
The assumption is that the angular momentum
is along the R vector
So
What is the angular momentum?
The angular momentum
The vector angular momentum
is some number
which is just the spin
the angular momentum of a
it's just some number
whatever it is,
we could call it L
and that's a number
times the unit vector
along this direction
or just R,
just forget unit vector
R
some number
I don't know what to call it
Let's call it L
some number times R
All this says is that the angular momentum
is constrained to be along this radial direction
along this
along the direction of the position of this point here
As it moves
the wheel moves with it
and the angular momentum stays aligned
with the axle
That's what this says
Now
Given this,
and this is just a number
whatever number of units of angular momentum
the thing has
Then it follows that L sub z
is just the same number
times z
times the coordinate position
of this point
x,
y,
z,
the coordinate position of the center of the wheel
Is little l a constant?
Yeah,
little l is assumed to be a constant
It doesn't vary with time
And that will be true
That will be true
if the angular momentum is very large
Yeah
We're postulating that despite
introducing the force of gravity
L will still largely be along this
That's right,
we're postulating that
We can prove that with a little more effort
But
But we'll just assume that
That the spin angular momentum
or the spin around that direction
doesn't change much
And it doesn't
As long as it's large
As long as it's much larger than
any other angular momentum in the problem
In other words,
if you really spin that thing up
That angular momentum about that axis
won't change much
Okay,
so let's assume that
Then all of the components of angular momentum
are proportional to all of the components
of the position vector here
But what is the position vector
Um
Not what is the position vector
But the
Potential energy
Is proportional to z
The potential energy
Is mg times z
Z is the height
This is the z axis here
Okay
Vertical axis I've taken to be z
Alright,
so the potential energy
Is proportional to the height of this thing
And therefore is proportional to Lz
That's all,
just proportional to Lz
With some constant
Some constant
I've called the constant
C
Y minus
Because the force is down
Uh
The zero point of z
Is where r
The n point of r
Right
Do I have
Is plus,
maybe it's plus c
Hold on,
did I get that wrong
Um,
it's plus L sub g
Yeah,
when you raise it
It gets positive energy
Yeah,
yeah,
yeah
It's plus L sub g
The higher it is the more potential energy
So the origin of the coordinate system
Where you're talking about x,
y,
and z is
Right there,
okay,
so
Z is the distance from
Yeah,
yeah,
z,
that's right
z is just,
I don't think I explained this well
But,
yes,
z is
This height
Yeah,
I'm sorry,
I did a poor job of that
And it's proportional to Lz
Because L and r
Are proportional
To each other
Alright,
so now we can calculate the equation
We can calculate what the components of L do
Uh,
let's
Let's start with Lz
Lz dot
That's just the Poisson bracket of Lz with Lz
That's zero
So the first thing we find out
Is that the vertical component
of angular momentum doesn't change
That means that this angle here doesn't change
It stays at the same angle
If it's spinning really fast
That will be true
That angle,
the angle relative to the vertical
Will be unchanged
But let's see what else happens
How about L sub x dot
L sub x dot
That's equal to the Poisson bracket of Lx with Clz
And what is that?
Uh,
that's
C times
Minus C times Ly
Did I get that right?
Okay,
so this is
I'm getting tired
I'm going to figure it out this time
Minus Cly
And how about Ly dot
Alright,
so Ly dot
We would put Ly here
And the Poisson bracket of Ly with Lz
This is a C here
I'm sorry
I'm really getting tired now
Minus C times Ly
And this one will be plus C
Times Lx
Alright,
so let's bring it over here
Lz dot
Equals zero
Lx dot
Is equal to C times Ly
Minus C
Minus C times Ly
And Ly dot
Is equal to plus C
Times Lx
So that's the
GL
Now we have to add in
Twouras
And we have to use
One
And we're on
Of this
And we just give it a name
Watch this
Look at this
Mind you
of the angular momentum along the xy plane,
it's processing around here with
an angular velocity that's z,
that's c,
that's c.
That's what's going on.
Yes,
and I think it's processing
in this case in a counterclockwise,
I may have
lost track of a sign somewhere,
I think I got it right,
but it's processing about
the z-axis and doing that sort of thing.
So that's the gyroscope as a thought
about from Poisson brackets.
I think I'm off at the
end of my line for tonight.
I
was going to work out the
Euler equations for a rotating body,
but the
message is...
Just to clarify,
I thought in order to
have precession you had to have a gravity
with part on it where it rests like...
Where is the...
This is the gravitational potential energy.
Okay,
okay.
This is the
gravitational potential energy,
right?
That is the gravitational energy and
that's the torque,
that's the source of the torque on the...
Right,
right.
But once
you know this,
you know exactly the same thing
would be true for any angular
momentum,
whatever it came from.
It's not just a matter of the angular momentum,
it's the source of the torque.
It doesn't...
Whatever the source of the angular momentum,
it might be a
zillion electrons spins all lined up.
It'll do exactly the same thing if a
torque is...
So this is quite general and...
This is equilibrium?
Well,
it's not...
It wouldn't be called officially
equilibrium,
but you could call it a steady-state motion,
you know,
or a
stationary motion.
Yes,
that's right.
If you give it a kickdown,
it'll oscillate around here,
but that
oscillation and it's not much of
an oscillation if it's really spinning fast,
that oscillation will go together with
small changes in the spin angular
momentum around here.
Am I right in saying that depending on
whether this thing is rotating clockwise or counterclockwise,
it will be minus c
or plus c or plus v?
Yeah,
you're right.
You're right.
And my intention here was not to teach about gyroscopes,
but to show you how Poisson brackets can be used very
quickly and efficiently to work out equations of motion for things.
And here we're not even working out the equation of
motion for angles or Euler angles or positions or anything else.
We jump directly to the angular momentum components and...
So...
Yeah?
What?
What is confusing to me,
and maybe it's past,
or I don't know...
It's confusing.
...is whether or not you have physical things associated.
You mentioned the axle or no axle in...
Yeah,
there could be an axle there.
but what I'm saying is it's also
true if there is no axle there.
Well,
if there's no axle,
it'll just fall down on the ground.
Well,
a wheel rolling,
what about a wheel rolling like a wheel?
It will maintain its full fall over.
In other words,
it's a physical thing.
But you're saying that it has to be supported somewhere,
whether it's...
Yeah,
the assumption is that the distance
between here and here is fixed.
In other words,
yeah,
that the distance...
I assume the distance between here and here was fixed.
Some ways in that derivation,
we assume that the distance
between here and here is fixed.
For example,
if it weren't fixed,
supposing the wheel could move this way,
then it would not be true that the component of
the angular momentum would be proportional to the z height.
It's only because it's fixed,
and this is a fixed length,
that as it rotates,
the angular momentum rotates
rigidly with the position vector.
Yeah.
Did you split the Hamiltonian,
or did you neglect the energy to
the angular rotation because it was so hard?
Right,
so we should add this to c times Lz,
right?
Yeah.
Or minus,
I don't know.
We should add that.
But we've already shown that the Poisson bracket of the components of
the angular momentum with respect to the sums of the squares is zero.
So that doesn't contribute anything.
Right,
that's a good point.
That implicitly,
I did have in my mind to add these two.
Right.
But when you take the Poisson bracket of the components
of the angular momentum with the sums of the squares,
you don't get anything.
It all comes from here.
And we see the precession.
This is exactly the same precession as the precession of an
electron spin or an electron magnetic moment in a magnetic field.
The magnetic field plays the
same role as a gravitational field.
It tries to pull the spin down that way,
and instead the spin precesses.
Or it doesn't have to be an electron spin.
It could be a nuclear spin,
in which case you get a precession
that's sort of the basis for NMR,
for nuclear magnetic resonance.
Or a planet around the sun.
What's that?
A planet around the sun.
Or three around the sun.
Well,
that's a different thing.
That is a different thing.
That's a different thing.
It's also called precession.
I think that's the only real connection between them.
But this is precession of angular momentum.
It's angular momentum due to a torque.
It could be a magnetic
field pulling down on the spin.
It could be the gravitational
field pulling down on the flywheel.
The net result is precession about the axis.
Yeah?
So this is exactly the same as a top,
except that you would have
drawn your vector maybe going upwards.
Yeah.
Mm-hmm.
Oh,
yes,
yes.
Right.
You call it a gyroscope if
it's sticking out to the side.
If it's almost vertically upward,
you call it a top.
Right.
Exactly so.
Yeah.
So if an electron in a nuclear particle,
there's not like a point that's fixed.
It's just the whole,
it's around the center of the atom is fixed?
Around the center of mass of the electron.
Yeah.
I'm sorry I mentioned that.
All right.
Yeah.
We don't want to give away
the punchline from quantum mechanics here.
Okay.
If there are no other questions,
we're finished for tonight.
For more,
please visit us at stanford.edu.