This program is brought to you by Stanford University.
All right,
let's start by talking about the
universe as it appears at different distances
from us,
and a couple of ways of thinking about it.
Different distances also means different times.
Here's a way to think about it.
First of all,
put ourselves at the center,
and then we can draw the surfaces
around us at different distances,
literally now I mean distances,
perhaps
measured in meters,
and we can ask what we see.
As long as we don't leave
look too far,
then the fact that we're looking
backward in time is not very
important and doesn't change things very much.
The universe a hundred years ago was
not very different than it is today.
The universe a year ago or,
you know,
whatever,
it's very little different.
So you have to go out an appreciable distance before
you discover the universe is aging or
that it is getting younger as you look
out.
And of course as it gets younger it gets denser,
meaning to say that early on
the universe was denser.
As it gets denser it tends to get hotter.
If you
look out sufficiently far to the point
where the universe was or where the
universe appears to have the same density as the universe,
then you have to go out
and then see that the universe has been
about as hot as the surface of the sun.
Of course it doesn't look to us when we
actually look up in the sky that it looks
like the surface of the sun.
And that's because of the red shift that all the
photons coming from that place where the
universe was as hot as the sun,
in the
process of being transported to us,
those photons are red-shifting
and they're going to get hotter and hotter.
And you can see that the
universe is a little bit more hot.
and they're redshifted by roughly about a factor of 1,000,
that effectively means that the temperature
that we would see in the sky
is about 1,000 times lower,
or it appears to be about 1,000 times lower
than the actual temperature
where those photons were being emitted from.
But if we forget about that redshift
and we just fold in the redshift into our calculations,
and ask how hot the universe was at various places,
then there's some place where it becomes as hot,
just about as hot as the surface of the sun.
That's the place where the universe became opaque.
It became opaque because the atoms,
particularly the hydrogen atoms,
the universe was mainly made out of hydrogen
and a bit of helium.
The hydrogen atoms,
the hydrogen was ionized at temperatures
higher than about 1,000,
well,
about a few thousand degrees.
And so out beyond some place,
there are not atoms but ions,
and ions consist of nuclei,
which basically means protons and electrons.
So there's lots of protons around
and lots of electrons.
I'll draw the electrons as crosses,
and they're freely moving around.
They're not bound to each other.
Even if they accidentally got bound to each other,
the high temperatures out there would cause collisions,
the collisions being energy,
collisions between atoms.
And also another thing which is out there is photons.
Those photons are all around us,
but when we go backward in time,
those photons have shorter wavelength,
and the shorter wavelength means
that they're much more energetic,
so what's going on out in the surface out here
is it's full of high energy,
not very high energy photons,
but X-rays basically.
X-rays,
X-ray photons,
and there are more X-ray photons.
In fact,
most of the particles out there
are these X-ray photons.
By a factor of about
10 to the eighth or something like that,
most of the particles out there are photons.
That's also true today.
Most of the particles in the universe are photons,
but the photons are so low energy today
that they're not a significant part
of the energy of the universe,
but at that time,
they were a significant part
of the energy of the universe,
so it's also full of photons,
and if by accident an atom happened to form,
you know,
an electron happened to get trapped,
very shortly it would become,
it would collide with a photon
and get reionized,
and so what's out there is mostly ionized gas,
and ionized gas,
the one thing that it's not is transparent.
Ionized gas is an electrical conductor.
Electrical conductors respond to electric fields
by sloshing back and forth
and re-emit radiation,
and basically they're opaque,
so out beyond some distance here
the universe is opaque,
it's opaque to us,
and so we can't see anything
behind that surface of last scattering.
The surface of last scattering is a
place like the surface of the sun
where you go from opaque to transparent,
and it happens reasonably suddenly,
reasonably suddenly,
basically when the temperature cools down
below the ionization temperature of hydrogen,
the universe becomes pretty clear
and we can see through it.
There's some region here which is hard to see,
and then inside it we begin
to see galaxies and so forth.
I want to go back a little bit further,
and of course going back
and further is a bit conjectural,
and it's conjectural,
but we can guess what it's like
on the basis of known laws of physics.
Laws of physics here that
we're talking about are atomic physics.
We know all about atomic physics.
We know a great deal more than just atomic physics.
We know nuclear physics.
We know particle physics.
We can go a fairly long way out.
I don't mean long in distance necessarily,
although it is long in distance,
but to higher temperatures,
and pretty well guess what was out there.
So let's talk about what was out there.
Incidentally,
the particles in here,
in addition to the photons,
are mainly protons and electrons.
Now,
protons mean the nuclei of hydrogen.
There's also some helium nuclei,
alpha particles,
and a few,
deuterons,
which are an isotope of helium,
but basically just very simple elements like
hydrogen and a little bit of helium.
As far as nuclei,
electrons freely moving around.
Now,
no antiprotons,
no positrons,
or practically no antiprotons,
practically no positrons,
just ordinary matter,
pretty much.
Ordinary matter except ionized.
Now,
as we go out,
we eventually come to a temperature
which is high enough
that when two photons collide,
two photons collide.
There's the wiggly lines represent photons.
The two photons collide.
Normally,
you think of photons as not things which collide,
you think of ordinary light,
light just passes through light,
but high energy photons do collide with each other,
and basically what happens
is they create electron-positron pairs.
What comes out of here
could be two photons again.
In fact,
the photons might not even collide,
they might just go right through each other,
but with some probability,
a probability of about one in 10,000
or something like that,
these photons can create an electron.
Let's call it E minus.
The minus stands for the fact
that the electron has negative charge,
and a positron,
which means the antiparticle of an electron.
A positron,
which we call E plus.
Positrons and electrons are very,
very similar to each other.
They are practically identical with one exception.
They have opposite charge.
They have the same mass,
exactly the same mass,
and properties which are almost
direct reflections of each other.
For example,
if you take two positrons,
they will behave exactly the same
way as two electrons would behave,
except with electrons being replaced
by positrons and so forth.
Almost exactly,
not quite.
So if you go back far enough,
now,
this will not happen with ordinary light,
the light in this room,
or the colliding light between the two bulbs up there.
The reason is that the photons don't have enough energy.
The energy of these two electrons,
even if the electrons were standing absolutely still,
if they had no motion at all,
the energy would be twice,
two because there are two of them,
times the mass of the electron,
times the speed of light squared.
Now,
that's a significant amount of energy.
It's a lot more energy than photons,
for example,
from the sun.
Two photons from the sun have energies much,
much less than that,
thousands and thousands of times less than that.
So two photons colliding,
for example,
from two different stars,
will not have nearly enough energy to do that,
but as the temperature goes up,
as the universe gets more and more dense,
going backward in time,
the photons become shorter and shorter wavelength,
and eventually,
out somewheres,
or at some very early time,
the universe was hot enough that photons,
when they collide,
make electron-positron pairs.
Electron-positrons can collide with
each other and make photons.
Exactly the inverse reaction can happen.
If you were to take a
pot of material at that temperature,
you would have reactions similar to chemical reactions,
except the chemicals now would be replaced by particles,
and the chem-nature of the chemical reactions would be
photon pairs become electron-positron pairs,
electron-positron pairs can collide.
In fact,
this positron over here can collide
with some other electron over here,
make more photons,
and eventually,
if the pot is allowed to just
sit there for a long enough time,
it will come to a thermal equilibrium.
And in that thermal equilibrium,
there will be a certain ratio
of photons to electrons and positrons.
The number of electrons and positrons,
you would think,
if we really,
really started
with no electrons and positrons to begin with,
now that's of course not accurate,
there are electrons in our universe,
but in fact the electrons are very,
very dilute compared with the photons.
There's approximately 10 to the 9th
photons in the universe for every electron,
so let's ignore the electrons
which are there to begin with,
but as we go backward,
electrons get manufactured by this pair production process,
and so that in the early universe,
the only way they can be manufactured in this way
is to manufacture both a positron
and an electron at the same time,
so apart from this little bit of
excess of electrons that's presently here now,
as we go backward,
we come to a time when the
universe had equal amounts of electrons and positrons,
or almost equal amounts of electrons and positrons,
at some temperature.
At first,
first means at temperatures which are not too high,
there will be more photons than electrons,
and so we'll have electrons and positrons.
Why is that?
Well,
if we lower the temperature down below
where the photons have enough energy for this,
there won't be any electrons and positrons.
So it stands to reason if
we raise the temperature a little bit,
just above the threshold for
making a few electrons and positrons,
there will be mostly photons
with a few electrons and positrons.
But as the temperature heats up,
and what this has to do with
is the fact that the photons,
the electrons have mass and the photons don't.
Photons have no mass,
electrons have mass,
electrons have some internal energy due to their mass,
photons don't.
But as you heat it up higher and higher,
the kinetic energy of the electrons becomes much,
much larger than their mc2 energy,
and the mc2 is not important.
So eventually when the temperature
gets much above the threshold
for creating electron-positron,
electron-positron pairs,
electrons and positrons,
their mass is not important,
the photons have no mass,
electrons,
positrons,
and photons become energetically very similar to each other,
and all of a sudden,
not all of a sudden,
but at that point,
the number of electrons and positrons,
the density of them,
is about the same as the number of photons,
roughly speaking,
electrons,
photons,
and positrons all have the same density,
and they're all colliding around like mad.
This is a very,
very dense soup of charged particles.
But what about the protons?
The protons are still present.
Incidentally,
they are rather dense by now.
Millions of times more.
They're sometimes denser than they are in this room.
They're very dense,
the protons,
but there is not yet enough thermal energy
to be able to create protons and antiprotons,
for either photons to collide
and create protons and antiprotons,
or electrons and positrons to collide.
Why not?
Well,
it's because the energy of a proton
is m proton c squared,
and that's about 2,000 times larger
than the energy of the mass of an electron.
The mass of a proton is
about 2,000 times larger than an electron.
If you wanted to create a proton and an antiproton,
you would need at least that much energy.
So,
as you go back,
the universe contracts
in the sense of going backward in time.
The universe contracts,
gets hotter and hotter and hotter,
and eventually it rises to the threshold
where it becomes hot enough
that the particles can create proton-antiproton pairs.
And so this dense soup
now becomes a soup of photons,
electrons,
positrons,
protons,
and antiprotons.
But
that's not really quite accurate.
And the reason...
No,
it's not...
It's more or less accurate.
Incidentally,
the number of protons in the universe
is about...
Not about.
As far as we know,
it's the same as the number of electrons
because the universe is electrically neutral.
There's no net charge in the universe.
So the universe is electrically neutral.
And if it's electrically neutral,
it must mean there's as many positively charged particles
as negative.
The only thing around today
are protons and electrons.
And so only charged particles around today
are electrons and protons.
So the number of electrons
and the number of protons
is the same today.
But of course,
once these positrons got into the act,
there were a lot more electrons and positrons
than there were protons.
But now we keep heating it up.
We keep heating it up.
What happens
is not that we really create large numbers
of protons and antiprotons,
but very shortly,
by the time we get to the energy needed
to create protons and antiprotons,
there's also enough energy
to smash the protons into quarks.
And so by the time you get to the energy
or the temperatures
where protons and antiprotons
become significant in this soup,
really what you have is quarks.
Three quarks for every proton.
Three anti-quarks for every antiproton.
And basically the kind of reaction
that can take place,
I'll just draw you some simple diagrams
that show you what kind of reactions
can take place.
The simplest one is an electron
and a positron come together,
E plus and E minus.
They create a photon.
That photon very quickly becomes something else.
It becomes a quark and an anti-quark,
Q,
that stands for quark.
Could be a positively charged quark
and a negatively charged quark.
There are in fact several different kinds of quarks.
There are quarks whose charges
are one third of the electron charge.
There are quarks whose charges are two thirds.
But I don't want now to get into the
particle physics of quarks.
The main thing is that
the soup becomes a soup
not only of electrons,
positrons,
and protons.
The protons are replaced by quarks
and in addition lots and lots of anti-quarks.
Almost as many anti-quarks as quarks.
And so if we go back far enough,
Yeah?
Is it mesons or pre-quarks?
Mesons are made out of quarks.
Once the temperature gets high enough
to shatter a proton,
it also shatters the mesons.
Now there's one more constituent,
there are other particles there too.
There are neutrinos
and all sorts of particles.
Also gluons.
What are gluons?
Gluons are very much like photons
but they're the things which are involved
in holding quarks together.
So there's all kinds of garbage.
It's a hot soup of all of the particles
that we normally consider in atomic physics
and in nuclear physics.
Okay?
That's when the temperature gets to be hot enough
for protons to be disassociated.
If you ask me in degrees how hot that is,
I will have to think for a while.
Ask me later.
We can work it out.
But at some temperature,
this begins to happen.
Now,
yeah?
This would be hotter than,
say,
inside a star.
Yes,
this is hotter than inside a star.
Definitely.
Inside a star,
there are no anti-particles
for the most part.
Right?
So there aren't even positrons
of any abundance inside stars.
Yeah?
So the sequence is going backwards in time,
right?
Yeah.
So the real sequence is the other way around.
Yeah,
the real sequence is the other way around.
That's what I want to get to.
I want to get back to a starting point
and then discuss how it happened that...
All right.
So if you get things hot enough,
there's going to be a huge density
of particles and anti-particles.
The particles and the anti-particles
will occur in pairs like this,
so there will be an equal abundance,
almost essentially an equal abundance
of positrons and electrons on the one hand
and almost equal abundance
of quarks and anti-quarks.
In fact,
if we go back sufficiently far,
then the universe contains
more or less equal abundances
of every kind of particle
and its anti-particle.
It starts out...
It's electrically neutral
because it's electrically neutral today.
Incidentally,
there's kind of an interesting reason
why the universe is...
or a simple way of thinking about the fact
that the universe is electrically neutral.
If the universe is closed and bounded,
in other words,
if it has the shape of a sphere,
a three-sphere,
not a two-sphere,
but if it has the shape of a sphere,
just think about this for a moment.
Let's use as our model of the universe
a two-dimensional sphere,
the surface of a balloon.
Now,
electrically charged particles
put out lines of force.
Those lines of force are the electric field.
So if I put an electrically charged particle...
Let's begin with flat space.
Here's flat space.
And let's put a positively charged particle in.
Electric lines of force
go out away from that particle.
And those electric lines of force
are simply the electric field
or a way of representing...
describing...
or representing the electric field
of the charged particle.
But it's useful graphically
to just think of it as lines of force.
And the lines of force
neither begin nor end
except at charged particles.
What law of physics is involved
in saying the lines of force
never end except at charged particles?
Maxwell's equations.
Well,
it is Maxwell's equations,
but it goes back a little...
to something a little simpler than Maxwell's.
It's the Coulomb force,
the one over r squared force law.
The one over r squared force law
is the rule that says that...
is equivalent to the rule that says
that the lines of force
never end except on charged particles.
Positive charged particles
put out lines of force.
Negative charged particles
suck in lines of force.
Now,
that's fine.
But supposing we lived in a world
which was this closed
and bounded spherical world.
Supposing we put a charged particle into it.
Let's put the charged particle over here.
Then the lines of force go out,
but they don't have anywhere to escape to.
What happens to them?
They just go around forever?
Well,
they don't move.
I mean,
they're...
They can't go around...
No,
they don't go around forever.
They simply refocus
on the other end of the sphere.
On the other pole.
Supposing...
For example,
supposing we put
a positively charged particle
at the north pole of the sphere.
Turn this up so that it's
the north pole of the sphere.
Then they simply refocus
at the south pole of the sphere.
I don't know how to draw that.
They refocus at the...
at the other end of the sphere.
But refocusing on the other end
means that the lines of flux,
which...
the lines of force which flow outward
from the positive charge over here
necessarily converge
at the antipode.
And what would that be
if this were a positive charge?
It would be a negative charge.
So in a closed and bounded universe,
you can't have a net charge.
So if you're saying
that there was no negative charge there,
there would be one there.
If there was no negative charge there,
there would be that one there.
Right.
It's just where the lines of flux converge.
All right.
But really,
charged particles
are charged particles.
So you can ask what kind of
charged particle would be there.
The answer is any kind of particle
with the opposite charge.
So if this were a proton,
this could be an antiproton
or it could be an electron.
The only rule is that every plus charge
has to match,
or the number of plus charges
and the number of minus charges
have to match.
In other words,
in a closed and bounded universe,
the net charge must be zero.
Now,
it's not clear that we live
in a closed and bounded universe,
but I just point this out to you
as a sort of mnemonic
for the fact that the net charge
of the universe is zero.
Or at least it looks to be zero.
Any place where we find positive charges,
we find negative charges.
And we don't find any large-scale
concentrations of positive
or negative charge.
They seem to cancel out pretty well.
Okay.
So...
Isn't the fact that we can see
the CMB evidence
of generally transparent space?
Uh...
Yeah.
That's right.
I mean,
that's right.
Yeah.
But the charge neutrality
is much better than that.
The charge neutrality is much better
than just the fact that the universe
looks pretty transparent.
Uh...
Anyway,
it's electrically neutral.
That,
of course,
does not mean
that the number of protons
is the same as the number of antiprotons.
It means the number of protons
plus positrons
plus all other positively charged particles
is the same as the number of the opposite
of negatively charged particles.
All right.
So we started out with a universe
with a very...
We started out,
or at least some time in the remote past,
as far back as we can trace,
using the known laws of physics
and maybe even going a little bit past
the known laws of physics.
We come to some stage
where the universe was extremely hot,
how hot?
Hot enough that,
um...
You name any experiment
that's ever been done
at a particle accelerator,
the universe was hot enough
to have had particles in it
whose energy was at least that high.
All right?
Uh...
That means pretty hot.
At that time,
the number of protons
and electrons...
The number of electrons and positrons
was about the same as each other.
The number of quarks and anti-quarks
were about the same as each other.
Uh...
And there was not only charge neutrality,
but...
Now,
I'm telling you empirical facts.
This is not obvious,
but I'm going to tell you
what the empirical fact is.
That,
uh...
Well...
The...
There is theory.
The theory says
that very early in the universe,
it was hot.
And it was...
When it was hot,
it's hot enough to have an abundance
of both particles and anti-particles,
because these collisions between photons
and other things create particles
and anti-particles.
All right.
Let's suppose
that the universe started
in a way which was symmetric
between particles and anti-particles.
Let's suppose it started
exactly with the same number
of electrons as positrons,
the same number of quarks
as anti-quarks.
And in fact,
as I said,
quarks come in different varieties.
So for each variety of quark,
let's suppose the numbers were symmetric
between particles and anti-particles.
The reason that this is
an interesting conjecture,
is because the laws of physics
are pretty much symmetrical,
not quite,
between particles and anti-particles,
almost symmetrical,
to rather high precision.
A positron behaves the same way
as an electron does.
As I said,
I keep saying over and over again,
not quite,
and it's true that it's not quite.
And that's symmetry.
That's symmetry between particles
and anti-particles,
between plus charge,
and minus charges,
has a name.
It's called charge conjugation symmetry.
It's the interchange of every particle
with its anti-particle.
Take all particles and replace them
by their anti-particles,
and that is a symmetry of nature,
which I will modify that statement
in a little while.
But if it were true,
you might say,
why on earth didn't the universe
not start out with an equal abundance
of charged particles of the positive type
and the negative type?
Or better yet,
why didn't it have an equal abundance
of quarks and anti-quarks?
Or did it have an equal abundance
Let's suppose that the universe
did start out with quarks and anti-quarks.
Let's suppose that it did for a minute.
Quarks and anti-quarks,
in your imagination,
you can replace that with protons
and anti-protons.
Protons and anti-protons are a good stand-in
for quarks and anti-quarks.
So for our purposes right now,
we don't really need to think about quarks.
We can think about protons and anti-protons.
Early,
early on,
let's suppose for a minute
that the symmetry of nature
under reflection,
replacing particles by anti-particles,
was actually a symmetry of the universe,
that the universe was like that.
As many positrons as electrons,
as many quarks as anti-
or as many protons as anti-protons.
And then the universe started to cool.
What happened as it started to cool?
What would happen as it started to cool?
Eventually,
it would cool down
to the point where the temperature
was not hot enough
for a particle to start to cool.
It would be hot enough
for photons to collide
and make protons and anti-protons.
It might still be hot enough
to make positrons and anti-
electrons and positrons,
but not hot enough
so that when photons or other pro-
or electrons and positrons collide,
not hot enough
to be able to provide
a large energy necessary
to make protons and anti-protons.
Then something will begin to happen.
The protons and the anti-protons
can collide with each other
and create photons.
The photons have no mass.
There's no problem with turning
a proton and an anti-proton
when they collide into photons.
But the photons simply don't have enough energy.
And then,
of course,
proton and anti-proton collide,
make some photons.
The photons,
of course,
have enough energy that they could
convert back to protons and anti-protons
because they have the same energy
that they started.
The proton and the anti-proton
become photon to photons.
But then the universe expands a little bit.
What happens to the photons?
The photons lower their energy
a little bit because they get stretched.
And when the universe is expanded a little bit,
all of a sudden those photons
no longer have enough energy
to be able to create the protons
and the anti-protons.
So it becomes a sort of wonderful thing
that we call the one-way street.
Protons,
anti-protons colliding,
making photons.
A little bit of expansion
sucks the energy out of the photons.
Not enough energy to collide
and make protons and anti-protons.
So there's a one-way flow,
sort of,
protons,
anti-protons,
to photons and electrons and positrons.
All right?
We start depleting
the protons and anti-protons.
And the temperature continues to get lower
because of the expansion of the universe.
And eventually
it goes down to the temperature
where the photons
can no longer
create electrons and positrons.
That's a very high temperature,
much,
much higher than the interior of the sun,
but much,
much lower
than temperatures associated with
protons and anti-protons.
And all of a sudden
the same thing happens.
Photons collide
Sorry.
Electrons and positrons
collide and make photons.
Universe expands a little bit.
Photon energies are diminished.
Not enough energy
to recycle back
to make electrons and positrons.
So the electrons and the positrons
start
being eliminated
in pairs.
The expansion of the universe
is relatively slow.
It's fairly slow
compared to
the rates of collisions
and other microscopic things
going on.
Universe is a slowly
expanding pot of stuff.
And it's mostly in equilibrium.
It's expanding slow enough
that things stay
pretty much in thermal equilibrium
except slowly decreasing
in temperature.
What would happen
under those circumstances?
Well,
what would happen
under those circumstances
is essentially
all of the protons
and anti-protons would disappear.
They would disappear
because they would annihilate
whenever a proton found an anti-proton
they would,
and remember
this soup is very,
very dense.
They would annihilate
and form a pair of photons.
The electrons and positrons
would do the same thing
and eventually all you would have left
would be photons.
Unless
for some reason,
let's say unknown at present,
there was a slight excess
or perhaps a large excess
of protons
over anti-protons.
Supposing that
in the beginning,
for whatever reason,
that protons
outnumbered anti-protons
two to one.
So for every
hundred
protons,
there was only
fifty anti-protons.
What would happen?
Well,
the
fifty anti-protons
would find fifty protons
to annihilate with,
but there would be no way
to get rid of the remaining
fifty protons that didn't have
partners.
So they would stick
around.
They would
stick around and continue to be there
and you couldn't get rid of them.
Why can't you get rid of them?
Because they can't find partners
to annihilate with.
Same thing
with the electrons and positrons.
Since the world is electrically neutral,
if it had more protons
than anti-protons,
it would have to have more electrons
than anti-electrons,
than positrons
to compensate.
But
exactly the same thing would happen
to the electrons.
Now there would be
what?
A hundred electrons
for every,
sorry,
for every hundred
electrons.
There would be fifty positrons.
In the end these things would
collide,
find each other,
and you
would be left over with fifty electrons
and fifty protons.
Okay?
Well,
that's,
logic
is okay.
That logic is fine.
But what would happen to the
energy of the
particles that annihilated?
It would become
photons.
Now to a good approximation,
the way the universe is expanding
is called adiabatic.
It means slowly.
It expands
slowly.
And for
reasons that have to do with thermodynamics,
much more with thermodynamics
and statistical mechanics than with
particle physics,
the net number of particles
doesn't change
very much with time.
When an
electron and a positron collide
to annihilate,
they
tend to turn into two photons.
So as
the time goes on,
this is really,
the really correct statement
is that the entropy of the universe
doesn't change as long as it's expanding
slowly.
Slowly means
the word is adiabatically.
As long as it's expanding slowly,
the entropy
of the universe doesn't change.
But entropy can be
translated into number of particles.
It's essentially the same thing.
So the number of particles doesn't change,
which means
that
the electrons and positrons
which annihilated,
and the protons and antiprotons
that were annihilated,
were basically replaced by photons.
So
the upshot
is we can count today
how many
particles there were
at a much,
much
earlier time
by simply
counting the number of photons.
The number of photons,
and remember,
almost all particles in the universe
are photons.
We can count
the number of photons,
and here's what we find.
We find that
the number of photons in the universe,
well,
the number of photons in the
universe is about
10 to the 10th,
somewhere between 10 to the 10th and 10 to
the 9th,
times bigger
than the number of either
electrons or
protons.
So
for every electron and proton
in the universe today,
there are something like 10 to the 10 photons.
That means
if we go backward in time
to the time when
everything was in this hot soup,
and there were more or less
equal number of every kind of particle and
antiparticle,
it means
that
for every
proton and antiproton,
no,
not for every proton,
for every
10 to the 9th protons
and antiprotons,
there was
one extra proton.
So there was a
terribly tiny imbalance
between
particles and
antiparticles that seems
to trace back practically
to the very beginning of the universe.
How do we know that it was such a tiny
imbalance?
Because we look today and we say
all the particles which annihilated
turned into photons.
So now we look today.
How many photons
are there for every proton in the
atmosphere?
The answer is about 10 to the 10th,
or 10 to the 9th,
or somewhere in there.
That means at early times
that the imbalance between
particles and antiparticles
was only about one
in a billion.
Roughly one in a billion
extra protons
for every proton-antiproton
pair.
Now,
it's
a good thing that there was that little
imbalance,
because if there wasn't
that little imbalance,
there would be no
atoms.
Everything would have been
annihilated.
Yeah?
Why don't you look at
it slightly differently in the sense
that,
let's say you started with
equal on
everything,
and statistically
you could say the probability
of when it cools
that the probability of
creating a proton
is 10 to the minus 9.
Rather than,
I mean,
you know,
you have these collisions and it
cools,
you're not making
collisions anymore.
Yeah,
we're coming to that.
That's what
we're going.
Right.
You're asking,
how do we know that as it cooled
that protons weren't
made?
How do we know that the only thing that happened
was annihilation?
I'll come to that.
In order for
protons to be created
in the process,
during the process of
cooling,
let's,
as you say,
let's suppose
there was equal number of protons and antiprotons.
Where is that,
where are those protons going,
where is that
extra proton going to come from?
We have to
create an extra proton.
Now,
to create an extra proton,
in order to keep electrically
neutral,
we also have to create
a electron.
So,
we start out with a world
with equal number of
electrons
and positrons,
protons
and antiprotons,
electrically neutral,
but also neutral
with respect to particles and
antiparticles,
and now we
want to make an extra proton
so an extra proton,
we want some
reaction where a proton comes out,
but something else has to
come out with it because of electric charge,
and that would have to be an
electron.
Or some other negatively
charged particle,
but for simplicity
let's just say,
where did the
mass for these come from?
Let's say it came from
a pair of photons colliding.
Well,
the only
problem with this,
is the standard rules of
elementary particles,
the standard model
of elementary particles,
does
not contain such a process.
It does not contain
any process where the net
number,
now I'm talking about the
standard model of particle physics.
Standard model of particle
physics means standard thing
that we know from laboratory
physics,
and not extensions
that may or may not be,
turn out to be correct in the future.
The standard model which
describes particle physics very well
up to
energies
of a thousand times the
mass of a proton,
contains no
processes that involve protons
or could create protons that don't
at the same time create an anti-proton.
This is called baryon
number conservation.
Baryon numbers for our
purposes is basically
the number of protons,
you can add in neutrons
protons and neutrons are very similar to each other,
the number of
protons and neutrons,
protons plus neutrons,
minus the number of anti-protons
plus anti-neutrons.
That number is
conserved in the standard model
of particle physics.
That means you cannot
create a
proton without creating
an anti-proton.
And this is not electric charge.
This process here
is perfectly good for
electric charge.
One proton and one
electron.
But it
violates one of the rules,
empirical rules,
entirely empirical,
that
you can't create a proton
without creating an anti-proton
at the same time.
I might add that the same
rule,
or the same physics,
tells you that you can't
create an electron without creating
a positron.
Now as I said,
this is not the conservation
of electric charge,
because as far as electric charge
goes,
a proton and an
electron together are electrically neutral.
It's the conservation
of baryon number.
Conservation
of the net number of
protons minus anti-protons.
And neutrons
and anti-neutrons.
So the standard laws of particle
physics do not
allow,
as you cool down,
to create an excess of protons.
I think that's the question you
asked,
is it?
Well,
I'm not sure.
You asked me how do I know
as I cool down that the excess
didn't develop.
What I'm saying
is that the rules of elementary particle
physics do not,
elementary particle physics
up to
or down to distant scales
a thousand times or ten thousand times
smaller than a proton,
do not
contain any processes
which would allow
an imbalance to
develop.
Now,
what does that really mean?
That doesn't mean that
in cooling down from some exceedingly
high temperature,
this imbalance could not have
developed spontaneously.
What it means is once the
temperature gets down low enough
to where we know
the rules,
where the
energies of collisions
are low enough that we
know the rules of
particle physics,
that there
are no processes
at those energies,
at those temperatures and lower
that can do what you want.
But,
of course,
we are always
acting to some extent
in a sea of ignorance where we
don't know what physics is like
at yet smaller distances
and higher temperatures
and higher energies.
So one speculation
which is,
I would say,
I would say it's speculative,
I would also say there's almost
complete consensus among
cosmologists,
experimental physicists,
theoretical physicists,
almost everybody,
is that in fact
the universe did really start
neutral.
Now why is it?
Why should there be
such consensus for something
we know nothing about
and we don't know
Hard to answer.
But it does seem a little bit odd.
If you go back early enough,
you really do,
where did this one part
in 10 to the 10th come from?
That's a very odd thing.
One part in 10 to the 10th
is a very odd thing.
It sort of makes you
want to believe that perhaps
the universe had as many protons
to begin with,
as many as electrons as positrons
and that as you say,
that as it cooled,
something caused it
to be biased
in one direction
to create a few extra protons
and a few extra electrons.
That is widely believed,
but
you have to go back
to times and temperatures
which were above the temperatures
where particles
and particle physics
has been successfully tested,
shall we say,
where the standard model
has been successfully tested.
So what does it take?
I just want to talk a little bit
about your question.
What does it take in the way
of changes in particle physics
or the way in the rules
of particle physics
to allow a universe
which started
with the number of protons
equaling the number
of anti-protons?
Now I should say,
when I say protons,
I mean things with,
I mean a collection of objects
that includes neutrons,
protons,
and other objects
called baryons.
But let's simplify the story
to just protons.
Let's start,
not that a proton equals
an anti-proton.
The bar incidentally stands for anti.
I don't mean that a proton
is the same as an anti-proton.
That's nonsense.
They have opposite charge.
I mean that the number of protons,
let's call it the number of protons,
equal the number of anti-protons.
Supposing we start that way
in the very,
very early universe.
Incidentally,
these speculations
were first made by Andrei Sakharov
in the Soviet Union
in about 1967.
They were totally unknown in the West.
Nobody knew about them.
They were rediscovered actually
by Dimopoulos and myself
around 1980,
13 years later.
And the subject is called
baryogenesis.
Genesis means the birth of,
and baryo here stands for
baryon number,
which means
proton number,
and so forth.
Alright,
so the idea is,
first of all,
the laws of particle physics
must violate
at some level,
at some high temperature,
it must violate the rule
that protons
cannot be created
without anti-protons.
In other words,
it must violate
a rule called the
conservation of
baryon number.
The conservation of baryon number
is basically the conservation
of the number of protons
minus anti-protons.
That's the
conservation of baryon number.
The conservation of that quantity
in the standard model of particle physics
is a known experimental
and theoretical fact,
the conservation of it.
But if you go back to earlier times
when the energies were higher,
when the distances were smaller,
when we go beyond what we really know,
there's no reason why
this law of conservation
of baryons,
or baryon number,
must be true.
In fact,
we believe it's probably
not true.
There's very,
very strong reason to believe
on a number of grounds
that the number of protons
minus anti-protons
can change.
Now,
the electric charge
cannot change.
So that means every time a new proton
is created without an anti-proton,
it must go together with an electron
being created.
That's okay.
We don't mind that.
But the first condition
for a theory
which starts out
with equal abundance
of particles and anti-particles,
the first condition
for it to get shifted a little bit
is violation
of condition number one.
Violation
of the conservation
of baryon number.
I'm writing down the three conditions
that Sakharov himself wrote down
and that Dimopoulos and I
rediscovered independently,
and which are
generally
almost complete consensus about this.
That's number one,
that the laws of physics
must allow processes
such as this
where a pair of photons
can come together and make a proton
and an electron.
It would require a new set of interactions,
a new set of phenomena,
which can only happen at energies
so high that we haven't yet seen them
in accelerators.
So that's number one,
violation of the conservation of baryon number.
Now,
number two.
Alright,
let's suppose there was a
violation of the conservation
of baryon number.
Let me give you an example
of conservation law.
Conservation of position,
my position,
well of course this is not a conservation law,
but let's just suppose for a minute it was.
That would mean I can't move.
Alright?
My conservation of my location
would literally mean
I can't move.
Now I could violate,
I could imagine
that that's a law of physics,
and then I could imagine a small violation of it.
A small violation of it would mean
I can move a little bit,
maybe slowly.
But it wouldn't necessarily say
that I can only move
to the left,
to my left,
your right.
It might say that I can move
a little bit and change my position,
but offhand,
perhaps
equally likely to the left or the right.
So a conservation
law can be violated,
but in a way which doesn't
bias either
more protons or more
antiprotons.
It simply allows,
in other words,
for example,
there could be a process in nature like
this,
and there could be another
process in nature,
the reflection
of it,
where
all particles are replaced by
their antiparticles.
This would become
antiproton
and positron.
You might think,
if this could happen,
this could happen.
That would mean that
the conservation law is
violated,
but it's not biased
in a particular direction.
It could increase the number
of protons or increase the number
of antiprotons,
and
both kinds of things might be going on.
Over here,
a proton
might be created.
Over here,
an
antiproton might be created.
Obviously,
on the average,
there would be no
biasing,
and on the average,
you would expect
again that
such processes would not lead
to a net imbalance
of protons
and antiprotons.
The key
is to say,
wait a minute,
how do I know
that
nature is truly
symmetric or truly
invariant
under changing every particle
to every antiparticle?
How do I know that this charge
conjugation is really
a symmetry of physics,
and that everything that can happen
can happen with equal probability
with particles being
replaced by antiparticles?
And the answer is not only
do we not know that that's
a symmetry,
we know that it's
not a symmetry.
Experimental
physics by now has uncovered
the fact that
there is not an exact
symmetry
where you replace every particle
by antiparticle.
That's been known
for many years now,
that
there are slight differences,
there are slight
small residual
differences in
reaction rates
and probabilities
when you replace particles
by antiparticles.
That
conceivably could
bias one of these
two relative to the other.
For example,
this process could
have a slightly different probability
than this process,
this one being perhaps a little more
probable,
this one a little less probable.
Then the bias would be towards
protons and electrons rather than
positrons and electrons.
That means that we
have to also have
a violation
of
charge conjugation
symmetry.
That there must be
a bias in nature
which distinguishes
particles from antiparticles.
Indeed,
Yes?
Could it be that there is a
even if they were
unbiased,
that sort of by
some kind of
random process,
just as you approach the
point of no return
where you didn't have
that reaction anymore,
you would have had some excess
of one over the other?
Yeah,
you might have had some excess
of one over the other here,
but over here you would have perhaps
the opposite excess,
and over here you would have
But still you might have had an overall excess.
That would,
on statistical grounds
you would expect under those circumstances,
assuming there was a symmetry,
you would expect the excess to be
of order the square root of the number of
particles.
This is usual square root of n
statistics.
There is something like about
10 to the 80th protons
in the universe.
Square root of n
is only 10 to the 40th,
and
that's,
sorry,
go back,
go back.
If I take all of the particles in the
known universe,
there is
something like about 10 to the 90th.
That includes photons.
The square root
of that is only 10 to the 45,
so that could account
for an imbalance of 10 to the 45
protons,
but there is more like 10 to the 80th
protons in the universe.
It's a very good question.
How do I know that it isn't
a statistical fluctuation,
but that's
way beyond
the
Yeah,
the numbers just don't support that.
So that's a very good question.
I thought of it myself years ago
and dismissed it very quickly.
Okay.
Well,
yeah,
but you might still expect
maybe the patchiness washed itself out
and,
you know,
it's thinkable,
but the numbers are too far from
that.
Now,
the last thing is a more
subtle thing.
There is
a symmetry of physics
which is not charge
conjugation symmetry,
but it's a combination of charge
conjugation
and time reversal
where
if you simultaneously
replace every
particle by its antic particle
and at the same time run things
backward in time,
then
that is an exact
symmetry of nature.
You can ask me how we know that.
Let me just say that
that is very deeply and fundamentally
built into the rules of relativistic
quantum mechanics,
relativistic quantum field theory.
I'm not going to try to explain it now.
It's called the CPT theorem.
You can look it up,
the CPT theorem.
And unlike
the charge conjugation,
the constant
That's a thing which could be wrong.
Empirically it's close to being correct
but doesn't have to be correct.
The CPT theorem
is a theorem.
It's a mathematical theorem about relativity
and quantum mechanics.
And what it says,
as I said,
is if you take every particle
and replace it by its antic particle
and at the same time
run time backward,
in other words,
take a movie of the universe or a movie of
something,
run backward,
then that's an exact symmetry of nature.
Now if I were
to take a pot of hot gas that had
been sitting forever and ever and ever for a
long time and it's come to equilibrium
and it's just sitting there so that
nothing is going in one direction or the other direction,
that means a movie of it
run backward and forward is exactly the same.
It's in equilibrium.
But if there's
a symmetry that says that if you
let time run backward and also interchange
particle with antiparticle,
but you're in a situation where it doesn't matter
whether you run time backward or
not because it looks exactly the same,
then
you have a symmetry between particles and antiparticles.
So the last condition in order
to break the symmetry between particles and
antiparticles is that the universe at some
point in its history must have been
sufficiently out of equilibrium so that
it definitely looked different going one
way than any other way.
Now you say,
of course the universe looks different
going one way than the other way.
The universe is expanding.
It's not contracting.
But on the other hand,
throughout most of the life of the
universe it has been expanding so
slowly that the expansion was negligible on
time scales of elementary particle reactions.
Today the universe expands on
scales of a billion years.
Particle reactions,
which are the things that
are relevant here,
are,
you know,
10 to the minus 25 seconds or whatever.
Very,
very rapid.
And so the very slow expansion of the universe,
you can just
think of that as the pot sitting there forever.
And for most of the history of
the universe it is expanding very
slowly compared to the particle physics rates.
Nevertheless,
sufficiently early in the universe,
sufficiently early,
the universe
was certainly out of equilibrium.
Sufficiently early it
was explosively expanded.
And during that period of time it looked different from
the microscopic point of view,
from the individual point of view of particle
collisions and so forth,
the expansion of the universe was very,
very significant.
And the universe did not
look symmetric going forward and backward.
And it's
during that time,
it's called,
the third condition is called being out of
equilibrium.
Now it's an interesting theorem that
if all of these conditions are satisfied,
number
one,
that baryon number is not conserved,
number two,
that the symmetry between particles
and antiparticles is broken,
is not a symmetry,
and third,
that the universe was for some period
out of equilibrium,
in other words,
that the expansion rate was fast enough to effect
particle reactions,
then even if you start with a
universe which is equal number of protons
and antiprotons,
equal number of positrons and antipositrons,
it will get tilted one
way or the other.
It's essentially a theorem that,
as I said,
it was discovered by Sakharov,
1967.
And,
Andrei Sakharov,
that is,
and is called the theory of baryogenesis.
The part of it that we don't know with certainty,
this we know,
the universe,
well,
we can conjecture that the
universe at the very beginning,
at the very earliest times,
was expanding rapidly enough
that it effected particle collisions.
This is very reasonable.
This is known to be true.
The violation of baryon number is the question mark.
We have never seen a reaction in
nature where the number of protons minus anti,
and when
I say protons,
I mean protons plus neutrons,
protons plus neutrons minus antiprotons minus
antineutrons,
we have never seen a reaction
in nature which violates this here.
That may simply be
because we've never had enough energy
to create reactions that do that.
Alright,
so this is the question mark here.
If it turns out that baryon number is not conserved,
then it's essentially a theorem that there
will be a little bit left over,
one sign or the other,
protons or antiprotons.
When people make models of this,
and they start calculating,
they're going to get a lot of results.
They get numbers not so different
than one part in a billion.
So the one part in
a billion is not an unreasonable answer,
but we simply don't really have a theory that
goes back that far.
And so at the present time,
this is conjectural,
that the universe started out neutral.
Neutral
with respect to this baryon number.
And then,
in the process of cooling,
has it went out
of equilibrium,
as it expanded very rapidly,
these other conjunctions ...
being satisfied,
tilted it a little bit,
one part in a billion,
the protons versus
anti-protons,
one part in a billion to electrons versus positrons,
and then in
the process of cooling down beyond that,
every excess anti-proton,
every
anti-proton found a proton,
annihilated with it,
and only left over this one in a
billion.
Same thing with the electrons and positrons,
and today what we have is
that tiny fossil remnant of the...
the universe looks like it's very,
very
grossly matter and not antimatter,
but it's a simple remnant of something which
was much,
much more equal at the early times.
So that's an interesting story.
Well,
Michael had a question.
Yeah.
Matching up the Cpt to the 1,
2,
3 here,
I think numbers 2 and 3 are C and
violation of T.
Okay,
let me,
let me clarify,
let me be more exact.
I just call this charge
conjugation where you replace
a particle by its anti-particle.
There's,
it's really
something called C times P,
where P is called parity
and it means spatio...
So number 2 is Cp violation.
Yeah,
Cp violation.
We could call this charge conjugation,
Cp violation,
Cp.
But it is replacing
particles by anti-particles and at the same time...
Number 3 is T.
Say it again.
Reversal.
This?
Yeah.
That's,
no,
that's time reversal.
Yeah,
time reversal.
time reversal,
right.
Okay,
and then number 1 is neither,
none of them.
Well,
1 and number 1 is just something different.
Completely different.
Now,
I should say there's very strong reason to
believe that baryon number is not a good,
real,
genuine conservation law of physics.
There are many reasons,
but however,
it has
never been detected,
the violation of baryon number.
Disappointing fact that the...
yeah?
How close are you to Big Bang?
Very close.
Well,
look,
it's a question of definition of
what you mean by the Big Bang.
There may
have been a long period of inflation which
preceded what we normally think of as the
Big Bang,
but what we normally think of as the Big Bang,
we're pretty close to the Big
Bang,
yeah.
Are there estimates for what energy levels
you would see the violation of baryon number
conserving?
Well,
you would see it significantly,
yeah.
And how many orders of energy would you see?
I mean,
there's a magnitude beyond what LHC can do.
No,
no,
no.
You see,
okay.
No,
it's more complicated than that.
All right.
Supposing
there was some reaction which
became important at high temperatures,
which really became
highly probable at high temperatures,
which allowed some kind of reaction to occur.
Well,
And it's not a collision to take place
which would change the number of protons and so
forth.
It might nevertheless be,
even though you don't have that much energy around,
that
a process can still happen,
but with very,
very small probability,
extremely small.
Now,
that's typical.
That's a typical kind of
thing where something can become strong
and important when you have a lot of energy,
and that doesn't mean that it's impossible
at low energy.
It just means it becomes very,
very improbable.
So if it's true that there
are reactions in nature which violate this baryon number,
but only significantly with
a high probability when the temperature is very high,
here would be a process,
for example,
a proton becoming a positron and a photon.
That's a perfectly good.
But you might,
I'm
Now,
it might only happen when the proton,
let's say,
not only happen,
it might mostly
happen when the proton collides with something else
at very high energy that shakes it up
a lot and then kicks off this collision.
Well,
it would still be,
in most theories,
that
it could happen even at low temperature and low energy,
but with a very,
very diminished
probability.
How diminished?
Well,
we know something about the life time.
We know that the life time
of a proton,
the life time of a proton,
how long must a proton last?
Well,
ordinary particle
physics reactions happen very fast,
in terribly small fractions of a second.
So just applying ordinary dimensional analysis to this,
you might expect that this would
happen in a terribly tiny fraction of a second.
But it doesn't,
it certainly doesn't.
Your
protons don't disappear spontaneously like that.
into positrons.
How long,
what's the minimum lifetime of a proton?
Well I can
tell you this,
that the proton basically have to
last the age of the universe for
sure.
Okay,
for sure they must last the
age of the universe because they're
still around.
So at least 10 billion years,
but in fact the age,
the lifetime
of a proton is much,
much longer than that.
The reason is because if the
lifetime of the proton was about 10 billion years,
then if you took 10
billion protons,
which is not very many,
then one of them on the average would
decay in one year.
If the average,
if the half-life of the proton was 10 billion
years,
then in one year if you
had 10 billion protons to start with,
one of the
protons would decay.
Now it's easy to see and,
and then if you had a large number of protons
you know,
ten to the twenty-third protons,
you would have a lot of reactions of
this type taking place.
Even though the likelihood that any proton decayed would
be very,
very small.
So we know that the lifetime is much,
much longer than the
age of the universe,
in fact it was known many years ago
that a proton would decay,
if you already have a proton,
to be upwards somewhere around more
than 10 to the 27 years.
It's a very,
very long time,
much,
much longer than the age of the universe.
Starting sometime in the late 70s,
people started to build very big experiments
where they would take very large quantities of material,
which usually meant water.
In fact,
it always meant water.
Why water?
Because water is transparent,
and you can look through it and see the light.
This,
incidentally,
would also,
this produces a photon,
for example.
Photons are light.
You want transparent materials.
Water is good.
Take huge quantities of water,
huge means,
you know,
many,
many swimming pools,
hundreds of swimming pools,
and sit and watch the many,
many protons
and wait for one proton to decay.
Can you see one proton to decay
in a big pool of water?
Yes,
you can.
You'll have many,
many protons.
many light detectors.
You have a great big pool of water.
Photo detectors all along the sides here,
and if a proton decays,
it emits photons,
and you can detect it.
So you can detect one reaction in a great big,
huge pool
of very transparent water.
There are all kinds of background noise,
so you bury the process
deep under the earth in a
mine somewhere is where cosmic rays,
et cetera,
et cetera.
It was fully expected that
with 10 to the 32 protons,
you would see one of them decay
in about a year's time.
Nothing happened.
So we now know that the lifetime of the proton
is longer than something like
about 10 to the 34 years.
That's a long time for the proton to last.
But what we don't know,
and what we won't know for many years,
is that when collisions happen
that really excite the proton,
that pump a lot of energy in,
that this process doesn't happen very readily.
There are many processes in nature,
many things in nature,
which are very,
very improbable unless you have a large energy
to excite them.
And proton change or the violation
of baryon number could well be
one of those things that it just
takes a very high temperature to precipitate.
And that's what we don't know.
This is still a question mark.
Question?
Yeah.
The baryon conservation describes why the
positive baryon and negative baryon whatever.
But since the universe is electrically neutral,
what guarantees that there are
just single number of protons and electrons?
Well,
the basic elementary particle physics process,
you have to start with the total number of protons,
and then you have the number of neutrons.
for deep mathematical reasons that we
don't need to go into here,
always conserve the basic processes of nature,
such as elementary particle processes,
always conserve the electric charge.
So roughly speaking,
this is a process where the electric charge
hops from the proton to the electron,
but electric charge can't disappear.
So what guarantees it,
Maxwell's equations,
fundamental symmetries of physics,
No,
no,
I mean like,
okay,
there's the same number of,
in the soup there's the
same number of protons as antiprotons,
positrons as electrons.
Right.
But as the universe cooled,
you know,
the antiparticles disappeared,
but the universe is still electrically neutral.
So...
That is what,
in fact,
happens.
Yeah.
But it's another question to ask
why it got biased towards protons
instead of antiprotons.
No,
my question is why is it
the same number of electrons and protons?
It's electrically neutral.
That's because the basic processes of physics,
whenever a proton disappears,
another charged particle has to reappear.
So it can't get out of balance electrically.
Where in this picture does,
if we keep rotating the clock back,
where do we un-freeze out the
protonic degrees of freedom of reabsorption?
To which degrees of freedom?
Photonic.
What does it mean to un-freeze photonic degrees of freedom?
Well,
if we suppose the photon arises
from spontaneous symmetry breakdown of the...
Oh,
of the standard model.
Yeah.
That happens at an energy of about 100 GeV,
or 200,
maybe 250 GeV.
Yeah.
So,
if the photon disappears,
it's that the weak interactions become much,
much more like the electromagnetic interactions.
The weak interactions meaning those
things involving neutrinos and so forth.
So,
the symmetry breaking,
which made the photon special relative to the Z boson
and the W boson and so forth,
that happened at a temperature about 100 times
or 200 times higher than the temperature of the neutron.
And that's when the proton gaps,
that happened at a temperature about 100 times higher than
and that's when the proton gaps are so
much larger than the energy at which protons
and antiprotons first were formed.
But that's known physics.
That's known physics.
That we know where that happened.
And it doesn't,
it plays a role,
but it doesn't play a
dramatic role in this story here.
Yeah?
Does dark,
how,
does dark matter modify this picture in any way?
Not particularly.
Um...
Dark matter...
itself,
you can ask whether dark matter is anything like,
it's not protons,
but whether it has
its own conservation laws which had to be broken
in similar ways to get
a net amount of dark matter.
Probably not,
dark matter doesn't influence
this particular question in any special way.
But it had to be hanging around there.
It was hanging around.
In the very early part of the picture.
Yeah.
Even at very high temperatures.
It was there.
Right.
But in most theories of dark matter,
the dark matter doesn't interact very much
with ordinary matter,
and so it was more or less spectator.
Now,
could it somehow have been involved?
It's possible,
it's possible.
In the very end.
It's possible.
It's possible,
but I don't think it would change
the basic principles.
Wouldn't change the basic principles.
Right.
好
Condition number three is the equivalent
to a violation of CPT symmetry?
No.
Well,
yes and no.
Let's just take T.
Forget the CP,
just T.
T is time reversal symmetry.
It means anything that can happen one way
can also happen if you ran things the opposite way.
But it doesn't say that the
actual history of the universe was symmetric.
It just says whatever the history of the universe is,
if it can go one way,
it can also go the other way.
All right?
Now,
all that this says is that
the universe was out of equilibrium,
which means that it wasn't static,
that it wasn't just sitting there
like a pot of stew on a plate.
It was changing.
The pot was expanding.
A violation of CPT symmetry would
mean that running the film backward
was not a possible solution of the equations of physics.
And that's something,
this is,
let's put it this way.
To violate this,
we would have to violate something very deep
about quantum field theory and
special relativity and quantum mechanics.
So while I don't think any of us can
say never that CPT violation is not a possibility,
it's not a possibility within the
current mathematics of quantum field theory.
So this is considered pretty sacred generally.
That doesn't mean that the universe isn't going one way.
It just means if it's going one way,
then you'll be safe.
If you run it backward,
that's also a possible world.
All right.
For example,
I mean,
I am right-handed.
Okay?
Does that mean that there's
a left-right asymmetry in nature?
No.
It just means that another creature could exist,
doesn't necessarily have to exist,
but another creature could exist who was
left-handed and be otherwise exactly like me.
It doesn't mean that I'm necessarily ambidextrous.
It means that whatever I am,
the reflection could exist.
Same thing about time reversal here.
Whatever the universe is doing,
it's a consistent set of solutions of
equations of a theory to run backward.
With the other changes,
the changes in parity.
Yeah,
with the other changes simultaneously along the set.
That's right.
Yeah.
How does gravity affect in all this?
Well,
gravity,
of course,
is deeply connected with the expansion of the universe.
But other than that,
okay,
let me give you a,
yeah,
let me tell you one of the reasons
that we have a fairly strong belief that this conservation
of baryon number cannot be an exact conservation law of physics.
And it does involve gravity.
Before I say that,
let me say that the gravitational
interactions between particles are so negligible,
at least at any reasonable energies,
that it really doesn't play much role in this.
But there's a logical point which is interesting,
and it has to do
with black holes of all things.
Imagine a black hole being formed
out of the material of a star.
I forget how many protons,
how many,
what the baryon number of a star is,
but something like about 10 to the 60th,
if I remember.
Something like about 10 to
the 60th protons in a star.
It has a net baryon
number which is large and positive.
Now the star collapses to a black hole.
It runs out of fuel,
collapses,
and becomes a black hole.
Well,
the black hole may have all
of those protons inside it somewheres.
But then,
at least according to theory,
if you wait long enough,
the black hole will start to evaporate.
It will evaporate into photons,
basically photons.
The temperature of a large black hole is very,
very low,
and it's nowhere near enough energy for
it to be able to create protons.
So this large black hole,
which started out as 10 to the 60th protons,
contracted,
became a black hole,
and started to emit ordinary black body radiation.
Slowly it heated up,
but by the time it heated up
enough to be able to create protons,
it was as tiny as a,
well,
it was very,
very small.
Very few protons left to be able to be emitted.
So we know from black hole physics and
the evaporation of black holes that at some level,
at some level,
the conservation of the number of protons,
the number of protons in the world,
must be violated.
That's something that most physicists believe.
But that's about the only
way that I can think that,
two ways that gravity comes into the story.
One is that it strongly suggests violation of conservation
of baryon number because of this black hole story.
The second way that it comes in is it
has to do with the expansion of the universe.
If it wasn't for gravity
and Einstein's equations and so forth,
there would be no expansion.
And without expansion of the universe,
there would be no out of equilibrium.
So the expansion of the universe,
which is a gravitational phenomenon,
is part of the out of equilibrium.
But apart from that,
gravity doesn't play any significant role in this.
If we had a black hole that was charged,
Yeah.
wouldn't that same argument show,
suggest violation of charge?
No.
That's a very good question,
but the answer is no.
And the reason is because charged black holes,
like any other charges,
have electric lines of flux coming out of them.
And that electric,
those electric lines of flux,
are sort of tied down at infinity.
And they keep track of the
electric charge of the black hole.
Electrically charged black holes
will not completely evaporate.
They will evaporate photons,
losing energy,
until they get down to some minimum energy
called the extremal energy of the extremal black hole.
And then they'll just sit there and stop evaporating.
And black holes which have stopped evaporating
because they have electric charge are called extremal.
They're extremal in that they have,
that their mass is the extreme
lower end of a charged black hole.
So no,
charged black holes don't indefinitely evaporate.
Yeah.
There's always a confusion when people talk about
Big Bang and black hole and the density.
If you think of a volume
of that great dense supermassive mass,
you calculate that the radius of a black,
that it would collapse into a black
hole based on its density and its size.
I mean,
this quark soup that you were talking about is much,
I gather,
much denser than,
say,
a neutron star.
And the mass is much greater than...
But it's expanding.
That's expanding.
Just because space is expanding.
Well,
I don't know.
It is expanding because...
All right.
It's because space is expanding.
Or just because it is expanding.
No,
it doesn't collapse into a black hole.
Instead,
it does something else.
It expands.
So,
no,
there's no issue.
There's no issue of all this
dense material somehow forming a black hole.
That's not an issue.
The black hole idea that I just expressed
is a thought experiment.
It's a thought experiment to try to convince yourself
that the laws of physics as we now know them
sort of force the issue here
that the conservation of baryon number is
not something that will persist indefinitely in physics.
By now,
there are so many reasons
to believe in the violation of baryon number that it's...
Well,
it's a half a check.
At least half a check.
Would one know how to amend the standard model
in order to include those reactions?
The trouble is the opposite.
Almost any way that you
try to amend the standard model
winds up making the lifetime of the proton too fast.
Yeah.
So,
yeah,
it's really easy to make...
To make it run...
To make it too much.
It's hard to keep the
proton as stable as it is.
Right.
Can a proton absorb a photon
and reach a higher energy level
with the quarks inside of it?
Say it again.
Can a proton...
Can a proton absorb a photon?
A proton can absorb a photon.
And it will get excited.
The quarks are...
The quarks will start to get excited.
They will get very excited.
And...
But,
of course,
the first thing that will happen
is they'll spit out more quarks,
but quarks and anti-quarks,
mesons.
Mesons.
Maybe they'll vibrate and spit out some mesons.
To the best of our knowledge,
the amount of energy that you
would have to shove into a proton
to make it decay and disappear,
leaving only a positron,
would have to be enormously large
simply because the proton is known to be so stable.
Known to be so stable.
And,
therefore,
this must be a very remote
and unlikely process.
The only way to make it unlikely
is to push it to very,
very high energy and...
So we could talk more about it,
but...
Yeah?
Yeah.
Before we complete this,
I have a question about square root of n statistics.
You have to speak louder.
We talked about square root of n statistics before.
Square root of n?
Square root of n,
yeah.
Well,
earlier,
was the number of particles nearly constant,
or is it possible that at some early time...
Yeah.
Some...
Some of this is theory,
some of it is observation,
and I'm not going to try to distinguish now,
but roughly speaking,
the number of particles in the universe
did not change from some very early time.
The number of particles within a certain coordinate patch,
within a coordinate patch.
And the correct statement,
the exact statement,
is that in a universe in equilibrium,
or just close to equilibrium,
in an adiabatically expanding universe...
Adiabatically expanding means
that the rate of expansion
is much slower
than any fundamental particle process,
or any fundamental process in nature.
What did you ask me?
I lost track.
Well,
just the number of particles...
Yeah,
yeah,
yeah.
In an adiabatic process,
which means a slow process,
entropy is conserved.
Entropy doesn't change in an adiabatic process.
Now,
if you take a gas
or a soup of elementary particles
and you calculate the entropy,
it is within a factor of two or pi
or some numerical number.
It's the number of particles.
So in an adiabatic process,
where the universe is expanding
slower than particle reactions are taking place,
even though particle reactions can take place,
and they do take place,
and they might even be biased
in one direction or another,
the net number of particles tends not to change.
And if it does change,
it changes maybe over the whole history of the universe
by a factor of ten or something like that,
not by an enormous amount.
So...
Originally,
the early questions about this subject
had the whole story upside down.
Instead of asking why there were so few
protons relative to photons,
the question was asked the other way.
Why are there so many photons
relative to the number of protons?
And the idea was
that there must have been something in the physics
which just proliferated huge numbers of photons
and increased the entropy of the universe.
Where did all this entropy come from?
So it was thought that what we needed
was an explanation of some kind of process
which just created wholesale,
enormous amounts of entropy
out of organized energy,
out of energy which was organized.
Eventually,
the question got turned around the other way.
A certain amount of entropy in the world,
that entropy has not changed very much,
but somehow the protons and antiprotons
disappeared,
became photons,
and left over only this very,
very small fraction.
So the emphasis changed
from trying to explain the production of entropy,
the production of photons from nothing,
basically,
to the question of why in the early universe
the imbalance between particles and antiparticles
was so small.
Nobody ever found a way
to create all that entropy
through the expansion of the universe.
All that entropy means
this very large number of photons.
So nobody believes now that the problem is
how do you create entropy.
Everybody believes the problem is,
well,
the problem at the moment
is verifying
in the laboratory or otherwise
that there's a violation of baryon number.
That'll probably happen sooner or later.
We,
in these big experiments involving these huge,
huge quantities of water,
wait 100 years and a proton might decay.
That's the sort of estimate that's out there now.
Wait 100 years and one proton will decay.
Make sure you're looking at that.
Hmm?
Make sure you're looking at that line.
Yeah,
that's the question.
I mean,
you gotta run these experiments
for a long period of time.
Who's gonna pay for them?
I don't know.
I'm gonna have to run all these experiments,
I mean,
I'm gonna have to do a lot.
I don't even know.
The answer is I don't know.
Okay.
I don't know.
So what happens
if it decays while the graduate student is asleep?
sleep.
Okay.
What are the questions?
Go ahead.
Yeah.
Neutrons will decay into a proton electron.
Right.
And neutrino.
Antineutrino.
I'm wondering how the neutrons persisted beyond
the 15 minute half life of the journey
left in the universe after that time.
Cool.
A free neutron will decay in 15,
12 minutes.
I forget what the number is.
12 minutes,
something like that.
A free neutron.
A neutron incidentally also has baryon number,
same as a proton.
So here's an example of a
process which does not violate baryon number.
It's called beta decay.
A neutron becomes a proton,
an electron,
E minus.
So far,
it's a perfectly good process.
An electrically neutral particle becomes a
plus charge and a minus charge.
And also at the same time,
an antineutrino is emitted.
Antineutrino is emitted.
That,
for technical reasons,
the antineutrino has to be there.
This is a process.
And it does happen.
All neutrons,
sooner or later,
decay like this.
And they last about 12 minutes now before they decay.
That's the half life.
Maybe it's 15.
I remember 12.
But it's an interesting question why they last so long.
Elementary particle processes are usually measured.
They're measured in very,
very small time periods.
Why does a neutron last so long?
And the answer is a combination of answers.
But one of the elements that goes in is
that the sum of the mass of the proton,
the positron,
and the neutrino is almost exactly or
very close to the mass of the neutron.
So that means if these
particles were a little bit larger,
a little bit heavier,
there wouldn't be enough energy for the neutron to decay.
So if the proton was
just a little tiny bit heavier,
the neutron could not decay at all because there
wouldn't be enough energy for it to make a proton,
an electron,
and a neutrino.
It just so happens that the neutron is almost equal,
is only a tiny bit heavier than the proton,
and just a teeny,
teeny bit heavier than the proton plus the electron.
So there isn't much energy there.
And for that reason,
the process takes a long time to happen.
But yes,
the neutron decays in...
That's a neutron,
a free neutron.
Now if a neutron is bound in a nucleus,
it may have some binding energy.
Let's put it into a nucleus with some protons,
let's say with a proton.
Then there's some binding energy.
There's some nuclear binding energy.
And the energy of the neutron
and the proton is not the sum,
or the mass is not the
sum of the neutron plus the proton,
but it's the neutron plus
the proton minus the binding energy.
Here you might say,
why doesn't this happen?
The proton just go off and the neutron decay.
And the answer is that there
wasn't enough energy to begin with.
Because there was all of this negative binding energy,
which was enough.
The binding energy of nuclei is very small.
It's not very big.
But the available energy was small to begin with.
So the neutron,
when it binds to the proton,
becomes stable because it just
doesn't have enough energy to decay.
So,
yeah.
Are neutrons created,
or are the number of
neutrons in the universe constantly decreasing?
Decreasing?
Yeah,
it's probably constantly decreasing.
But,
yeah,
if a neutron gets knocked out of a nucleus somehow,
then it will decay.
So,
for example,
cosmic rays don't have neutrons in them.
Why don't they have neutrons in them?
Because the neutron decays before,
what does it become?
It becomes a proton and an electron and so forth.
So,
yeah.
I guess it's probably fair to
say the number of neutrons is decreasing.
Where do they come from?
Nuclei.
But I mean,
the Big Bang.
Well,
actually,
I take it back.
There is a source of creation of neutrons,
and it's a big source of creation.
It's neutron stars.
Neutron stars.
When a star collapses,
it can become very dense and...
チョコレート
hydrogen burns into helium in the sun?
Yeah,
yeah,
there's nuclear reactions which,
there are nuclear reactions which,
right,
yeah,
I take it back.
It's probably not true that the number of neutrons
is decreasing,
probably increasing because of what you say.
Okay,
if we're finished.
Thank you.