Stanford University.
Let's review a little bit and
then I want to move on to
generalizations of what we've talked about so far.
I think we worked out
the equations of an expanding universe.
There were Newton's equations.
Let's talk about something else first.
Does Newton's equations really get it right?
Yeah,
Newton's equations does get it right for the most part.
And let me explain why.
Einstein's equations have to do with curved space-time.
Now,
the universe that we're ultimately
going to study has curved space-time
all right,
and in fact,
some versions of it even have curved space.
That's simply because it's a curved space.
So,
curved space basically means that space itself,
forget space-time,
just space itself,
if you measure triangles on it,
if you do various kinds of geometric exercises on it,
you'll discover perhaps that space is curved.
At the moment,
it looks pretty flat,
but it's possible that it will turn
out on the average to be curved.
And if it is curved,
well,
maybe it looks like a three-dimensional version,
let's say,
of a sphere.
Well,
we're going to study later,
not tonight,
maybe partly tonight,
that's a portion of a sphere.
That's a portion of a sphere.
We're over here.
We look out.
We can only see so much.
We can't even really see that the sphere is curved.
Okay?
But at a large enough distance,
we may be able to
see that the sphere is curved.
On the other hand,
supposing we just decide to look at very nature-like things.
Very neighboring galaxies.
Now,
very neighboring galaxies can mean
a billion light-years from us now.
Very,
very neighboring galaxies,
much smaller than what we think the
radius of curvature of this universe is.
Well,
then it looks flat.
And if it looks flat,
it should mean that at least for that portion,
if we're not interested in the whole thing,
but we're just interested in the local,
nearby behavior,
we should not have to worry about that.
We should not have to worry
about the fact that it's curved.
If that's correct,
then it means that the way
these galaxies move relative to each other
and how they move apart from each other,
at least in the small here,
can be studied using Newton's equations.
That's what we've been doing.
We've been looking at the universe in the small
and studying how a small little fraction
of it is expanding or not expanding,
whatever it's doing.
And it's perfectly legitimate and
in fact entirely consistent with Einstein,
with relativity,
except for one thing.
Except for one thing.
We would run into trouble if
the galaxies or whatever is present,
galaxies,
particles,
whatever is present,
if they were really moving past each other
with a significant fraction of the speed of light.
One of the assumptions is that,
the neighboring things are moving relatively
slowly with respect to each other.
Something very,
very far away may be moving
with a large velocity relative to you,
but as long as the things
nearby are moving with non-relativistic velocities,
relative to you,
you can take a small patch of it,
now small could mean 10 billion light years,
but you can take a small patch of it,
and study it without using any relativity really.
If we discover that there are particles
moving with close to the speed of light,
past each other,
then of course we will have to modify the equations.
But there are particles moving fast by
comparison with the speed of light past us.
What are they?
Neutrinos.
Well,
neutrinos for one,
but photons.
Now I don't mean photons from the sun,
I mean photons that would be
there even if there was no sun.
The universe is filled in the
same way that it's filled with galaxies,
it's also filled with radiation,
homogeneous radiation.
And that homogeneous radiation does
move with the speed of light.
That means that we have to modify our equations somehow
to account for this very,
very fastly moving,
rapidly moving material,
photons.
We're going to do that tonight.
But I want to just review
what we did last time quickly.
We first of all said,
suppose that space is homogeneous and filled with galaxies,
and I'm not going to
try to draw all the galaxies.
They form a gas,
if you like,
that kind of fill the blackboard,
with a certain number of particles.
And that number of particles is
a number of particles per cubic meter.
In other words,
a density.
A density that we called rho.
And that was the content of
the universe in kilograms per cubic meter,
if you like.
You could use some other units,
but whatever units you like.
Physical units,
kilograms per cubic meter.
And we called it rho.
We laid down a grid on this universe.
And laying down the grid,
there was clear ambiguity.
Imagine that we laid down
the grid at some specific time,
like today.
We laid down the grid,
and you could ask,
what is the spacing between the grid,
was a coordinate system,
let's call the coordinates x,
and the distance between x equals
something and x equals something plus one.
In other words,
one grid separation here,
one lattice separation,
is a certain distance associated with it.
How big is that distance?
Well,
we called it A.
But how big is A?
That depends on the grid that we laid down.
If we laid down a very coarse grid,
it would be one thing.
If we laid down a fine grid,
it would be another thing.
And so it had better be that our equations,
at least at the moment,
do not prefer any specific value of A.
We could lay down a different grid.
The different grid could be twice as dense.
So here's the black forms one grid,
and the black and green together form another grid.
If we looked at the more dense grid,
we would also invent an A,
let's call it A prime.
A prime is the distance between
neighboring points on the dense grid.
That would be one half A.
So if you ask me,
what is the value of A,
I'm going to say,
I can't tell you until I
know precisely what grid is laid down.
And so A itself doesn't have a physical meaning,
at least at this stage.
Later on,
we'll discuss more what A means.
But at the moment,
on a flat blackboard,
it doesn't mean anything by itself,
until you specify exactly what
the size of the grid is.
Okay,
so A is just a sort of bookkeeping device.
On the other hand,
ratios of A may mean something.
Let me give you an example.
Supposing I told you,
now A is a function of time.
The universe is expanding.
The distance between neighboring galaxies,
the galaxies are embedded in the grid,
they move with the grid.
The actual physical distance between galaxies is growing.
Okay.
Supposing I told you that over a period of time,
A doubled.
That has meaning.
That means the distance between every galaxy,
every pair of galaxies doubles.
So ratios of A,
particularly ratios of A at different times,
are recording a history of how
the universe is expanding or contracting.
And that's why our equations tend to
only involve ratios of things with A.
Let me give you an example.
Let's take A dot,
the time derivative of A.
Well,
that will depend on whether I use
the black grid or the black-green grid.
Every A associated with the
black grid is twice as big
as every A associated with the black-green grid.
And if every A is twice as big,
A dot,
the time derivative,
will also be twice as big.
On the other hand,
if I take A dot divided by A,
and let's compare it with A prime dot
divided by A prime,
they will be the same.
They will be the same
because the ambiguity in the scale
of the grid will cancel out.
A prime will be a half A,
A dot prime will be a half A dot,
you know what I mean,
and the factor of two will just cancel out.
So things involving ratios of A,
those are invariant,
physically meaningful things,
and if you remember,
A dot over A is just
the Hubble constant at a given time.
So it really does mean something.
But A itself,
an ambiguity in how big it is,
but it's a once and for all ambiguity,
once you fix it,
then you stick with it.
Okay,
another thing which is ambiguous
was we introduced a constant nu.
Remember what nu was?
Nu was the mass contained within a single cubic cell
of the grid.
In other words,
a grid element here,
one by one by one by one.
Well,
one what?
One grid unit.
The amount of mass within that cube,
which we called nu,
is ambiguous because we haven't figured,
we haven't determined exactly what the grid is.
Nevertheless,
once the grid is fixed,
nevertheless,
the amount of mass within a single cube
is called nu.
But it also changes when you change the grid.
Now let's go to the
equations that we derived last time.
The equations we derived last time,
I'll just remind you how we derived them.
We took the universe filled with galaxies,
we called them particles,
uniformly,
and we placed ourselves right at the center,
arbitrarily,
but still consistently.
We placed ourselves at the center,
looked at another galaxy,
which was at a specific location on the grid.
Some x,
some x on the grid,
and we studied Newton's equations
for the motion of that galaxy,
which you would think would be horrendously complicated,
horrendously complicated because they're interacting with
loads and loads of galaxies.
But we used the famous theorem of Newton.
Well,
first of all,
we imagined smoothing things out
and then we used the theorem of Newton.
So that we could think of
the distribution of these galaxies as smooth,
smooth and uniform.
We took a sphere,
centered at the center,
centered at us,
excuse me,
and we used Newton's theorem
that told us that relative to us,
in the coordinate system where we are at rest,
the force on that galaxy
only depends on the mass within that sphere.
As if all of the
mass were concentrated at the center.
So,
we just said,
let's concentrate all the mass
within that sphere at the center
and then study how under such circumstances
the galaxy at x would move
if it were under the influence of just that mass.
You don't have to worry
about the masses on the outside,
you only have to worry
about the masses on the inside,
and we worked it out.
And the simple way that we worked it out,
the simplest way we worked it out,
was just to say,
if there was a particle over here
moving under the influence of
a fictitious mass at the center,
then the energy of that particle would be conserved.
The energy consisted of two terms.
Well,
I think I'll,
yeah,
let me come back to the derivation again.
I just want to review the derivation very quickly,
but I'll come back to it in a moment.
Let me remind you what the equation was.
The equation that was derived
was that a dot over a squared,
that came from the kinetic energy,
was equal to
the density of matter,
rho,
measured in physical units,
in other words,
measured in kilograms per cubic meter,
not this new object over here,
but rho,
and there was a little more.
There was an eight,
a pi,
and a g,
g Newton.
That was the equation that we derived
by just looking at the conservation of energy.
Rho,
oops,
yeah,
rho,
oh,
sorry,
you didn't catch me,
over three.
That three ultimately came from the volume of a sphere,
four-thirds pi r cubed.
Okay,
that's where the three,
that's where the four,
the eight is two times four.
Pi,
pi is pi,
and three is three.
This is related to the volume of some sphere.
Okay,
that was the equation that we worked out.
That was in the case of zero energy.
That was in the case where
the potential energy of this point
and the kinetic energy of it exactly canceled.
It could also be understood as the situation
where every galaxy is exactly at the escape velocity,
just on the knife edge between
being able to escape and not escape.
That's what that formula was.
We added one more thing to it,
and the one more thing is we said that rho,
rho,
which is the amount of mass,
it's the amount of mass per unit volume,
is related to nu.
Is it the same as nu?
No,
because nu is the amount of mass per grid box.
But the grid box,
you don't know what its volume is.
This is the mass within one cube.
If you want the density,
then the density is related to nu,
by dividing nu by the
volume of one of these boxes.
This is density per cubic meter.
This is per cubic box.
You divide that by the volume of a box,
which is a cubed,
and that's one more fact that we put in,
that rho is nu divided by a cubed.
Now,
is rho constant with time?
No,
because a changes,
but it's a constant with time.
But is nu constant with time?
If nu just represents ordinary particles
sitting in the universe,
which are never destroyed,
never created,
particles of protons,
let's forget whether the proton decays for the moment,
protons are forever,
and galaxies are forever for a moment,
not forever,
we won't believe that forever,
but we will believe for the moment,
that galaxies are forever.
Did you get that?
Yeah,
okay.
If galaxies were forever,
or protons were forever,
then nu would be constant.
The number of protons within a box
is the same at all times.
All that happens is the box grows.
So the protons thin out,
but the number of them in a box stays fixed,
and so nu stays constant.
What is it?
What is its numerical value?
I can't tell you what the numerical value is,
because that has to do with
the exact grid that I use.
If I change grids,
I change nu.
Okay,
so but in any case,
once I've established all of the conventions,
I can replace rho
by nu divided by a cubed.
Nu is a constant.
It doesn't change with time.
8 is a constant.
Pi is a constant.
3 is a constant.
g is a constant.
All of these are constant.
All of this stuff here
is just a numerical constant.
In fact,
by judiciously
changing your definition of the grid,
since changing the grid changes the magnitude of nu,
I can,
if I like,
choose 8 pi g nu
over 3 to just be 1.
It doesn't make any difference.
The point here is that the numerical constant
that appears here
really doesn't make any big difference
to the way the universe evolves.
And the way you can
see that is by changing definitions
of the grid,
you can change the constant.
So we could,
if we like,
just set 8 pi g
nu over 3 equal to 1,
and then we would have a very nice differential equation.
a dot over a squared
is equal to 1 over a cubed.
Now,
would you like to see how to solve that?
We solved it last time,
but we solved it by guessing.
How many people want to see
me solve it in real time?
I know when you want to
see me solve it in real time
because you're hoping I'll make a mistake.
Yeah,
you were going to ask a question.
Okay.
Well,
it's too bad.
I'm going to solve it whether
you want me to or not.
Here's the way you solve it.
Here's the way you solve all these equations.
You first of all take
the square root of both sides.
On the left side,
that's easy.
It's just a dot over a.
On the right-hand side,
it's a little bit of a nuisance.
It's 1 over a times square root of a.
Do you see where that came from?
a cubed is a squared squared.
Times a,
the square root of it is a,
times the square root of a.
Okay.
Let's multiply both sides by a to
get rid of it in the denominator.
And that just tells us that a dot
is 1 divided by the square root of a.
That's where we would like to begin.
Okay,
now.
We're going to write this dA by dt,
which is what it is,
is equal to 1 over square root of a.
But now we're going to do something tricky.
The very tricky thing we're going to do
is instead of thinking of
a as a function of time,
we're going to think of
time as a function of a.
We're going to take a to be the independent variable.
And to do that,
here is dA dt.
That looks like a is a function of time
and we're differentiating it.
But if I turn it upside down,
meaning taking 1 over it,
it's dt dA.
And now it looks like it's the derivative of time
with respect to a.
And that's equal to the square root of a.
So how do we solve it?
We look for a function of a
whose derivative is the square root of a.
What function has as its derivative
the square root of a?
8 to the 3 halves,
right?
Well,
2 thirds 8 to the 3 halves.
So we find out that
t is equal to 2 thirds.
The 2 thirds is absorbed into other constants
that we've been ignoring.
Times a to the 3 halves.
Alright,
we can solve that now.
What we really wanted was
a is a function of time,
but that's easy.
If we just neglect the 2 thirds,
I just don't feel like writing it.
To get the 2 thirds,
this tells us that a is equal to t
to the 2 thirds.
a is equal to 2 thirds,
t to the 2 thirds,
which is a function a t,
which looks like that.
And it gets flatter and flatter and flatter.
The flattening of it is deceleration.
The universe is decelerating,
but it never comes to rest.
We could see that it never comes to rest,
because when we look at this equation,
there is no point at which
a dot over a becomes 0.
How do I know it doesn't become 0?
Because the right-hand side is never 0.
It gets smaller and smaller
as a gets bigger and bigger,
but it never goes to 0.
And that's why the universe decelerates.
Another way to see that it decelerates,
it's just a particle moving
away from a fixed force center.
It will decelerate because of
the attraction by the force center.
And that was,
that was lesson number one.
I redid it because,
well,
I always think it's worthwhile
redoing the most important derivations.
It's okay if we throw away the negative square root?
Yes,
it's okay to throw away the negative square root.
What's the logic?
The logic from the equation,
you cannot tell whether the
universe is expanding or contracting.
Both are the same.
Both are possible from the equation.
If you start,
it's exactly the same deal
as saying you have a planet over here.
Yeah,
coffee is a good planet.
And the almond here is a rock.
And you see the rock is right over here.
The equations of Newton will not tell you
whether the rock is moving away
or whether it's moving toward.
There's one thing you can be sure of.
Let's ignore for the moment moving in orbit.
Let's assume we know that the rock is moving radially.
There's one thing we know for sure,
that it's not standing still.
It may be momentarily at rest.
It might have come up and stopped,
but it's not going to stand still.
It's accelerating.
It's accelerating back toward the planet.
Okay?
So it could be going out and decelerating,
or it could be going in.
You can't tell from the equation.
In the same way,
you can't tell from the equation
whether it's expanding or contracting,
and that has to do with the two possible solutions
whether the ADT is positive or negative.
If it's contracting,
it's negative.
If it's expanding,
it's positive.
Okay.
Excuse me.
All of these objects are kind of moving radially
with respect to each other.
Of course,
I think of all these objects out there,
they're all kind of spinning around each other.
Okay,
so that's right.
But still,
on the average,
they tend to move as if
they were embedded in this grid.
Given that they are embedded in the grid,
the only option they have is
to move radially relative to each other.
Now,
you're perfectly right.
There are motions on top of that average motion.
The motions are not moving.
The motions on top of the average motion
don't,
of course,
satisfy this.
They're called,
by astronomers,
peculiar motion,
meaning,
I don't know,
are they peculiar?
Well,
I don't know.
The Earth moves around the Sun,
and the Earth is not participating
in this expansion relative to the Sun,
but if you go a few galaxies over,
the whole thing is.
So,
the real motion of real galaxies
is a combination of this average flow.
Think of it as a flow,
a river going downstream.
How fast is any given molecule moving?
Well,
I don't know how fast any given molecule is moving,
but I do know on the average
that clumps of molecules sufficiently averaged
are moving with whatever the velocity of the river is.
On top of that,
there's the peculiar motion
of the molecules relative to each other.
So that's the way to think about it.
A flow,
and on top of the flow,
fluctuation.
And we're ignoring the fluctuation at the moment.
Okay.
There's two directions I want to expand it,
well,
not expand,
there's two directions I want to generalize in today.
The first,
well,
probably the first,
but probably the second.
The second will have to do with what happens
if you replace massive particles,
galaxies or protons and so forth,
by photons,
by radiation.
How does this whole story look different?
If there was a universe,
a fictitious universe,
which had nothing in it but photons,
how different would this be?
Now,
why am I doing that?
What a silly thing to do.
Why take a fictitious universe
which is only made of photons?
Well,
what we're going to find,
is that early on in the history of the universe,
the most important thing in the universe was photons.
Today the most,
and when I say most important,
I mean the largest concentrations of energy.
Early on,
the most concentrated,
the biggest form of energy in the universe was radiation.
Today,
the most dominant form of energy in the universe
is just the masses of particles,
E equals mc squared kind of thing.
That's what this theory is about.
It's about the behavior of massive particles,
non-relativistic,
slowly moving particles.
Yeah?
I thought today it was dark energy.
That's also presumably made of particles
that are pretty much standing still.
Oh,
oh,
oh.
30 years ago we would have said that,
we're still 30 years back.
We're still 30 years back.
Or 25 years back or something like that.
You're right.
Good,
good,
good.
Yes.
But dark matter,
by contrast,
is part of this story.
So,
yes.
Thank you.
That was helpful.
Yeah.
What I'm telling you now is an old story.
But it's a story whose basics are important to us.
Okay,
two directions I want to go.
The first has to do
with what happens if the universe
is made out of other kinds of stuff,
other than just particles more or less
irrestriably relative to each other.
Well,
radiation in particular.
And the other is to move beyond the assumption
that the energy is zero.
There was no reason for that.
It was arbitrary.
We said arbitrarily,
let's assume that every galaxy
is moving away with exactly the escape velocity.
Let's back off that now.
And how do we back off it?
We go back to the energy equations
and say,
the energy of that particle moving in the fictitious field
not the fictitious field,
but the field of the
fictitious concentrated mass at the center.
This is not a real galaxy now.
This is the combined mass
of everything within the green sphere.
So,
we have a particle out here,
moving outward,
and let's apply the conservation of energy to it.
Let's go back through the derivation,
apply the conservation of energy,
and then see how the equations change
when we go away from the limit of zero energy.
Okay,
so what is the energy of this particle?
This whole glob here has mass m.
We'll come back to what m is in a moment.
But it has mass m.
It's not the mass of the sun,
and it's not the mass of any specific galaxy.
It's the mass of everything in the sphere.
Okay.
And the energy of this
fellow over here is one-half m.
m is the mass of this fellow,
not the big mass in here,
the mass of this galaxy,
times its velocity squared.
That's one term.
And then the other term is minus,
uh,
m g over the distance between them.
Let's call the distance d as we did last time.
Oops,
I missed something,
didn't I?
Another factor of little m,
right?
Right.
Product of the masses,
Newton's constant,
distance between them.
That's the energy of this particle moving out.
And what do we know about it?
We know that it doesn't change with time.
It doesn't change with time because our model,
that's a useful model,
is just the motion of a
particle in a fixed background of mass.
The energy is constant,
and so let's set the energy
to be equal to some constant.
Now what does constant mean?
Does it mean a numerical
constant that's independent of everything else?
No,
it doesn't.
It could depend on which particle we're talking about.
Could.
In fact,
if the universe is homogeneous and isotropic,
the only real thing it could
depend on is the distance away.
So,
I'll simplify the discussion for now
by taking this particle to be at x equals 1.
Let's,
in other words,
we're going to take a specific particle,
a very definite one,
at x equals 1 and focus on it.
It has some specific energy,
and that energy will never change,
so let's just call it E,
and it's a constant.
What value of the constant?
I don't know.
I can't tell you offhand.
No more than I can tell you
if I know that there's a nut over here,
and there's a planet over here,
there's no way I can tell you a priori
what the energy of that particle is.
I don't know how fast it's moving.
All right?
So we have to study all possible cases.
So we just put the energy and call it E
and take it to be a constant,
a numerical constant.
Let's write out now everything.
Let's divide this.
Let's first of all divide it by m,
little m.
Let's divide by little m,
divide by little m,
and then over here we get E over m.
Now,
E is a constant.
M is a constant.
E over m is a constant,
so I really haven't made it any more complicated
by dividing by m.
I'll leave it here as E over m,
but the right-hand side is just a numerical constant.
Let's even do a little more.
Let's multiply by 2.
It's still just a constant,
and since I didn't tell you
in the beginning what E was,
all I know is that this is a constant.
So let's,
well,
let's leave it that way.
Now,
what about the velocity?
If this is the galaxy at x equals 1,
then its velocity,
well,
its distance,
the distance is a times x.
The velocity is a dot times x.
And so now we can just plug that in here,
and x is 1.
I've chosen x to be 1,
so it's very simple.
The distance of the galaxy
is just the scale factor a,
it's called the scale factor,
and its velocity is just a dot.
So let's plug it in here.
This just says a dot squared
minus 2mg over d,
and d is a,
is equal to some constant.
Now I'm just going to call it c,
constant on the right-hand side.
This has many of the elements of this equation here,
but this equation,
this nice equation,
we divided by a twice to
get a dot over a squared.
Why did I do that?
Because I knew in the back of my head
that a itself is not a meaningful thing.
It's only ratios of a's.
So in the back of my head,
I knew that what I really
want to get is an equation
for ratios of a's,
or a dot divided by a.
So I divided this equation,
by a squared.
A cubed.
Notice something's happened on the right-hand side here.
It's no longer a constant.
c is still a constant,
but a squared now has something new in it.
And finally,
we used,
that the mass
divided by the volume cubed,
now this is a sphere.
This is a sphere of radius a,
x is equal to one,
a sphere of radius a,
and the volume of a sphere of radius a,
is four-thirds pi a cubed.
So I have a cubed down here,
that's not quite the volume of the sphere.
Let's fix it so that it
is the volume of the sphere.
Let's multiply,
well,
I don't want to botch up this equation too much.
Let's rewrite it.
a dot over a squared,
minus twice mg over a cubed,
is equal to a constant over a squared.
But now,
let's multiply and divide by four-thirds pi.
So this is four pi over three,
and we have to multiply out here by four-thirds pi.
That becomes eight-thirds pi.
That's where our eight-thirds pi came from.
Okay,
four-thirds pi a cubed over three,
that is the volume of the sphere.
And what is the mass divided by the volume?
The density.
So,
by fiddling around,
I got the Friedmann equation,
but with a right-hand side now.
A right-hand side that knows about the total energy.
If c is positive,
it meant the total energy was positive,
it meant the kinetic energy outweighed the potential.
Sounds like,
and it does,
means that the galaxies are
going to continue to recede forever.
You've beaten the escape velocity.
If c is negative,
then the energy is negative,
more potential energy,
more negative potential energy than kinetic energy,
and that's the situation where you
expect everything to go out of ways
and then come back and crash.
So,
we now have a new equation,
the Friedmann equation for non-zero energy.
The energy can be positive or negative.
Positive or negative,
both are allowed,
total energy.
And we're going to write it down.
And let's examine it a little bit
and see if we can see
a little bit what it says.
It's not too hard to solve for any given case,
but let's not solve it.
Oh!
One other step.
Let's write it over here.
a dot over a squared.
And let's transpose this factor to the other side.
Equals,
equals,
eight-thirds pi g
times rho,
but rho is nu divided by a cubed.
Remember nu?
Nu was the mass per unit cell size.
Nu over a cubed,
that's rho.
And there's g.
Oh,
g is there.
Plus c over a squared.
This is the new thing.
c over a squared is the new thing.
So we have a new thing that was not here
in our initial study of this equation.
What does it do?
All right,
so
let's look at it first.
This is the real Friedmann equation
with this other term on the right-hand side.
And it was derived from general relativity,
not from special relativity.
Sorry,
not from Newton.
But nevertheless,
we just derived it from Newton.
Good.
Okay,
so here we are.
Let's see what these things mean.
Let's assume for the moment
that the universe continues to grow.
If c is positive,
if c is positive,
and everything else on the right-hand side is positive,
a,
pi,
g,
nu,
a cubed,
they're all positive,
then the right-hand side is strictly positive,
and a dot over a is positive.
In other words,
the universe continues to grow.
If a dot is positive,
and a is positive,
if a dot,
the time derivative of a,
is positive,
the universe continues to grow forever.
It may slow down and slow down,
but it will continue to grow,
or at least it won't contract,
and it will continue to grow.
So,
if c is positive,
the universe will continue to expand,
it will eventually get arbitrarily big,
a,
by arbitrarily big,
I mean that a will eventually exceed any bound
and become very large.
So let's look at it in the limit
that a becomes much larger,
very,
very large.
Excuse me,
why does,
I mean,
why does a dot over a have to be positive?
the square root of it,
obviously,
has to be positive.
Right.
The square of it is,
that's right,
good.
The square of it has to be positive.
So let's assume that initially it is positive,
that the universe starts out expanding.
Okay?
Then the only way it
can ever get to be negative
is if it goes through zero.
And it can't go through zero
if the right-hand side is positive.
Good.
So that's a good point.
Uh,
the right-hand side being permanently positive
disallows this from being zero,
and therefore it can only continue to grow.
Can't jump from positive to negative
without going through zero,
and this is never zero.
Okay.
Now,
which term here is bigger?
One over a squared or one over a cubed?
Well,
that depends on whether a is big or small.
All right.
But in particular,
let's go and think about
very large L's.
Let's start with small a first.
For a being small,
which is bigger,
one over a cubed or one over a squared?
One over a cubed.
Uh,
if you take a to be small enough,
this will always beat this,
and so for a sufficiently small a,
this is negligible compared to this.
We've already studied the case
with...
out this,
and we know the answer.
We know the answer as long as a is small,
in other words,
in the very early phases
of the expansion,
when a is just starting out growing,
it's just beginning to grow,
this term is not important.
And what do we find?
We found out when the term was absent
that a expands like t to the two-thirds.
But now let's go to the other limit.
This is a standard way of thinking about
all kinds of things go to limits.
Often an equation...
This is...
This equation is solvable,
incidentally,
but it's nasty.
We don't have to solve it.
We just have to know what it's doing
at the two ends.
The two ends mean when a is very small
and when a is very big.
Okay,
so what about when a is very big?
Which term is big?
This term is the biggest term when a is big.
One over a squared is much,
much bigger
than one over a cubed.
You may have to wait a while,
and how long you have to wait
may depend on this constant here,
but eventually this term will become much larger.
So let's study that equation.
Let's study the equation a dot over a squared
is equal to some constant,
any constant,
over a squared.
We first take the square root of it.
And what's the square root of a constant?
Another constant.
So I won't change its name,
but it's really...
This new c here is the
square root of the old c.
And of course,
the reason I'm allowed to do that
is because it doesn't matter what the constant is here.
We'll get an answer which is qualitatively
the same for every c.
All right,
a dot over a is c over a.
Now let's multiply by a.
Okay.
A dot is a constant.
A dot is the velocity of the galaxy
at x equals one.
In other words,
in the situation where the energy is positive,
when the galaxy gets far enough away,
the effect of gravity becomes negligible,
and it just moves off with uniform velocity.
That's what this is saying.
A dot is just constant.
And that tells us that
a is just proportional to time.
The constant c times time.
The galaxy just moves off with uniform velocity.
And so that tells us this is for positive c,
for positive constant.
c is not the speed of light here,
incidentally,
although it happens to be a velocity.
All right.
So it tells us that at a late time,
this just moves as a straight line
with constant slope.
A dot is just a slope,
moves with constant slope,
and the universe just expands with linear
and unaccelerated,
non-accelerated motion.
Nothing as deep is going on here.
Hmm.
Why am I using nuts
when I should be using apples?
All this is saying is if
you throw this up hard enough
so that it escapes from gravity with a good margin,
with a margin,
then it will just move off uniformly with constant velocity.
So,
in fact,
we find that.
We find exactly that.
What happens in between?
Where's the crossover point?
Well,
I'll leave that to you.
You can figure out approximately
where the crossover point is.
It goes as eight to the,
T to the two-thirds,
and then makes a transition to just T
and sort of fuzzy in between.
That's the matter-dominated universe.
Why is it called the matter-dominated universe?
Uh,
because the right-hand side
of this equation contains a term
which is just the density of ordinary matter.
Ordinary non-relativistic,
slowly moving matter.
That's it.
Okay,
so,
oh,
well,
let's go to the other case.
What happens if C is negative?
That's the case of negative energy.
Now you should be able to guess.
A particle or the apple moving away from the Earth
with,
uh,
um,
less than escape velocity
has negative energy and it just falls back down,
huh?
So,
that's actually not hard to work out.
I'm just gonna tell you what happens.
What,
what happens,
first of all,
then you have a negative sign here.
You have a negative sign here,
and now the right-hand side can become zero.
Initially,
this is the biggest term.
At a late time,
this is the biggest term,
but they have opposite sign.
That means somewhere in between,
this became zero.
That is nothing but the point
where the,
uh,
the up-going apple
simply is momentarily at rest
when A dot over A is zero.
Hmm,
hmm,
hmm.
Hmm?
Okay.
So with C negative,
there's a crossover,
and
instead of moving off linearly like this,
bang,
crash.
Everything falls together.
That's the matter-dominated universe,
and it was a classic cosmology
until,
um,
until other things were discovered.
Okay.
Any other questions?
Any questions?
There must be,
you know,
my assumption when I get no questions
is either I was perfectly clear or perfectly...
Yeah?
I'm trying to understand this.
So at some point,
um,
uh,
those two terms are canceling each other.
You get A prime over A
squared equals zero,
but the other side always has to be non-negative,
so...
Which does?
The right-hand side always has to be non-negative.
No,
it's gonna become negative.
How can it be negative?
A prime over A squared has
to be equal to that thing.
Say that again?
Your left-hand side
has always got to be non-negative.
Hence your right-hand side always has to be non-negative.
Well,
you have to take a square root.
Pardon?
You have to take a square root.
Square root can have a part...
Well,
you can take a square root.
Just that equation there says that that right-hand side...
Since the left-hand side is always non-negative,
then the right-hand side is always non-negative.
Sure,
it could be zero.
Yeah.
So...
But that's because...
I'm just wondering what happens if it becomes zero,
then it might become positive
again or stay zero or something.
No,
I made an assumption that...
that,
um,
that the universe was expanding.
And that breaks down at the
point where it comes to rest.
The mathematics is entirely identical to this here.
The,
uh...
What would you write?
You would write 1 half mv squared...
is equal to g m over the distance...
Am I missing anything?
...times the mass of the Earth...
Uh...
No.
Minus this...
is equal to the energy.
If the energy is negative,
let's call it minus here...
then...
this is plus g m m over r.
Basically,
or...
over distance.
It's the same equation.
Um...
How does it happen...
if the,
uh...
if E is negative...
then there can be a crossover point.
It's the same...
exactly the same thing.
Exactly the same thing.
And you know what happens.
You know that the,
uh...
that the,
apple just falls back down to Earth.
It's just a question of taking the root...
the v...
there's a plus root and a
minus root of a square root.
Yeah.
But...
But what do we assume is...
a third of r...
E...
whatever over...
a cubed has to be...
greater than or equal to c over a squared.
Otherwise,
something squared goes negative,
which is mathematically impossible.
You say this has to be bigger than this?
Or equal.
It's in that,
yeah.
Hmm.
I think that's what he means.
The point is,
a can never get big enough...
uh...
to turn into a...
I'm assuming the sign of this.
A can never get big enough...
Let's see.
If a is big,
then this term is bigger,
and it will go negative.
But it never does get negative.
No,
no,
okay,
good.
The right-hand side never gets negative.
You're right.
The right-hand side can never get negative.
All that tells you
is there's an upper bound on how big a gets.
Right.
A gets so big,
and then stops getting bigger,
and comes back down.
A is always in a region
where this is positive,
but it goes through zero.
Going through zero is just coming to rest
and falling back down.
Okay.
Right.
And on the way back down,
you have to take the negative root.
a dot over a is negative square root.
Good.
All right.
Yes.
Okay,
so that's...
that is the matter of the equation.
We have a dominated universe,
three possibilities,
positive energy,
negative energy,
or zero energy,
and three different behaviors.
Who decides whether the energy
is positive or negative?
Who knows?
But we're going to find out
that the connection
of that positiveness or negativeness
is connected with the geometry
of the universe.
Not tonight.
Next time,
we'll talk about
the connection with this constant c
with the spatial geometry
of the universe.
That's what...
That's the main thing at this stage
that general relativity
brought to bear on this.
The equations are exactly the same,
but the significance of this constant c
takes on a new dimension
and has to do with geometry,
but not tonight.
One more thing we're going to do tonight.
We're going to take up the question of
what happens
if instead of being made
out of material points
slowly moving,
what happens if the universe
is made out of photons,
made out of radiation?
All right,
to understand that,
of course,
we really do have to think
about relativity,
but really there's only one important idea,
and it's just E equals mc squared.
If we were to have done
Einstein's equations,
the right-hand side
of Einstein's equations here,
of the left,
basically...
All right,
let's...
I'll tell you what the connection
with Einstein's equations is.
On the left,
we have a dot over a squared,
and then I'm going to add
plus c over a squared,
transpose it to the left,
and on the right-hand side,
good old 8 pi over 3 g rho,
nu over a cubed or just rho.
Now,
this is mass density here,
but Einstein's equations
are of the form that something
on the left having to do
with geometry
is equal on the right side
to things that have to do
with the density of energy
and momentum.
Energy-momentum tensor
on the right-hand side,
geometry on the left.
This clearly has to do
with geometry,
the rate at which
the universe is expanding.
I'm going to tell you next time
that c over here has to do
with the curvature of space.
So this side here
is Einstein's geometric side.
The right-hand side is the source,
namely the energy,
momentum,
whatever it is in the universe.
What is the energy on the right-hand side
of this equation?
It's just the mass points
and E equals mc squared.
So,
oh my goodness,
I'm calling this c,
but please don't get the idea
that it's the speed of light.
It's sometimes called
kappa minus c,
it's sometimes actually written
minus kappa.
Unfortunately,
kappa is positive
when the energy is negative,
and kappa is negative
when the energy is positive.
But it's often called kappa.
Okay,
that's the basic connection
with the general theory
of relativity,
but the only thing that we really
need to do to this equation
is to remember that when you go
from Newton to Newton,
to relativity,
what was mass density
becomes energy density.
All forms of energy density,
all forms of energy density
are what go on the right-hand side here.
Well,
it's energy density
times the speed of light squared.
Is that right?
m,
no,
m is E over c squared.
So it's energy density
divided by c squared,
which goes on here.
We'll just set c equal to one.
We're not going to worry about
the speed of light.
Speed of light c is equal to one.
With that idea in mind,
the right-hand side,
instead of being the mass density,
becomes the energy density,
total energy density,
some of which is just
the E equals mc squared energy
of the particles at rest,
and some of it might be
kinetic energy of particles,
which we haven't really included
at this point,
the kinetic energy of
a relative fast motion of them.
But if the universe is filled with photons,
then it's radiation energy.
All right,
so let's talk about
radiation energy
and how it's different
from the E equals mc squared energy.
All we have to do is think about a box.
A box now,
the box,
the box just corresponds to a unit cube
in the grid here.
Take one unit cube of the grid.
It has a volume of a cubed.
Let's suppose it has a certain number
of photons in it.
Now,
photons have a wavelength,
so here's our box.
It's delta x equals one
on each side.
Its volume is a cubed.
The ordinary particles,
which are just sitting in that box
and not moving,
they have an energy
which is just their mass.
It doesn't change.
Their energy doesn't change
those particles.
They're just their mass
and nothing else.
But a photon behaves differently.
So I'll tell you how a photon behaves.
The first thing to know about a photon
or electromagnetic radiation,
first thing to know about a photon
is that its energy
is related to its wavelength.
It's related to its wavelength
to Planck's constant,
h.
What else?
Lambda,
the wavelength,
and the speed of light,
which I'll set equal to one.
Important thing is that it's
one over the wavelength.
So,
what's the wavelength?
Now,
something which I am not going to prove,
but I'm going to tell you,
is that if you take a box
with a photon in it of a given wavelength,
let's say you have a photon
of a given wavelength,
and you expand the box,
you expand the box slowly,
for example,
and the universe is expanding pretty slowly,
takes 10 billion years for it to double in size,
it's pretty slow.
You take a box,
and you expand the box slowly,
then what happens to the photons inside it?
What happens is the photons inside
is their wavelength just stretches
in proportion with the box.
Now,
this phenomenon,
anybody who plays a guitar
knows the phenomenon very well.
The box is replaced,
here's the string of the guitar,
it's pinned down at one end,
at the bridge over there.
At the other end,
it's pinned down by your finger
at the fret,
and you pluck it,
it starts to vibrate,
and then if you slide your finger,
what happens is you slide your finger,
you're effectively changing the size of the box.
This is changing the size of the box,
you change the size of the box,
the wavelength just changes,
and the tone,
the note changes
in correspondence with the change
in the size of the box.
The same thing happens to radiation in a box.
Radiation in a box,
the wavelengths just stretch in proportion
to the size of the box.
Because the wavelengths change for the photons,
that means the energy of each photon changes
as you change the size of the box.
The world is filled up with photons,
you can pretend that each of the photons,
the number of photons in each box stays fixed,
that's a true statement,
the number of photons stays fixed,
but their energy changes
as you change the size of the box.
In particular,
the energy of each photon
will be proportional
to one divided
by the size of the box.
So we take one box,
change the scale factor,
then the energy of each photon decreases.
Same phenomena as the frequency going down or up
as you change the length,
the effective length of the guitar string.
So what does that mean?
Yeah?
That makes sense if the box is conducting
and the electric field has to go to zero,
then that makes sense,
but you don't have conducting boxes in space.
Don't you get the same thing
if you have free space expanding?
Get the same result.
One way I've thought about it is,
like if you had mirrors,
this box may have mirrors,
the mirrors move away and get its operative shift
when the photon goes back.
That's one way to think about it.
Last week you said that the expanding universe
is sort of a mathematical artifact
and that you can just take a particle...
I never used the word artifact.
You did.
But you agree with me.
It depends on what your conclusion is.
Okay.
Well,
that's what I'm trying to understand is
that clearly there's something more going on
where the wavelength wouldn't change.
Yeah.
That's right.
Okay.
Now...
We'd have to do a little more quantum mechanics
or a little more classical electromagnetism
in the presence of an expanding universe
to justify what I said.
Let's take it for the moment as a given,
and we can come back to it.
The answer is a correct statement,
that...
And let me see if
I can think of an example.
Offhand,
I can't think of a good practical example
where something similar happens,
but nevertheless,
it is true
that the radiation in the box,
the wavelengths of the photons,
readjust themselves to the sizes of the box.
In other words,
the photons stretch along with the universe.
If you like,
you can just think of the space stretching,
and with it,
the photon wavelength stretches.
Let's leave it at that for tonight.
For tonight,
let's leave it at that.
Let's just examine the consequences of it.
Um...
Let's examine the consequences of it.
The consequences of it is...
is that the energy per photon
decreases like one over A,
in contrast to the case with ordinary particles
where their mass stays the same and doesn't vary.
So,
by contrast with the particle case,
ordinary particle case,
the energy in the box,
the mass in the box,
effective energy or mass,
does not stay constant,
but it decreases...
total energy in the box decreases
like one over the scale factor.
Every photon,
its energy decreases when it gets stretched,
so every single one of them,
and so compared with the previous case,
there's one more factor
of A in the denominator.
The energy in the box
goes like one over A,
and the energy density,
goes like one over A to the fourth
instead of one over A cubed.
Remember previously,
the,
uh,
the density here,
we said was some constant nu
divided by A cubed.
Now we get one more
factor of A in the denominator,
and it's just the fact that every particle,
its energy decreases by one extra power of A.
That means,
relative to the previous case,
there's an extra A in the denominator.
Nu could be taken now to
be the number of photons per unit,
or in a box,
and the energy would be
one over A to the fourth.
That's the only nu thing that happens.
This is matter dominated,
and this is radiation.
A dot over A,
squared,
again,
eight pi over three,
G,
some constant nu,
and then A to the fourth,
downstairs.
We can also put in this term here,
minus C over A squared,
but let's study the case when,
the case that corresponded to zero energy,
just to see the difference.
To see the difference.
Let's see what different behavior we get
with this formula.
This formula says,
again,
by appropriate choice of the size of the grid,
you can make all the constants here,
if you like,
be one.
By appropriate choice of the size of the grid,
you can rearrange it so that it's just
A dot over A,
squared,
is one divided by A to the fourth.
What was it before,
do you remember?
One over A cubed.
Okay.
So let's see if we can figure out what happens.
Again,
we're going to solve the equation now.
We're going to go through
the steps of solving the equation.
First take the square root.
A dot over A equals one over A squared.
That means that A dot is just one over A,
right?
Did I do that right?
That's dA dt.
Alright.
We'll do the same trick as before,
turn it upside down.
dT by dA is equal to A.
So now,
if we think of A as the independent variable,
we're looking for a function whose derivative is just A.
What function has its derivative A?
A squared,
right?
Yeah.
So what function has its derivative A?
A squared.
One half A squared,
to be exact.
So that says that T is like A squared.
Maybe there's a one half here,
but that's not important.
The thing is that T varies like A squared,
or that the scale factor varies like T
to the one half square root of A.
Well,
I'm not much of an artist,
and I can't really draw the
difference between T to the two thirds
and T to the one half.
There's T to the two thirds.
T to the one half is a little bit smaller,
huh?
Doesn't grow as fast.
So T to the...
But it looks pretty similar.
And does pretty much the same thing.
You have to be an astronomer
who are really interested in this
to care about the difference
between T to the one half.
By that I mean,
you know,
they're sufficiently similar,
qualitatively similar.
But if you really want to
know what's going on in the universe,
the difference between T to the one half
and T to the two thirds can be very important.
Okay,
so that's the radiation-dominated universe.
The radiation-dominated universe expands like
the square root of T.
Not T to the three halves.
T to the two thirds.
T to the two thirds
and T to the one half.
What about the mixed case?
Supposing the universe has
both ordinary particles and radiation,
like the real universe really does.
Let's worry about that.
Let's come to that.
The mixed case.
Neither pure radiation nor pure non-relativistic particles.
In that case,
the energy density is two components.
One for radiation,
that goes like one over A to the fourth.
And one for ordinary matter that
goes like one over A cubed.
So the kind of equation that we're going to have,
I'm not going to write the details,
I'm going to write down the general form of it,
will be A dot over A squared.
And that's going to have two terms now.
One of which,
call it constant non-linear,
number one divided by A cubed.
That's ordinary particles.
Constant C1 is just some measure
of the number in each box.
And then another term,
and they're both positive.
The energy of particles and
the energy of photons is positive.
And the other is some other
constant over A to the fourth.
That's the equation of motion for a universe which contains,
like our real universe does,
ordinary non-relativistic matter plus radiation.
Which one is more important?
One over A cubed or
one over A to the fourth?
Depends on A.
Right.
When A is big,
which one is more important?
This one.
Excuse me.
My mother always told me not to
take such big bites from the apple.
For small a,
this is the more important.
And the smaller the A is,
the more,
more important it is.
When A is big,
this is the more important.
And again.
Swamps,
the other term,
when A is really big.
So what that tells us,
without too much work,
is that when A is small,
in the beginning of the expansion,
the only thing that's important is the radiation.
This one.
The radiation term is dominant compared to the material.
Protons,
neutrons,
galaxies.
There were no galaxies at the beginning,
but the...
And...
The radiation was the most important thing.
And so the universe started expanding
like T to the one half.
But then,
eventually,
this term took over,
became the more important term,
and it made a switch.
Let me get another color.
It made a switch.
And started to grow like T to the two thirds.
Are you assuming that the proportions
of radiation and matter remain constant?
Yes.
That's correct.
And you might say,
well,
how do you know that energy of
matter doesn't get converted to energy of radiation?
That's something we're going to have to discuss.
The answer is,
when the...
When things get cold enough,
when the universe expands enough,
things cool down,
and there's not much exchange
between radiation and ordinary matter.
And they are pretty well conserved,
each one separately.
They don't talk to each other too much.
In fact,
once things cool down to a certain temperature,
that's a rather high temperature,
one in a thousand degrees,
or more than a thousand degrees,
ten thousand degrees,
but once things cool down to a certain temperature,
pretty much the photons are just free-streaming
and don't care much about the particles,
and the photons are too long wavelength
to even scatter the particles very much.
So that's right.
That's exactly right.
That we've assumed that the two
constants here are pretty much time independent.
All right.
That's the nature of a universe built of two components.
Now,
that's only two components.
That's only two components.
And there is a third component.
There is a third component.
It's the discovered dark energy.
That's what we're going to talk about next time.
We have ordinary matter.
We have radiation.
Those are commonplace things.
Dark matter belongs to the matter category.
It's simply a part of the ordinary particle matter
that's invisible simply because it doesn't have any charge.
It doesn't radiate much.
So we don't see it optically.
That's part of C1.
This should be C2 here.
I meant to write C2.
Or maybe we should call it Cm
for matter and C radiation for radiation.
There's more than one component to the radiation.
There's photons.
There's presumably gravitons.
And there are neutrinos.
Now,
neutrinos have mass.
But the mass is so tiny that even today the neutrinos are moving with very
close to the speed of light and simply mimic the same behavior as the photons.
So there's a radiation component.
The radiation component consists of all particles which are so
light that they're moving with close to the speed of light.
The C1 or the C mass here consists of all particles which
are heavy enough that they're basically at rest relative to us nearby.
And that's cosmology sort of as
it was known 30 years ago.
This is the cosmology of 30 years ago.
Yeah,
Mark.
So in that box that's expanding and
the wavelength of the wave is stretching out,
the total energy inside the box is decreasing.
Where is that energy going?
The energy is doing what?
Decreasing.
Decreasing,
yeah.
Where is it going?
Doing work on the walls to expand it.
Well,
another way to say it is
it's going into the kinetic energy,
the kinetic energy of expansion.
This equation is,
remember what it was.
It was the equation of conservation of energy.
That's where it came from.
So if you think about it that way,
then start tracing.
If this part of the energy decreases,
then,
or let's put it this way.
Let's write the equation in a different form.
Let's put a minus sign over here.
Well,
let's first,
one step at a time,
put minus,
and make it equal to zero.
I haven't changed anything.
Now change the sign of the whole thing.
Minus,
plus,
plus.
This equation reads the following way.
That there's a certain amount
of energy and mass and radiation.
If it changes with time,
that energy gets transferred to a negative term.
What's a little bit bizarre is that the
energy associated with the kinetic energy of expansion,
the kinetic energy of expansion,
this term here is negative.
This can be read as a conservation of energy.
It can be read,
energy never changes because it's always zero.
It contains three terms,
matter,
radiation,
and a term that has to do
with the rate of change of expansion.
Normally in the ordinary world,
where,
when the rate of expansion,
the rate of expansion is very,
very small.
It's a tiny,
tiny number.
This here is a tiny,
tiny number in our world at the present time,
a tiny number.
This never changes very much.
And so,
it's not zero.
I take it back.
This is not a tiny number.
It's a number,
but it doesn't change much over a course of time.
The sum of these two is,
well,
it's a number.
It's zero,
and it stays zero.
That's the conservation of energy.
Am I saying that right?
I'm not saying it right.
Yeah.
The conservation of energy is a symmetry with time,
when you think about it
in terms of the Northward charge.
Would the fact that A is time dependent
sort of excuse you from conservation of energy?
There's two ways to think about it.
You could say the universe is a
time dependent background that everything moves in,
and because the universe is time dependent,
that means all of your equations have a time dependence.
There is no longer a time translation symmetry,
and energy doesn't have to be conserved.
The other way to say it
is that there's a time translation symmetry.
If you start the universe at this time
or that time or that time or that time,
you get exactly the same response.
If you start the universe at t equals minus seven,
it would be exactly the same as
starting the universe at t equals plus four.
And thinking about it that way,
you'll discover there's another term in
the energy associated with the expansion rate.
Let's not go into it now.
This is very,
very subtle,
and I want to spend at
least 15 minutes on it later.
Energy conservation.
But just to keep in mind that these equations,
their origin was energy conservation,
so there's no way that
we can be violating energy conservation.
Yeah?
You said that Freeman equations are interesting
because you can derive them
through Newtonian mechanics or general relativity.
Newtonian mechanics presupposes a flat geometry,
and relativity assumes a curved geometry.
A geometry of space.
Forget space-time for a minute.
Ah,
okay.
All right.
We'll go about geometry of space.
Einstein's equations permit flat space.
These are,
okay.
Would that mean that space is flat
because you can derive it from either,
not space-time,
but just space?
Would that be a conclusion?
Those are equations.
I think you raised it.
Yeah.
Okay.
Minus some kappa over a squared,
okay?
This had to do with the total energy,
the fixed total energy.
If kappa is positive in this equation,
the energy is negative.
If the kappa is negative,
the energy is positive.
Sorry,
it goes this way.
Kappa is minus the energy,
essentially.
Do I have it right?
No,
I have it wrong.
Okay.
It doesn't matter.
One way or the other.
This term over here has to
do with the curvature of space.
So we're going to study three cases.
There are three interesting geometries
that we'll be interested in.
There's a flat geometry where space itself is flat.
This goes on and on endlessly,
homogeneously,
and triangles have the usual properties.
That's the case k equals zero.
There's the case where the
universe is curved like a sphere.
So if you go around it,
you come out the other side,
you go around it.
Finite and compact.
So if you go around it,
you come out the other side,
you come out the other side.
That's the case k equals positive.
Any positive number here corresponds
to a radius of curvature
of the expanding universe.
Expands like a balloon.
You know,
the classic picture of the expanding balloon.
That's k equals positive.
k equals negative is a negatively curved space.
And we're going to have to talk
about what a negatively curved space is like.
Less easy to visualize than the sphere.
So the next time,
it's exactly what we're going to do.
We're going to talk about the geometry of space
and the three cases.
Flat,
positively curved,
and negatively curved.
They correspond to k being zero,
positive,
or negative.
So would that mean then that in the Newtonian case,
k has to be zero?
Well,
except that you can sort of mimic up
the case with k not being
equal to zero if you want,
but it's a little bit of a fake.
Yeah.
A little bit.
Yeah,
OK.
Right.
Question.
A box full of photons where the box is expanding
and the number of photons stays the same,
the energy would be going down with that box.
What happens?
Where does that energy go?
You may answer that question,
but I don't understand.
Where does that energy go?
It does work on the box.
Take a literal box.
A literal box with reflecting walls.
Take a box with reflecting walls and ask what happens
to the energy in the
box when you expand the walls.
OK.
Well,
what does happen?
There's pressure in the box.
There's pressure exerted by the
photons bouncing off the box.
The pressure,
when you expand the box,
does work on the walls of the box.
For a real box,
the energy could go to a number of places.
They could go to stretching the
distance between the molecules in the box.
It could go into making kinetic
energy of the walls of the box.
But one way or another,
it does work on the box
and increases the energy of the box itself,
either by stretching the little hookslaw
springs that are inside the box
that hold the molecules together,
or causing the box to have a kinetic energy,
kinetic energy of expansion,
or whatever else,
just heating the box.
Just heating the box.
So that energy has to be going into space,
into the grid,
right?
You said the grid is actually absorbing energy,
is that correct?
Yeah,
in a sense,
that's right.
Yeah.
Right,
we'll talk about that.
We'll talk about energy conservation more clearly.
Right,
but it's still,
it's a correct thing to analyze it.
This is not obvious,
but it's correct.
It's correct to analyze it as
if it were stuff in a box.
And the stuff that gets reflected off here
from a real box with reflecting walls
is compensated for in the fake box case
by every particle which goes across here
is approximately compensated for by a particle
which comes in the other side.
So on the average,
the expanding space behaves like an expanding box.
Particles,
instead of reflecting,
go from one box to the other,
but on the average,
as many particles go from this box to this box,
as from that box to this box.
And so in a sense,
it can be mocked up
by saying that the particles reflect off the box.
Increasing the size of the box
means that work is done against the walls,
and we'll have to talk about what that means
in general relativity when we come to it.
Yeah.
A couple questions.
One,
how soon after the Big Bang
did the universe cool down to where the matter
and radiation components were not really interacting?
How long did it take to change the heat?
About 100,000 years.
And then the second one was,
what astronomical evidence do we have
to see the T to the 1 half behavior?
What do I have to say again?
What evidence do we have to observe
the T to the 1 half expansion behavior?
Is that in the cosmic microwave background?
That's the expansion history.
That's the expansion history of the universe.
And remember that looking out at the universe,
you effectively see a history.
Looking to different distances,
you're seeing the universe at different times.
So by looking at the universe at different times,
assuming that it's homogeneous,
you can reconstruct the history of expansion.
We'll talk about that.
That's something that we can do.
Basically by looking at the combination
of density of galaxies on the sky,
distance of galaxies,
and we'll spend a little
bit of time going through that,
the combination of careful measurements
of distance,
density,
and so forth
allows us to reconstruct the history.
And we can reconstruct the history
because we're seeing it at different times.
It seems like the two of us
I mean,
the one half behavior
would be before galaxies formed?
Indeed.
But we can still infer it.
Wouldn't that be sensitive to the big bang
nuclear synthesis?
I mean,
wouldn't we be off on those calculations
if it didn't do T?
You bet.
Yeah,
yeah.
And,
you know,
combining it with CMB
and all of those things,
yeah.
Yeah,
it was before galaxies formed,
but in the temperature history
of the universe,
there's plenty of evidence
that this picture is right.
No,
you're right.
The T to the two thirds is easy to see.
The T to the one half
largely has to do with microwave background
and things like that.
Get the equations down,
and then we'll go and talk about
how we know how much of this picture is right.
And the answer is we know it's wrong.
Yeah.
Okay,
yeah.
So I think that this isn't a problem
but I don't understand why.
I can't hear you.
I said I think that this is not a problem
but I don't understand why.
Okay.
The apparent speed of an object
relative to any observer
is a function of how far away it is.
Yeah.
So conceptually it seems like
an object far enough away
could appear to be exceeding
the speed of light.
But I don't think,
that doesn't violate this idea
that nothing can exceed the speed of light,
but I don't understand why.
Well,
you have to ask what it really says,
what the principle that things can
or can't exceed the speed of light.
What it literally says is
you can't see anything going past you
faster than the speed of light.
It doesn't say that two objects
in an expanding universe
can't be receding from each other
at faster than the speed of light.
That is quite allowed.
And as you point out,
that if you have a formula which says
velocity is equal to distance
times the Hubble constant,
and you make the distance big enough,
the velocity will,
sure enough,
exceed the speed of light.
It's connected with the idea of a horizon.
But you're right.
These equations say that things can move,
recede from each other
at faster than the speed of light.
But for sure,
they don't allow you to send signals
in time faster than the speed of light
to get from one place to another.
And they don't allow you to work.
You have to witness something
moving past you faster than the speed of light.
So,
it's...
Right.
Does this mean that objects
sort of at the limit,
right before where the expansion rate
exceeds the speed of light,
eventually disappear?
In a sense,
if you know what I mean.
Yes,
they'll pass through the horizon
and we won't see them.
Right.
But that has to do with dark energy.
Oh,
that has to do with dark energy.
Without dark energy,
nothing would really move out of our ability to see.
Right.
I will show you how the geometry works,
and I will show you how all these things
can be understood.
But little steps.
Good.
Okay.
Professor.
Yes.
Is the beginning of the universe
said that we will never see
more of the universe,
no matter how long we wait
than we do today?
Is that related to the fact that
objects far enough away
are receding at a speed faster than...
would appear to be traveling faster
than the speed of light?
It's more than that.
It's the accelerated expansion
of the universe.
That is true.
That is true,
but the universe will slow down.
No,
sorry,
excuse me.
If this picture were right,
and the universe were to slow down,
then things which are currently moving
away from us faster than this picture
with a speed of light
would in the future be moving away
from us with less than the speed of light.
And at that point,
they would become visible.
So if this were the pattern,
eventually we could see everything
no matter how far away.
Okay.
This is not the pattern.
The pattern is that.
And if this pattern is correct,
then there will be,
then there is an ultimate limitation
that you cannot see past a certain point.
But let's hold back on that.
We're going to spend a lot of time
on those particular things.
Those are the really interesting things,
and we'll explore them.
The way I've always thought about the question
of why would the...
when the box expands,
the radiation,
the protons lose energy,
is that there's a wave phenomenon going on.
The wavelengths increase.
Is there a way to think about it?
That the wavelength increases.
Yes.
Yes?
So the energy of the photons
is decreasing because the wavelength...
That is correct.
The question is,
why do you have to suppose
that as the universe expands
that the wavelength of a photon
will match it?
Why is the wavelength of a photon
sort of rigidly attached
to the grid,
if you like?
That's the question.
Why is the wavelength of the photon
somehow rigidly attached to the...
to the...
to the grid?
Now anybody who knows a little bit about waves
and wave propagation
knows that there's
what's called an adiabatic invariant.
The adiabatic invariant is the number of nodes,
the number of times the wave
passes through zero.
And as long as you change things slowly,
the number of nodes stays fixed.
This is called an adiabatic invariant.
And if we had a...
some sort of closed circle
that waves could propagate on,
this is something in principle we could build.
And we have waves propagating on it.
And somehow we...
well,
I was trying to think of an example.
I couldn't think of one.
I still can't think of one.
But imagine we have a dial
that allows us to change the radius
of this ring here
that things are propagating on.
In other words,
change the circumference of it.
Changing the circumference of it
will not change the number of nodes.
You might ask yourself,
how could it change the number of nodes?
Suddenly?
I mean,
we're gonna expand...
we're gonna change the radius
gradually or continuously.
At what point would you expect...
here,
how many nodes are here?
About 10 or something like that?
You know what...
everybody know what a node means?
Number of times that the wave goes to zero.
It has to be integer.
For one thing,
it has to be integer.
The wave going around...
a standing wave.
Let's take a standing wave for simplicity.
A standing wave on here
has to go around and be periodic.
So the number of nodes
has to be an integer.
Now you start stretching the space
that it's propagating on.
It can't suddenly jump.
At what point is it gonna jump
from seven nodes to eight nodes?
It doesn't jump.
What it does is the waves
just get longer wavelength
and shorter wavelength
to match the thing that it's on.
It's the same phenomenon
except replace this ring
by the universe itself.
Number of nodes,
number of zeros is invariant,
never changes,
and the only way that can be accommodated
is if the wavelength of the photon increases,
wavelength of the wave increases.
Now,
any wave,
even if it's not a nice thing like this,
let's suppose it's just a lump over here
and then nothing,
and nothing over here.
By Fourier analysis,
it can still be expanded
in waves that have this nice periodic smooth structure.
Each one of them,
each one of them has a number of nodes
which is fixed,
and so that's good enough for us.
The individual waves of definite wavelength
can't jump the number of nodes,
and so instead,
the wavelength has to accommodate
the size of the thing that it's propagating on.
Yeah?
Yeah,
as you look out in the universe
and galaxies move faster and faster,
relativity says the mass of them relative to us
would,
as things move faster and faster,
correct?
The energy,
the energy.
The energy.
Yeah.
Okay.
The kinetic energy.
If you were to weigh it,
it would weigh more.
Well,
you can't weigh something that's far enough away.
No,
no,
no.
It's important.
But go ahead.
Yeah,
I think you may have answered my question,
but assuming you can,
it grows continuously,
at some point it goes
exactly at the speed of light,
which means the mass must be zero?
Intonate.
Mass.
No,
oh,
sorry.
Yeah,
the momentum.
Mass is a thing that never changes.
Yeah.
Mass never changes.
Mass of the electron is always whatever it is.
Yeah,
I think what it means
is the question itself is silly,
because you can't talk about the mass,
you have to talk about the energy and the momentum.
You have to talk about the energy.
Okay.
So from a naive perspective,
if mass goes from really,
really a lot to zero,
since particles are so small,
things with mass can't go at the speed of light.
But as you just said,
that is not the way of thinking about it.
No,
no,
that's not the way of thinking about it.
Yeah,
I understand.
Well,
look,
to do,
yeah,
okay.
Things move faster than light,
wouldn't the time and space,
I mean.
What's that?
Time and space actually get,
it gets interchanged,
right?
I mean,
how does that thing work out?
How does which thing work out?
I mean,
you just said you think
that things move faster than light,
but if the far away
stuff moves faster than the light,
then at that place,
what we see as a,
I mean,
what we refer to as a space,
what time axis of the place is.
Why don't we wait?
We're going to talk a great
deal about horizons and the geometry.
We cannot,
the point is we cannot analyze those kinds of questions
and,
and by just thinking in terms
of Newtonian or even special relativistic geometry,
we have to analyze them by saying there's a metric,
that there's a geometry,
and we have to analyze that geometry.
And we will do that.
We will do that.
We can just,
we can go only so far without introducing real relativity.
So far we've been okay.
We didn't have to introduce relativity.
And the reason we haven't been okay,
why is because we stuck to a small enough region.
All these equations were derived by
looking at galaxies which did not
have to be very far away.
We follow some galaxies
which are reasonably close,
and we follow them.
If they're close enough,
they'll be
moving with a very tiny
fraction of the speed of light.
So that's what we did.
We followed
things which were close enough that they
never got anywhere near the speed of light.
If we
want to study the whole universe and out to distances,
out to distances where the Hubble
constant times the distance is
comparable to the speed of light,
if we want to study
the universe on that scale,
then we can't do it without relativity,
and we really can't
do it without general relativity.
Subtitles by the Amara.org community
Right?
So you're jumping ahead of the game
and trying to get there thinking only about
Newton,
Newton and special relativity.
Coming back to the energy of the photon,
just by stretching the wavelength,
how does it decrease the energy of a single photon?
It's more the density that is decreased,
right?
What's that?
Say it again.
If you stretch the wavelength,
you said that the energy of an individual photon decreased.
All that happened was that the
energy is spread over a longer wavelength.
No.
The energy itself decreases,
and the easiest example is to think about
the photon in the box or the violin string.
The photon in the box exerts
pressure on the walls of the box.
because it exerts pressure on the walls of the box,
it does work on the box as it expands.
The work is the pressure times the change in volume,
and that's equal to the
change in energy of the photon.
So the photon is doing work on the box,
and in doing work on the box,
its own energy is decreasing.
Look,
this is also true incidentally.
Forget photons.
Just take ordinary particles,
a gas and a box.
What happens to the temperature in
this box if you increase the volume?
Down.
What does that mean about
the kinetic energy of each particle?
It goes down.
If you do it adiabatically or what?
If you do it infinitesimally slow.
Hmm?
If you do it infinitesimally slow,
it doesn't go down.
it does or does not?
It does not.
It does.
Yeah.
If you do it very,
very suddenly,
what will happen?
If you do it suddenly,
here's the molecules,
okay?
And you absolutely instantaneously suddenly
increase the volume of the box.
What you find is a big empty space.
The molecules are still in the original volume here,
and nothing has changed,
their energy,
their momentum,
or nothing else.
That's the non-adiabatic case.
The adiabatic case means you increase it slowly,
and slowly means there's plenty of time for
molecules to bounce off the walls many times.
Then it will cool.
If you do things suddenly,
it's likely to heat.
Even if you expand or contract,
if you do things really suddenly,
it's likely to heat.
Or at least not cool.
But if you increase the volume of the box slowly,
then it will cool.
Isn't the whole redshift the
same as this wavelength increasing?
Mm-hmm.
The scale?
It's connected,
yeah.
It is connected.
But it's a phenomenon that doesn't
particularly have to do with photons.
It simply has to do with pressure against the wall,
and increasing the box means that work is done
by the pressure on the walls of the box,
and to conserve energy,
it has to cool.
So this is the phenomenon of the photons cooling.
Okay.
Good.
I just wanted to è and subscribe to this
channel and check out get thành phนน Modern которая
Because in data science you have
kind of the general perception that yellสν