Stanford University.
Okay,
let's come to some observational facts,
or connections between observational
facts and the equations.
It's impossible to really give any
kind of justice to the observational facts
without putting them into a
context of the fundamental cosmological equations.
So let's begin with them.
We've already begun with them,
but let's begin with
them again and define some observational quantities,
quantities which astronomers
can and do observe.
All right,
the basic equation,
as always,
at least for a homogeneous universe,
is the
Friedman equation,
a dot over a squared,
and that we can also give another name.
We can call it the Hubble constant squared,
or the Hubble,
somebody suggested that we
call it the Hubble function,
since it depends on time,
and that's
fine,
you can call it the Hubble function.
And I suppose you could call its value today,
at the present time,
I suppose you could call it the Hubble constant,
keeping in mind that it's not a constant.
But when people quote,
when they quote the
Hubble constant is so many
kilometers per second per megaparsec,
or whatever it is,
they're quoting the value of the Hubble function today.
I'll just say that the Hubble
function is the Hubble constant squared,
and that's fine,
you can call it the Hubble function.
I'll just say that the Hubble
function is the Hubble function today.
If I call it the Hubble constant,
and just forgive me,
I simply mean a dot over a.
This is the Hubble constant squared,
and as we know,
that is equal to good old 8 pi g
over 3 times the energy density minus a term for,
and the usual energy density,
minus a term coming from curvature,
and that curvature term has
a k in front of it.
It's not a constant,
it's a constant.
And so we can conclude that k
is either plus or minus one or zero.
It's never anything but plus or minus one or zero,
positive for a spherical geometry,
negative for the hyperbolic geometry,
and zero for the flat geometry,
divided by a squared.
The role of a is to go into the metric.
Over here I'll write the metric.
Well I think we need
a little more room for it.
I'll write the metric.
The connection between A and the metric is that the metric dS squared
is equal to minus dt squared plus the radius at time t squared.
And now I'm going to use a bracket,
dr squared,
and then what goes in addition?
An angular piece,
and the angular piece is one of three possibilities,
depending on k.
The first one would be flat space.
Let's take the case of flat space,
that's k equals zero.
Then this would be r squared d omega two squared,
the two sphere of the sky.
What about k equals plus one,
what do we put there?
Anybody remember?
Sine of r squared.
So this could be sine of r squared,
or if it's negatively curved,
hyperbolic sine of squared.
So let's give it,
instead of writing three separate equations,
let's just call it xi squared of r,
where xi squared,
where xi has the following meaning.
xi is equal to sine of r.
When k is equal to plus one.
xi is equal to hyperbolic sine of r.
When k is equal to minus one.
And xi is equal to r
when k is equal to zero.
That makes one simple formula,
and we just have to remember which one we're using.
Three different spatial geometries,
and an equation of motion for A.
That's our basic...
Okay.
All right,
now the energy density
can come from various sources.
The actual only sources that we
really know in the current universe are
of three kinds.
There are three contributions to rho.
And...
rho
appears,
as far as we can tell,
to have only three main important contributions.
The first is radiation.
And radiation
energy density is some constant,
representing the amount,
the number of photons per unit volume,
or the number of units of energy per unit volume,
today.
Divided by A to the fourth.
Then there's another contribution
associated with ordinary particles,
non-relativistic particles.
We usually call that matter.
And that's divided by A cubed.
Then there's the possibility of vacuum energy.
Let's actually put here eight pi
g or...
over three.
And continue to use the right-hand
side the way I've written it.
Then,
the vacuum energy would be times lambda,
the cosmological constant.
That does not dilute with increasing radius.
That's it.
But let's add in,
to rho,
let's add in minus k over A squared.
Minus k over A squared.
Plus this,
in other words,
let's include this over here as part of rho.
And then we will put in
here minus k over A squared.
I'm not sure why I did that.
Why did I?
Well,
yeah,
that's okay.
We can do it.
Um,
yeah.
Okay.
That's this.
And what is this equal to?
It's equal to H squared.
So,
that's this.
And what is this equal to?
It's equal to H squared.
Now,
think about this equation today,
at the present time.
This says that a certain set of four
quantities has to add up to H squared.
That's a constraint.
That a certain set of four quantities
has to add up to H squared.
And we can ask,
how much do we,
how much,
today,
present,
in the present universe,
how much
of adding up to the right-hand side of the equation,
comes from radiation,
how much comes from matter,
how much comes from dark energy,
lambda,
and how much is left over in this curvature term?
That's a reasonable question.
The scale factor today is some number.
We're going to talk about it in a little while,
how big it is.
But it's some number,
and each one of these terms has some value.
And H has some value.
How do we measure these terms?
Let's think about how we measure them for the moment,
or how we might measure them if we could.
H is the Hubble constant.
Hubble measured the Hubble constant.
What he did was he measured the relation between velocities
as determined from redshifts.
We'll go back to redshifts in a little while.
He determined velocities as a function of distance.
How did he get distance?
Velocities from redshift,
how do you get distance?
That's the invariable.
Luminosity,
brightness.
A distant bulb looks dimmer than a close bulb.
So it was basically redshift
versus luminosity that he plotted.
And he measured the Hubble constant.
The fact that he mismeasured
it by a factor of 10,
that was not the important thing.
And that's true.
He did mismeasure it by a factor of 10.
But in principle,
with better measurements.
And these were not cosmological measurements,
incidentally.
By cosmological,
I mean measurements taking place on a scale
of tens of billions of light years.
These were measurements of our local properties
of a few clusters of galaxies.
And so they did not
penetrate back deep into the past.
For his purposes,
since they weren't penetrating back deep into the past,
the Hubble constant was a constant.
He wasn't looking at it at different times.
He was looking at it now.
Well,
slightly,
not quite now.
But not too bad.
So,
yeah.
This is a strong question.
How do we know these
things all have the same brightness?
It seems like there's a
kind of catch-22 or something there.
Yeah.
There's the whole story of the cosmic distance ladder.
And how...
And it's a story of
many different little pieces overlapping...
Overlapping...
You know,
how do you measure the distance to the nearest stars?
You do it by parallax.
And then you find certain stars
that always behave in a particular kind of way,
called Cepheid variables.
They behave in a certain very definite way,
and they have a very,
very definite relation
between their period and their luminosity.
And that you determine
from stars which are close enough
that you can get the distance to them from parallax.
Those were in the Milky Way.
For sure they were in the Milky Way.
And that gave you a candle,
a standard candle to work with,
the Cepheid variables.
You could then apply it to more distant things.
And you worked your way up a ladder.
Supernovae are...
The best standard candles.
And we're going to talk about that.
We're going to talk about that.
And of course velocity he measured by redshift.
Velocity by redshift and distance
by a sequence of overlapping standards
that were around.
Let's double check.
Are C sub r and C sub m absolute constants,
independent of time?
Yeah.
They're constants independent of time.
Radiation scales like 1 over a to the fourth.
Matter scales or dilutes like 1 over a cubed.
Vacuum energy doesn't dilute.
And the curvature term,
which you can think of as a kind of energy,
if you like,
an energy of curvature,
scales like 1 over a squared.
Okay.
So Hubble measured h.
We do a better job of measuring h.
But basically you measure h
by measuring the relationship
between distance and velocity
or redshift and luminosity.
But you want to do it...
You don't need to go to very huge,
huge distances to do so.
And therefore you're not looking back deep,
deep,
deep into the past.
And you don't have to
worry too much about age varying.
So Hubble measured this.
Now,
what about C radiation?
Well,
we can actually look at the
amount of radiation in the universe.
Most of it is in the
form of the cosmic microwave background,
which we will come to.
But it's very feeble.
There isn't much energy there in the form of photons.
It's a tiny,
tiny fraction of the other kinds of energies.
And that we know just by measuring the photons
that exist around us.
The black body photons,
the ordinary photons.
And again,
there's nothing terribly cosmological about the measurement.
You don't have to go
very deep into the distant past.
Nor do you have to go very far away.
You have to have a
big enough volume to average over.
But we pretty much know that radiation is today
inessential,
not very important.
OK,
that's not there.
Matter?
Well,
what do we know about matter?
We look at the galaxies.
We see how much hydrogen is in them.
We see how much luminosity is coming out of them.
We make studies of stars.
We know a good deal about average stars.
And from the average properties
of stars and interstellar gas
and things which are technical
but not conceptually terribly difficult,
we measure all the matter that we can see.
The luminous matter.
The matter that can be seen.
We add it all up.
And we have a pretty good idea.
As the years go on,
we measure better and better and better
how much luminous matter is out there.
The luminous matter is presumably all
in the form of atoms and protons
and nuclei and electrons.
And we get an estimate of this number here.
That number today,
the density of energy in the universe today
on the average is about one proton per cubic meter.
So it's very low.
But much higher than the radiation energy density.
So one proton per cubic meter is this term.
For the moment,
let's forget about vacuum energy.
We'll come back to it.
And let's ignore it for a moment.
Yeah?
What about the dark matter?
Yes,
yes,
yes.
We're going to come to that.
I'm being slightly hysterical.
Historical.
Slightly historical.
Yeah.
I want to do this with
a bit of history in mind.
This is as it was
when I was a young physicist,
let's say.
C radiation,
negligible.
C matter,
substantial.
Big deal.
One proton per cubic meter.
Nobody believed there was a lambda.
So we forgot lambda.
And then H had been measured.
Incidentally,
the relative ratios of these,
the relative ratios of these today,
the ratios depend on time,
because they scale differently.
But the ratios today are called omega.
So this would,
not the values of these,
but the ratios.
The ratios are omega r,
omega m,
omega lambda,
plus omega curvature.
Omega curvature may be negative.
And the rule is,
these must add up to one,
for the simple reason that their definition
is just the magnitude of them today
divided by H squared today.
In other words,
the omegas are the fraction of H squared today
contained in each one of these terms.
All right,
so as I said,
as a young physicist,
everybody thought that omega r
was equal to essentially zero,
which it is.
Omega matter was what you measure
when you look out and
look at the light coming in.
The stars,
interstellar matter,
and so forth.
Roughly one proton per cubic meter.
Omega lambda,
nobody ever heard of it.
Didn't believe it existed.
Einstein had told us it didn't exist.
And so we then had a situation
where we could compute
and know what omega k was.
Or in other words,
going back to this equation over here,
this term was negligible.
This term was believed not to be negligible.
This was unknown.
And H had been measured.
H had been measured at about,
a factor of roughly 20 or maybe 30
times this over here.
H had been measured pretty well,
and it was too big to
correspond to Cm over A cubed.
In other words,
in other words,
of this one here,
this had not been discovered.
This was negligible.
The omega matter was something like 1 over 20,
maybe 1 over 30,
I'm not sure exactly how big,
roughly 1 over 30.
This was small.
And the only conclusion
was that omega k
was almost equal to 1.
Almost equal to 1
meant that k over A squared,
or minus k over A squared,
had to be close to H squared.
So let's write that down.
k,
well,
we can say what the sign of k is immediately,
right?
The sign of k has to be negative.
That was the first conclusion.
The sign of k is negative.
Open,
infinite universe,
it looked like.
k was negative,
and 1 over A squared
equal to Hubble's measurement of H squared.
Now,
what the...
And why?
Because this just appeared to be too small.
Too small to make up H squared.
The only thing around that was big enough was this.
And that,
in turn,
told us,
or we thought it told us,
how big A is in terms of H.
Now,
H has another meaning,
at least within the context
of matter-dominated universe.
Let's go back to the matter-dominated universe,
which,
after all,
this is what we have here,
and write down the equation for A.
If you remember,
A in the matter-dominated universe
goes like t to the 2 thirds.
For most of the history of the universe,
in fact,
this term is not as important
as the matter term.
1 over A squared for small a,
when the universe was small,
was smaller than this term here.
At late times,
it's true,
this one got bigger,
but at early times,
for most of the history of the universe,
even though the matter was pretty small,
it was still true that this term,
for most of time,
competed favorably with this term.
So this was pretty good.
This was a pretty good approximation.
It fails at late time,
but it's pretty good at early time.
And so let's calculate A dot over A,
A dot over A.
What's A dot?
A dot is the time derivative
of t to the 2 thirds,
which is 2 thirds,
t to the minus 1 third,
and then we divide it by A.
So we divide it by another
t to the minus 2 thirds.
All right,
so we have a time derivative
of t to the minus 1 third,
All together,
A dot over A
is just 2 over 3 t.
So the Hubble constant,
in fact,
we know how the Hubble constant varies with time.
In this model,
in the model of a matter-dominated universe,
the Hubble constant,
we can write this now,
another way to write the Hubble constant,
is it's just 2 divided by 3 t,
and of course it's not a constant.
But we can ask,
what is it today?
This equation was being applied today,
so what is it today?
The Hubble constant today is just equal,
let's call it h today,
is just equal to 2 thirds the time today.
What does the time today mean?
It means the age of the universe.
Let's call it capital T.
Capital T stands for the age of the universe.
In other words,
how long it was
since the universe was very small.
We don't know exactly how small,
but how long since the scale factor
was many orders of magnitude smaller than it is today.
That's what h is.
It's essentially 1 over the age of the universe,
or to be more exact,
it would be 2 thirds
over the age of the universe.
What is the units of t?
Time.
No,
what is the...
Seconds.
Sure.
No,
but it's just 2 thirds.
1 over t,
I mean,
it's...
There must be some speed of light...
No.
No,
no.
The units of the Hubble constant are 1 over time.
But I mean,
time can be years,
hours,
seconds.
That's what I'm asking.
Which time unit is this?
Which time,
which units would you like to use?
Which units would you like to use?
Seconds?
Years.
And this is about 1 over 10 to the 10th.
Doesn't it just depend on what h is?
I mean,
you can define h in whatever units you want.
That's right.
And whatever units you define the age in,
those are the units of h.
If you define it in terms of...
I just realized it has units of time also.
Yeah.
Yeah,
look,
what is the Hubble constant?
It's a relation between velocity and distance.
What is the connection between velocity and distance?
Time.
So the Hubble constant,
even though people...
If you go and you look in
Wikipedia or something for the Hubble constant,
they were quoted as something like
80 kilometers per second per kiloparsec,
something,
something.
I don't remember.
But that's an astronomer's unit.
The astronomers use the unit...
I don't know.
Because it's good for telescopes.
But from our theoretical point of view,
the Hubble constant is just 1
over the age of the universe,
at least for the matter dominated.
Incidentally,
if it was...
Let's suppose it was radiation dominated.
If it were radiation dominated,
in other words,
if there was no matter,
only radiation,
this would be t to the 1 half,
and h today would be 1 over 2t.
So whatever kind of nice equation of state you have,
for most equations of state,
the Hubble constant today is related
to the inverse age of the universe.
That's...
Good.
Okay,
so we know something else from the Hubble constant.
Having measured it,
Hubble knew...
As I said,
he was wrong by a factor of 10.
The Hubble constant too large,
if I remember.
And therefore the universe was too young.
By a factor of 10,
I think he got roughly a billion years.
And the answer is more like 10 billion years.
But that's just from measuring Hubble constant.
Okay.
So...
All right.
Would you defer to one of the other concepts,
or would you just be on your own?
I believe so.
It seems odd,
doesn't it?
The...
As far as I know,
yes.
And as far as I know,
he got it from the measurements.
As far as I know.
I don't know that he
had any deep insight into it.
All right.
So now,
looking at this equation here,
and seeing that this is negligible compared to this,
1 over a squared then is h squared,
and h squared is 1 over
the age of the universe squared.
It's telling us something.
about the size of the universe.
It's telling us the size of the universe is
basically the age of the universe.
Now there is a speed of light in here.
A is
measured in length,
t is measured in time,
and so this is what this is telling you
is that the size of the universe is essentially
وبي
يا
size of the universe
is about equal to the distance light
will travel in the age of the universe
no no no this is not true none of
this is true this is what was expected to be
true
on the basis of cosmology forty years ago
uh...
these equations
with dropping uh...
the various terms that were thought to be
negligible
and as i said
uh...
one ingredient in this
several ingredients
first of all radiation negligible
this true this is true
uh...
matter being
substantial
but still small
only one proton per cubic meter
and only about a twentieth of this side here
and lambda
being as far as anybody knew
was zero was thought to be zero
so that's what went into that
and that's why for all these
years people thought that the universe
that the radius of curvature of the
universe was about equal to its age
something that we no longer think is true
okay
the first
uh...
change
had to do with dark matter
so let's just talk about dark
matter a little bit what uh...
what has to do with
i think probably most of you know
the dark matter story but let's uh...
let's spell it out anyway
ordinary matter
made out of electrically charged particles radiates
it radiates when it's accelerated it radiates when uh...
uh...
when you collide with it
and it's called luminous
because it radiates
it's a kind of matter that we know about
from direct telescopic observation and
it's what went into here
on the other hand
there's another kind of
definition of matter
which is how much it gravitates
what's the mass of matter which gravitates
and of course at first it was thought
that the galaxies were made of luminous matter
and the mass of a galaxy was
just the mass of its luminous matter
uh...
it goes way back I didn't
know how far back it went
it went back to the nineteen thirty two i didn't know
this i thought it was a little bit later than that
1932,
the Dutch astronomer Oort,
I'm not sure how you say his name,
noticed that there were
some things wrong with the way galaxies were behaving.
A year later,
Fritz Zwicky,
who I did know about,
noticed that clusters of galaxies were
misbehaving.
And by misbehaving,
it meant that the gravitational behavior
of them was inappropriate to Newton's
laws,
also Einstein's laws.
Inappropriate to Newton's laws,
and suggested that there simply was more matter out there
than had been accounted for by this.
So I'm going to take you through that.
I think most of you
know the story of dark matter.
Yeah?
When you say luminous matter,
do you include things like diffused gas that
might not be radiating,
but it could if it were under the right circumstances?
Yeah,
yeah.
And how you separate the diffused gas.
Almost everything radiates a little bit.
Almost everything...
Black holes in the center of all the galaxies.
What's that?
The supermassive black holes,
do they amount to very much?
And would we count those as luminous matter?
Yeah,
count them as luminous matter.
Okay.
Now,
how...
And of course,
they're not luminous matter.
They're black holes.
But the point is,
it doesn't matter whether we count
them as luminous matter or not,
because
they're a small fraction.
The galaxy at the center of a black hole...
No,
take that back.
The black hole at the center
of the galaxy is roughly about...
Anywhere between a million and a billion solar masses.
The galaxy is 10 billion...
No,
100 billion solar masses.
And so the black hole content is small.
It's not a major...
And that's not the...
And besides,
it certainly could not be the dark matter,
because it's concentrated at the
center.
Whatever the dark matter is,
I presume it was Oort who first understood,
it is not concentrated
at the center of galaxies.
So let's just go through the argument.
The argument has to do with
the so-called rotation curves of galaxies.
You have a galaxy.
And...
You look at stars.
You look at stars at different radii.
And you look at their tangential velocity,
v.
Let's begin by assuming something which would
follow if all of the matter was luminous.
The fact is that most of the luminous matter
in the galaxy is in the center of the galaxy.
By far,
the majority of the overwhelming majority of the
material is at the center of the galaxy,
at the galactic center.
And so for gravitational purposes,
the outer things in the
outer parts of the galaxy are
moving under the influence of a central force,
where the central force is just the mass near
the center.
Now this turns out to be wrong,
but let's follow the logic of it for a minute.
Let's use Newton's equations,
F equals mA.
The gravitational acceleration due to a
mass at the center would be m.
Because a mass is always
between a wave's and a force's
FIRST CONTROL Можно us bandage
the space around the exponent.
YAH
Buy Pull out at least ten already I did,
won't take much advantage of that.
Buy ducting is probably like nothing else.
You just say,."That's what it's supposed to look like.
Must be more in order for it
to be some kind of cast off.
falls off
like one over r
this is somebody's law,
do you know whose law this is?
this is kepler's law
this is kepler's planetary law
it's usually expressed in terms of
the period rather than the velocity
but this is essentially kepler's planetary law
one of the laws,
which one is it,
the second law?
uh...
whatever it is
telling you how
uh...
the velocity of planets
varies as a function of the radius from the sun
same law here
and in particular it says that the
velocity falls off like one over the
square root of r
velocity falls like one over the square
root of r as you move away
that's not what was seen by ort,
and it's not what's seen by anybody since
now since
we have to all deal with
the idea of a certain number ofowanae
uh...
roughly
or in summary
alpha
Dual
this is a birth
that's one .
this is the webcam
this is theirty
again,
it's very simple
let's say the mass is distributed and
let's say let's introduce a function m
of r.
m of r is the amount of
mass contained within a sphere out to radius
r.
A planet,
not a planet,
a star at distance r moves under the influence not
of a constant mass at the center but
a varying mass which varies like m of r
and in that case let's put back
the equation mg over r squared equals v
squared over r.
Let's multiply it by r and
now say that v is constant.
If v is
constant,
oh we put here now m of
r not just m but m of r.
you
can see that m of r
is the mass of the center.
v is constant,
doesn't change with
distance and therefore we find that
m of r must grow like r.
Just multiply by r,
think of v as a constant,
m of r increases as
you move away from the center.
And so as
you move out,
this is not the mass density incidentally,
this is the total mass with
values of sin .
so ourchan tells us that at the
feet of the planet within a radius r,
apparently increases linearly with r out
to the outer boundaries of
a galaxy and even beyond that.
We see things,
you know,
at the very,
very far edges of galaxies we do
see a stray star here and there and,
this can,
yeah
So the luminous matter,
you know,
is much more dense in the center.
That's right.
But the non-luminous matter seems to sort of magically
adjust for that so that the density,
not the density,
but the mass is a linear function of the radius.
We know,
is there any theory as to why that would be?
Because it seems very neat.
If there is a theory,
I don't know it.
But my guess is that by now,
people
who simulate galaxy formation could probably
tell you that this is not an unnatural thing.
I definitely do not know a simple explanation for it.
So at the moment,
it looks like a piece of luck
that the velocity curve is just flat.
And I don't know a good,
substantial,
simple argument
about why that's the case.
So tell you what,
I'll ask some of my colleagues
if anybody knows.
I know people who work on galaxy formation.
But my guess is by now,
it's a combination
of observational fact and simulation fact.
OK.
So.
So that's the status of galaxies.
The other thing,
incidentally,
is we know that from the motion,
even from the motion of stars perpendicular
to the plane of the galaxies,
that it
looks as if this distribution of mass
is spherical in character rather than conforming
to the odd spiral or flattened shape of galaxies.
Now,
I can tell you for sure.
I do not understand why galaxies have spiral arms
or why they look like flattened disks.
I looked it up more than once.
I've looked it up in various places.
And you get some very complicated explanations.
It's not.
It's apparently not simple.
And it's certainly not that the galaxy is
going around like a pinwheel.
It is not doing that at all.
So what do we know about this document?
I mean,
it electrical mass.
How are we designed laboratory technology
In低氧 and high氧 Nepal Now,
we cannot know whether I
am rotating in a pulling moment
But theellksam
mat stick weird pour natural and
nonsense argument.
And it is roughly a factor
of somewhere between 5 and 10.
And when I say it's
a factor of 5 and 10,
I mean to say that somebody
knows whether it's a 5 or 10,
but I don't.
I always thought it was 10.
I looked it up today,
and it was more like 5.
So let's say 7 times.
But whatever it is,
it's of order of magnitude
10 times larger than the luminous mass.
Now,
why doesn't it collapse?
And it's bigger.
It's bigger in size.
If a galaxy looks like this,
you know,
it's a little pinwheel about that big,
the halo around it is quite a bit bigger.
Why didn't it also fall together
the same way that the luminous,
the luminous mass did?
Well,
the luminous mass fell together,
meaning to say it collapsed in this form,
by losing energy.
It lost energy to radiation,
among other things.
It lost energy to collisions.
What kind of collisions?
Collisions having to do
with electromagnetic forces and things.
And in the process of colliding,
losing energy,
radiating,
it sort of fell into the center to some extent.
So what we need to
expect then about the dark matter
is that whatever it is,
it's much more weakly interacting.
In particular,
it's not electrically charged.
Now,
of course,
if it were electrically charged,
we would see it.
It would radiate.
So it's not electrically charged.
But the fact that it's not electrically charged
and that it is very likely rather weakly interacting,
maybe like neutrinos,
maybe a little stronger than that,
means that these particles that may be in the center,
make up this halo here.
They circulate around.
They may go back and forth this way.
Some of them are going this way.
Some of them are in elliptical orbits.
But they don't interact with each other very much.
And because they don't interact with each other very much
over the period of 10 billion years,
this halo matter has not
collapsed and followed the luminous matter.
So the luminous matter...
There's no question that to some degree,
they do follow each other.
There are no,
as far as I know,
no large lumps of dark matter
that don't have some kind
of luminous matter at the center.
And I don't believe there are
any galaxies out there that are visible
that don't have luminous matter around them.
But it doesn't follow...
They don't follow each other in the detail
that the dark matter has a
shape which looks like a galaxy.
It just looks like a great big sphere.
A halo.
Before he discovered this,
he was interested in looking at galactic clusters.
I think he was looking at clusters.
Galaxies.
Yeah.
That's right.
He was looking at the motion of galaxies in clusters.
That's correct.
Oort was the one who looked at galaxies.
And I understand he was first.
The scale of the...
Good.
So that's right.
So there is evidence for this
kind of thing on multiple scales.
It's not all coming from galaxies.
It's coming from galaxies.
It's coming from interaction between galaxies.
And it's coming from whole galactic clusters.
Yeah.
So when you say that these...
that dark matter is mutually interacting...
It's made out of particles.
Which everybody believes it's made out of particles.
Does it interact...
Are the gravitational laws the same for dark matter?
We sure think so.
Okay.
So in that sense,
like two pieces of dark matter
are going to be attracted with the same forces.
Mm-hmm.
So what do you mean by
the fact that they're weakly interacting?
No electrical forces?
Yeah.
No electrical forces.
No...
Yeah.
The emission of gravitational radiation
by stars and other things moving
in galactic orbits and so forth
is completely negligible on the energy balance.
So radiation of gravitational waves
is not an efficient way to...
for things to lose their energy.
Wouldn't dark matter tend to congregate around black holes
because they do interact gravitationally?
And it does.
It does.
It's very likely that the dark matter,
the...
This was controversial for a while.
I don't think it's controversial anymore
that the galaxies formed
by first the dark matter
collecting in these great big halos
and then the baryons,
the protons,
neutrons,
electrons,
and so forth
falling into the dark matter halos,
that the dark matter,
that the big things were there first
and then the smaller galaxies formed.
They formed stars and probably the...
I don't know how early the black holes formed,
and I don't know if anybody does,
but the black holes may have been consequences
of simply a lot of stars falling together.
So it wasn't that the dark matter
formed around the black holes.
The black holes are a negligible amount
of the mass at the center of the galaxy.
It's that the galaxies formed
as a consequence of the halos of the dark matter.
That's probably the way that it worked.
But would the density of dark matter
be higher near a black hole because of gravity?
Yeah,
it would be somewhat.
Yes,
it would certainly be somewhat.
And would they radiate when they fall?
Yeah.
I mean,
we think that the density...
For example,
we think that the density of dark matter
near the center of the galaxy
is significantly higher than the density of dark matter
away from the galactic center.
And therefore,
people who are looking for,
for example,
radiation coming from the annihilation of dark matter,
two dark matter particles colliding,
annihilating,
forming radiation,
where would you look?
You would look toward the center of the galaxy,
for sure.
So yes,
it's more dense near the center of the galaxy.
Is there any way that we can know
at what level dark matter is aggregated?
Is it gas or is it dust or clods?
It's probably just lonesome particles.
We don't know.
But it's probably just lonesome particles.
What does dust mean?
Dust means assemblages of large numbers of particles
that hold themselves together by what?
By electrostatic forces,
by all the usual things that hold things together.
If those kind of forces existed between those particles,
they would not have survived.
They would not have survived as
these kind of dark matter particles.
So the expectation is that they are simply lonely particles
that are lonely.
If the sun is moving through space through these particles,
What's that?
wouldn't they tend to be trapped in the solar web?
Well,
they were...
Yes,
there's probably some abundance of them
that is somewhere trapped near the sun.
Yeah.
Yeah,
but...
If I combine these two,
it says that velocity is independent of r.
Is that correct?
Yeah.
Velocity is independent of r.
So that says that the angular
frequency goes like one over r.
Yeah.
So doesn't that explain that kind of sequence?
Go look up the spiral arms of galaxies
and try to see if you can decipher the explanation.
Some people think that they're
shock waves of star formation,
shock waves propagating around in circles
and not moving with the galaxy,
incidentally,
not moving with the dark matter.
There's other pictures,
none of which I understand.
Yeah.
Why would you think it's
not one of the standard particles,
like a neutrino or...?
Neutrinos are very light,
and because they would be so light,
they would have to be pretty relativistic
to have that much mass.
And relativistic particles...
Okay,
so one fact about these particles,
which is most important,
is that they cluster.
That they tend to cluster...
that gravitation makes them cluster.
Um...
Things cluster less
when they have high velocity.
If these particles had high velocity,
they would tend to cluster less.
It's kind of obvious that if
you have a gas of stuff
and it has gravitational attractions,
if it's hot,
it will tend to resist the clustering tendency
due to attractive forces.
If it's cold,
it will tend to cluster.
Neutrinos...
being so light,
would tend to be pretty relativistic.
They would be what is called hot dark matter.
Hot dark matter is no longer an option.
It's thought that the dark matter...
basically because of this tendency to cluster,
a strong tendency to cluster,
is cold.
Cold means to say that the particles are moving
relative to the local reference frame
with much less than the speed of light.
So Neutrinos are moving,
but Neutrinos are not a good option for dark matter.
Yeah?
One thing I'm confused about in your explanation.
You were saying,
well,
that matter in that equation up there
with the four pieces,
that the curvature piece dominates over the matter part.
That's what they thought.
Yeah.
But then at the same time you're saying
in a matter-dominated world,
A goes like T to the 2 thirds.
Oh,
up until the time...
up until the time that this gets bigger than that.
Okay.
Right.
You'd have to correct...
All right,
so the equation that...
that...what is it?
That H is like 1 over T,
that would get somewhat corrected,
but not a lot,
because most of it was happening earlier
before this crossover point.
So...
Again,
a theory 30 or 40 years ago...
And the point is you can work it out.
You can work out the detail.
Yeah.
Like 30 or 40 years ago,
what was considered...
what was dominant?
What is time now?
Is it like...
is the matter dominated over the curvature?
Or is the curvature dominated over the matter now?
When,
now?
Today?
Yes,
today.
You mean...
You mean today according to yesterday's theory
or today according to today's theory?
The way they were thinking about
it 30 or 40 years ago.
Okay,
so there was massive confusion.
There was a lot of confusion about it.
But I think if you would have...
put things together without worrying about dark matter,
I think you would have had to say that...
that this term was big,
that it was of the sign that K was negative,
and that A was roughly the
same as the age of the universe.
Yeah.
And people resisted it to some extent.
The main reason I...
You know...
I don't know what people were thinking.
Each person was thinking something different.
But I think one of the prejudices
was that the universe was closed and bounded.
So they would tend to write equations
that were appropriate for K equals positive,
and that didn't...
and that conflicted with the observations.
So there was a lot of confusion about it.
Later on,
20 years ago,
I'm not sure exactly when,
it sort of settled down that...
that...
that K was probably negative.
Okay?
Now,
what happened...
Let's come now.
What did dark matter do to this equation?
Well,
the left...
If we just ignore this,
the right side and the left side,
the matter-dominated term over here
and the Hubble constant
differed by a factor of 25 or something like that.
So it was pretty serious.
A big gap in the equation.
It was a gap between these two.
At best,
the dark matter
is five or six or seven times the luminous matter,
and it did not fix this.
It fixed it somewhat,
but it didn't fix it...
it didn't fix it...
uh...
It didn't make the matter term
equal to the Hubble constant term.
What it did,
was it still...
not only left room for a K over A squared
with negative curvature,
it required it.
It required this term to still be there.
So it didn't...
it didn't...
Well,
when I say it didn't fix things,
I'm not sure what fix means.
There was nothing particularly wrong
with saying that H squared
largely came from here.
But the matter term
was not sufficient to fill the gap.
It still had this present.
Are there any sort of restrictions
on the mass of the particles
with dark matter?
No.
Essentially none.
If you got too light,
would you have a problem that...
Yeah.
Um...
It depends...
All right,
there's...
If the particles are light and fermions,
you're in trouble.
They can't all occupy the same state
and be moving together slowly
relative to each other.
If they're bosons,
they can be extremely light
and be in a phase called a Bose condensation,
and the Bose condensation
just has very,
very slow particles
all in the same quantum state,
moving like a Bose...
like a Bose-Einstein condensation,
and that is one of the theories of dark matter.
It's called the axion theory,
that the axions are incredibly light,
very,
very light.
I don't remember the exact numbers,
but extremely light,
much,
much lighter than neutrinos,
and that they form a Bose condensation.
That's one theory of dark matter,
and it's a good theory.
It's not a crazy theory,
but mostly people think about theories
in which the dark matter
are particles that could be dark
and be detected in big accelerators,
particles whose mass
are in the range of masses
that could be discovered at the LHC.
Is that because...
Is that wishful thinking?
Yeah.
They can't get enough power yet,
right?
They don't have enough power yet
in the accelerator
to try and reach the theoretical maximum.
No.
No,
there is no theoretical maximum
unless you assume that the particles interact
with roughly standard model
weak interaction cross-sections.
Then the maximum is probably up in a few TeV,
a few,
maybe at most 10 times 10 TeV.
And,
yeah,
I mean,
is there enough energy?
Is there enough energy to have detected them?
Apparently not.
Well,
in two years,
we'll be out of more,
right?
In two years,
we'll have more information,
and it is possible
that particles will be discovered,
and they may have the right properties.
So would it be fair to say
that the dark matter,
could we blame string theory on it
and say...
No.
The reason that we can't see it
is because it's saying a dimension
that we can't see from our eyes.
No,
no,
no.
I mean,
they are particles.
They can be seen.
They can be measured.
We do measure them.
We measure them gravitationally.
I guess you're asking,
is it conceivable that these are particles
which are so unusual
that they have almost no interaction
with ordinary material,
and therefore we don't see them?
Yes,
it's possible.
But that's what...
But,
yeah,
that's right.
But it is possible
that they are just so weakly interacting
with ordinary matter
that there's no chance of detecting them.
It's possible.
One of the reasons that neutrinos are so fast
is because during the Big Bang
they were formed in a...
So if this dark matter
was formed at the Big Bang,
would it have been formed later
when the universe was cooler or something?
No,
no,
they're just heavier.
Oh,
I mean,
if they were light.
If they were very,
very light,
okay.
If they were light,
then they were going to
be faster than a gate block.
Yeah.
But if they're bosons,
it's okay.
They can boson condense,
and they don't have to be moving fast.
If they're fermions,
they have to be moving fast.
But,
okay,
the axion theory is not a theory
in which the axions were ever in thermal equilibrium.
If they were in thermal equilibrium at one time,
then they would be moving fast today.
But this is not what we're talking about.
This is not where I was going with tonight's lecture.
I wasn't going to get into axions.
We know with any confidence nothing about dark matter.
The most likely thing is
that some form of elementary particle
that hasn't been discovered yet,
a good chance that they're heavy enough
to have escaped detection in the LHC
but light enough to be able
to be detected in future experiments.
But that's it.
That's about all we can say at the moment.
And they're there.
The other alternative to dark matter
was to modify gravitational theory
so that Kepler's laws doesn't work for galaxies.
But that doesn't seem to have worked very well.
There don't seem to be any nice modifications
of standard gravity theory which explain this.
So...
Most of us think it's particles.
But you're free to make other theories.
It hasn't necessitated any modifications
to the Newtonian mechanics by which
we understand our own solar system.
It has not.
So by that we can conclude that there's
a negligible amount of dark matter around us.
That's right.
Yeah.
Keep in mind...
The density of matter in the solar system
is a lot higher than it is out in...
Yeah.
The dark matter in the solar system
does not compete with the gravity
of the Sun at the center.
Not by a long shot.
And so that's right.
It doesn't affect the solar system.
Okay.
All right.
So it's natural then to ask,
can we make a...
How do we test...
the candidate theory?
Here's the candidate theory now.
The candidate theory is matter dominated.
We forget this.
We forget lambda because that's
something we hadn't heard about.
K here is negative and...
negative curved space.
How do we test that theory?
Okay.
How do we test any particular model?
A model incidentally consists of two things.
It consists of a specification of K,
whether it's zero,
plus one,
or minus one.
And some kind of equation of state
for which you could substitute a history,
an A of T.
An A of T and a K is
a model that you can try to test.
So what do we know
and what can astronomers measure
and how do they compare it
with a particular...
with a particular model?
Well,
pretty much the same thing Hubble did.
Except a sophisticated version of it.
You can measure two things to a large extent.
You can measure the redshift of things,
which tells you something about their velocity.
And you can measure distance by...
by luminosity.
How do those two things come together
to tell you anything about...
about K and A of T?
So let's talk about that a little bit.
First,
let's ignore the fact that...
that H,
the Hubble constant,
changes with time.
And let's just suppose we didn't have to worry
about the fact that the universe evolves.
Let's just suppose for a minute that it was...
that it was all at an instant
and that it didn't change.
What could you do to measure K?
Whether the universe is open or closed or what?
And the way to do that...
um...
is...
to measure the number of galaxies out there
of a given brightness.
What does the brightness have to do with K?
So let's talk about that.
If...
the number of galaxies as a function of distance,
really,
that's what you want to do.
You want to measure the number of galaxies
as a function of distance.
If you happen to think
that distance is related to redshift,
which of course it is,
then you could be talking about the...
the number of galaxies as a function of redshift,
but let's just talk about the number of galaxies
as a function of distance,
where the distance has been measured in some way
that we'll...
that we need to come back to.
All right.
So...
if we're living in a flat space...
if we're living in a flat space,
uh...
then it's clear...
and space is homogeneous,
and everything is homogeneous,
then it's pretty clear that the...
number of galaxies...
in a region dr,
let's say within a shell surrounding us,
the distance dr,
uh...
goes like r squared.
That's just the volume of a r squared dr.
It's also true that if
we lived in negative curved space,
it would go like hyperbolic sine squared.
And that means something which grows exponentially with r,
e to the 2r dr.
If we were on a sphere,
if we were living...
not this sphere,
but if space was a sphere,
this would become sine of r squared dr.
But let's forget that.
The evidence seems to say negative curvature.
This is the case for negative curvature.
And so the first thing you
can see is the number of galaxies
as a function of distance
would grow much,
much more rapidly
as a function of distance.
Um...
What about as a function of luminosity?
What can we say as a function of luminosity?
How does the luminosity,
in particular,
another question you could ask is
how does luminosity depend on distance?
Well,
how does luminosity depend on distance in flat space?
Um...
What's that?
It goes like 1 over r squared.
It's just the same fact here.
If you thought of a light bulb at the center
and us out here,
then the luminosity of the light bulb,
the amount of radiation coming out,
would simply be spread over
the area of the sphere here,
and the area grows like r squared.
So the luminosity itself goes like r squared.
But supposing you were living
in this negatively curved space
where the area of the sphere
grows like e to the 2r,
then the luminosity would be
much,
uh,
much smaller.
So what you would find would be
a very rapid fall-off of luminosity with distance.
You would find many more galaxies out there
at a given distance,
but you would find the luminosity
as a function of distance would fall off much faster.
So in particular,
you could ask,
what about luminosity as a function of redshift?
And you would find a characteristic behavior
of the luminosity as a function of the redshift,
which would say the luminosity really gets small fast
because of this e to the 2r here.
So that would be...
That's pretty much the way
of determining whether k is plus 1,
minus 1,
or 0.
That,
uh,
that in particular,
if k is minus 1,
meaning to say negative curvature,
one should find that the,
um,
that the number of galaxies at a given distance,
or let's say at a given redshift,
anomalously grows rapidly with redshift.
Okay.
As the redshift,
uh,
gets,
deeper and deeper into the red,
number of galaxies should grow
much faster than it would in flat space.
So that's a test.
You can also...
Think about calculating the number of galaxies
that you see as a function of redshift.
How many galaxies do you
see as a function of redshift?
Forget the dimness and the brightness for a minute now.
Just how many galaxies do you see at each redshift?
That's something you can also calculate.
Let's talk about it a little bit,
how you do that.
Well,
in order to talk about it,
we have to talk about redshift.
What is redshift?
All right.
Redshift is a function of light
If light is emitted by a source
that has a wavelength lambda,
we can call that the wavelength of the light
when it's emitted.
The emitted,
uh,
just the usual.
It's a light bulb that has a certain wavelength.
When it's detected,
it's a wavelength of light
and when it's emitted,
the light may or may not have the same wavelength.
There could be various reasons
for a shift of the wavelength.
Doppler shift is one.
Gravitational redshift,
uh,
from,
from gravity due to a black hole
is another one.
And the expansion of the universe,
which happens to be equivalent to the Doppler shift,
is not a third.
It's equivalent to the Doppler shift.
But the expansion of the universe is the one
that we're interested in.
So here is what is going on.
Let's draw a map of the universe.
This is time.
Horizontal is space.
And here's today.
We're right at the center.
This is r equals zero.
And
different r
correspond to different vertical lines here.
This is r equals one,
r equals two,
r equals three,
and so forth.
All right.
We look back.
And we look back along light rays.
So how do light rays move?
Well,
in flat space,
in the Minkowski metric,
they move on 45 degree lines.
But this is general relativity.
There's a complicated metric here.
We'll discuss a little later
how light rays move.
But however they move,
they move somehow.
Either straight lines
or curved trajectories,
or somehow light rays.
We'll figure that out later.
But we look back,
and we see a galaxy over here.
We see a galaxy over here.
And we see a galaxy over here.
We see them at different times.
And because we see them at different times,
we see them,
first of all,
with different scale factors.
The scale factor varies vertically here.
There's an a of t.
Up here,
there's a today.
Let's call that a today.
The emission point over here,
let's just call a of t.
The light emitted over here
has to stretch
to get to here.
The universe increases
by a factor
of a today
over
a
at the emission time.
a today can just be
thought of as a number.
a at the emission time
depends on the emission time.
That's the factor
by which the wavelength
of an electromagnetic wave
will stretch,
and going from here to here.
And that's,
in fact,
the redshift factor.
Oh,
we should define redshift carefully.
Let's define redshift carefully.
It is the ratio of
lambda
when it's detected
divided by lambda emitted
and that's not quite right.
Is it minus one
or plus one times that?
Minus one.
Why is the minus one there?
For historical reasons.
And it's called z.
z is the redshift.
And lambda detected
over lambda emitted
is just the ratio of
a today over a of t.
So we look back
along a light ray
we see light emitted
over here,
we see light emitted over here,
and each emission
has a different redshift factor.
The redshift factor
are
the two
this minus one
is equal to z.
a today,
yeah,
this minus one is equal to z.
So if we know
the scale factor
at the time of emission
then we know what z is.
Okay,
so that's good.
But so far we don't know anything
because we don't know how the light ray moves.
Until we know how the
light ray moves
we don't know how to compare these points.
So let's talk about how the light ray moves.
Let's work out all the things we need
and then I'll write down
some equations for you
which an astronomer would actually
work with.
Okay,
so
what's the next thing?
How does the light ray move?
We go back to the metric.
Here's the metric
over here.
And light rays are null rays.
Light rays,
in particular,
light rays
that are moving radially
relative to us,
here we are over here,
light rays moving radially
to us are null rays
which means that dt
squared is equal to a of t
squared times dr squared.
Alright,
so we can write
then for a null ray,
for a light ray
moving backward like that,
an imaginary backward moving light ray,
that dt
dt
dt is equal to
a of t dr.
Now I don't quite have it right here.
I have the sign wrong.
Um
Of
course what's true is d t squared
is equal to a of t squared times dr squared.
Now there are two solutions.
One for going back into
the past and one that's going forward
in time.
Obviously the one we're
interested in is the one which goes back
into the past and for that dt is equal
to minus a over t dr all this says
is that R gets bigger as T gets more
negative as T gets more negative R
gets bigger alright so there's this funny
minus sign there it's a peculiar minus sign
or well more that dr dr is equal to
dt over a of T with a minus sign
alright so this is one equation and that tells
us how light moves that tells us how
light moves along here and let's now see
if we can invent an equation and
invent a question that an astronomer would be
interested in
here's the question what is the number
of visible galaxies of a given redshift
that just that what is the number of
let's call it dn the number of galaxies
within redshift z and z plus dz
the number of visible galaxies per unit
redshift that's something that surely can be measured
look out you see the galaxies
or if they're galaxies or whatever the
standard candles are and you count the
number at each redshift that will give
you dn dz let's see if we
can figure out an equation for it
what about dn what about dn dn
let's just take that to be the number
of galaxies within a sphere of radius R and
differential r
a distance dr what's that going to be
it's going to be equal to the area of
the sphere times d r so dn is going
to be dr and what's the area of the sphere
nope not in general not in general
that would be correct in flat space in
general that's proportional to C of R squared
yeah
ok
In other words,
in the case of interest where k is negative,
this would be hyperbolic sine of r,
and at large distances it would be some exponential.
But of course we can study all of the cases.
We can study all of the cases
simultaneously by putting psi of r squared.
Times what?
Times a number which is the
number of galaxies per unit volume.
But let's leave that out.
Let's just write proportional to.
The number of galaxies within a shell is
proportional to dr times psi of r squared.
Now what about dz?
Let's look at z.
Here's z.
And we're interested in the change in z from going
from one radial point to another radial point at distance dr.
How much does z change?
Well,
let's just.
Take this equation here and differentiate it.
dz is equal to derivative of minus one to zero.
a today.
What's varying incidentally?
Is a today varying?
No,
a today isn't varying.
a today is just a today.
What's varying as you look back along
here is a at the emission point.
a of t.
So that's equal to a today.
And I want to.
Differentiate one over a.
So that's minus a of t squared.
Different derivative of one over a is one
of a of t squared times da right.
Da of t.
Everybody recognize that equation.
So we have to divide by dz.
Let's.
See.
That's.
Minus.
A today.
Over a squared.
Da.
What is da?
Da is da by dt.
Times dt.
So.
That's.
I haven't done anything.
I've just manipulated the equation a little bit.
What is dt?
dt.
Is.
Dr.
It's not quite.
No,
it's not quite dr.
It's not quite dr.
That's what.
That's.
No,
we have dr by dt.
What's dr by dt?
Here it is.
The r by dt is
minus one over a of t.
Right.
Along the light ray.
That's why I had to do this.
That's why I have to figure out what that.
So ba.
Let's see.
So d.
Let's put the r by dt.
And the r by dt is minus one over a.
So that gets rid of the minus sign.
And gives us a.
Another a downstairs.
Good.
The a.
The a's cancel.
This a cancels this a.
I don't like it.
It's not what I have in my notes.
Yes,
it is.
What's a today over a?
z plus one.
Okay.
So a today over a is z plus one.
So here I have the number
of galaxies seen at redshift z.
Contains a factor one over z plus one.
Okay.
That's just.
That's known if we know z.
And then we have c of r divided by.
A dot.
What can we do with that?
All right.
Let's see what we can do with it.
Um.
We can.
There's nothing we can do with it now.
There's nothing we can do with
it until we make a model.
Until we make a model.
So let's make a model.
Let's make a model and see what we get.
Do we really want to do this now?
Yeah.
Let's do it.
All right.
Let's make a model.
Our model is the matter dominated universe.
Let's take the matter dominated
universe with k equals minus one.
And for the matter dominated
universe for most of the evolution.
Again,
a looks like t to
the one to the two thirds.
Here's what we want to do.
I'm not going to go through
the whole go through the whole story.
We can calculate a dot.
A dot.
Is equal to.
Two thirds.
Divided by one over t to the one third.
We calculate a dot.
What about r?
Can we calculate r?
Yes,
we can calculate r.
Once we know a of t.
We can calculate r.
I won't do the calculation.
But we also know r of t.
It's known.
We can compute it.
Moreover.
Once we know a.
We can calculate z.
The point is that everything a,
a dot,
r can all be expressed in terms of z.
We know that and a today.
We know the relationship between a and z.
We know the relation between a and t.
In other words,
we can write everything in terms of z.
Everything here is known in terms of z.
And so we get a
thing here which depends on z.
But it's known only because
we substituted a particular model.
Had I used a different equation of state,
I would get a different answer.
C of r.
That's an interesting quantity.
That exponentially increases with r.
That's easy to detect.
That's really easy to detect.
That C of r,
this explosive thing which just increases with r.
That means since r increases with redshift,
that makes an anomalously large number of galaxies.
A large redshift.
If k is negative.
And a dot can be
computed directly in terms of z.
In other words,
the point is with enough little bit of labor,
you can take a model which
means an a and a k.
And convert it into a statement of
how many galaxies you see per unit redshift.
Together with the other piece of information
which was the relationship between redshift and luminosity.
Those two bits of information together can give you
a complete history of the expansion of the universe.
That's enough to give you a complete description of the expansion
of the universe and to tell you what C of r is.
I've assumed something about C of r,
but I didn't have to.
I could have done this calculation in flat space.
I could have done it in a closed universe.
The two pieces of information are...
are...
um...
redshift or...
not redshift...
luminosity as a function of redshift.
And the number of galaxies as a function of redshift.
Those two things together are enough
to determine A of t and k.
Whether it's plus one or minus one or zero.
Alright,
so you do that.
Astronomers do that.
They've been doing it for fifty years or more.
And the final upshot...
is first of all inconsistent with
this matter dominated universe with k equals...
with k being negative.
What it's consistent with...
the best fit...
the best fit from...
Incidentally,
when I say galaxies,
I mean standard candles of some kind.
And the standard candles which are best
at the redshift we're interested in are supernovae.
Supernovae are things which are very controllable.
We can't control them,
but we can...
Nature controls them.
And...
the result is...
not this formula at all...
but...
omega radiation,
again,
essentially equal to zero.
Omega matter...
and this includes both dark matter and luminous matter.
Dark matter and luminous matter about point three.
Omega lambda...
about point seven.
And...
omega k about zero.
This is observational fact.
Very little theory has gone into this.
Well,
theory has gone into it,
but...
no particular biases about...
what to expect.
This is pretty much what the unbiased raw data says.
And zero,
he means...
it could be point one,
or it could be minus point one.
But...
No,
no,
take that back.
Point oh one.
Could be point oh...
point oh one.
Plus or minus.
It could be that small.
Or it could be that big.
Omega lambda is about point seven.
Omega matter about point three.
That's the best fit...
to these various pieces of information here...
using models which depend on the equation of state.
Okay?
So...
Just from counting...
just from counting galaxies,
redshift and...
and luminosity...
that's the picture that emerges.
Why is...
I thought...
I thought lambda wasn't even known yet.
No,
no,
I'm talking about today.
Now I'm talking about today.
This model...
This theory failed.
It failed.
It failed this test.
It just could not reproduce the...
the observed luminosity...
luminosity z relation and dn dz.
Just...
Just failed.
So...
So the way we know
omega lambda is from the equation?
We're not measuring...
We're not measuring the...
Yeah.
No,
you put in...
Yeah.
You put in numbers for these things.
The model consists of numbers for these things.
That's what goes into the model.
A value of omega k,
a value of omega lambda,
and a value of omega matter.
Or equivalently...
c matter...
c is the value of lambda...
Radiation is not important.
Lambda and...
k.
I guess my...
My question is...
From...
From what you're talking about,
taking these measurements,
just taking measurements,
you said we could solve...
We could kind of figure
out what k had to be...
No.
Or what omega k and omega m had to be.
Is that right?
You have to process it through this.
Right.
You have to...
You...
This is what you begin with.
No,
no,
no.
You don't begin with this.
You begin with a value of omega k,
a value of omega lambda,
a value of omega m,
and a
value of omega r.
Just to get sort of a guess?
No,
no.
You start with a number.
You start with a set of numbers.
That defines a model.
Now you process it.
Now you run it through the equations.
You run it through the mill,
and what you calculate is L of
z and the n by the z.
You compare them with experiment.
If it fails,
you throw the model away
and put in some new numbers.
And you keep trying numbers...
What are you saying is that one works?
That one works.
With some uncertainties,
but the uncertainties are not big.
This one is rather small,
0.01.
They're all small.
They're all in...
I think this is 0.28,
if I remember.
2.8 and whatever.
Let's call it 0.1.
So they're known to about 1%.
These numbers are known to about 1%.
And if you vary them very much,
much more than 1%,
these tests fail.
So a model then,
again,
a model consists of a specification of these values,
which means the values of the various components here today.
But you don't measure them completely.
Some of them you measure,
some you don't measure.
But you just feed them in,
grind the wheels,
calculate A of t from the Friedmann equation.
Calculate A of t.
Once you have A of t,
you can feed it into here,
calculate the n by dz,
and luminosity is a function of z,
and test it.
Yeah?
Just to remind us,
is A today,
where does that come from,
the Hubble constant?
Yes.
Well,
once you have a model,
you're juggling various things,
but once you have a model
that fits these two pieces of data,
then you have an A as a function of time,
and you can read off it what A today is.
Yeah.
And it's roughly speaking from the Hubble constant today.
Yes,
it's from the Hubble constant today.
So that is one of the outputs.
One of the outputs is A today.
And...
Earlier you said that,
I think you said something along the lines of,
you're doing this looking not that far back in time.
If you were to have gathered this
data by looking very far back in time,
wouldn't that distort it because you'd be,
maybe it's the same point,
but you'd be looking back at it.
You know,
if you only took your data from very,
very far in the past,
the only term that's important here is this one.
If you go to very small a,
which means long in the past,
this is simply much bigger than this and this.
But is that something like
if you're not going that far,
I mean,
let's say you look back a billion years to...
Oh,
a billion years is not very far.
But that's not enough to distort
the answers that you got from this.
What do you mean to distort it?
That's what you do.
You go back a billion years,
two billion years,
three billion years,
four billion years,
and that's what...
That's what goes into these equations.
A of t.
A of t as a function of t
all the way back up to the present.
Yeah.
You...
All right,
let's go back through it again.
You begin with a set
of values of the matter density,
the cosmology,
the logical constant density,
all of these.
They go into the Friedman equation.
I know your answer was
for where do we come from?
These numbers.
No.
I'm finished.
You just invent them.
No,
but really,
I mean,
the...
The ratio of that over the Hubble...
Where did you get those values?
We start with some other values.
We feed them into here.
We calculate the n by dz.
That's an observable thing.
The number of galaxies...
How the number of galaxies varies with z.
We observe it.
We calculate l of z.
That's also an observable thing.
If the model doesn't work,
we throw it away and try some new numbers.
No,
I understood all that.
Where did you get those?
I didn't get them.
Trial and error.
How did you ever know that would work?
It fits the data the best.
That's right.
You have a machine that starts
with a set of four numbers.
This one is not important.
Everybody knows that this is not important
because you measure it directly.
It's just too small to matter.
So you put these in a Friedman's equation
and that allows you to compute
d and dz and l of z.
And these numbers give you a good fit.
Yeah,
these numbers give you the best fit.
Well,
this is what you do with spreadsheets all the time.
Yeah.
All right.
Some of them...
Look,
this one here is more or less measurable directly.
Why?
You can measure h.
h is measurable.
And you can measure the dark matter
and the luminous matter together.
And basically,
omega m
is the ratio of this factor over here,
this one to this one.
You measure the energy density in matter.
You measure the Hubble constant.
And the ratio of them is omega m.
So that actually is measurable.
It's really this one here,
which was the unknown.
So,
all right.
So what can you say?
This one is pretty much directly measurable,
omega matter.
And it's 0.3.
With an assumption about dark matter.
Hmm?
Yeah.
Including the dark matter,
omega m is about 0.3.
These two are the ones which are not known.
But what is known,
at least in theory,
is that this plus this
plus this has to equal 1.
This plus this plus this has to equal 1.
This one is known.
Therefore,
this one follows.
But you want to do better than that.
Really what you want to do is,
you really want to do better than that.
You just don't want to say,
well,
this was 0.3.
This one's not really known.
Nobody's ever measured the curvature.
And therefore,
this one must be 0.7.
That's not what you want to do.
You want to take this as given,
this is unknown,
and omega k,
whatever it is,
to fill up the difference.
Okay?
You with me?
You take this one as known,
this one as unknown,
but we'll put it in as a trial.
And omega k is just what's left over.
We put that into these equations.
We run it,
and we calculate L of z in dn by dz.
Having done that,
we just look for the best fit.
I think I probably didn't say this clearly,
so let me just try it once more.
These two,
this one and this one,
are measurable.
This is negligible.
This is 0.3.
These two are unknown,
but what's known is that
the sum of all of them
should add up to 1.
All right?
So,
we take a test value for omega lambda.
That tells us what lambda is.
We run it through the Friedmann equations,
find out what A of t is.
Having computed A of t,
we go to this blackboard over here
and compute the observable signature,
the number of galaxies per unit z,
and the relationship between z and luminosity.
The relation between z and luminosity
is a generalization of Hubble's original calculation.
Luminosity is distance.
Z is velocity.
The only reason we have to do better
is because we're looking at it at different times.
All right?
So,
the additional ingredient
is to have these curves
knowing how light moves and so forth.
That involves the model.
That involves the details of the model.
But once you put the details of the model in,
you look for your best fit.
And the best fit is the one
that's the best fit is with these numbers here.
So the last two you treat as adjustable parameters?
Last two you treat...
Well,
only one of them
because they have to sum to...
That's sort of a question.
Why just one of them?
I mean,
both of them appear in the equation.
So why couldn't you guess lambda equals 0.4
and k equals 0.3 or something like that?
No,
no.
I have to add up to one.
These are...
No,
they would add up.
All that would add up to one.
Instead of lambda equals 0.7
and k equals essentially zero,
why not lambda equals 0.4
and then k equals 0.3?
Good.
You take this.
You take your trial.
You solve the Friedmann equations with it.
That tells you what A of t is
for your model.
You then feed it into here.
This is not what you get.
You get something different.
Feed it into here
and calculate the number of galaxies per redshift
or the number of supernovae per redshift
and the luminosity as a function of z.
The only thing I'm pointing out is that
that's different than what you said.
You said just take lambda,
forget k,
and let it fall out.
I'm not even sure what that means.
You were saying we only have one parameter,
lambda,
that we have to deal with.
But I don't understand why...
Because this plus this plus this has to be one.
Right,
but as I said,
if you just...
Okay,
so you...
Can we take it offline?
All right,
I don't want to waste time here.
Yeah.
The point is that if you set lambda,
you're forced to set a certain...
可以
okay yeah
I have a question about k
you can say plus one minus one zero
is it really k is greater than zero?
no,
the way we formulated it,
plus one minus one is zero
but omega,
yeah
I'm having trouble seeing how the
dimensions work there
k over a squared has to
have the same dimensions as a squared
that's right
speed of light is equal to one
apart from the speed of light,
that's correct
oh I see,
so there's a c in it
there are some c's in there
there are some speeds of light
but you know,
get used to working with speed of light
equal to one and then this is dimensionally
correct
that's it
does this method rely on the assumption that
the density of galaxies is isotropic over space and time?
No,
what does it mean for it
to be isotropic over space and time?
Jinities
what does that mean?
meaning that earlier in the universe there
might have been more galaxies but smaller
ones per unit of space
it assumes that in every time interval you
can get middle space alignment aleo Caroline willst
time space is homogeneous and isotropic.
It does assume that.
But you know that's to a
large extent tested,
not completely,
but if you want to know whether it's isotropic at
this time over here,
you just look at galaxies that you
can see at that time and you see
that it's isotropic.
You look in different directions at different redshifts,
at the
redshift you're interested in,
and it's isotropic.
These omegas are the way it is today,
but in the past it would be different.
So like
in the early days...
The omegas are defined to be the ratios...
Okay,
so you have these four numbers,
CR over A to the fourth plus CM over
A cubed plus lambda minus K over A squared equals
H squared.
That's true at all times,
okay?
Now we plug in today.
Now we plug in today,
today,
today.
Now we just take the ratio,
divide it...
I was going to say that.
Like a zillion years ago,
the omegas would be different.
A zillion years ago,
So my question is,
is...
Does the derivative of the omegas,
in reference to time,
what do they look like?
Obviously
the wave one...
Here they are.
Here you can see that long in the past,
radiation was much more important
than matter.
Well,
it's much,
much more important than lambda.
So long in the past,
a long,
long time ago,
omega radiation was large.
Large means essentially equal to one.
Long in the past,
omega radiation was about all
there was and everything else was small.
Right,
so therefore d omega r is negative.
The derivative of that...
Yes,
the omega...
Omega is...
Omega r is decreasing.
Right,
and omega matter and the other one...
What are they doing?
Are they increasing...
Probably omega is probably zero.
Zero.
The derivative of it.
Yeah,
omega...
Look,
okay,
so let's...
The most...
When a gets large,
what is going to
be biggest here?
Lambda is going to be biggest,
right?
So long in the future,
omega lambda
will be one.
Omega lambda will be one
and everything else will be small.
Omega curvature
will be less than...
Less small than omega matter,
which will be less small than omega radiation.
But long
in the future,
it will be dominated by lambda.
Long in the past,
it was dominated by radiation.
Okay.
So,
Mike,
the real question is what is
the time derivative of matter look like?
It obviously
starts small,
then it gets larger,
then it gets small again.
The...
Yes.
Yes,
that's correct.
That's correct.
The omega matter starts small.
Why?
Because it's
almost all omega radiation.
Right,
then it gets bigger.
It starts to dominate.
It gets up near...
Pretty big,
up near...
Close to one.
That's before lambda became important.
And then lambda becomes more important
than this.
That's today.
So omega matter is 0.3.
And omega lambda is 0.7.
And omega...
Lambda gets really big.
And omega k is...
Omega k always stays...
Well,
we don't know that.
We don't know that.
Let's see.
Omega k is...
Yeah,
no,
it...
Right,
it's not...
No,
that's correct.
It's not going to...
When I said...
When I said we don't know that,
I mean to say that we
know that it's zero to within
about...
About 1%.
The next round of experiments
might discover that it's not zero,
that it might
be 1%,
either plus or minus.
That won't...
No,
that won't change much.
No.
Well,
let's
see.
Yeah,
it will change.
Sure,
it will get smaller.
It will get smaller.
It will get
smaller because this will eventually
defeat this by any arbitrary amount.
So yeah,
this
one will get smaller.
And eventually,
all there'll be will be lambda.
That's as far as we can tell.
I mean,
that's...
There's some theory that goes into that,
of course.
When you put the values in,
fit the data,
is there any kind of systematic deviation
that's not understood?
I don't think so.
No.
So it's a good problem.
Yeah.
No,
this has achieved the level of precision.
Yeah.
It's a good problem.
It's a well-defined precision
cosmology where everything does fit.
Now,
the only thing is,
it's a 1% model,
it's not a tenth of a percent,
and it's not a hundredth of a percent.
It's
a...
It's a 1% fit,
and everything fits to 1%.
Independent of this,
had they been trying to do
experiments where they could show if
A is positive,
negative,
or zero by trying to do huge triangulations and...
looking at angles to see if they're,
you know,
some up to 180.
That's correct.
And we're going to come to
that when we study next week
the microwave background.
And the microwave background,
or at least the lumpiness of the microwave background,
allows triangulation and allows you to study triangles.
And again,
probably if all you use is the supernova data,
which is,
this is the supernova data,
I don't think that gets you to 1%.
Maybe it gets you somewhere between 10% and 1%.
Combined and supplemented with
a cosmic microwave background,
it's 1%.
Yeah.
When the value is k to 0,
then it says the universe is becoming flatter?
Becoming?
Flatter?
Yes.
Oh,
yes,
for sure.
For sure.
Sure,
the bigger it gets,
the flatter it gets.
That's just...
Big is flat.
In any case,
if it continues to grow,
will it become flatter?
Okay,
this...
This is tricky stuff,
but the way to think
about it is what I said.
You start with a model,
which means a set of parameters here.
You feed them into Friedmann equations.
You go to this side.
Once you have Friedmann equations,
and you can read off from the Friedmann equations
the observable quantities,
L of z and dn by dz,
and you compare.
There's incidentally no reason why
any particular set of numbers
has to agree with the data,
other than theory.
Without a theory,
there'd be no particular reason why any set of numbers
would agree with the data.
So,
it's not just testing a particular model,
it's testing a particular model,
and it's testing the theory.
Yeah.
For more,
please visit us at stanford.edu.