This program is brought to you by Stanford University.
Please visit us at stanford.edu.
Well, good evening everybody.
I'm glad to see you back, all of you.
So nice to have such a large class.
The last time we discussed the influence of electric and
magnetic fields on charged particles.
We know what they do.
We know what electric and
magnetic fields do on charged particles.
They push them around, they pull them, they exert forces.
In fact, we even wrote some equations.
Let's write down the basic equation.
The basic equation is that the
force on a charged particle, F,
is equal to the electric charge of the charged particle.
Why is that there?
That's there because if the charged particle wasn't charged,
if it didn't have any charge,
there would be no force on it.
And then that gets multiplied by the electric field.
Let's just call it the electric field.
Plus something that depends on the magnetic field.
And the thing that depends on
the magnetic field is the cross product
of the velocity with the magnetic field.
That's the basic influence of electric
and magnetic fields on charged particles
is to exert forces on them
to push them and pull them around
and so forth.
The missing piece, thus far, is what
is it that determines the electric and
magnetic fields in space?
What is it that determines
whether there's a electromagnetic wave?
What is it that determines if a
electric charge field can create a electric change?
What is it that determines what matters to you?
And that's the final question.
There's lots, there's lots to be solving
in Make it, but hear me out please,
produces an electric field and so forth, what
are the equations which govern the fields themselves?
Those equations are called Maxwell's equations, and those
are the equations we want to discuss this evening.
They're the equations which tell
you how charged particles affect fields.
Here is the equation which
says how fields affect charged particles.
The other half of the coin
is how charged particles affect fields.
Why is it necessary that charged particles affect fields?
Well, it's a kind of action and reaction thing.
If electric and magnetic fields can
influence particles, what does that mean?
It means an electromagnetic wave can come, hit a charged
particle, and send it off flying off in some other direction.
It can add energy to the charged particle.
Well, if an electric field can
add energy to a charged particle,
then it had done the same thing.
It better be that a charged particle
can suck energy out of an electric field.
Otherwise, energy wouldn't be conserved.
So it stands to reason, it's
a kind of action and reaction thing,
that if electric and magnetic fields
can do things to particles, charged particles,
then charged particles, charged currents, electric charges, had better
be able to do things to electric and magnetic fields.
So that's the topic for tonight.
But as always in this course,
the basic question is whether the laws of physics,
and in this case the laws
of the electric and magnetic field,
are the same in all reference frames.
That's the thing we've been concentrating
on in the study of relativity,
is the idea that the basic laws of
physics are the same in all reference frames.
Now, one of the things, we're going
to write down Maxwell's equations in a moment,
but one of the basic things that,
we learned,
by, well, let me go back a step.
One of the basic questions has to do with light.
All of relativity theory had to do with light.
If Maxwell's equations are the theory of light,
and Maxwell's equations tell you that
light moves with the speed of light,
and Maxwell's equations are the
same in every reference frame,
it stands to reason,
that light will move with the
speed of light in every reference frame.
This was precisely the puzzle
that Einstein wrestled with so hard.
How is it possible to get a description of nature
in which light moves with the
same velocity in every frame of reference?
That, the thing which ensures that,
is that the laws of physics
are the same in every reference frame,
and in past lectures we saw that what that meant,
is that the,
equations of physics should be expressed,
in terms of,
quantities which have definite transformation laws,
when you go from frame to frame.
That means scalars,
that don't change,
it means vectors,
four vectors,
it means tensors,
and it means all the
things that we discussed last time,
when we discussed the transformation properties,
of the various things in physics.
Let me just remind you,
what this equation looks like,
if it's expressed in a covariant form,
in a form which is
the same in every reference frame.
It looks,
like,
an expression,
involving not electric and magnetic fields,
well yes, electric and magnetic fields,
but a tensor,
a field tensor,
and I'll remind you in a
little while what that field tensor is,
but,
it's an anti-symmetric field tensor,
which is built up out
of the electric and magnetic fields,
and it's multiplied,
by the four vector of velocity,
this is the,
mu component of the force.
The mu component of the force
is written in terms of a,
four by four,
anti-symmetric tensor,
whose transformation properties we know,
and the four vector of velocity,
in this form,
the Lorentz force law,
is written in a form,
which is manifestly the same in every reference frame.
So, that's our goal,
is to write all of the laws of physics,
in particular the Maxwell equations today,
in a form,
which is the same in every reference frame,
which means writing it in terms
of vectors and tensors and so forth.
Now, let's just talk for a little bit,
before we get into it,
deeply,
let's talk about the kind of effects,
that charges have on electric and magnetic fields.
Not that electric and magnetic fields have on charges,
but that charges have on electric and magnetic fields.
Well, first of all,
we know that if we have an electric charge,
we'll call an electric charge Q.
Q stands for the electric charge.
If we have an electric charge of a certain magnitude,
it creates around it an electric field.
You've all seen pictures of this,
the electric field spreads out away from the charge,
very much like a fluid emanating from a,
from a pipe might spread out,
except it spreads out in three dimensions.
That's the electric field created by a point charge.
Another example is if we have
an electric current moving through a wire,
and electric currents are
nothing but moving electric charges.
Electric charges moving through a wire,
those electric charges,
their motion creates a magnetic field,
and the magnetic field is a
field which circulates around the wire,
like that.
So these are examples of
how charges and currents create fields.
What happens, for example,
if you move the charge?
Supposing I suddenly move the charge
from one point to another point.
Then the field has to rearrange itself.
Instead of pointing out of this point,
it will still point out of this point.
But it can't do that instantly.
Why not?
Because somebody out here is
not allowed to see an effect
before light could have been transmitted to this point.
So the field cannot suddenly
rearrange when you move a charge.
It rearranges
by spreading out a wave.
By spreading out a wave of rearrangement.
So that a little bit
after the charge has been moved,
nearby the charge,
the field has been rearranged,
but far away,
it's just as it was before.
And then as time goes on,
a wave spreads out, away from the charge,
that signals the field far away
to rearrange, to accommodate the
fact that the charge has moved.
If you move the charge back and forth,
what will spread out is an electromagnetic wave.
If you vibrate the charge back and forth,
then what you will see going out
is an electric and magnetic wave
that spreads out, just like a light wave, in fact.
That's what an antenna does.
An antenna simply moves charge back and forth like that.
The same thing is true of currents and wires.
If you suddenly reverse the current in a wire,
you would reverse the sign of the magnetic field.
Instead of the magnetic field circulating around this way,
the magnetic field would circulate
around in the other direction.
But that signal can't get very
far in too short a time.
Einstein's rule was no signal ever
gets faster than the speed of light.
So it takes some time
for somebody far away to discover
that the current has been reversed.
That means that the magnetic field
the change in the magnetic field,
the fact that it's changed direction,
spreads out in a wave,
and again, it's an electromagnetic wave.
And if you oscillate the charge back and forth,
if you oscillate the current back and forth,
you send out an electromagnetic wave.
That's the basic physics
that we want to describe
by Maxwell's equations.
Before we do,
I want to do a little bit of review
from last time.
First, I just want to remind you about wave equations.
Equations describing fields,
in this case, describing fields
that can produce waves.
The first example, and we talked about it last time,
was a scalar field.
A field that doesn't have any indices mu and nu,
but is just a single
number at each point in space.
Each point in space,
there's a quantity,
the field phi,
it depends on x and t,
and it can vibrate, it can shake,
it can do all sorts of things,
it can form wave fields.
The last time, we discussed the kind of equation,
the kind of wave equation that governs such fields,
and I'll just remind you.
Remember what d mu is.
d mu stands for the derivative
with respect to the derivative.
d mu stands for the four directions of space-time,
x and t.
mu runs over four values,
x, y, z, and t.
Incidentally, remember that x here
really stands for x, y, and z.
Perhaps I shouldn't call it x,
I'll call it x,
well, let's continue to call it x.
But it really stands for the four components of space,
and also t stands for the time.
d by d mu means the derivative
with respect to any one of these,
so that's an ordinary derivative.
And we can differentiate phi.
A simple wave equation,
a very simple wave equation,
would just say that the
derivative of a field is zero.
That's not a very interesting wave equation,
and the reason is,
what it says is the field is absolutely constant.
If all of its derivatives,
the x and the y and
the z and the time derivative,
are zero,
that means the field doesn't change at all,
with anything,
and so that's a very boring wave equation.
Completely boring.
A less boring equation
we get if we differentiate it again.
I'm now using notation
that we described last time,
or several times in the past,
where an upper interval,
an upper interval,
and a lower interval,
differ only by the sign of the time component.
So that this would really mean
the second derivative with respect to time
of a field,
minus the second derivative
with respect to x squared,
minus the second derivative with respect to y squared,
minus the second derivative with respect to z squared,
is equal to zero.
Notice, as usual,
because I'm lazy,
I've set the speed of light,
c, equal to one.
You can go home,
and as an exercise,
figure out where the speeds
of light go into this equation.
Alright, let's imagine now,
a wave moving down the z-axis.
A wave moving down the z-axis.
It's moving down the z-axis,
and that means phi only depends on z.
It doesn't depend on x and y.
It may also depend on time.
If a wave is moving,
and you're standing still, watching it,
of course, you're going to watch it
go up and down and up and down,
so it will depend on time,
and it will also depend on z, where you are,
but it won't depend on the other directions.
So a wave moving down the z-axis,
we can completely ignore
these two terms,
which are the derivatives of phi
in the direction in which it doesn't change.
This is not there.
And our wave equation,
for a wave moving along z,
along the z-axis,
sorry, this should be z, shouldn't it?
It should equal zero.
What kind of solutions does such an equation have?
We talked about it last time,
and there are two basic solutions
that this equation has.
One of them is a function
of z plus t,
and the other is a function of z minus t.
These are the two solutions
which represent waves moving to the right
along the z-axis,
and waves moving to the left.
This one represents waves moving to the right
along the positive z-axis.
This one represents waves moving
along the left, to the left.
And the function of z is
any function,
any shaped wave profile,
take any shaped wave profile at all,
and allow it to just move
uniformly along the z-direction,
that constitutes a wave
moving down the z-axis
along the positive z-direction.
That's a function of z minus t.
If the wave moves in the other direction,
then it's the same function of z plus t.
So that's the basic fact
that we learned last time about waves.
And there's one particular special kind of wave,
the sine or cosine wave.
Let's just write it down
for future reference.
A wave which really has a wavy look to it,
like this.
Well, you can guess that's
either a sine or a cosine.
And so, for example,
a wave of this type moving off to the right
would be a solution of the wave equation
which has the form cosine
of z minus t.
z minus t because it's moving to the right.
And furthermore, you can throw in a constant here,
usually called k, the wave number.
Any constant.
The bigger the constant is, incidentally,
the shorter the wavelength of the wave.
So if k is big, the wave looks like this.
If k is small, the wave looks like this.
Those are the basic facts
that I want you to remember
about wave equations
and, in particular, wave solutions.
That they are functions of
z minus t, z plus t.
They can have different wavelengths.
And they can be sines, cosines.
And they move to the right,
or they move to the left.
That's it.
That's what we need to know about waves.
Before we go ahead with Maxwell's equations,
just to remind you,
just to, since it's been a
week since we went through this,
I will remind you of a little bit of mathematics.
Elementary mathematics.
First of all is the notion
of the cross product of two vectors.
If we have any two vectors,
these are ordinary vectors, not four vectors now,
ordinary three-dimensional vectors
in three-dimensional space,
then we have the cross product,
b dot a,
b cross a, excuse me,
the cross product of two vectors.
The cross product is itself another vector.
If we have two vectors,
each pointing in some direction with a given length,
we can multiply them together
and make another vector.
The cross product is defined by its components.
So for example, the x component
of b cross a is defined,
this is definition,
is defined to be
by times ax minus bx times ay.
And now if you want to find the other components,
you just cycle through x, y, and z.
So for example,
b cross a, the y component,
you go x to y,
equals b,
well, y goes to z,
x goes to y,
the root is x to y, y to z,
z back to x.
b goes to z,
sorry, y goes to z,
x goes to y,
minus b, y,
a goes to z.
And likewise for the last,
I'm doing this once, I won't do it again.
b cross a,
z component of it,
is equal to
x, y, the next,
y, z, the next one must be x, b, x,
x, y, the next one must be z,
minus b, z, a, x.
These are definitions.
These are definitions of the
cross product between two vectors.
Notice that the cross product itself has components,
and so it must be a vector.
Okay?
Now, another way of multiplying two
vectors together is the dot product.
The dot product,
the dot product of two vectors
is a scalar,
a dot b, and it only has one component.
It's the same in every reference frame,
or the same
when you rotate the reference frame.
And its definition is a, x, b, x,
plus a, y, b, y,
plus a, z, b, z.
Can that be read? I hope that can be read.
a, x, b, x, plus
a, y, b, y, plus a, z, b, z.
That's the dot product,
and it's a scalar.
That's one set of concepts that,
that we've been through several times.
Now the other set of concepts
are the curl of a vector
and the divergence of a vector.
And here's the way you think about them.
They're built up out of derivatives
of the components of the vector.
Partial derivatives with respect to x, y, and z.
All you have to imagine in your head
is that derivative with respect to x,
and derivative with respect to y,
and derivative with respect to z,
pretend that those symbols
are the three components of a vector.
They're not.
They're the three components of a derivative.
But just pretend that they're
the three components of a vector.
And now, imagine del cross a vector a.
What does that mean?
It's something that's made up out of the derivatives
of the components of a,
but, oh, I'm sorry,
the three components are called the vector del.
Del is just a shorthand for upside down triangle.
Del cross a. How do you make it?
Well, you just go back to this formula,
and wherever you saw a stick in,
either d by dx, d
by dy, or d by dz.
So the curl of a is then just,
well, we have a, so that's d by dx.
I should have called this b, shouldn't I?
It would have made more sense
and been nicer if I would have called this b.
All right.
So instead of a,
we write the three components of the derivative.
Wherever we see b, we just stick b.
So that's bx,
and we're going to do the curl.
We're doing the curl.
Slow down.
The curl is over here.
The x component of the curl,
del cross b,
the x component of it,
all right, that's this.
All right.
So it's ax by,
well, that's d by dx by,
d by dy,
minus d by dy bx.
We can go through it and cycle through it
and find the other components of the curl of b,
but they're always made up,
d by dy, d by dy.
They're always made up of
derivatives of the components of b
in the same pattern,
in the same exact pattern that
the cross product is made up.
What about del dot b?
That's called the divergence of b.
Del dot b,
well, we come to the definition of the divergence
of the dot product.
Ax times bx,
that will be d by dx,
bx,
plus d by dy,
by,
plus d by dz,
bz.
Now, these two objects,
they're composed out of derivatives of the components
of vectors.
If a vector is constant in space,
if it's a vector field which is constant in space,
it has neither a divergence nor a curl.
Roughly speaking,
a vector has a divergence
when it seems to be emanating,
a vector field has a divergence
when it seems to be emanating out of some place,
like this.
A vector has a curl
when it seems to,
curl around some place.
So if we had a magnetic field, for example,
in a wire that was going into the blackboard,
that vector would have a curl.
If we have an electric charge
giving rise to an electric field
pointing out from some point,
that field would have a divergence.
We've gone through these things before,
these are not new,
just reminding you of them.
And now I want to write down Maxwell's equations
in terms of these objects.
Our goal is going to be to write Maxwell's equations,
that's easy,
you can get them off somebody's t-shirt,
lots and lots of t-shirts with Maxwell's equations on them.
But then to understand in what sense
they are the same in every reference frame.
That's our goal,
to see that Maxwell's equations
can be written in a form
which is the same in every reference frame.
Alright, so let me write them down.
Curl of the electric field,
of the electric field, you construct its curl,
is equal to minus
the time derivative of the magnetic field.
That's Maxwell equation number one.
Maxwell equation number two,
divergence of the magnetic field,
is equal to zero.
All that says,
is that the magnetic field
doesn't have any sources
in the same sense that the electric field does.
It doesn't emanate out from a point,
it tends to wind around things.
Okay, the next equation
is an equation similar to this,
but it involves del cross of the magnetic field,
and it's equal to plus
dE by dt.
So these two equations look very similar.
It's almost as though you interchanged
the electric and magnetic field,
but not quite.
There's a sign difference between them.
If you just interchanged the magnetic and electric field,
you'd get the wrong sign here.
And the last one is just
del dot E equals zero.
And this is the same equation
in quite parallel with the magnetic field here.
These are the basic Maxwell's equations,
but these are the Maxwell's equations
when there are no charges around,
in the absence of charges and currents.
Let me put back in
what happens when there are charges and currents.
In other words,
these are the equations that are called
the vacuum Maxwell equations.
They describe electric and magnetic fields
in completely infinite terms.
They have no electric charges,
no currents.
Let me just tell you now
what happens if you add in
some electric charges,
some electric currents,
and so forth.
They do have an effect on things.
And so, for example,
I'm going to write in red here
the actual thing that goes.
The charge density
is called rho,
and it's the amount of
electric charge per unit volume.
At every point in space,
there may or may not be some charge.
In every little cell of space,
there may be some charge.
The charge per unit volume
is called the charge density.
So what really goes here
is the charge density.
But if there is no charge density,
well, then it just isn't there.
Over here,
there's another term,
and it's the electric current.
It's called J,
and I'll define it for you later.
But for the moment,
I want to study the Maxwell equations
without electric current and charges.
We want to see if we can understand
why those equations
are the same in every reference frame.
How can that possibly be?
Why is it a puzzle?
It's a puzzle because,
as we're going to see,
these equations describe light waves
moving always with the same speed.
They're always moving at the same speed.
They always move with the same speed,
the speed of light.
They move down the axis with the speed of light.
How can they possibly be the same
in every reference frame?
After all, if I was a reference frame
moving down following the wave,
I would expect to see it moving slower.
Nevertheless,
these equations are the same
in every reference frame,
and in every reference frame
they say the speed of light is exactly the same.
So let's see if we can recast
these four equations
which is the same in every reference frame.
We have the tools to do it.
What we have to remember
is that
the electric and magnetic fields
combine together, we did this last time,
combine together
into a tensor,
into an anti-symmetric tensor.
So let's remind ourselves of that.
Anti-symmetric tensor,
F mu nu,
and it's made up
it's 4 by 4, it's a matrix,
and its components are made up
out of the electric and magnetic field.
Since it's anti-symmetric,
it has zeros on the diagonal.
Incidentally,
in the first row, in the first column,
I'm going to put the time component,
the time component,
the x, y, and z components.
Alright, let's
we don't need this here.
Alright, so let's
let me just fill it in for you.
Minus the x
component of the electric field,
minus the y
and minus the z component
of the electric field.
And down here, we have plus
e sub x,
plus e sub y,
and plus e sub z.
An anti-symmetric matrix always
has the property that what's above
the diagonal here is the
negative of what's below the diagonal.
Alright, now what about
in these missing slots over here?
That's where the magnetic fields go.
Right over here, you have minus
b sub z,
b sub y,
and minus b sub x.
And then down here,
you just have
the
reflected
plus b sub z,
minus b sub y,
and plus b sub x.
This is the electromagnetic
field tensor.
It transforms
under Lorentz transformations
as an anti-symmetric tensor.
I showed you how to do that last
time, and
there's nothing new about it
for the moment.
Let's see, we would call this
component over here
the tx component.
The first row here refers to
time.
The second row, well,
the first row is time, the second row is x,
the third row is y, the fourth row is z.
And likewise for the
columns. We would call this
e,
or we would call this f,
this element over here
would be
mu equals t,
mu equals x.
So as mu and nu
both run over x, y, z, and t,
we fill out this matrix.
That's the notion of the electromagnetic
field tensor. And as I
said, it transforms in the
right way to be a tensor.
There is another
tensor that you can make up out of
the electromagnetic field.
It is also a tensor,
and it is made up
by simply replacing
electric field by magnetic field,
and magnetic field by electric field.
We just look at these
equations and we see that the electric field
and magnetic field occur almost
symmetrically. It might not
be a great surprise that there's another
tensor
which is made up of exactly,
I won't write equal, but another tensor.
It's usually
called f with a little
twiddle on top of it.
And all it is,
is it's the same object, except with
electric and magnetic fields
in it. So,
you don't quite change
electric to magnetic and magnetic
to electric. You change
electric to magnetic,
but magnetic to minus
electric. Do I have that right?
No, I don't quite.
You replace electric
by minus
magnetic, and
magnetic by electric.
That's in order to account
for the sign difference here.
When you do that, you
discover that there's another tensor quantity
I'm not going to try to prove
for you that this transforms like a tensor
It's just a straightforward exercise
And I'm not as young as I used to be, so I
don't do as much exercise as I used to on the blackboard
I won't do it, but we'll just write it down
Wherever you see electric, put minus magnetic
Wherever you see magnetic, put electric
So, F twiddle, the other electromagnetic field tensor
Again, zero on the diagonals
And then plus B sub X,
B sub Y, and B sub Z
And then wherever we see magnetic, we put back electric
So minus EZ
Z
EY
Minus EX
And then on the other side here,
you just have to remember that it's anti-symmetric
So everything on the reflected side of the matrix here
is just the opposite, the negative of what it is
In the upper half of a matrix
I won't bother writing it out
These are two tensor quantities
Both of which have the same transformation properties
And on the Lorentz transformations form a
coherent set of objects which are a tensor
Anti-symmetric tensor
If we can succeed in writing Maxwell's equations
Here they are right here
If we can succeed in rewriting them in terms
of these objects in a way that looks covariant
Which looks the same in all reference frames
Then we will have proved that these
ways are the same in all reference frames
And we can prove that these equations
here are the same in all reference frames
This is not hard to do
So let's see if we can guess the answer
Notice that Maxwell's equations each
have one derivative in them
They don't have second derivatives
There are many derivatives of course
There is a derivative with respect to t
There is a derivative with respect to x
But they never have higher derivatives
They never have second derivatives, third
derivatives, fourth derivatives, these are not possible
fourth derivatives and so forth. And so we
might try to see if these equations here can
be rewritten in terms of these field of tensors.
What can we write? We have F mu nu. That's
the electric and magnetic field. We can differentiate
it. But what can we differentiate it with
respect to? We can differentiate it, of course, with
respect to some x. But we want to make
this equation, whatever it is, we want to
make it the same in every reference frame.
And that means we want to match
indices, covariant and contravariant indices. About the only
thing we can write down is this. Derivative with respect
to x mu of F mu nu is equal to
zero. First of all, let's count how many equations
there are.
Let's count how many equations there are.
There's one for each nu. Remember, we sum
over mu. Mu is a summation index. So
that's not a free index in this problem. There's
one equation for each nu. That means
there are four equations. Those four equations we
will see are, let's see, they are these four
equations right here. Why do I say there are
four equations here?
Here's one. And now there are three components
of this vector equation. This is a vector
equation. There are three components, e x, e
y, and e z. Three components here, one here.
Those are four components. Let's check. Let's
actually check that these four equations are
what we get from this. It's not hard. We just
write it out. First of all, mu can be t. So
in this equation, of movie z. And n times n.
So mu x or mu y, you can write mu, du,
ju. Let's write the off, the
fate, the gozone, and dec glacier
força. All in all, that's
the secret to everything we have.
Then remember, M is infinity.
We're going to write this by the direction we want.
xz plus d by dy of fyz
plus d by dz of fzz equals 0.
That's what this would say if it's true.
What about this term?
Derivative with respect to z of fzz.
fzz is 0 because all
of the diagonal elements are 0.
Alright, so we can forget this.
This isn't there.
fzz is 0.
What is fxz?
Well, to see what fxz is, we go
to the x row and the z column.
That's by.
That's my.
So let's just plug it in.
That's by.
What is fyz?
For that, we go to the y row
to the zth column and that's minus bx.
So that gives us minus bx.
Well, that's looking good.
This is d by dx of
by minus d by dy of bx.
This looks very much like a
piece of the curl of b.
And that's what it is.
What about ftz?
Well, we go to the t row to
the zth place and we get minus ez.
So this is minus e sub z.
So this is minus the derivative.
So this is the time derivative of
e sub z with respect to t.
All of that equals 0.
Well, if you look at it carefully, you'll
see that it's exactly the equation over here,
the zth component of it.
The time derivative of e sub z is
the z component of the curl of b.
That's exactly what we have here.
So we check that the.
The.
Let's see, which component was that?
That was the z component over here.
The z component just gives us
back one of the Maxwell equations,
namely the z component of a Maxwell equation.
The only other case which is interesting is to
write down the time component here or the t component.
t for time.
Well, let's continue to call it mu nu.
Let's work out.
Let's work out the time component of this equation.
What does this read now?
First of all, it has a term
which is d by dt of ft t.
That's mu equals t.
But that's 0.
ft t, that's right here.
That's 0.
So that's 0.
And then we have, what else?
d by d.
d by dx of fxt plus d by dy
of fy t plus d by dz of fzt.
Well, what is fxt, yt, and zt?
Those are just the components of the electric field.
So fxt minus, with a minus sign, is ex.
The other one is ey
and the other one is ez.
So all this says, when packaged neatly, is
that the derivative with respect to x of ex
plus the derivative with respect to y of ey plus the
derivative with respect to z of ez is equal to 0.
That, my friends, is just del dot e equals 0.
For the moment, we've been
ignoring charges and current density.
Charges and currents.
So you can see that, um, that two of the, sorry,
four of the Maxwell equations, four of the eight Maxwell equations,
just have the form
of a relativistically
covariant, same in every reference frame, vector equation.
It's a vector equation because
the left-hand side is a vector.
It's a vector because it is the
derivative where you've contracted the index mu.
There's only one index left over.
And so this is a vector equation.
It's the same in every reference frame.
The point is that if
you went through the entire labor
of doing the Lorentz transformations on the coordinates
and on the components of e and b,
you would find out that after the
Lorentz transformation, the equation was exactly the same.
Okay.
What about the other half of the Maxwell equations?
Well, those have exactly the same form,
except
with twiddle here.
So,
with twiddle here,
of course they have exactly the same form.
f twiddle is the same as
f except with e and b interchanged,
and an extra minus sign thrown in.
Well, that's exactly what's here.
If you go from here to here by interchanging
electric and magnetic fields with an extra sign here,
the equations are the same.
So, this is a powerful way to rewrite Maxwell's equations.
Again, without charges, without current densities.
This is a powerful way to rewrite
them in a simple and elegant form,
but it's not the simplicity and elegance which is important.
It's the recognition that these are four vector equations,
and therefore the same in every reference frame.
Okay.
So, Maxwell's equations then are relativistically invariant.
They don't change from frame to frame.
We'll put back charges and currents in a little while,
but, or maybe next time,
well, I think we'll do it this time,
but, um,
now that we've found that Maxwell's equations
are the same in every reference frame,
what do they say?
What are the implications
of these eight equations?
What kind of electromagnetic fields do they allow?
What do they describe?
So, let's again forget currents
and densities for the moment.
Zero, nothing there.
And let's study these four,
they're not four equations, they're eight equations.
Let's study them and see if we
can make wave equations out of them.
Now, if we go back,
I don't know what we did with the wave equation,
we had it someplace here.
There it is.
The wave equation is an equation with second derivatives.
Second derivatives mean you differentiate twice.
Okay.
Maxwell's equations all have only first derivatives,
but they have two distinct fields, E and B.
We're going to find out that having,
we have first order equations
because they only have first derivatives,
but we have first order derivatives,
first order equations for E and
first order equations for B, two variables.
We're going to find out that
that's equivalent to having second order equations
for either the electric field
or the magnetic field separately.
This is not hard to do.
This is easy to do, so we need,
let's see, we'll need a clear blackboard over here,
and we'll need to manipulate this a little bit.
I have E and B all mixed up,
but I want to write an
equation just for the electric field.
I want to try to isolate just the electric field
and see how it behaves.
So here's what I do.
Let's see.
Take this equation over here,
and let's differentiate it with respect to time.
It's got only one time derivative in it.
Let's differentiate it again with respect to time
so that we get a second time derivative.
Then it will be d second E by dt squared,
second derivative of the electric field,
and that's going to equal del
cross the time derivative of B.
If I differentiate with respect to time over here,
I just get the second
time derivative of the electric field.
If I differentiate with respect to t over here,
that just differentiates,
the magnetic field with respect to time.
Okay, that hasn't helped yet.
I still have the electric and
the magnetic field in the same equation.
The goal was to get rid of the magnetic field.
But look, right here I have the magnetic field,
or its time derivative,
written in terms of the electric field.
So I can be clever and
simply get rid of dB dt here
and call it curl of E,
minus the curl of E.
Okay, so let's just...
Let's first...
It was...
What was it?
It was del cross dB dt.
And now for dB dt,
we substitute minus curl of E.
So that gives us a minus sign
and a curl of E.
Here we have an equation
which only involves the electric field,
second derivative with respect to t,
on the left-hand side,
and various complicated derivatives on the right-hand side.
What I'm going to do is I'm going to take
the x component of this equation.
Both sides of the equations are vectors.
E is a vector.
Differentiating it with respect to time leaves it a vector.
And the cross product, or the curl of a curl,
is also a vector.
So let's take the x component of both sides.
The x component of both sides.
What we have to calculate
is the x component of the curl of the curl.
That's a slightly tedious operation.
If you like, you can
go to sleep for two minutes
until I get the answer,
but I will do it on the blackboard for you.
Okay, del cross del cross E, the x component.
All right.
What we have to know is that the x component
of a curl,
the x component of a curl,
is equal to the derivative of the z component
with respect to y,
minus the derivative of the y component
with respect to z.
All right.
We are taking the x component of del cross A,
of del cross A.
That's this.
All right.
So now we want the x
component of del cross del cross E.
That means I just substitute for A.
Wherever I see A, I substitute del cross E.
So let's see.
What's that going to give me?
That's going to give me d by dy of Az,
which should be del cross E,
the z component of it,
minus d by dz of del cross E,
the y component of it.
But now we substitute for these components the same trick.
The same trick.
And here is the result, the grand result.
It's d by dy with derivative
of Ey with respect to x,
minus the derivative of Az,
which is the z component of the y component.
So that's d by dy with respect to x,
minus the derivative of Ex with respect to y.
That's d by dy of this term.
And then there are two more.
Plus d by dz of the Ex by dz,
minus the Ez by dx.
I think that's it.
That's it.
Two terms.
Okay.
Okay, wake up now.
The worst is over.
Let's see what we have.
We're calculating the x component of a vector.
Let's see what we have here.
We first of all have second
derivatives of Ex with respect to y.
Now let's see what we have here.
First of all, we have the derivative of X.
Now, what we have is this term.
We have exp of z.
Let's call d by dy squared of Ex.
That's this term.
We cross them out as we pick them off.
That's this.
d by dy squared, two derivatives
with respect to y of Ex.
We have two derivatives with respect to z of Ex,
plus second derivative with respect to z squared of Ex.
this
and then we get two other terms
which look a little
mysterious
what are they?
they are
derivative with respect to x
of
dy ey
that's this term over here
it looks a little different because
I've interchanged the x and y derivative
it was derivative with respect to x
followed by derivative with respect to y
you're allowed to interchange those
so the first term here is d by dx of
dy ey
and then there's another term which is
d by dx
of
I think it's dz
ez
neither one of these, the top one
or the bottom one, looks very elegant
but if I add a term to the top
and subtract the same term
from the bottom
the whole thing will have a nice form
so let's add
plus
d by dx squared ex
and let's now subtract
d by dx
of
ex
I have added and subtracted exactly the same thing
now you should be able to see a pattern
first of all we have
dy ey plus dz ez
this should be a
I think I
overall sign mistake
yeah
dy ey plus dz ez
d z ez and d x ex
appear inside here
what is that
that's just del dot e
but del dot e is equal to zero
that's one of Maxwell's equations
and so all of this
d x ex plus dy ey
plus d z ez is just zero
not there at all
what about this term?
this is nice
but what about this term?
the second derivative with respect to y squared
x squared and z squared
of the same quantity
e sub x
let's put it together now
let's put it together
what was it?
here's what we were doing
the second derivative with respect to x of t squared
is minus
del cross del cross e
the x component of it
and that's exactly what we computed over here
that long tedious computation
just give us a left hand side
let's erase it
and let's replace it by what we computed
and you'll see a pattern
it is
d by dx squared
ex
plus d by dy squared
plus d by dz squared
e x
if you've kept track
which you probably have not
of the original wave equation
you'll see that this is just a wave equation
for the component e x
e x is a field which satisfies
just the same old wave equation
that we wrote down for phi
if you remember we wrote
down a wave equation for phi
it had exactly the same form
and so what we're going
to do is we're going to
we're going to write down a wave equation
which satisfies the same form
and so e
the electric field
itself
satisfies a wave equation
a good old wave equation
the same wave equation which had
right moving and left moving solutions
which could be sines and cosines
what have we learned
we've learned that there are waves
of electric field
that can propagate
we've learned that
the wave equation
propagating waves
that can move to the left or right
applies
or any other direction of course
but which applies to
to the scalar field
also applies directly
to the components of the electric field
alright let's see whether we can build ourselves
an electric wave
an electromagnetic wave
this equation
has solutions
of the form
for example
e
is equal to cosine
of
let's just take a simple example
z minus t
this would be a wave
moving down
the axis
it's a wave equation
it has a solution
which is a wave moving down the z axis
alright that's what this cos is
z minus t is
I could put a constant k
but let's leave it out
it only complicates things
alright
this would be a wave
whose electric field
is pointed along the x axis
let's draw some coordinates
here's z
here's x
and here's y sticking out of the blackboard
this is a wave
moving down the z axis
its electric field
is along the x axis
for simplicity
let's take it not to have it
but to have any component along the y axis
and it looks like a cosine
so it's an electric field
points up
points down
and it propagates
needless to say with the speed of light
why the speed of light?
we've worked in units in which
the speed of light is one
and this is just a
wave moving down the z axis
with unit velocity
z proportional to t
the whole thing just makes
an excursion down the z axis
without changing shape
alright
that's the electric field
and I've chosen it arbitrarily
to point in the x direction
incidentally
a wave, an electromagnetic wave
where the electric field points along the x direction
is called a polarized wave
polarized along the x axis
this is polarized light
polarized light polarized along the x axis
what about the magnetic field?
can the magnetic field be any
oh, wait, before we do that
let's do
we've decided arbitrarily somewhat
to set the y component equal to zero
let's just do that
we could have put a y component in also
but I decided just to keep it simple
what about the z component of the
of the electric field?
let me prove to you
that that has to be zero
it has to be zero because
del dot e is equal to zero
what is del dot e?
it's the derivative of the
x component with respect to x
but the x component doesn't depend on x
plus the derivative of the
y component with respect to y
also doesn't depend on y
plus the derivative of the
z component with respect to z
these two terms in the
divergence of the electric field vanish
so must this one
so what that says is that the derivative of
ez with respect to z must be equal to zero
in other words, the z component of the magnetic field
of the electric field cannot
vary as you move along here
it must be constant
constant
could be a constant electric field
let's just throw it away
a constant electric field is not very interesting
it's certainly not part of a wave motion
we could get rid of it
by putting it between capacitor plates
and canceling the uniform electric field
the point is that the wave part of the field
the part that varies as
you go down the z axis
must not be there for the z component
so only the x component
of the electric field is there
the y component and the
z component are just not there
zero
what does that mean about the magnetic field?
well, we can use this equation over here
to tell us something about the magnetic field
first of all, what about
the curl of the electric field?
the curl of the electric field
what components does the curl of the electric field have?
well, the only components that it can have
would have to come from something like
dx by dz
that's the kind of thing that appears
in the curl of the electric field
well, you would also have minus dz by dx
this would be the y component of the curl
but the z component isn't there
we've already established that
so that's not there
so for example, this would be the y component
of the curl of the electric field
it's there
if you differentiate ex with respect to z
you'll get an answer
you will get an answer
so there is a y
component to the curl of e
and that's all
there is no other component to the curl of e
except for the y component
we could look for some other component
let's look for the z component
that would be dx by y minus dy by x
well, ex doesn't depend on y
and ey is zero altogether
there's no other component
so the only component of the curl of e
is along the y-axis
the electric field is along the x-axis
is the z-axis
and the magnetic field is along the y-axis
why is the magnetic field along the y-axis?
because its time derivative is along the y-axis
if the time derivative is along the y-axis
the field itself must be along the y-axis
right, here
So we see then that the magnetic field,
let's draw the magnetic field in green, lies perpendicular
Let's see if we can draw it.
Here's the magnetic field. Here's the electric field.
Electric and magnetic field are perpendicular to each other
and they're also perpendicular to the motion of the wave
That's what follows from these equations. The whole set of equations
has wave-like solutions with the electric and magnetic field both oscillating
They're both going up and down, except the magnetic field is going
left and right, and the whole thing is proceeding down the z-axis
That's the nature of electromagnetic field
So we have electromagnetic waves. Electric and magnetic fields perpendicular to the direction
of motion, all moving uniformly down the axis with the speed of light
What's more, you can be sure that if you were to take this electromagnetic wave
and look at it from another frame of reference, it would have exactly the same properties
Why? Because the Maxwell equations are
the same in every reference frame
So the properties of electromagnetic field
are the same in every reference frame
And they'll always have this property of moving with the speed of
light and having electric, crossed electric and magnetic fields perpendicular to each other
And to the direction of motion
That's the character of light
and all other electromagnetic radiation
Alright, now let's put back the things we took out
Namely, let's ask the question, what
is the relationship between the two?
Let's ask what happens when we
have charges and currents in Maxwell's equations
How do we describe it?
How do we describe it and what does it do?
Most important, is it Lorentz invariant? In other
words, is it the same in every reference frame?
That is our major goal, to show that the
laws of electromagnetism are the same in every reference frame
So what do we have to do?
I'll just remind you
That the two Maxwell equations on the right hand side
Strictly speaking, the four Maxwell
equations on the right hand side
Get modified
They get modified by putting a charge density
And I will explain what that means
on the right hand side over here
Plus a current density
The current is the current of electric charge
So let me explain what those things mean
The charge density is the current of electric charge
The charge density, which is called rho
This is the symbol rho
I don't know why charge density has
always had the symbol rho associated with it
Nor do I know why the current
has the symbol j associated with it
But it goes way back
I think it goes back to Faraday
But if not, it goes back further than me anyway
Rho, the charge density, is the
charge density of electric charge density
Rho, the charge density, is defined in the following way
Imagine you have lots and lots and lots of electrons
And they could be other kinds of charged particles
Protons, even some neutral particles, it doesn't matter
But that space is filled with a lot of particles
So many of them, charges of different kinds
That you're tempted to think of
it as a continuous distribution of charge
Just like water is a bunch of molecules
But when you look at water in a coarse-grained way
You think about water as being
a nice continuous distribution of stuff
Okay
Now, you take a little volume of space
A little volume of space, let's call it volume V
Make it a small volume
We're going to think calculus,
we're going to think differentially
A small volume of space
Let's call it dV
And take the charge density
And the charge in that small volume of space
If the volume of the space is very
small and shrunk to smaller and smaller dimensions
Of course the charge will also
shrink to smaller and smaller dimensions
But the ratio, let's call
the amount of charge in there
Let's call it dQ
A small charge in a small volume
And the ratio of the amount of
charge per unit volume is called the density
Okay
So it's the charge per unit volume
Except that each point of space evaluated separately
So it could vary from place to place
You can have regions with heavy charge density
Regions with light charge density
And in calculating this, you add up the plus charges
You subtract off the minus charges
All the obvious things
Add the protons, subtract the electrons
And get a net charge
density of the volume of space
And that charge density is itself a function of position
But it could also depend on time
How could it depend on time?
Well, for example, charges could
move from one place to another
This whole pile of charge could move over to here
In which case if we stood at a particular point
The charge density would change
It would change from something to nothing
So the charge density also depends on the time
Now it can't depend in any old way
There is a rule in nature
And it's called the conservation of charge
The total amount of charge
in the world must not change
So how much, what is the total
amount of charge in the whole world?
You add up all of the
charges in each little cell of space
So the total amount of charge in the whole world
Is the total amount of charge in the whole world
You add it all up and that becomes an integral
The total charge, let's call it capital Q
Total charge in the world is the integral
Over all the volume of space
Of the charge density
Little dv here, that just means
you add up all of the cells
In each cell there's a charge
Which is equal to dq
Which is rho times dv
So you add up all the rho times dv
That's what an integral is, it
just means add them all up
And that gives you the total charge
In this case in the whole world
We could also for example just talk
about the charge in a region of space
We could pick a particular region of space
With well defined boundaries
This room
Or some other particular region of space
And talk about the charge in that
In that region
In which case this integral wouldn't go over all space
It would just go over the selected region
In this case for example the room
And that would be the charge inside the room
Now charge is not allowed to just change some place
And reappear some place else
It's not allowed according to the laws of physics
For reasons that will become more
or less clear in a second
To suddenly disappear over here
And reappear over here
Well let's go back a step
First of all
The rule of nature
And it's an empirical law of nature
The empirical law of nature is
That the total amount of
charge in the universe never changes
That's called conservation of electric charge
But the rule is stronger than that
For example you could have a situation
Where charge on the earth disappears
And instantly with nothing happening in between
The same charge appears on Mars
That would satisfy the rules of the conservation of charge
That the amount of charge doesn't change
What was lost on earth reappeared on Mars
And the conservation of charge does not tell you
That something has to happen in between
But that's forbidden
That's not the way charges change
And that's not the way charges move
They can't disappear over here
And reappear over here
Unless there's a flow of charge in between
In other words
If charge disappears over here
And reappears over here
Somebody in between had better be
seeing a current flow between them
How do we express this idea
That charges don't just appear and disappear
And in fact they don't
They don't move from one place to another
Except by virtue
Of a current of electric charge
Flowing from one place to another
So for that
We have to invent the idea of a current
So let me explain what a current is
It's a simple idea
Let's put this upstairs
And bring this downstairs
Let's take a little area in space
There's a little area in space
I'm going to redraw it
A little area, a small area
An infinitesimally small area
It's normally called d sigma
D indicating that it's small, differential
And sigma standing for surface area
So the amount of surface area is called d sigma
But when people write d sigma
They mean something a little more
They mean a vector
Now how the hell can an area be a vector
Well what you do is you take that area
And you assign to it
A vector perpendicular to the area
To the area element
We'll decide in a few minutes which direction
Do I do it to the
left or do it to the right
But for the moment
Just imagine assigning
To every little element of area
A vector whose length, whose magnitude
Is the little area
And whose direction is perpendicular
to the direction of area
That's called the surface element vector
The surface element vector d sigma
I could put a little vector symbol above it
But we don't need it
Just d sigma
Now we can ask how much charge
Flows through that area
In a unit of time
How much charge flows through that area
Per unit time
Or better yet
We can ask how much charge
Per time per unit area
Flows through there
The charge flowing through there
Will certainly be proportional to the area
If the area is tiny
A small amount of charge will
be able to flow through it
For a given situation
If the area is made large
A larger amount of charge can be flowing through it
The charge per unit area
Per unit
Time
Charge per unit area
Let's write the words
Charge
Per unit
Area
Per unit time
Through a little surface element
Is called
The current
Now the current is a vector
The current is a vector
You can see why that should be so
Current is kind of like
Flow
Think of it as a flow
of all the electrons and protons
Flowing through space
At any point
The flow has a direction
Namely the direction that the charges are flowing in
And it also has a magnitude
And the magnitude is
The charge per unit area
Per unit
Per unit time
Flowing through that area
That's the definition of the char- of the current
And as I said it is a vector
If I want to know
The amount of charge per unit time
Flowing through the surface element
Then what I do is I take the dot product
Of the surface element
With
The current
Both of them being the current
Both of them being vectors
If for example
The current is flowing
Parallel to the surface
That means the current is perpendicular to d sigma
Then this product is zero
So if the current flows
If the current flows along the surface
No current flows from one side to the other
If the current is flowing perpendicular
To the surface
That means it's parallel to d sigma
Then you get the full maximum brunt of the flow
Through the surface element
That's why it's the dot product
The dot product measures the component of
one vector in the direction of the other
So this measures the component of the flow
In the direction perpendicular to the surface element
And it is
Not the charge per unit area per unit time
But just the charge per unit time
This is the charge per unit time
Charge
Per unit time
Through
The surface element d sigma
So now you have the idea
Of the flow of charge
And the
Sometimes called the flux of charge
Flow or flux of charge
And current or electric current
Are all the same thing
Okay
So we're not necessarily talking
about a current through a wire
A current through a wire is a special case
And if we opened up the wire
and made it a little bit big
We could put little surface elements of area in there
And see that the current through a wire
Is made up out of exactly these kind of currents
Fluxes of charge through the wire
But that's a special case
We can have currents flowing through space
Space currents
Or just currents flowing along sheets
Or just currents flowing along three dimensional space
And that's the definition of J
Okay now let's concentrate on the following question
Here we have a region of space
It has some charge in it
And the charge in it
is the integral over the volume
Of the charge density
Okay
If there are currents flowing
There may be currents flowing
into or out of the region
Let's choose
Let's choose to make up the boundary of the region
Out of a whole bunch of little surface elements
Alright so the boundary is made up
I don't mean
I mean the boundary
If we thought of this as a balloon
Then the rubber of the balloon
Would make up
Out of a lot of little surface elements here
And now let's by definition
Point their little d-sigmas out of the balloon
Let's choose to make them out of the balloon
Supposing there's a net current flowing out of the balloon
What does that say about the charge inside the balloon?
Incidentally I'm not imagining the
balloon changing its size or anything
It's just a fixed region of space
If there's current flowing
Net current flowing out of the surface
Then the current on the inside must be changing
The only way that the current can change
The only way the charge can change on the inside
It's by passing from the inside to the outside
So if the charge is just changing
If the charge on the inside is changing
You can be certain that there must be
that there must be a
flow of current through the boundary
and that tells you that there must be a J
In fact we can write down a simple equation
We can write down that the time rate of change
of the charge inside this region
dq by dt
that's equal
to the integral dv
of d rho by dt
The time rate of change
of the electric charge inside this region
must equal
the current that's passing out through the boundary
actually with the opposite sign
If current is passing out through
the boundary with a positive sign
then the charge must be decreasing on the inside
So it must have a minus sign in this formula
And what's the total charge that passes
out of this region per unit time
The total charge passing out
of the region per unit time
is just the integral
of the current
dotted into the surface element
We just add up all the currents passing through
each one of these surface elements
That's the integral here
And this is a theorem now
Or if you like
perhaps it's a law of nature
rather than a theorem
that
the time rate of change
of the current on the inside
is equal to the flux of charge
passing out through the surface of the balloon
And that's given by the integral of the current
dotted into d sigma
Okay
Now we need a true theorem
A mathematical theorem
rather than a law of nature
And the mathematical theorem
which we won't prove
It's called Gauss's law
Sorry
It is not called Gauss's law
It is called Gauss's theorem
Look up Gauss's theorem
It's sometimes called the divergence theorem
But I will tell you what it is
It's a relationship
between
This is called a surface integral
It's an integral of a vector quantity
over a surface
over a bounding surface
It can be related
to an integral
over the interior
And here's the theorem
called Gauss's theorem
Gauss's theorem
It says
that the integral
of any vector
integrated over the surface
is equal
Now this is an integral
over the surface
Let's call it surface
is equal to an integral
over the volume
Now if I had my class here
I would ask them
what goes in there
Anybody know?
No, okay
The divergence of the vector
The divergence of the vector itself
So it's a relationship
between a surface integral of a vector
and the integral
over the volume
of the divergence of the vector
It's not obvious
I'm not going to prove it
It actually doesn't take
very many lines to prove
But let's assume it
If we assume it
then we can write
the right hand side of this equation
as an integral over the volume
So it's an integral over the volume
another integral over the volume
of the divergence of the current
It's the spreading out of the current
The spreading out of the current
You know what it's like
It's almost like this
I'll give you a picture
of what the divergence of a vector is
If you thought of the vector
as the flow vector of some water
Perhaps
a flow vector of some water
And supposing some water
was being pumped in
at each point of space
Some hidden little pipes
that you can't see
are bringing water in from outside
and dumping it in
The pipes end
in different places in space
So the water is diverging out
away from the tips of the pipes
and going out and filling up space
The divergence of the vector
is the divergence of the water
or the divergence of the flow of the water
is basically just the water
coming out of these individual pipes
And what this theorem says
is that the amount of water
that's coming out of these little pipes
that are ending at this point
and flowing out
Where's that water going to go?
It has to go out of the surface
And that's this expression here
The divergence, the integral over the boundary
of the surface flow
is also equal to the integral over the interior
of the volume of the divergence of the vector
So that's a general theorem about vectors
It doesn't have anything particular to do with electricity
It doesn't have anything particular to do
with anything special
other than
mathematical properties of vectors
Alright, so now we have a new theorem
that the integral over any volume
take any volume whatever
the integral over any volume
of the time rate of
change of the density of charge
is the integral over the volume
of the divergence of the current
If two integrals like this are equal
but they're equal not only
for some particular volume
but they're true
it's true for every volume that you can think of
then there's only one way that that can be true
If for any region that you can pick
the integral over the volume of one thing
is equal to the integral
over the volume of another thing
the only way that that can be true
is for the things themselves to be equal
That again is a mathematical theorem
but it's more or less obvious
that for any region
the integral of one quantity is
equal to the integral of another quantity
the two quantities have to be equal
and we come to an interesting conclusion
about the connection between charge density and current
It says that the derivative with respect to time
of the charge density
that's this
plus
I'm bringing everything over to the left hand side
the divergence of the current
let's write that out
that's derivative with respect to x
of j sub x
plus derivative with respect to y
of j sub y
plus derivative with respect to z
of j sub z
equals zero
Now if this is to be true
in every frame of reference
and I didn't specify anything particular
about any particular frame of reference
when I told you this little story
if it's to be true in every frame of reference
it better have the form
of some invariant equation
and it's not hard to imagine
how you make an invariant equation out of this
You first of all
say
that the current
well, not first of all, you say
jx, jy, and jz
together with rho
four quantities
rho
jx
let me put the x upstairs now
jy
jz
form a four vector
they form the four vector
j mu
where mu goes from time
and the three components of space
that is what
is suggested
by having these four components
rho
jx, jy, and jz
and then
this equation
which is called the continuity equation
it's called the continuity equation
it takes the simple form
that d mu j mu
is equal to zero
what does that say?
it says derivative with respect to t
of jt
plus derivative with respect to x
of jx
blah blah blah
is equal to zero
which is exactly what this says
so the way
to make this continuity equation
be a equation
that's true in every frame of reference
is to think of the four components
of current and density
as a four vector
that's not too surprising
the current
kind of represents the velocity
of the motion of the charges
as we've seen over and over again
the velocity vector
is a four vector
the velocity vector of an object
the velocity vector of a particle
the relativistic velocity vector of an object
is a four vector
and so it's not so surprising
that the flow of a fluid
should also be described by a four vector
and the four vector is the four vector
of current and density
well
okay, now we have a object
the four vector
of current and velocity
that we can try to put into
Maxwell's equations somehow
let's go back to
Maxwell's equations which seem to have
disappeared off the blackboard
so I guess, well let's see if they have
maybe they're underneath here
okay, so let's write Maxwell's equations again
this time
putting in the charges and currents
okay, here they go
del dot e
is equal to rho
del dot b
is equal to zero
del cross e
is equal to minus
db by dt
these are all vector equations
and del cross b
is equal to
de by dt
plus j
where j is exactly
the same j that I defined here
the current per unit area
per unit time
what I assert
and which we'll check
is that these equations are exactly the same
as the following equations
d mu
f mu nu
remember what f mu nu is
f mu nu is a four by four
anti-symmetric matrix
a tensor which is built up
out of the electric and magnetic field components
alright
that that is equal
to j nu
notice the left hand side
you've contracted the mu index
so the mu index is not
really a real index here
it just has one nu index
on the right hand a nu index
ok let's check
that this simple
covariant equation
this is clearly a covariant equation
this is a tensor
differentiating a tensor gives you a vector
this is a vector
and so this equation
would be invariant
and the same in every reference frame
assuming that j transforms as a vector
so let's just check
that we get the same equation
let's see the ones
that's relevant here
are the ones with the right hand side
the ones with current
and
charge density
there are four equations here
for nu, for the four different
values of nu
there are four equations here
one, two, three, four
so let's check to see if
any of them are the same
first of all let's take the
time component
the time component would be d mu
f mu t
is equal to j t
but what is j t? that's the time component
of the
of the four
vector of current
it's rho
so on the right hand side we have rho
and what about the left hand side
to see what the left hand side
is we have to go and rewrite
the field tensor but we don't need
the whole thing
all we really need to remember
is let's see that
in the
that we have
the components of the electric field
zero, e x
e y and e z
along here
we also have
minus e x
minus e y
minus e z
and then we have the magnetic field
sitting in here in various ways
okay so let's see what we have
we have only the time
components of f
that means the components along
this first row here
we can write this as
d x
f x t
plus d y
f y t
plus d z
f z t
am I missing one?
yes I'm missing one
I'm missing d t
f t t
but f t t is zero
all the
diagonal elements of the matrix are zero
so this is zero
now what is f x t f y t
and f z t
those are the components of the electric field
so what is this
this is just d x e x
plus d y e y
plus d z e z
in other words
it is
del dot e
the left hand side
is just del dot e
and the right hand side
is row
we could go through the other components
in other words
exactly the same thing
instead of taking the time component here
we could take
space component for example
and set this equal to j x
and then we could take
and we would discover
the x component of this equation
so the upshot of it is
that the connection
between
charges and fields
the way in which charges
charges and currents
electric charges
electric currents
the way they generate fields
is Lorentz invariant
it's the same in all reference frames
on the other hand
we've already seen
that the way that the fields
influence the charges
as forces on them
are also the same in all reference frames
so we see that basically
all of the equations of electromagnetism
can be written in a form
in which we can immediately check
that they're tensor equations
and therefore the same in every reference frame
that was the real goal of this
to show that
the laws of electromagnetism
are the same in all reference frames
are the same in every reference frame
number one
and number two
to demonstrate that the laws of electromagnetism
lead to light waves
moving with the speed of light
from those two things it follows
that light travels with the speed of light
in every frame of reference
and that sort of closes up
and finishes up
the task started by Einstein
of rewriting
all the laws of physics
and that's the same in every frame of reference