This program is brought to you by Stanford University.
Please visit us at stanford.edu.
All right, let's review a little bit.
Now, I am not going to be consistent
about my choice of the speed of light.
Sometimes I will put it in and call it
c, other times I will just call it 1.
I will try to tell you
when I do and I don't.
It's just formulas get too complicated
when you put the c's in.
And you all should be able to figure out, if I give
you a formula in which the speed of light is equal to 1,
you should be able to figure out by dimensional analysis
where the speeds of light, where the little c's go.
But here and there, I'll sprinkle in the c's.
And I'll sprinkle them in when it's
important, when I think that it's relevant
in nature.
And it's interesting to do so.
Otherwise, I will choose the speed of light to
be 1, which means we work in units like
light years per year, or light
seconds per second, or such units.
All right, so let me review quickly.
Let me just start with Galilean relativity.
The Galilean pre-Einstein, Newton, Galileo.
The relationship between reference frames,
moving and stationary reference frames, is
given by the simple equations which
are called Galilean relativity, or Galilean transformations.
For example, for motion along a
one-dimensional line, the relationship between the coordinates
in a moving railroad train and the stationary
station are x prime is equal to x.
Minus the velocity of the train times t.
And t prime is equal to t.
Time is the same for everybody.
And the difference between x coordinates is
just there because the origin of the moving
frame is moving with velocity
v relative to the stationary frame.
To draw a picture, let me just draw
a picture of what these transformations look like.
If this is, I'll think of myself as the
moving train, and I'll think of you as the stationary
observers at rest.
So when I speak of me, that's moving.
When I speak of you, that's at rest.
Of course, I think I'm at
rest, and I think you're moving.
And that's of course what relativity is all about.
But let's look at Galilean relativity first.
Galilean relativity.
If I were to plot.
The time axis and the x axis, and then
on the same graph, draw the t prime axis.
The t prime axis, which stands for the location,
the locus of points of the origin of coordinates
for the prime moving observer.
It would look at an angle, like so.
And the slope of that angle, or that
angle, would be controlled by the velocity of the
moving reference frame.
It would be, that line would be given by
x, well, it's just given by x equals vt, which
is the same as x prime equals zero.
So that's so much for how the moving frame moves.
But then if I were to plot the lines
of constant time, as seen in the prime reference frame,
they're exactly the same as the lines
of constant time in the unprimed reference frame.
And so they look like this.
They're like that.
You don't have to draw two axes for space, but
you do have to draw the t axis, and this
would become the t prime axis for
the moving reference frame, for the moving coordinates.
So if we manage, if we made a grid, this
would be the grid for the moving observer, and the
grid for the stationary observer would be similar.
Except the lines would be vertical.
These are the basic equations that
govern the relationship between observers in Galilean
relativity.
Notice that if you solve, if you
invert the equations, they simply look like this.
They look like x equals x prime plus vt, but
I can also write that as vt prime, since t
and t prime are the same thing.
And t is equal to t prime.
The relationship between the primed and unprimed
coordinates is exactly the same as the relationship,
the inverted relation between the unprimed
and the primed coordinates, with one exception.
You change the sign of the velocity.
That just represents the fact that if you
see me moving down the track with velocity
plus v, I see you moving backward
in the opposite direction with velocity minus v.
And I just get a little
bit more of the same thing.
But if I move down the track with velocity
plus v, I see you moving backward in the opposite
direction with velocity minus v.
So this is like a trick.
It's just a trick.
It just goes back and forth.
It's not like you have to
think about the right direction at all.
You don't have to think
about the right direction at all.
You just move forward with velocity minus v.
So that's how Galileo, if he would have
written the equations, would have thought about relativity.
It is the way Newton thought about it,
and it's the way everybody else did until the
advent of the discovery that the speed of
light is the same in every reference frame.
Those equations are not consistent with the speed
of light being the same in every reference
frame.
They have to be corrected.
time we worked out what the rules about
light imply about the corrections to those equations
up there. So let me write them down for
you to remind you. They are of course the Lorentz
transformations and they look like x prime is
equal to x minus vt exactly as Newton and
Galileo might have written it, but then there's
a square root of 1 minus v squared downstairs.
Now that's, if you want to put back the
speed of light, let's put c equals 1 sometimes.
If you want to put back the speed
of light, this equation doesn't make good dimensional
sense. The velocity has units of length per unit
time, you want, and a 1 has no units
at all, so what you really want to do is
divide this by the speed of light squared, v squared
over c squared. And of course if the
velocity of the moving reference frame, the train of
the train in this case, is ordinary velocities,
50 miles an hour, 100 miles an hour, 1000
miles an hour, even a million miles an
hour. That's quite small by comparison with the
speed of light. And v squared over c
squared is very negligible, even for a million miles
an hour. V squared over c squared is a
very small number, and so for most practical purposes,
terrestrial physics, physics not involving things
moving like a pendulum, or something
with anywheres near the speed of light,
this just becomes the same as Galilean. Square
root of 1 is 1, it's exactly the same as
Galilean. What about t prime? Now that was the new thing,
this was the really new thing, that t prime
isn't just equal to t. In other words, that
time is not as universal as Newton had
thought. Newton had believed in a universal time, God's
time, he, uh, I don't think
he called it that, but, uh,
we could call it that, that everybody
has exactly the same timekeeping, and therefore
t prime is equal to t, well, that
was exactly what was wrong, um, with Galilean relativity
that made it inconsistent with the rules that the
speed of light is the same in every reference
frame. To correct it, Einstein wrote it that way,
t, then minus v x divided by that square
root, same square root of 1 minus v squared
over c squared, but this is also not dimensionally
correct. To get it to be dimensionally correct,
you'll have to write velocity divided by c
squared times x. Again, if the velocity is
small by comparison with the speed of light,
so that v over c is a
very small number, then you can ignore
this term, and you can ignore the v
squared over c squared in the denominator, and it
just reproduces t equals t prime. Alright,
but this is the correct, uh, formula, and
it differs significantly from the Galilean formula
when the velocities get up near the
speed of light. In fact, when the velocity
gets to the speed of light, something crazy
happens here, because v equals c,
v over c is equal to 1,
1 minus 1 is 0, and you're asked to
divide by 0, that's not a good thing, uh, mathematically
inconsistent, and so what it tells you is
that a frame of reference can never quite
be moving with the speed of light relative
to another one, but when it starts to get
close to the speed of light, we start
to see significant deviations from Newton and Galileo.
Now, you might ask, what about x and y?
There are two other coordinates of space, be-tow- besides
Sorry, what about y and z? I didn't mean x
and y. What about y and z, the two other components?
If we're moving down the train track, then
there's the coordinate of space along the track,
but there's also the coordinates
of space perpendicular to the track.
Those are y and z, and the
Lorentz transformations for them are very, very simple.
They are simply that y prime is the same
as y, and z prime is the same as z.
In other words, coordinates along the direction of motion
get mixed up with the time in this complicated way,
but the coordinates perpendicular to the motion, they
are the same for both frames of reference.
Now, if you want to know why, just
imagine having a meter stick moving on the train,
and a meter stick standing still, and
the meter sticks pass each other, like so.
Now, does an observer, and they pass each other,
and they just touch at an instant of time,
and the question is whether the ends of
the meter sticks are at the same place.
If they're at exactly the same place, then the
two meter sticks will look the same to every observer.
The question is, will they actually pass each other?
Now, the argument that says
that they will pass each other,
will stay exactly the same size, goes like this.
Imagine yourself in a reference frame halfway
between the moving train and the stationary train.
I'm sorry, the stationary station.
When halfway means an observer moving along,
who sees me moving with the velocity, and
sees you moving with exactly the same velocity backwards.
There's some frame of reference, not
moving as fast as the train,
not standing as still as close
to you, somebody riding a bicycle,
who is sort of midway between the two reference frames,
and that they see me going with velocity
something, and you going backwards with the same velocity.
That person sees an entirely symmetric situation.
Entirely symmetric situation.
And what he will see, will see the two
meter sticks approaching each other with exactly the same velocity.
Two meter sticks in the perpendicular direction,
approaching each other with exactly the same velocity.
And since the situation is entirely symmetric,
between the left and the right,
there's no expectation that one of the meter sticks
will pass the other one looking shorter than it.
They'll pass each other looking exactly the same length.
And so for that reason, there's no funny
business about x and y, sorry, y and z,
but x and t get mixed up with each other.
Okay, let me show you another
way to write the Lorentz transformation,
which might be illuminating.
It gives you a little bit of
a geometric picture about how these equations work.
Let's come over to this blackboard over here.
First of all, let's get rid of the
speeds of light in them, because they're a nuisance.
Let's just set it equal to one.
Just for simplicity.
Okay.
And now, let's add these two equations on both sides.
What we'll get on the left-hand
side is x prime plus t prime.
That's the left-hand side.
What will we get on the right-hand side?
We're going to get, first of
all, something with the same denominator.
So what we get is going to have
a denominator square root of 1 minus v squared.
And then in the numerator, it
looks like we'll get x plus t.
But then we're going to get another term, which
is going to be minus v times x plus t.
So that will be x
plus t times 1 minus v.
x plus t and then
minus v times x plus t.
All right.
1 over 1 minus v.
Sorry.
1 minus v divided by square
root of 1 minus v squared.
What's that?
Let's work it out over here.
1 minus v upstairs, and then square
root of 1 minus v squared downstairs.
That's the same as the square root
of 1 minus v times 1 minus v.
That's just 1 minus v.
I just rewrote 1 minus v.
Divided by the square root of
1 minus v times 1 plus v.
1 minus v.
1 minus v squared is 1
minus v times 1 plus v.
The 1 minus v is cancel.
And all of this is just equal to the
square root of 1 minus v over 1 plus v.
Okay.
So first of all, let me rewrite this equation.
It says that x prime plus t prime.
Is equal to x plus t.
Times something which depends on the velocity.
And it depends on the velocity as
1 minus v over 1 plus v.
Now let's look at x prime minus t prime.
All right.
Instead of x plus t.
x prime plus t prime.
And let's see what we get.
x prime minus t prime.
When we subtract them, we're going to
get an x minus t from here.
And we're going to get
a plus v because we're subtracting.
You know what I want to do?
I just want to make a small change in this.
I want to write this
as t prime plus x prime.
Same thing.
I haven't changed anything.
t plus x.
Just because it agrees with my notes.
So I'm going to write this
as t prime plus x prime.
And now I want to write this
one as t prime minus x prime.
t prime minus x prime.
That's to subtract this from this.
What do we get then?
We get t minus x times 1 plus v.
Divided by the square root of 1 minus v squared.
We'll get a 1 plus v.
Because of the opposite sign that appears here.
Let's see.
We'll get t minus x.
And then we'll get minus v times x minus t.
That all adds up to a 1 plus v
divided by the square root of 1 minus v squared.
But if you go through the same exercise here.
1 plus v.
What you get is square root of
1 plus v over 1 minus v.
And that's almost the same as the
equation for x prime plus t prime.
But with a slight difference.
That the square root that appears here.
Is square root of 1
plus v over 1 minus v.
Now let's stop now and look at what we have.
Instead of working with x and t.
I've worked with new coordinates.
New coordinates x plus t and x minus t.
You know what you can think of those as?
If.
This is t and this is x.
And 45 degrees remember represents the motion of light rays.
Then x prime plus t prime.
Or x plus t.
Is a coordinate along that axis.
And x minus t is a coordinate along this axis.
This is the x plus t coordinate.
And this is the x
or the t minus x coordinate.
What this is telling us.
Is that.
X plus t.
When it's Lorentz transformed.
Just gets multiplied by something
that depends on the velocity.
And at the same time.
T minus x.
Also just gets multiplied by something.
But that something is the inverse.
The something here is 1 over the something here.
So one picture.
Of what these mathematical transformations are like.
Is that.
T plus x.
Depending on whether v is positive or negative.
Gets stretched.
That's what this says.
It either gets stretched or squeezed.
Depending on.
Let's see.
If v is positive.
Then 1 minus v is less than 1.
This would be less than 1.
That would say.
That this transformation squeezes.
T plus x.
T prime plus x.
Prime is t plus x.
Times a number less than 1.
So it squeezes one axis.
And stretches the other axis.
Axis by the inverse amount.
So for example.
A Lorentz transformation with the appropriate velocity.
Would squeeze this axis by a factor of 2.
And double this axis by a factor of 2.
That's the nature of Lorentz transformations.
They're really quite simple.
They're stretching along one axis.
One 45 degree axis.
And squeezing along the other 45 degree axis.
But notice the important thing.
Is they don't change the 45 degree axes.
The 45 degree axes stay 45 degrees.
Why is that important?
Because that tells you that light rays
continue to move with the speed of light.
In any reference frame.
So you see Lorentz transformations are really quite simple.
They're stretching along one axis.
And squeezing along the other axis.
But they preserve the 45 degree axes.
They don't preserve other lines in here.
Other lines will get stretched this way.
And squeeze the other direction.
But the ones which are along
the 45 degree axes are maintained.
So that's the nature of Lorentz transformations.
Sort of a squashing of one light-like direction.
An expansion of the other light-like direction.
Along.
The direction of motion of the
relative motion of the two reference frames.
Alright.
Any questions about the
structure of Lorentz transformations?
Before we go on.
Yeah.
Back to the transverse meter step.
You proved it to the intermediate and third group.
Okay.
Does that show that to the
two of third and third group...
One has to make some assumptions.
But...
The assumption is that if two
objects cross at an instant of space-time...
If two events are at the same instant of space-time...
And now that would mean, for example,
when these two meter sticks cross each other...
A flash of light could go off from each...
From the end of each one at
the moment that they hit each other.
We call that an event.
If an event occurs at a particular space-time point...
Or if two events occur at the same time...
Or if two events occur at the
same space-time point in one reference frame...
Then they occur at the same
space-time point at another reference frame.
So that's an added ingredient that sort of...
If you really trace every possible assumption...
I'm sure there's an infinite number
of assumptions, hidden things like that...
But they're also easy to believe.
That if two events in space-time...
No.
Yes.
If two events in space-time occur...
At the same space-time location...
According to one observer...
Then they occur at the
same space-time according to another observer.
The notion of an event...
An event...
A point of space-time at which a thing could occur...
That's an invariant concept.
And so you could bring it
back to the question of the events...
Of the crossing of these two meter sticks.
Yeah?
Doesn't the bicyclist also have to be
in the middle of the meter stick?
In the middle of the meter stick.
Well, the bicyclist, of course, stands
for a whole moving frame of reference.
But he has to measure when he's
at the middle of the meter stick.
Well, or he can see the flashes of light come
out from when the two meter sticks crash into each other.
He can see the flashes of light come out...
And then deduce that the flashes of
light came out from the same two points...
From the same points.
So I don't think he
really has to be right there...
He has to be able to deduce what was
going on right there by looking at the light rays.
So what does he see?
He sees two meter sticks come past each other...
And then sees a pair of flashes
of light emanating from exactly the same points.
Two flashes...
Four flashes altogether.
One from the right end of this meter stick.
One from the left end of this meter stick.
One from the left end.
And sees that these two rays of
light emanate from the same point in space-time.
And the other two back on my shoulders here.
Which I can't squeeze together.
I'm not as flexible as I used to be.
Okay.
So...
That's Lorentz transformations.
What I forgot to do, which we'll do next time...
Was to show you how to compound velocities.
We'll do that next time.
But...
For the next thing...
I want to tell you about proper time.
Now I don't remember...
I don't think we talked about proper time last time.
Many of you know what proper time is.
Some of you don't.
But let's spell it out.
As I said...
Newton believed that time was the same for everybody.
Moving, stationary, accelerated...
Whatever you do...
Time will agree.
If you synchronize two clocks...
Whatever you do with them
thereafter, they will stay synchronized.
If you have a whole collection
of synchronized clocks, they will stay synchronized.
That, as we will see, is not true
for moving clocks in the special theory of relativity.
And there's a notion of time which is proper time.
Now here's what proper time means.
It...
You're going to take a walk.
You're going to walk around.
You're going to walk around with a
high velocity, upward near the speed of light.
But you carry your wristwatch with you.
Okay?
Everybody sitting still has their own timepiece.
And the sitting still people all synchronize
their timepieces so that they all agree.
They synchronize their timepieces with light rays.
And according to the way
that Einstein described synchronizing light rays.
So you people all have perfectly synchronized light ray...
Sorry, perfectly synchronized clocks.
And I have my clock.
And I start walking around.
At first when I start,
I synchronize my clock with yours.
We all agree.
And then I walk around and I take
a walk around the table a few times.
At close to the speed of light.
And at the end, I
look at my timepiece and you...
And I compare it with the timepiece of
the person standing next to me over here.
In general, there's no reason for
them to agree and they won't agree.
The proper time of my moving clock...
Is the time read by the moving clock.
Okay?
The coordinate time...
These are definitions.
The coordinate time is the
time measured by your stationary clocks.
So proper time is something which
sort of follows the observer around.
And ticks off intervals of proper time...
As a clock following, as a
wristwatch would tick off instance of time.
Alright, let me give you the formula for proper time.
And then show you that
proper time is an invariant concept.
The proper time between two events.
We're talking about now two events.
We could think of them as two
events along a trajectory if we wanted.
The trajectory could be the trajectory of a moving clock.
But for the moment, let's just
think of them as two events.
And one of them, for
simplicity, let's take at the origin.
So the origin of coordinates.
So this point over here is x equals 0, t
equals 0, x prime equals 0, t prime equals 0.
Notice, incidentally, where's our Lorentz transformation?
We seem to have lost them.
Let me write them back over here.
x equals x minus v...
x prime equals x minus vt over
square root of 1 minus v squared.
t prime is equal to t minus
vx over root 1 minus v squared.
Notice that when x and t are both equal to
0, x prime and t prime are also equal to 0.
So we set it up in such a way that
the origin of space-time coordinates is the same for both observers.
Okay, so here's our moving observer.
Or let this not even be a moving observer.
It's just a moving particle or moving person.
It doesn't have to correspond to a reference frame.
It's just some object moving.
And it could be moving with an accelerated velocity,
but let's just take a small piece of its trajectory
along which we can approximate it by a straight line.
Okay.
Now, if we replaced space-time by ordinary space...
If we replaced it by ordinary space,
forget this and just think about ordinary space.
Not x and t, but x and y.
We could also have different coordinates describing
the same x prime and y prime,
namely coordinates which were just
rotated relative to the original coordinates.
What kinds of things are the same for both...
I'll call them observers, but
I simply mean rotated coordinate frames.
Well, one very invariant quantity is
the distance from the original coordinate frame.
The distance from the origin of any point
necessarily is the same in both coordinate frames.
That's clear.
Your distance from me doesn't
depend on which way I'm oriented.
I have my x and my y.
It doesn't matter which way I'm oriented.
You're still sitting three meters or three or four
meters from me, no matter which way I turn.
So that implies that the
distance from the origin, the square...
Let's take the square of the distance
from the origin, call it s squared.
That's equal to x squared plus y squared.
It must also be equal to
x prime squared plus y prime squared.
In other words, the quantity x squared plus
y squared is the same in any coordinate system,
ordinary coordinate system,
involving the rotation of coordinates.
Something like that is true for Lorentz transformations.
Something slightly different, a
little slightly different mathematical expression.
This is x, this is t.
And this is some point here with
coordinates x, t or x prime, t prime,
depending on which frame of
reference I'm looking at that event.
The statement which we can
work out from this equation here...
In fact, let's do it.
Let's do it.
Let's take the point x, t, which
could also be labeled by the prime coordinates,
and work out the quantity x prime squared,
not t prime squared plus x prime squared,
but t prime squared minus x prime squared.
So, we have a little bit of a glitch on
what we would do if we were just rotating coordinates.
t prime squared minus x prime squared.
Let's write it on the right here.
First of all, in the denominator,
we'll get 1 minus v squared,
because we've squared everything.
All right, now let's look at x prime squared.
That has x squared.
It has plus v squared t squared.
Minus 2 x v t.
That's...oh, that's x prime squared, huh?
That comes in with a minus sign here.
But then let's add in t prime squared.
t prime squared has t squared plus v
squared x squared minus 2 x v t,
also divided by 1 minus v squared.
All right, so this is t prime squared.
This is x prime squared, and we subtract them.
The first thing that we notice is
that these things, these cross terms, cancel.
When we subtract these two, the cross terms cancel.
Now, the x squares don't cancel,
because here we have v
squared x squared minus x squared.
All right?
So that's minus 1 minus v squared x squared.
And then what about the t squared term?
There's t squared here minus v squared t squared.
So that's t squared times 1 minus v squared,
all over 1 minus v squared.
To make a long story short,
let's write it out.
t prime squared minus x prime squared
is equal to t squared minus x squared.
Just work it out.
If you didn't follow a little bit of algebra here,
just work it out.
Square this, square this, subtract them in either way,
and you'll find out that t
prime squared minus x prime squared
is the same as t squared minus x squared.
Very, very much.
Like when you rotate coordinates,
the square of the distance stays the same.
The square of the distance
from the origin stays the same.
Now, a physicist would say that means that the quantity
t squared minus x squared is invariant.
It's the same no matter whether you look at it
from the point of view of
the primed frame or the unprimed frame.
And it has a name.
Because it's invariant, it's important.
Anything which is invariant and which
is the same for all observers
must have a special importance.
It's something which everybody will agree upon,
and so we ought to give it a name.
The name for it is proper time.
The proper time between this point and this point.
Proper time.
The proper time between the origin
and the point is by definition, proper time,
is equal to the square root
of t squared minus x squared.
Why the square root?
Well, it's very similar to the...
It's a definition, of course.
It's a definition.
We could have worked with
a definition where the proper time
was just t squared minus x squared,
but it's a definition.
Take a look.
Take a look at the square root.
But it's very much like looking
at the distance between two points
and using Pythagoras' theorem.
The Pythagorean theorem says that
the distance between the points
is the square root of x squared plus y squared.
All right, so in parallel with that,
we call this the proper time between
the origin and the point x, t.
And that, as I said, is definition,
but it's a highly useful definition,
and we'll see why it's useful as we go along.
But the main thing about it
is that everybody agrees about it.
Okay, first of all, let's look at some possible values
that the proper time can
have for various points, x, t.
If t is bigger than x,
what does it mean for
t to be bigger than x?
In magnitude, if t squared is bigger than x squared.
If t squared is bigger than x squared,
that means we're talking about points
which are in a wedge here,
where time, where the time component
is larger than the x component.
t squared is larger than x squared,
all in here.
But let's, in particular, stay
in the upper half space here.
t squared is bigger than x squared
if you're within this wedge.
The wedge is the light cone.
Oh, I should add in,
yes, I should add something in.
If we are working in three dimensions,
not, sorry, three spatial dimensions,
not one spatial dimension,
then we should also add in
minus y squared minus z squared here.
Minus y prime squared minus z prime squared.
That's the first thing.
That makes sure that our definitions
don't depend on direction and space.
As long as we know that we're only talking about
Lorentz transformations along a given axis,
we don't really have to worry about y and z.
But if we wanted to do Lorentz transformations
along some other axis,
and we wanted to add in y and z,
we would note that this whole quantity,
t prime squared minus x
prime squared minus y prime squared
minus z prime squared is invariant.
Why is that incidentally?
Well, remember that z prime and y prime don't transform
when we go from one frame of
reference along the x axis to another.
And so that doesn't make any difference
if we put in y prime and z prime here,
but it's a convenience to add it in,
and then we have an expression here
which doesn't depend on direction and space.
But if you only want to think more simply
about directions along a single axis,
then you don't have to worry about y and z.
Okay.
So here we are.
This point here,
t squared is greater than x squared,
and that means that t
squared minus x squared is positive,
and the square root of a positive number
is another real number.
So in this time-like region,
this is called the time-like region
because the coordinates are more in the direction of time
than they are in space,
and in the time-like region,
the proper time is just a positive number,
square root of a positive number,
and we take the positive square root.
So t squared, so that's perfectly normal.
Positive proper time up in here.
What about along the light cone?
Along the light cone,
that's exactly where x is either equal to t
or x is equal to minus t.
Along here, x is equal to t.
Along here, x is equal to minus t.
Oops.
x is equal to minus t.
So in either case,
t squared is equal to x squared.
So along the light cone,
along the place where light rays can travel,
the proper distance between,
or the proper time between the
origin and that point is zero.
Now, this is a big difference
between ordinary distance and proper time.
Ordinary distance,
if the distance between two points is zero,
those points are the same point.
There's no way that the distance
between two points can be zero
and then not be sitting on top of each other.
In Minkowski space,
in the space describing the special theory of relativity,
the space-time,
two points can have zero proper distance between them
or zero proper time between them
and still not be the same point,
here and here.
What is true
is that if two points
are separated by zero proper time,
then a light ray can
go from one to the other.
So the trajectories of light rays
correspond to paths
which
have essentially zero proper time along them.
Real particles,
sorry, not real particles,
but mass,
but particles moving with less than the speed
of light,
have trajectories
which are in the time-like direction like that.
They're moving slower than the speed of light
and the proper time along those is positive.
Now, let me prove a simple thing.
Proper time
measures
ordinary time as seen by
a clock moving with the object.
For example,
supposing we have a clock which is at rest.
A clock which is at rest in our frame
just has a vertical world line.
It's perfectly at rest.
And for such a point,
let's take a point along here,
what's the proper time from the origin?
It's the square root of t squared minus x squared,
but x is zero for this point.
So it's just the square root of t squared,
which is just t.
So the proper time along a trajectory
which is standing still
is just the ordinary time.
What does that tell you?
That tells you that the proper time
is nothing but the time read by a wristwatch
standing still.
What about,
what about the proper time
along a trajectory which has a finite velocity?
For example, supposing it has a finite velocity like that,
and we look at the proper time
for a particular point over here.
Well,
the principle of relativity,
the equivalence between different reference frames,
tells us the following thing.
We could always think
of this
particle, object, observer
as being at rest.
We could always do a Lorentz equation,
a Lorentz transformation.
So this guy is the guy at rest,
and then use the same logic
that we used a second ago.
In the reference frame where this is at rest,
this point here would have x prime equals zero,
but t prime not equal to zero.
Why is it x prime equal to zero?
Because
in the moving reference frame,
moving with this guy over here,
this whole trajectory corresponds
to his origin of coordinates.
So x prime would be zero
for somebody moving along this trajectory here,
but t prime would not be zero over here.
And we could work out exactly the same argument.
The proper time to this point over here
would be t prime squared minus x prime squared,
but x prime squared is zero.
And so the proper time along here,
in the same way as along here,
as along the vertical trajectory,
measures the time
as read by a moving watch,
a moving clock.
Moving clocks tick off proper time.
That's the message.
That the meaning of proper time
is nothing but the meaning of the time
as read by a watch
which is moving with the moving object.
So that's the notion of proper time.
It's kind of funny,
in these regions over here,
x is bigger than t,
and so t squared minus x squared is negative,
and the proper time is imaginary.
Points up in here are called time-like,
relative to the origin.
Points along the light cone here
are called light-like,
and points out here are called time-like.
So,
points out here are called space-like.
Space-like points have an imaginary proper distance,
an imaginary proper time relative to the origin,
but points in the,
within the light cone,
have a real proper time.
Okay, any questions about
the notion of proper time?
It's very similar to distance along a trajectory,
except with a funny property
that there's a minus sign that you throw in here.
A minus sign that you throw in,
instead of a plus sign.
t squared minus x squared.
But it has many similar properties,
and in particular,
it's the same in every reference frame.
The proper time between two distinct points
is invariant.
Okay.
Now,
we can use that fact.
We can use that fact,
and facts similar to it,
well, that...
The time interval between two points.
The time interval as read by a clock
that moves between those two points.
Well, yeah, it's just,
you were using the same,
you were using the same word for both interval
and reading the clock.
Uh...
Never mind.
Okay.
I meant time interval, but,
yeah.
Yeah.
So, to put it another way,
if there are two points in space-time,
and a clock,
a physical real clock,
can move from one to the other
along a straight trajectory,
that means a trajectory with constant velocity,
then the difference of time readings
at the two ends of the trajectory over here
will be the proper time.
In other words,
the distance,
the difference between the time read at this point
and at that point
will be the proper time along that trajectory.
You can calculate that,
you can calculate then,
if I give you two points in space-time,
we can calculate very easily
how long it takes to move between these two points
as read by the moving clock.
Not as read by stationary clocks.
That's different.
As read by stationary clocks,
the time difference is just
whatever the time was at this point
and whatever the time was at this point,
where the times were just, um,
t.
But the moving clock,
the moving clock reads its own time.
That's the message of special relativity,
that the rate at which clocks move
depends on how they move.
Now we can work out,
in some detail,
the relationship between moving clocks
and stationary clocks.
Let's do that.
And the tool is to use proper time.
So,
let's take a clock,
which starts at the origin,
and moves along a trajectory,
which takes it to a point,
let's call,
on the origin of the moving coordinates.
I'm sorry,
that line does not look very straight, does it?
I intended it to be a straight line.
Here we have our moving coordinate frame,
and a clock moves from the origin,
to a point over here.
Now what is that point over here?
That point over here is x prime equals zero.
It's the origin of spatial coordinates
for the moving observer.
And,
it's some point, t prime.
It also has coordinates,
x, t.
In other words, in the stationary reference frame,
it has coordinates x, t,
in the moving frame,
it has coordinates x prime equals zero,
and some t prime.
I would like to know,
if I know x and I know t,
what is t prime?
Incidentally,
x, of course, is equal to vt.
So really all I need to know is t,
and the velocity of the moving observer,
is the moving observer,
his trajectory is x equals vt,
here's t,
and here's x equals vt.
What is the time read by the clock
moving from here to here?
What is t prime?
Well, now that's easy to find out.
t prime squared minus x prime squared
must equal t squared minus x squared.
What are t,
sorry, this should be prime,
t prime squared minus x prime squared
should equal t squared minus x squared for this point.
Why?
Because the expression for proper time is invariant.
Same expression in either reference frame
for the proper time between this point and the origin.
What do I know about this point?
I know that it's x prime is equal to zero,
so let's cancel that out.
No, let's not cancel that out, let's just rewrite it.
t prime squared equals t squared,
but now at this point, x is equal to vt.
So that's minus v squared t squared.
Well, that's interesting.
We now have a simple formula for t prime.
First of all, let's write that as
one minus v times t squared.
One minus v squared.
Times t squared.
Well, we just take the square root.
t prime, the time read by the moving clock,
is equal to the time read by the stationary clock.
The time read by the stationary clock
is just this time here,
times one minus square root of one minus v squared.
That's the famous formula of time dilation.
That when you see a moving clock,
that moving clock will appear
to move a little bit slow.
Why slow?
Because one minus v squared is less than one.
But everybody will agree about
the value of the proper time
between these two points,
although they will disagree
about the actual coordinate times.
In particular, the coordinate time t prime,
seen in the moving reference frame,
will be the coordinate time
in the stationary reference frame
times square root of one minus v squared.
So what that says is that the moving observer,
well, the stationary observers,
will see the moving clock run a little bit slow.
We really should at this point put
in the speeds of light, c squared.
v squared over c squared is
typically a very, very small number.
So this is almost t prime equals t,
but with a slight discrepancy.
This is the time dilation of a moving clock.
Now, how can it possibly be that we have relativity,
which says there's a complete parallel between,
or a complete symmetry,
between the moving observer and the stationary observer.
How do we then account for the fact
that the stationary observer sees the moving observer
having his time slowed down?
What does that mean if we
look at it the other way?
What does the moving observer
see about the stationary observer?
Does he see the stationary observer's time sped up?
No.
Also sees the time slowed down.
So if I move past you with my clock,
my clock seems to slow
down as far as you're concerned.
On the other hand, if I watch one of you,
and I have all of my fellow's,
lined up with me forming a reference frame,
they will also see your clock go slow.
How can that possibly be?
That sounds contradictory.
Well, they're talking about two different things.
The moving observer,
remember that the moving observer,
his time,
or his lines along which time are constant,
are not these horizontal lines here.
They're lines which look like this.
This is t prime equals a constant.
This is t prime equals a constant, and so forth.
So the lines on which t prime are constant
are different than the lines on which t are constant.
This is this relativity of synchronicity,
the relativity of being synchronous.
Different observers call different things synchronous.
Now, let's take the moving observer here,
and the moving observer looks
at the stationary clocks
at an instant of his time,
and asks, what does the stationary clock read?
Well, an instant of his time
looks like this.
So he's really asking
not what the stationary clock reads at this point,
but what the stationary clock reads at that point.
So there are two different questions.
When you ask
what one observer sees of the other one's clock,
there is a complete symmetry.
Let's see how to say this.
I think I've already said it,
but let's try to say it more clearly.
We're comparing different things.
The surfaces along which t is constant
and along which t prime is constant
are different surfaces,
and so when you ask whether a clock
is synchronous or not synchronous,
and so forth,
you have to account for this difference
in what you mean by synchronous.
That's all.
So that's the time dilation,
the fact that moving clocks appear
to stationary observers to go slow,
and stationary clocks appear
to moving observers also to go slow.
We could have been certain from the beginning
that whatever one observer sees
of the other's clock,
that they will be reciprocal
because of the reciprocal nature
of Lorentz transformations.
Okay, that's the slowing down of clocks.
Let's talk about the twin paradox.
Somebody asked me about the twin paradox.
We're now in a good position
to do the twin paradox
and see what it says.
Let's work it out.
The twin paradox,
two twins are born
at the origin of coordinates.
One stays home,
that means stays at rest,
doesn't move,
doesn't accelerate,
doesn't move at all,
and just moves along a trajectory like that,
a world line like that.
The other one is shot out
at a high velocity
not quite the velocity of light,
for a certain period,
and then at the end of that period
turns around and comes back
and meets the twin
at that point there.
They compare their clocks.
Well, all kinds of clocks they could compare.
Their clocks, their watches,
their heartbeats,
their aging rate,
their metabolic time differences
between here and here,
how long their beards are,
or whatever,
whatever corresponds to a good clock.
They compare their clocks at this point
and ask what the relationship
between the time read by a clock moving here
and the time read by a clock moving here.
Well, we're all set up to calculate it now
because all we have to do
is to calculate the proper time
between this point and this point
along the vertical trajectory
and the proper time along this,
uh, trajectory
which consists of two different pieces.
We just add up the proper time
from here to here
and the proper time from here to here,
and that will tell us what the clocks measure.
Clocks measure proper time.
All right, first of all, this triangle,
assuming that the observer,
that the second twin comes back
with the same velocity that he was shot out with,
with some velocity v,
then this triangle is a nice isosceles triangle
and the second triangle
is a vertical triangle.
And we can divide this vertical line in half,
call this side t,
this half side t.
It takes, therefore, time to t
in the ref-
from the, uh, stationary person here,
it takes time to t
to go from this world point to this world point,
and therefore, the person who stays home
says it took a amount of time twice capital T
for my twin to return.
All right, so that's twice capital T.
That's what the observer who stays home
says the time interval
between birth and meeting the twin is.
Now, what about the twin
who goes out and comes back?
Let's, uh, calculate what the total proper time
is along this trajectory here.
He goes out with velocity v.
How far out does he get?
He gets out a distance v times t.
All right.
v times t is the distance
along the x-axis
that the moving twin gets out.
So this point, then, has coordinates
x equals vt
and time t.
Let's calculate the proper time
from here to here.
The proper time,
the square of the proper time,
is t squared minus x squared.
So the proper time along the
first leg of the journey here
is t squared
minus v squared t squared,
which is equal to 1 minus v squared
times t squared.
That's the square of the proper time.
We have to take the square root of it
to find out how much the clock
changed from here to here.
And so the time change, the proper time
along this trajectory here is square root
of 1 minus v squared times t.
What about on the second leg of the journey?
The second leg of the journey
is exactly parallel to the first leg of the journey,
except going backward.
The proper time between here and here
is exactly the same as the proper time
between here and here.
There's the same x coordinate
and the same t.
So the answer for the observer
going along this bent trajectory here
is twice this.
Twice t times square root of 1 minus v squared
as opposed to just twice t.
Which one is smaller?
The smaller one, the smaller proper time,
is associated with the twin
who got shot out and came back.
Why? Because 1 minus v squared
is smaller than 1.
So the amount of time read off
by the moving clocks here
is smaller by factor square root
of 1 minus v squared
than the time measured along
the trajectory of the twin who stayed home.
All kinds of times,
as I said, the length of a beard,
the number of heartbeats,
all sorts of things,
the time read along this moving trajectory
will be less,
and the consequence is that the moving
twin comes back looking younger,
feeling younger, looking younger, being younger
than the twin who stayed home.
Now, is this a paradox?
It's not a paradox,
because there's nothing inconsistent about it.
Doesn't look inconsistent.
There's nothing particularly inconsistent.
Sometimes people ask,
how do you tell which twin moved
and which twin didn't move?
Well, that's not hard.
This twin reversed its trajectory
and accelerated at this point over here.
And so if they were in a rocket ship,
they would feel the rocket ship accelerate,
and there is no symmetry between the two twins.
One twin just stays at home,
experiences no acceleration,
experiences no tendency to be thrust back and forth
by the acceleration of whatever he's sitting in.
The other twin suddenly experiences
a sharp acceleration at this point,
and so there's no symmetry between them.
There's no more of a contradiction
than asking about the size of a triangle.
The distance along the side of a triangle,
is not the same as the distance along
the broken path composed of the other two sides.
There's nothing more paradoxical than that.
The proper distance along the sides of these two triangles,
this broken trajectory here,
is just different than the proper distance along here.
Now, Newton would not have understood that,
or at least probably Newton would have understood it
if it was explained to him.
He was certainly smart enough.
But, uh,
with his own view of time
and his own view of space,
this would have been a shock
to discover that a twin
that goes out and comes back
comes back younger,
uh, than the twin who stayed home.
Yeah, question?
Uh, typical question.
So at that point,
the physics is now different.
Well, the twin feels something quite different.
How does one argue around
the fact that there are accelerations?
Well, you don't argue around it.
There's acceleration there.
But, well then, you don't know any longer
if this analysis about clocks is correct.
Okay.
Um, the assumption,
first of all, you can smooth this out.
There's nothing, there was nothing, uh,
uh, there was nothing very special
about making this a sharp turn.
All right?
All right.
To say that it's smoothed out
just says that there's a finite acceleration
rather than an instantaneous infinite acceleration.
All right, that's good.
That's it.
The assumption is that the clocks that we have,
the way that they tick is insensitive to acceleration.
All right, now this isn't true of real clocks.
Real clocks, if you accelerate them too hard, they'll break.
All right?
If you accelerate your clock real hard, you'll break it.
Now, it also depends on the size of a clock.
The bigger the clock is,
if you give it a hard acceleration,
the easier it is to break it.
If you take a tiny, tiny, tiny little clock
and you accelerate it, it's harder to break.
Taking an atom and accelerating it
at 10 meters per second per second,
the atomic clock that's composed of the electron
going around the nucleus is not going to be affected
by that 10 meters per second per second.
On the other hand, a great big clock,
uh, 100 miles wide and so forth,
that's, that you try to accelerate it,
uh, it's going to be very, very delicate
to accelerate it without changing the way that it ticks.
Okay?
So, the assumption is that
the clocks tick off proper time.
All right, that's an assumption.
That good, faithful, small clocks,
which are very well built
and built to withstand acceleration,
that they simply tick off proper time.
If they tick off proper time,
all we have to do is
measure the proper time along there.
Now, as I said, we can do this experiment
in a way that minimizes the amount of acceleration here.
We don't need a lot of acceleration.
We can have, um, we
can have during this period here
the acceleration be very modest.
It could be a small fraction of
the 10 meters per second per second
that we feel in this room here.
We don't normally think that,
that 10 meters per second per second
has any, any very big significance
and any big, um, effect on our wristwatches.
If we swing our arm around a little bit,
we can swing it around at more
than 10 meters per second per second.
If the clock is built
to withstand shock and so forth,
then the acceleration won't have much effect on it.
And so the assumption is that the acceleration
doesn't have much effect on the clock,
but the meaning of that is that
the clock always ticks off proper time.
Uh, so it ticks off the number
of units of proper time along the trajectory.
الآن
هذا
هو
المعتقد
This is an assumption, it's
the assumption of an ideal clock
It is what you mean by an ideal clock
Does that help?
Hmm?
Hmm
No
Yeah, the thing is that my impression is
that all this follows a very, very careful analysis
of the kinematics of every column
Yeah
for, without accelerations in them
Yes
and light signals
Yes, yes, yes
So
Right
It seems to me like the
analysis in a way breaks down there
The analysis, the logic of the analysis has
to be supplemented with some additional physical facts
that I don't think you can
derive just from what we said
But we derive them from the experience of
knowing that if we have a small clock
well made, built to resist the shock and so forth
that as a matter of experience we
know that that clock's rate of ticking
will not be sensitive to modest accelerations
will not be particularly sensitive, yeah
You did this in a, you know
relativity and you've got all that gravitational
so if you threw a clock out
of the light and it comes back down
Yeah
You would get the same sort of answer
or if you swung it around the star
Yeah, yeah, but would you can't,
no, no, no, no, you see
it's not going to help to say general relativity
because then what you're going to be asking
is what is the effect of the gravitational field
on the way the clock behaves
and I can't answer that unless
I know more about the clock
I have to know the details of
how the clock works and so forth
Again, if the clock is a big
sloppy clock made out of very big components
and components which aren't very rigid and so forth
then it's going to be very
sensitive to acceleration on the one hand
but it's also going to be, if
I put it on the table here
it's also going to be
squashed down by the gravitational field
and so it will also fail
to be a good faithful clock
If I take a small hard clock
you know, by hard I mean hardened against acceleration
then number one, it will report faithful time keeping
if I put it on
the table in the gravitational field
number two, it will report faithful time keeping if
I swing it around my head on a rope
but I can't prove that
from the things that we've done
from the mathematics we've done
I can say that's a matter
of experience and a matter of physics
and a matter of how clocks are made
and what they're made out of and so forth
Yeah, but what you've been talking about here is
what I would call, say, the mechanics of the clock
Yeah, you have to, right
But there's the other thing which is
I don't know the proper word,
the fabric of space under acceleration
Right
Because it's a different matter
Okay, right, right
So to the extent that we
talk about the fabric of space
what we would be talking about here would
be proper time measurements along this trajectory here
The fabric of space, or whatever the right
word for it is, the geometry of space-time
The geometry of space-time is a
geometry of proper times and proper distances
So what you're saying then is you can
I can reduce the thing to small intervals
Yeah, oh yes
So within each interval
Absolutely, absolutely
That was implicit, I should have made that explicit
Yes, absolutely indeed
Yes, I should have been explicit about that
Right, we divide the trajectory into small little segments
each of which has approximately a
very constant velocity along that little trajectory
So we have a very
constant velocity along that little segment
We calculate the proper time along that segment
We add it to the
proper time along the next segment
But it's very, very similar mathematics to the way
that we would calculate the length along a curve
We calculate the length along a curve by
dividing it up into a lot of little intervals
And for each interval, calculating the
length by x squared plus y squared
square root, add them all up, and
that gives us the length along the curve
In very much the same
way, we take this curved trajectory
and we divide it into small little intervals
Each interval can be thought
of as almost a straight line
And therefore each interval can be analyzed by
thinking of it as having a constant velocity
And along that trajectory, we
add up all the constant times
Is that what the question is?
Is that why we were...
No, I know exactly what you're asking
The way to analyze that is to
imagine actually sending light rays back and forth
Let's tick off some time intervals here
Let's imagine ticking off one
second intervals along both trajectories
One second intervals of proper time along both trajectories
So here, one second intervals
might look something approximately like this
for the stationary person
This isn't very many seconds, so it's
not going to grow a very long beard
And one second intervals would be longer along here
because the moving clocks appear to
go slow to the stationary observer
They might go a little bit faster in this...
So it'll look like that
Okay, now we can start
sending light signals back and forth
Every instant, the stationary observer could send
a light signal to the moving observer
Now look what would happen
The first set of light signals that were sent
early would come to the moving observer stretched out
This is Doppler shift, this is Doppler shift in fact
But we don't even have to
think about it as Doppler shift
If this guy is moving fast, he sees
the light coming, the series of light pulses
coming from the stationary observer,
coming delayed, very delayed at first
and then all lumped up
Not delayed, but squeezed together in
the second part of the trajectory here
So he sees all the light signals, the one, two,
three, four, five, six, or six or five light signals
but sees the first set of them come very slowly
and the last set of them come very quickly
Now, what about the stationary
observer looking at the moving observer?
The moving observer may also send out light signals
And also there would be kind of Doppler shifts
But the number of light
signals that the stationary observer sees
would equal the number of light
signals that the moving observer sent out
And the number of light
signals that the moving observer sees
would equal the number of light
signals that the stationary observer sees
So in both cases, they would see
something taking place somewhat irregularly in time
At first they would see
things stretched out and slowed down
And then they would see things speeded up
In both cases, but at slightly different rates
And rates which would...
Which would...
Which you can calculate
But they won't see any missing frames
By missing frames, you would mean missing light signals
They would see all...
Each one would see all the light
signals that the other one sent out
But coming at rates which would
depend on their relative state of motion
Does that answer your question?
No
Hmm?
It sort of answers it
But there's...
When you're talking about Doppler and something else...
It kind of bothers me
If the person...
The astronaut coming back
Sees the shift...
Sees the light shifted
Let's say the first person...
The first one
He transmits light that's of a low frequency
This person transmits light of low frequency, yeah
The person coming back, he collects the light
Would he be collecting more energy than was...
I mean...
I'm sure the answer is no
But it sounds like he
would be actually collecting more energy
Okay
Before we can answer that, we
have to know more about energy
So let's wait on that kind of
question until we know something about energy
At the moment, all we're
talking about is X's and T's
But it's a reasonable question
What are...
How does the energetics appear to both observers?
And the answer is that energy really only makes sense
In the usual sense
To an observer who is not accelerated
To talk about the energy of the
moving of the accelerated observer is very tricky
And...
Yeah
So...
You have to talk loud
It's not quite clear
There's a question about energy here
But in previous classes you talked about theories
like the Lusser Line and the Spring Theory
That have a concept of
spatial dimensions that are curved up
And in that case, you could have the two winds...
If they were moving...
If they were moving to it...
If they were moving around...
Moving around the direction...
Dimension that was curved up
You have to be...
Without any of them actually accelerating
Without any of them doing what?
Sir, without any of them accelerating
Oh, oh, oh, oh, oh
Yes
But there would nevertheless be an asymmetry
between the one that went around the...
The direction and the one that stood still
So how would they notice that
this is the direction that is...
Well...
The moving observer would discover a surprise
He would discover that he kept
repetitively passing through the same places
You know, if we were moving on a circle...
And we would discover that repetitively
we keep passing the same place
Well, I have to think about that
That's a good question
But the answer is definitely that they're asymmetric
That they're asymmetric
The person moving around the closed loop...
And the one standing still...
Yeah
If he's moving around, it's the other guy moving around
That is the issue
No
No, no, no
That is not quite right
Let's come back to it
Give me...
I need to think about the good answer to that
It's a nice question
I want...
Give me some time to think about it
I don't want to give you...
I don't want to give you an unthought-out answer
So let me come back to it
Does everybody understand what the question was?
The question is an interesting one
Yeah
Supposing you lived in a
world of two dimensions of space
Two dimensions of space
This was only a world of one dimension of space
And your world was a cylinder
A cylinder of space
Okay
Now, this is space
This is not space-time
You can imagine such a world
Special relativity doesn't actually quite make sense for it
There's a problem with special relativity here
But let's suppose perfect special relativity made sense
Then an observer could stay home over here
And another one could move
around in a trajectory of space
Move around in a trajectory that...
Well, sorry, this isn't time
Vertical isn't time
Vertical is space
One observer could just stand there, stand still
And the other could go around at
a large velocity and then come back
That observer who was moving around with a large velocity
It would be unnecessary for
him to experience any acceleration
And going around here
Just moving with the same velocity
And would leave and come back
Without ever having experienced any acceleration
However, it is not true that they wouldn't experience
the fact that they were on the closed contour
They would
Yeah
He would experience radial acceleration
Sorry?
Moving around in this closed curve here?
No, no, no
No, no, no, no, no, no, no, no
This...
No, no, okay, I see what you're asking
No, you're not living in a
world which is a solid cylinder
In which the radius means anything
You're just living in a world
which is just a pure surface
A pure surface
There's no notion of distance from the center here
Because there's nothing in there
Let's come back to it
This is way, way, way beyond
what I wanted to discuss today
Kaluza-Klein theory
This is not...
This is a...
A somewhat more advanced question
What I did want to get to
Before we quit
Is length contraction
We did time dilation
By doing proper time
We do length contraction in a very similar way
Let's...
Let's do length contraction in a very similar way
Look, the first thing
When you want to understand the special relativity problem
Is draw a picture
Always draw a picture
And see if you can't cast your question
In a diagrammatic language
Which you can then answer
By using Lorentz transformations and that sort of thing
So let's begin
Always start that way
Always
For reference
We put in a light cone
That's the speed of light
Nothing moves faster than the speed of light
Okay
Now we have our moving observer
We have a stationary observer
We have our moving observer
Here's the trajectory of the moving observer
Here is the surface of constant time
This is t equals vx
This is x equals vx
This is vt
One of these is the surface
Along which the moving observer's clocks
Are all synchronized
This motion here is just the origin of coordinates
Or the origin of spatial coordinates
Of the moving observer
And now let's imagine a meter stick
Let's take a meter stick
Which is at rest
In the rest frame
So I need another color
Let's see, red may do
A meter stick which is at rest
Has two ends
Let's take the left end of the meter stick
The left end of the meter stick
Might start over here
And it's at rest
So the left end of
the meter stick is over here
The right end of the meter stick
Is at x equals one
And it's over here
The meter stick sweeps out
A space-time strip
At each instant of time
The meter stick is one meter long
But as time moves on
The meter stick sweeps out
A kind of ribbon
A ribbon through space-time
Alright, now we want to know
How long the moving observer
Says that the meter stick is
How long is the meter stick
According to the moving observer
Now what does the moving observer mean?
The moving observer means
By the length
And this is of course a definition to some extent
The definition of the length of the moving observer
The definition of the length of the meter stick
In the moving frame of reference
Is the following
You take the two ends of the meter stick
At the same instant of time
But whose time?
The moving observer's time
The moving observer takes the two ends
Or looks at the two ends of the meter stick
At a synchronous time
In his own reference frame
And asks in his own reference frame
How far apart
Is the front end of the meter stick
And the rear end of the meter stick
At a given instant of time
Well a given instant of time
In the moving reference frame
Means this t equals vx
Trajectory over here
Or this t equals vx surface over here
So here's one end of the meter stick
At that instant of time
Here's the other end of the meter stick
At the same instant of t prime
If you like
In the stationary reference frame
These two points are synchronous
In the moving reference frame
So if we want to know
how long the meter stick looks
In the moving reference frame
What we want to know is not
what the x of this point is
But we want to know what
the x prime of that point is
We want to know what the
x prime of that point is
Which would be what the moving observer is
Would call the length of that meter stick
Now there's an easy way to find out
Well one way to find out is
just to compute where this point is
And then do a Lorentz transformation
to find out what x prime is
But there's an easier way
And it's just to use proper distance
Proper distance means
t squared minus x squared
Or the square of the proper distance
Or x squared minus t squared, it doesn't matter
One or the other
And use the fact that they're
the same in the two reference frames
So let's take this point over here
What is its proper distance
I won't call it proper time because it's not time-like
But instead of looking at t squared minus x squared
We could look at x squared
minus t squared, it doesn't matter
What is the invariant distance
Four dimensional or space-time invariant distance
Between this point and that point
Well, on the one hand
If I work it out
In the primed frame of reference
It's just
t prime squared minus x prime squared
That's the square of this proper interval here
Where this point has coordinates t prime and x prime
But what's the t prime of this point?
The t prime of this point is zero
This is the surface t prime equals zero
This whole surface corresponds to
the origin of time coordinates
For the moving observer
So along here, t prime is equal to zero
And the proper distance from the origin is just
Or the square of the proper
distance is just minus x prime squared
On the other hand, let's find
the unprimed coordinates of this point
This was supposed to be
a meter stick one meter long
So this corresponds to x equals one
x equals one in the stationary reference frame
The stationary meter stick in the stationary reference frame
Is exactly one meter long
So this point corresponds to x equals one
This whole trajectory here
What about the height of this point?
That's t
Alright, that's t equals vx all along this trajectory
So along here, t is equal to just v
t equals vx
But x equals one
So along here, this point here is x equals one
t equals v
Alright, so on the left hand side here
We have the proper distance
expressed in terms of primed coordinates
Let's express it now in terms of the unprimed coordinates
That's going to be t squared, which is v squared
Minus x squared, which is one
x squared, which is one
So what do we find out?
We discover that the primed space
coordinate of this point over here
Is x prime is equal to the
square root of one minus v squared
I've just changed the sign
And taken the square root
And now we know that the point is
That the meter stick, which is
at rest in your frame of reference
In my frame of reference
Appears to have length square
root of one minus v squared
In other words, the coordinate distance
Between the two ends of the meter stick
In the moving reference frame
Is square root of one minus v squared
x prime at this point is zero
x prime at this point is
square root of one minus v squared
So you see what that says
That says that the stationary meter stick
Is seen in the moving reference frame
As having a shorter length
Again, an application of the invariance
Of the proper distance
t prime squared minus x prime squared
Is equal to t squared minus x squared
That's what I've used
Let's just go through it again
For this point, or first
of all for the first point
On the left here, everything is equal to zero
x, t, x prime, t
prime, they're all equal to zero
And that's trivial
But this point
On the one hand, t prime is equal to zero
So we cross this out
On the other hand, x is equal to one
And t is equal to v
So that gives us the
one minus v squared over here
And it tells us that x prime is
equal to square root of one minus v squared
So
The comparison of the length of the meter sticks
In the two reference frames
Says that when a meter stick is at rest
A moving observer sees it as being shorter
Of course the converse is also true
And could be worked out in a similar way
The moving, what did I say?
Yeah, we said the stationary meter stick
Looks short to the moving observer
The moving meter stick looks short
To the stationary observer
That's the reciprocal character of a moving observer
But it's a different type of
Of Lorentz transformations
Okay, any questions about length contraction, time dilation
Lorentz transformations
Or any of the geometry that we've done, yeah
Does anything go to speed light except light?
No, well yes, gravity
Do we know that?
No, do we know it?
Well
We certainly know it within the framework
of the general theory of relativity, yes
Yes, within the framework of
the general theory of relativity, yes
Do we know it as an experimental fact?
Um
We really have never directly seen gravitational waves
We'd like to see gravitational waves
But what we have seen is that
The effects of gravitational waves coming from
Binary pulsars
And what's known about that
Tends to suggest
Not terribly strongly that light and
gravity travel with the same speed
So no, there's no direct experimental evidence that
gravitational waves travel with the same speed as
As electromagnetic waves
On the other hand
Einstein would have had to have been very wrong
For it not to be untrue
Yeah
From the perspective of, say, an astronaut
He can actually accelerate faster than light
You don't, wait, accelerate faster than
the speed of light doesn't mean anything
I mean, how
As in, let's say they wanted to get from here
To another star that's, say, ten light years away
They could, from their own reference frame
Get there
In less than four years
Yes, that's true
Yes, that's true, and
And the way to see that
Is, okay, so here's a moving
Observer
There's a moving observer
Here's star number one
Here's star number two
And that's four light years away or whatever
We want to find out how long
Not in our stationary reference
frame it takes to get here
But how long does the
moving observer say that it takes
And for that we have to calculate
The proper time between here and here
Now the point is that
the proper time of this point
This point here
It may be t
And x
The point is the proper time
Which is t squared, the square of the proper time
Is t squared minus x squared
That means it's always smaller
Than just t squared by itself
So the proper time between here and here
Is less than the actual coordinate time
So for that reason, yes, you're absolutely right
This person over here would
say that it takes less time
Than the four light years or whatever it would be
That the stationary observer would
From his perspective, wouldn't it
also be right to say that
The star actually came to him
Well, what the moving observer would say
Is that he would
What the moving observer would say
He would put himself first of
all in his own frame of reference
And then he would look at the two stars
And he would see that the
two stars were a lot closer together
Than what the stationary observer said
So he would say it took a short amount
of time to go from one to the other
In other words, the moving observer would see
The Lorentz contracted distance between the stars
And so would conclude
That it took a small amount of time
to go from one star to the other
But to him, that length contraction
Wouldn't it look like the stars are traveling
Faster than the speed of light?
No, no, the stars would not appear to
be traveling faster than the speed of light
They would appear to be
traveling with exactly the opposite velocity
The stars see the astronaut
traveling with a certain velocity
And the astronaut sees the stars
traveling with exactly the negative velocity
But when he starts up, when
he looks up and observes the stars
And measures the distance to be five light years
Then he...
Yes, but you have to ask when he's moving
How far apart does he see the stars
And moving with close to the speed of light
Then he sees the stars as being
Not five light years or four
light years or whatever we said
But four light years times the
square root of one minus v squared
And that in his reference frame would be the description
So...
It started to look like it was five years away
And a few minutes later it looks
like it was two light years away
Wait, sorry, why does...
If you start out, before you accelerate,
the star looks like it's five years away
Then you accelerate
Okay, so...
It looks like it's two light years away
Okay, okay, you're correct
But then we have to analyze a more complicated problem
A complicated problem then starts with
an observer which is at rest
And again, the observer starts to accelerate
And has to accelerate up to this velocity
And we have to take
into account this effects of acceleration
The simpler calculation to do is to imagine an astronaut
That was always forever and
ever moving with uniform velocity
Remember, the special theory of
relativity, just like Newton's theory
Only makes sense in inertial reference frames
To find out what happens in a non-inertial reference frame
We can answer the question
We can answer the question, but
the question will not be answered
By application of exactly the same formulas
that we would use in an inertial frame
The speed of light is always the speed of light
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, absolutely
Yeah, everything we've been talking
about is in inertial reference frames
To study non-inertial reference frames,
we have to begin over again
And as you correctly point out, there's
obviously going to be some effects of acceleration
Which we have to take into account
Okay, yes?
So you would have...
So the twin paradox, say for example, if
a rocket took off and had to decelerate
You know, you would still get the same end product
But you have to...
Wait, wait, sorry, again
I mean, the twin paradox
Yes
If the person...
If the person took off with
a rocket, had to decelerate to...
Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah
I mean, if it wasn't
born moving with a large velocity
Right
Yeah
Right, but you would still do the same thing
You would still calculate the
total proper time along its trajectory
Yeah
So the total proper time
would have contributions from different velocities
And we can work those out
They're simple to work out, but yes
Right
No, we assume one twin
is born with a huge velocity
And the other one is at rest
Oh, the poor woman
The only second thing is the person
Very male audience today
Not to dwell on this issue of time, but
it seems that all these problems that we have
Are generated by the fact that we
put time in such a special place
When in fact...
Well, we're going to see that
time is not in a special place
Yeah, you're right
In the back of our minds,
we tend to isolate time as special
But the lesson of special relativity
is that time is not that special
But we'll...
The real question is, can we recover
all of the physics of slow velocities
That we normally know and learn
and love from our Darwinian circuits
That we inherited from all the years that
nothing ever moved faster than 50 miles an hour
Can we recover it by
taking the formulas from special relativity
And specializing them in the case of very slow velocities
And yes, of course we can
I've also come to think about
it in a way which is
Not only that it's special, but it's sort
of elevated to the level of a special dimension
Or a fourth dimension
Well, yes
Is this necessary?
Is it necessary?
It's not only not necessary,
Einstein never thought about that
He never said that time was the fourth dimension
It's not necessary to think
of time as the fourth dimension
But once you start mixing it up with space
Where are our Lorentz transformations here
There's an awful lot of the physics
Which looks very symmetric between space and time
Sort of pseudo-symmetric
T squared minus x squared
minus y squared minus z squared
They do get mixed up
with each other under Lorentz transformations
In a way that they wouldn't
Under these Galilean transformations
So here you see, in Galileo
Time really just is time
Whereas in Einstein or Lorentz
Time really does, oh here it is
Time really does get mixed up with space
In a way that makes you
not want to think of it as
Fundamentally separate
Decoupled, yeah
Yeah, they're geometrically part of a whole
Which is bigger than either of them
Yeah
If I have a hydrogen atom in front of me
I see a particular value there
You know, I think if we want
to get in there we better get in
I'm sorry, I'm sorry
The preceding program is copyrighted by Stanford University
Please visit us at stanford.edu
Thank you