This program is brought to you by Stanford University.
Please visit us at stanford.edu.
All right, so we want to talk a
little bit about the laws of nature and
the form that the laws of nature take.
Now, let me give you an
example of a possible law of nature.
Which is not a law of
nature, but discuss what's wrong with it.
So here's a law of nature.
Particles collide.
Here's my axes, x and y,
fixed and permanent on the blackboard,
or fixed and permanent in space.
And the rule is particles will collide and
go away, and then they'll go away.
And then they'll go away.
And then they'll go off in weird
directions whenever their x coordinate is the same.
Whenever the two particles, whenever
their x coordinates become the same,
they suddenly turn around or
go off in some other direction.
So, for example, if this particle is moving
this way, and this one is moving this way,
when they get to the same value
of x, the rule is something happens.
We needn't specify precisely what happens.
Maybe they get turned around, or maybe
they go off in some other direction.
If they're moving like these two other particles,
they're moving in some other direction,
not horizontally, but they're moving this way.
That one's moving this way,
and this one's moving this way.
Again, the rule is whenever
their x coordinates become the same,
they collide more and more.
And then they're moving in different directions.
They can go off and do something else.
Well, that's a possible law of nature.
It could have been like that.
There's nothing mathematically inconsistent with it.
But it just doesn't seem right.
It seems to violate something that's deeply ingrained,
both in physics and the laws
of physics, and in our own intuition.
What is it?
What's the rule that's being violated?
What?
Homogeneity.
Not homogeneity. No.
Okay, good.
It's not homogeneity.
Homogeneity says that you can translate
things, and they'll stay the same.
That the laws of nature are independent of
where you put the center of your coordinates.
And this is independent of where
you put the center of your coordinates.
You didn't specify the x.
Because you didn't specify the x.
Yes, I didn't specify the x.
I just told you whenever x becomes equal,
they collide.
So we could say it this way.
If we have two particles,
and they have coordinates, one called x1,
and this is not the component of the coordinate,
this is just labels which particle we're talking about.
When x1 minus x of 2 become equal to 0,
they collide.
That's our rule.
When the difference between the
two x's are equal to 0,
they collide.
Well, that doesn't specify what particular value of x.
It could be x way out here,
it could be x way over there.
They'll collide if we lift everything up vertically,
they'll collide if we lift everything down vertically.
So, in fact, it doesn't violate homogeneity of space.
Space is everywhere is the same in this rule.
Yeah?
That means you can always find some coordinate where
you can make them collide at any time you want.
No, but the rule here is they always collide,
and if and only if their x's are equal.
Right.
This violates the isotropy of space.
It violates the idea that when you rotate coordinates,
the laws of physics stay the same.
That the laws of physics are the same
and independent of the orientation of your axes.
Not the place where you put your origin,
but the orientation of your axes.
So, for example, if I reoriented my axes,
so that they look like,
well, I'm going to reorient them
so that this becomes the y coordinate.
Let's see, the y coordinate now is over here,
and the x coordinate is over here.
I'm simply relabeling.
It is a rotation of my
coordinates, a rotation by 90 degrees.
Then exactly the same physics will require us to
say that particles collide when the y's are equal.
Different law.
Different form.
If we oriented the axes
in some awkward and arbitrary direction,
then the law would become much more complicated.
Some combination, they would only
interact or they would only collide
when some combination of the x's and y's were equal.
So, what would be violated here is the law
that says the laws of physics are the same
in every coordinate system independent of the angles,
or independent of the angle of the x axis.
However, we do have to ensure that
the coordinates are perpendicular to each other.
There are things in the rules of physics which
require us to use perpendicular coordinates to express the law.
We can express the laws of
physics in any coordinates we like,
but they take a special and simple form.
In coordinates for which the
axes are perpendicular to each other.
But the rule that says that it
doesn't matter which way we orient our coordinates,
it doesn't matter if I look at you this
way or this way or this way or this way,
the laws of physics should be the same,
that's violated here.
Let me give you an example of
a law of physics which is not violated,
which does not violate the rule that
laws of physics should be the same.
Rotational invariance. This is called rotational invariance.
Invariance under rotation of axes.
Let's require that particles only interact
if both the x coordinates of the two particles
and the y coordinates of the two particles are equal.
In other words, if x1 equals
x2 and if y1 equals y2,
what does that say?
That says that the particles collide with each other,
whatever it is they do, maybe they turn around,
I'm not going to specify exactly what they do,
but the rule now would be they can only collide
if they hit the same point.
In other words, if both the x
coordinate and the y coordinates are equal,
then they collide.
In fact, they don't even have
to be moving along the same line.
If a particle comes in along this axis
and a particle comes in along this axis,
and they find themselves at exactly the same point,
then they collide.
That would be a law of
nature that would be the same,
no matter how we orient our axes.
If they collide when they come to the same point,
then it doesn't matter whether we use this axis,
whether we use this axis.
And so this law of physics would be one
which was invariant under rotations,
would be the same no matter
what orientation we chose for our axes.
I am not, for the moment I'm just ignoring time.
For the moment, yeah, of course we do,
but I was about to come to that.
Okay.
If there's a z coordinate, yes.
Right, so, exactly so.
And if space is three dimensional,
if z of one is equal to z of two,
if and only if these conditions are satisfied,
then two particles will close.
Come to time in a minute.
All right, we can re-express this
in a single equation using vectors.
We think of the position
of a particle as a vector.
Let's call that position r.
I put a little arrow
on top to indicate a vector,
but now I mean a three dimensional vector
in ordinary space.
No time for the moment.
We'll come back to time in a minute.
All right, we can write this as one equation.
We can write it that the particle collides only
if r one is equal to r two,
or r one minus r
of two is equal to zero.
And this equation implies all components
of r should be equal to zero.
It's a vector equation.
It has three components,
and it's rotationally invariant.
Okay.
Here's a fact.
If a vector is zero,
and this vector is zero,
this is the rule.
Particles collide when a certain vector is zero.
If a vector is zero,
it's zero in every coordinate system.
In other words, if all components,
a vector being zero means all of its components
are equal to zero.
If all of the components of
a vector are equal to zero,
that's true in every coordinate system.
If one or two components of
the vector is equal to zero,
and the other one is not,
then that is not something which
is true in every coordinate system.
For example,
here's a vector whose x component is equal to zero.
Right?
In some other coordinate system,
the x component of that
vector is not equal to zero.
So a law,
or a rule,
that would say this or that happens
when a certain x component of
a vector is equal to zero,
that law will not in general be rotationally invariant.
On the other hand,
if we have a vector which is equal to zero,
that means that it has no length at all,
or that it's just a vector of zero length,
just the origin,
then that vector is zero in every coordinate system,
no matter how we rotate it.
That's why we express laws
of nature in terms of vectors.
That's why we choose to
express them in terms of vectors.
And the advantage of a vector description,
vectors transform in a certain way.
They transform when you rotate coordinates,
the components of vectors change,
they transform,
but all vectors transform the same way when you rotate.
So if a vector is
equal to zero in one frame,
it's equal to zero in another frame.
If two vectors are equal in one frame,
they are equal in any frame.
And that's why we express,
that is the reason that we
express physics in terms of vectors,
because we know that when we
express it properly in terms of vectors,
then the rules are in place.
And that's why we keep our variables
independent of the orientation of our axes.
Now let's come to time.
What about time?
We could,
let's let the horizontal axis be x again,
but now let the vertical axis be time,
x and t.
Now,
again,
I could have a rule which says,
particles collide
when
Well, let's see.
Particle collisions take place only when the
time of the two particles is the same.
What would that mean?
That would mean that it's
possible for two particles to collide.
This indicates a particle going forward and
then going backward, so it's moving along
the x-axis, it's moving along, moving back along the x-axis.
It's possible for particles to collide like
that when the two times are equal.
It's possible for them to collide at a later
time, as long as the two times are equal.
Collide means both of
their velocities simultaneously change.
That's what I mean by collide,
that their velocities simultaneously change, but always
at the same time.
That's a perfectly good law of physics.
It's a true law of physics in Newtonian physics.
And in fact, it is even a
true law of physics in Newtonian physics.
Well, it is a true,
it's a possible law of physics.
Particles collide only, their velocities change
simultaneously if they change at all.
It's not a possible law in the special
theory of relativity, and the reason is because of
the idea of simultaneity, it is not invariant.
So if I had a law of Newtonian
physics, I would have a law of relativity.
I would have a law of relativity that
said that two particles collide in one particular
frame, in your frame, only when the times are equal.
Then in some other frame of reference, this
frame of reference here, the times of collision
would not be the same, and we would
come to the conclusion that the relativity principle
was not correct, that the laws of physics
are not the same in all reference frames.
There's one particular reference frame
in which particle collisions take place.
At equal times.
And in other frames of reference, it's
a more complicated story in which some combination
of x and t's have to be equal.
All right, that's not the way physics works.
The way physics works is Lorentz invariant.
Lorentz invariant means, again, that the laws of
physics are the same in all reference frames
moving one with respect to the other.
What does that entail about simple particle collisions?
Very simple.
What do you mean by simple particle collisions?
Well, for very simple particle collision,
the simplest kind of particle collision, particles
collide, they don't produce any other particles,
not very much happens, they just bang into
each other and they go off.
That implies that collisions can only take
place when the two particles find themselves
at the same spacetime point.
In other words, not only when their
times are equal, but when they're persistent.
But when their positions are also equal.
If two particles only collide when they're at
the same event, the same point of spacetime,
then it doesn't matter which coordinates you use.
Being at the same spacetime point is an invariant concept.
So that's a good law of physics from
the point of view of relativity theory, that particles
collide not just when they're at the same
position in space, but also only when they're
at the same point in space.
So it's a good law of physics.
But also only at the same time.
That also can be expressed
in a kind of vector notation.
If we represent the location of a particle,
or a location of a point along a particle
trajectory by a four vector, the four vector now
has not only components x, y, and z, but
it also has a component t.
Then we would add in one more equation
here, that the particles can only collide at an
event, and that event has to have
the same location in space and in time.
Now you can say very much the same
words about spacetime that I just said about space.
If a vector in spacetime, if a vector in spacetime,
if a vector in spacetime, if a vector in spacetime,
has one or two or three components which
are equal, sorry, which are equal to zero,
if a vector has space component equal
to zero, that doesn't mean it's zero.
It can have a time component.
Here's a vector which has a
time component but no space component.
If I have some law of physics that
says nothing more than something or other happens when
the space components of a vector are
equal to zero, that's not Lorentz invariant.
And the reason is because in some other
frame of reference, the x's of these two points
are not the same.
The x's of these two points are not the
same in some other frame of reference, and so saying
that something special happens when the x components
or the y components or the z components
of a vector are equal to
zero, that can't be Lorentz invariant.
The only Lorentz invariant statement that you can make,
concerning a rule about a vector, is that all
of its components have to be equal to zero.
If in some frame of reference, if the
law of nature is that some components equal zero,
then it had better be all of them.
Why?
Because if you rotate or Lorentz transform
your coordinates, you will find an inconsistency
unless you require all of the
components to be equal to zero.
So as I said,
a law of physics could be,
that all four components of the location of two events,
what are the two events?
The two events are the
sudden turning around of one particle,
and the sudden turning around of another particle.
Those are both events.
This law of physics would tell us that
this event, the two events, could only happen if
they were at the same spacetime point.
So we express laws of physics in terms of,
four vectors,
or objects which transform in a particular coherent way.
Four vectors transform,
the components transform into each other.
We've seen for example that under Lorentz transformations,
x and t for example
get mixed up with each other,
but they get mixed up with
each other in such a way,
that if all the components are
equal to zero in one frame,
they get mixed up with zero in another frame.
So we express laws of physics
in terms of objects which transform,
and we always require,
either we transpose everything to the left hand side,
and say that its components are a four vector,
transform is a four vector,
and must be equal to zero,
or sometimes we might express the laws of physics as an
equation with the left hand side and the right hand side,
and we do that by saying that,
x of two,
y of two,
z of two,
t of two,
we express this particular form
as expressing a certain rule,
by saying that two four
vectors are equal to each other.
Not that some four vector is equal to zero,
but a certain four vector associated with one event,
is equal to a four
vector associated with the other event.
So sometimes we express them by setting something to zero,
sometimes we express something by expressing a
left hand side equals a right hand side,
but the equations only make sense,
in this particular kind of case,
if they're whole expressions for entire four vectors,
not just for pieces of a four vector.
Four vectors are of course
things which transform under Lorentz transformations,
the same way that x, y, z, and t do.
So let's define a four vector.
It's an object with four components,
one for each direction of space,
and one for time,
and it transforms,
what does it mean to transform?
It means its value as
measured in different reference frames,
transforms,
so that if I know it in one reference frame,
I can give you the rule
for computing it in another reference frame.
For example, position, velocity, and so forth,
transform from one Lorentz frame to another.
Position, we know how that transforms.
Let's take the case of first a Lorentz transformation,
where x equals x minus v,t,
y, this is x prime, equals x minus v,t,
over square root of one minus v squared.
Incidentally, the notation, I keep writing square
root of one minus v,t, but it's okay,
it's not even a second
equation, it's a fundamental solution.
squared in the denominator here. There's a
standard notation, gamma is equal to 1
over the square root of 1 minus v
squared, gamma of v, gamma of v. It saves
writing. There's nothing deep about it,
it's just a way of rewriting, so
another way to write this is that it's
gamma times x minus vt. Okay, what else?
y prime, say it again? Yeah, yeah, yeah, c is
equal to 1. If we want to put c back
into the formulas, we put it down here.
Alright, c is equal to 1. y prime is
equal to y, z prime is equal to z, and
t prime is equal to t minus vx divided by
y.
So we have root 1 minus v squared,
or gamma times t minus vx. This is the
transformation properties of coordinates
of an event. Other transformation
properties involve rotations of space.
Let me write down the transformations
associated rotations of space. Rotations of
space are given, here's an example.
There are many, many axes that you
can rotate about, but if I just rotate
about the z axis, vertically is the z
axis, I rotate my coordinates, x and y get
mixed up with each other. Z does not
get mixed into it, and neither does time. If
all I do is rotate my, my
coordinate axes, then the equations would look not,
not totally dissimilar to this. Well, not
so, not totally similar either, but they
would look like this. X prime is equal to, z is equal to two, and t is equal to z, and t is
equal to t. over and over, times t, and t is equal to t, and t is equal to t. over and over.
equal to x times cosine of an angle plus
y times sine of an angle. Let's put in
here plus 0 times z plus 0 times t,
just to remember that z and t are also
part of the game. y prime is equal to
minus y, minus x, sorry, minus x cosine theta,
no, minus x sine theta, minus x sine theta,
plus y cosine theta, plus 0 z plus 0 t.
z prime is equal to z. I'm stacking
things equal to z. I'm stacking things up so
that x always appears in the same place,
y always appears in the same place, z
always appears in the same place.
We would have to do that again.
We would write 0x plus 0y plus z plus
0t. I'm being pedantic by putting in all these
zeros here. And finally, t prime is equal to
t, with all the others being 0, and so
forth. This tells me how things
transform under a rotation about the z-axis.
This tells me how they
transform under a Lorentz transformation.
There are similar kinds of equations. In
each case, they're linear equations of a form,
of a particular form. A matrix is involved.
So I wanted to write this in matrix form.
I think I wrote that last time in
matrix form. In each case, they're linear equations which
have the form x prime mu. Now, mu
goes from they were from the inflammation by example,
x-prime mu theseражions we have formed X prime mu
now mu goes from t here. Qu County means
T problem. We already know what T is. So without
that I know what t is. So that's just the realization
we have of the equation. But because big rechtization is
work and process, this is what WOODHER gets better and
1, 2, 3, and 0. 1, 2, 3, and 0. 1
means X, 2 means Y, 3 means Z, and 0 means time.
Thereof the form X prime is equal to
some matrix mu nu times X nu. For example,
let me write down the matrix
governing the Lorentz transformation. In that case,
the matrix... Let's make some
notation. The first column will
stand for X, the second column will stand
for Y, the third column for Z, and the
fourth column for T, or the zeroth column.
And same with rows X, Y, Z. I'm just
labeling now the entries. Okay, what are
the entries here? Well, from here you can
see...
that x prime is equal to gamma x, so
there's a gamma over here, there's a minus v gamma
over here, and a zero zero.
That indicates that y and z don't come into
this equation, but there's a gamma x and a
gamma v t with a minus sign, and so on.
Let's see, y prime, that's equal to zero times
x plus one times y plus zero times z plus
zero times t.
Same with z, one zero.
And t prime, that's equal, that has a
minus v gamma here, zero zero and gamma.
That's the matrix.
The matrix which governs
the simple Lorentz transformation here.
The matrix which would govern a rotation of
space would also be a matrix with four by
four structure, but here I can just read
it right off here, the corresponding matrix for
a rotation about the z-axis.
A rotation about the z-axis would look
like cosine theta, sine theta, zero zero.
Minus sine theta, cosine theta, zero zero,
zero zero one zero, zero zero zero one.
That would be the matrix which represents a rotation.
Now you can combine these transformations together in
a wide variety of ways by making them
a little bit more complicated.
So let's start with the first one.
Let's start by mixing
up rotations and Lorentz transformations.
For example, if I wanted to do a Lorentz
transformation along some different angle, let's say an angle
in the xy plane, then first I
would make a coordinate transformation that turned the
x-axis into the new x-axis.
I would use the rotation matrix here to
find new coordinates along which the new x-axis
is along the direction that
I want to do the later.
So I would do the rotation.
I would do the new x-axis.
I would do the rotation.
I would do the Lorentz transformation.
Then after having done that, I would do
a second transformation, which would be a Lorentz
transformation between time and the new x-axis.
That would entail multiplying
these two matrices together, basically.
That's what the matrix for the full rotation would
be, is it would be the product of the
full Lorentz transformation, or
the full combination of rotations.
So the Lorentz transformation and rotation
would involve the product of these.
But really, it's enough to know that physics
is invariant under rotations and know how to
write the rotation matrices and
invariant under Lorentz boosts along.
This is called a Lorentz boost.
Boost means you speed up the velocity.
It's enough to know those two forms here and
know that you mix them up in all kinds of
ways to do more generalization.
More general Lorentz transformations.
More general transformations.
Can you do the order, rotate first and then...
Well, you get different answers.
You get different answers.
Yep.
If you first Lorentz transform, let me show you why.
Imagine you first Lorentz transform.
So that brings you to a new coordinate frame
in which this is the new space axis here.
And then you do your rotation.
Your rotation is a rotation.
You do your rotation about
this plane here, not this plane.
So it depends on the order.
If you first Lorentz transformed and then
rotated, you would be rotating about a different
surface.
You'd be rotating a different surface than
if you first rotated and then Lorentz transformed.
So the order of action does matter.
But it's enough to know these two and how
to combine them to know how to do more generalization.
OK.
So we can do any transformation
of the kind that applies to vectors.
All right.
So the more general statement is
that there's a matrix of some sort.
The matrix has to satisfy some rules.
All right.
But basically the rules are that it's
various kinds of products of these matrices.
And we just write it in a more
general form that the primed coordinates are some matrix
times primed coordinates.
And for each specific situation where we
want to transform from one coordinate system to
another, we have to know what the matrix is.
But usually we can figure that out.
We can also write this in the form a
column vector x prime is equal to a matrix.
Now let's just think of that as
a matrix now times a column vector x.
OK.
All right.
Just think of it as
matrix multiplication or manipulation of indices.
Remember, I want to remind you
one thing, when you have repeated four-dimensional
indices like this, particularly when one of
them is exhibited as an upper index
and one of them is exhibited as
a lower index, repeating the indices means sum
over the indices. It's the same
summation that you would do if
you multiplied the matrix, or let's
put it x1, x2, x3, x0.
Alright? When you work out the components
of the product, you have to sum gamma
times x prime plus 0 times x, I'm sorry,
gamma times x1 plus 0 times x2 plus 0
times x3 and so forth. That's
the same sum that's implicit here
and summing over the repeated index.
Alright, so this is just a notational
device for writing out generally, what
a Lorentz transformation does. It's a
linear operation like that. That's a special
case. This is a special case of
the transformation of vectors with a vector,
in this case happens to be the
space-time position of a point. There are
other four vectors. There are other four
vectors which are interesting. For example,
the four vector associated with velocity.
We'll come back to it. The four
vector associated with proper velocity. Remember what proper
velocity is. Proper velocity is not dx by dx by
dt, but it's dx mu by d tau. Tau is
proper time. First of all, before we even
go ahead, even before we talk about four vectors,
we should talk about scalars. Scalars are
things which are the same in every reference
frame. For example, if we're talking about
only rotations, let's forget for the moment
Lorentz transformations, just rotations. The temperature
at this point right over here
is the same no matter which way we
orient our axes. So temperature is a thing which
doesn't transform.
Temperature is a scalar. It's a scalar
quantity which means it doesn't have components, it's
just one number characterizing it. And the
temperature of a point in space doesn't depend
on what axes are used to describe it.
How about the distance between two points?
The distance between two points. Now I'm not
thinking about spacetime, I'm thinking only
about space. The distance between two points,
it doesn't matter which way you orient your
axes, it's just the distance between the two points.
The number of inches between these two points is
the same no matter which way I orient my
axes. So distance is also a scalar
quantity. Components of vectors are not scalar quantities.
They change from one reference frame to another,
but the distance between two points is a scalar
quantity. I might have a, not a law of
nature so much, but a simple claim. I might tell
you, for example, that the distance between two
points is a scalar quantity. I might tell
that the distance between two points measured in meters happens
to be the same as the temperature measured in Fahrenheit.
Right, it's a stupid thing, but it
might be, I mean, it might be.
What is the temperature in
Fahrenheit in here, about 70 degrees?
Yeah.
Alright, so I can imagine
two points separated by 70 centimeters.
And then I would tell you, it just
so happens that the distance between my fists
measured in centimeters happens to be the
same as the temperature in the room.
Does that depend on which axes I use?
No, because the distance between the
points doesn't depend on the axes.
The temperature doesn't depend on
the axes, they're both scalar quantities.
And so the statement that
the temperature equals the distance,
that's a rotationally invariant statement.
And if it's true in one frame,
it will be true in every frame.
In this case, it's a statement about scalar quantities.
I should have talked about
scalars even before I mentioned vectors.
Vectors are more complicated.
For vectors, if a thing is true, it
better be true for all components of the vector.
Thing is true in every frame of reference.
Alright now, this is a four vector.
And the meaning of saying it's a four
vector is first of all it has four components,
but let's call it, well let's just call it,
well let's just call it, well let's just call it,
the general four vector, not this
specific one, but the general four vector,
let's call it for the moment a mu.
This one is usually called u mu.
But let's just generalize and think about
the general notion of a four vector,
and let's call it a mu.
Its components are equal to a1,
a2,
a3,
and a4.
Or a naught, sorry.
The definition of a four vector, and
it does apply to the four velocity,
or the proper velocity,
the definition of a four vector
is it's a thing which transforms,
again, transforms means that if
you know it in one frame,
you can determine it in another frame.
The definition is,
that it transforms exactly the same way as x,
as the components of x.
So, if I know a in one frame,
in another frame, in the primed frame,
the components a prime mu
are equal to l mu nu
times their values in the first frame.
Exactly the same as x.
For example, the four components of a,
if I just did a ordinary equation,
the Lorentz transform,
or transformation,
would vary in exactly the same
way as x, y, z, and t.
I won't bother writing it down.
The transformation properties of a four vector are the same
as x, y, z, and t.
That's the definition of a four vector.
If a four vector is zero,
in one frame of reference,
if this is zero in one frame of reference,
it's obviously zero in every frame of reference.
Just that every component is zero here,
then every component will be zero here.
If two vectors are equal in one frame of reference,
then they will be equal in every frame of reference,
assuming all four components are equal.
So, that's the value of
thinking in terms of four vectors.
The things which are true,
are true in every frame of reference.
This makes them useful for describing
the laws of physics,
which are supposed to be
true in every frame of reference.
Now,
representing a vector in this form here
is called the contravariant form of the vector.
There is another form for the same vector,
which is called the covariant form,
or the covariant components.
It's really imagined to be the same gene
as the geometric object,
just described in a different way.
And to describe it,
we put the mu downstairs.
It's upstairs, downstairs.
And what it is,
is it's the same collection of components,
exactly the same,
except the space components,
one, two, and three,
are changed in sign.
A1, A2, A3,
minus, minus, A naught.
Why on earth would I want to do that?
Well, first, before why I want to do it,
let me just describe it mathematically
a little bit differently.
Here's the mathematical connection between the two.
A mu is equal to a certain matrix,
I'll write down that matrix in a moment,
mu nu times A nu.
Now, before we do anything else,
let's look at this equation.
Before I even say what it means.
It has the nice feature that
it's first of all summed over,
the nu index.
Always, when you sum over a nu, an index,
it had better be one downstairs with one upstairs.
Otherwise, you're writing something that doesn't make sense.
Now, you can't, so far I
haven't even told you what this means,
so whether it makes sense or not,
I'm just telling you now.
For future purposes,
if you're writing out some equations like this
and you discover that you're summing over indices,
both of which are upstairs,
or both of which are downstairs,
you made some mistake.
This is the nice form that
Lorentz invariant equations should take.
Summing over indices should always
be one up and one down.
But you'll understand why in due time.
But let's see what this means.
Let's see exactly what this means.
So what is eta?
Eta is a matrix.
And it's the matrix
minus one, zero, zero, zero,
zero, minus one, zero, zero,
zero, zero, minus one, zero,
zero, zero, zero, plus one.
What does it do when it multiplies a column?
Here's a column.
So let's put the column there.
Let's multiply eta by mu, by a.
Eta times a,
thought of as a matrix,
times a column vector a.
That we just get by writing down
a1, a2, a3, and a4.
And let's see what we get.
Forget the left-hand side here.
Just let's look at the product.
It gives us minus a1
in the first entry,
minus a1, minus a2, minus a3,
plus a naught.
This should be naught.
Minus one times a1, plus a bunch of zeros.
Minus one times a2,
a bunch of zeros, and so forth.
So you go between the covariant form
and the contravariant form
by multiplying by this matrix eta.
It's a convenient notational device.
Why do we do it?
Yeah?
In your last column vector,
that should be a negative 2 upstairs
when you're getting confused.
Yeah, yeah.
Good. Thank you.
In the equation above it,
a lower than mu,
the indices on the component
should be upstairs.
Absolutely right.
Yeah.
And in fact,
we could identify this with a1, a2, a3, and a0,
where these are lower indices.
You're absolutely right.
That was not consistent.
Thank you.
Okay, why would we want to do this?
We want to do this because it's a useful trick
in forming scalars,
and it's a very simple thing.
We want to do it because we want to
have a variance,
things which don't change
under coordinate transformation.
For example,
supposing I take a mu,
and I multiply it by a mu downstairs.
Again, summed over indices which are repeated.
What does this mean?
This means we can read it directly off here.
It's a1 upstairs times minus a1 upstairs,
a1 squared plus,
no, minus a1 squared minus a2 squared,
minus a3 squared plus a4 squared.
Well, this is very much like taking the x vector
and computing the proper length
or the proper time associated with the x vector.
If we go back to the x vector here,
we remember that
the difference of the time squared components
and the space squared components
are what we called tau,
tau squared.
Tau squared was the difference of these components,
and the main feature of it
was that it didn't change
from reference frame to reference frame.
It was invariant.
Well, since the a's,
by definition, transform exactly the same way as x's,
it follows that this quantity
does not change under Lorentz transformation
or rotation or any other kind of transformation
of the kind we're dealing with.
This is an invariant or a scalar.
So, just as a notational trick
to write in a compact way
a1 squared,
well, minus a1 squared,
minus a2 squared,
minus a3 squared,
plus a4 squared,
we invent the notation
with a lower index and an upper index.
Where the lower index
changes the sign of all three space components
and leaves the time component.
I keep writing a4, but I mean a0.
So that's just a trick
to keep track of this minus sign
in multiplying vectors
to form Lorentz invariant scalars.
For example, in this language,
we would just write
that the proper length of a vector x
is x mu, x mu.
And this would stand for t squared
minus x squared, minus y squared,
minus z squared.
So that's the notational trick
to keep track of minus signs.
And this eta matrix here
is part of that notational trick.
It's just another compact way
of writing that the thing with the lower components
is the thing with the upper components
with the appropriate sign changes made.
Yeah?
That might look like it was a column vector
times a row vector,
but we're looking at this more
as just a neural product,
so you don't worry about that.
Would that upper mu first?
Say it again.
Oh.
It looks like column vector
times row vector
instead of row vector
times column vector.
Am I writing it wrong?
Uh...
I always think of this as column.
This is matrix.
還是肉薯烤
It's also a column, yeah. Both
should be thought of as columns, yeah.
This is not going from columns to rows. Well,
in some sense you can think of it that way,
but I wouldn't. Not now. Just think
of them as rows. Sorry, as columns.
Another way to write A mu A mu, which is the
invariant, is to write eta mu nu A mu A nu.
Why is that? Because if I multiply eta mu
nu by A mu, well, let's change to nu, nu,
nu. When you sum over an index,
it doesn't matter what you call it.
Okay.
All right. So this lowered the index of
A and then multiplied it by the contravariant, A.
All right, so we have various
ways to write the same thing.
The order doesn't matter.
No, the order doesn't matter. No. The order doesn't matter.
It's diagonal.
It's diagonal. First of all, it's symmetric.
Yeah. The order doesn't matter. Even if
it wasn't symmetric, the order wouldn't matter.
No. The order does not matter. Not
until we start doing quantum mechanics anyway,
which we're not going to do. Okay. Let me
prove something else. Suppose you have two four vectors.
Let's call them A and B.
Okay.
Am is of course exactly the same thing, incidentally,
as ab nước đó là
tất nhiên lgent trumps được lengui.
The b is the separating measure.
Why is that?
Well, both of them are just
hoc 10-A b final f ,
minus A 1B1 minus A 2B2,
minus the same thing for 3.
It doesn't matter if you put the upper index
on A and the lower index on B or
swap them. Lower index on A, upper index
on B. Same thing. You get the same thing.
So basically the product, we could just think of this
as a new kind of product of A times B
for two 4-vectors.
It's not the product of two numbers. It's the
product of two 4-vectors and the product of two 4-vectors,
the only thing new about it is that
this eta is in there, this funny sign business.
Otherwise, it would be very much
like the dot product of ordinary vectors.
Now,
what about this object here? Is this object invariant when you
have two different vectors? If you just have one vector, A, and
it transforms on the Lorentz transformations,
then this particular combination doesn't change
as you go from frame to frame.
What about if you have two vectors, A times B?
That also is invariant.
There's a simple way to prove it.
If A is a 4-vector and B is a 4-vector,
then A plus B and A minus B are both 4-vectors.
That means that
A plus B, and B plus B, are both 4-vectors.
A plus B times A plus B,
these are both 4-vectors, A and B are 4-vectors, A
plus B is a 4-vector, and now when I write product,
I mean product in this sense, one upper and one lower, but
it doesn't matter which one is upper and which one is lower.
This must be invariant because if A and B are
4-vectors, so is A plus B, so this is invariant.
What about the difference?
A minus B
times A minus B,
that's also invariant because if you have two or
four vectors, the difference between them is another 4-vector.
Well, this is A squared, this is
A times A plus B times B
plus twice A times B. This is A times
A plus B times B minus twice A times B.
If both of these are invariant, then
it had better be that A times B
is also invariant.
Why? Because if you subtract these, if you subtract these,
the A squares will cancel, the B squares would
cancel, and you'll just get twice A times B.
Twice A times B is also invariant. So anything
with one upper index like this and one lower index,
combine them together, you form an invariant quantity,
which is the same in every reference frame.
Now, of course, it's good to find things
which are the same in every reference frame,
because a law of nature is supposed
to be the same in every reference frame.
Or a measurement. A measurement of a, you know,
distinct quantity should be the same in every frame.
Temperature, distance between particles, whatever.
All right, let's go on to consider some
specific 4-vector, the velocity 4-vector,
which we did last time.
But now armed with some
powerful notation, let's define some things.
If we have a world line of a particle
and we have two neighboring points, then the separation
between them is a little infinitesimally small 4-vector,
and we can write it as dx mu.
It has, let's just write what its components are.
Its components are d, which is the distance between particles,
and its components are d, which is the distance between particles.
So it's a little bit of a difference,
but it's a little bit of a difference.
So it's dxdydz and dt, or
equivalently dx1, dx2, dx3, and dx0.
That's a component, that's a 4-vector.
It's infinitesimally small.
If we divide that by d tau,
and let's work out what d tau is.
D tau squared, the square of d
tau is dT squared minus dx squared.
So that's the 4-vector.
And if we divide that by d
tau, then it's dT squared minus dx squared.
square minus dy squared minus dz squared.
But that's just dx mu dx mu.
dt squared minus dx squared minus dy
squared minus dz squared is d tau,
is d tau squared, or d tau is just
the square root of this. The x mu divided
by d tau. Okay, so this is the rate
of change of the x, of the x coordinate, of
the x mu coordinate of the particle,
but not rate of change with ordinary time,
but rate of change with proper time.
The rate at which the coordinates of the
particle are changing, but is measured by
a clock moving with the particle. That's
the x mu d tau and
that is called the proper four velocity.
Okay.
U mu. What are its components? Well, let's,
we can, before I talk about the components
of it, yeah, this is the four velocity.
Notice it has four components. That's weird. You
would think that if you know the three
components of velocity, that you know everything about
how the particle is moving, and that's
true. The reason is because the fourth component
of the velocity is determined in terms of
the first three components. Why is that? That's
because this velocity here satisfies a
constraint, satisfies a relationship which allows you
to compute the fourth component from the
first three. Let's see what that constraint is.
I maintain that this object here is a
unit vector. What does a unit vector mean? Well,
it means that it's in a product with itself or
that u mu, u mu is equal to one. It's kind
of like a unit vector in ordinary space. If
you have a unit vector in ordinary space and
you know its x component, then you also know
its y component, up to a sign. There's an
ambiguous sign. All right. Why? Because the sums
of the squares of the component are the
same. So the sum of the squares of the
component must be equal to one. Well, the four velocity
is a unit vector. How do we see that?
Let's just check that. Let's just check that. All
we have to do is work it out. dx mu, this is
equal to dx mu by d tau, dx mu by d tau.
Upper component, lower component. But look here. d
tau squared is just dx mu dx mu. That's
what we have in the numerator.
So the numerator and the denominator are the same
thing. The x mu dx mu is d tau squared
and the denominator, you also have d tau
squared. And so the four velocity is a kind
of unit four vector. The four components
of the four velocity are not independent. The
fourth component, apart from an ambiguous
sign, is completely determined in terms of
the other three components.
For speeds much less than c, does the
four velocity become similar to the regular velocity?
Yes, let's do that right now. We did it
last time, but I'll remind you. That was exactly
what I was about to do. So let's do it. Let's
do u1, u2, and u3. All right? Just the x and
y and z components. Let's just call it ux.
When I'm talking about u1, u2, and u3, I'm
thinking about space. For some reason, I rather
think about x, y, and z than 1, 2,
and 3. But let's say u sub x, or u super
x, is equal to dx by d tau. But that's the
same as dx by dt times dt by d tau.
So we need to know, what is this, of course? This
is just ordinary velocity. We can do the same
thing for the y component. This is equal to
dy by dt.
dt by d tau. Same thing for uz. This is equal
to dz by dt, dt by d tau. So for the space
components here, we can just write a simple
equation. We can write one equation. We can
write that u, thought of as an ordinary
three-dimensional vector, is equal to ordinary velocity. Let's
just call this ordinary velocity.
That's the same as u sub x. So we
can just write a simple equation. We can write one
equation. We can write that u sub x is
equal to the velocity times dt by d tau. That's
true for all three components. We'll worry
about the fourth component in a minute. We'll
come to the fourth component of u in a
minute. But let's just take the first three components.
The relation between the ordinary velocity and
the proper velocity is a simple factor,
dt by d tau. Let's work out what that is.
Let's work out what dt by d tau is. d tau
is equal, now I'm going to write it out
explicitly, dt squared minus dx squared minus dy squared
minus dz squared. d tau squared, sorry, that's
d tau squared, so it's the square root of
this. Let's leave it this way, d tau squared. Now
what we want is dt by d tau. The ratio
of dt and d tau.
Let me divide this by dt squared.
dt squared, dt squared, dt squared, dt squared.
Well this is easy. This
is just 1 minus v squared.
This is equal to 1 minus the velocity squared.
The velocity of the particle. Now we're not
talking about velocities of two frames of reference necessarily.
We're really just talking about the velocity of a particle.
And to indicate that it's
a three-dimensional velocity, ordinary velocity,
I'll put a little arrow on
top of it to indicate ordinary vector.
1 minus velocity squared is dt by d tau squared.
Sorry, d tau by dt.
So all I have to
do in order to compute this,
to compute dt by d tau, is turn
it upside down and take its square root.
So dt by d tau, that's equal to 1
divided by the square root of 1 minus v squared.
That's what we called gamma up there.
It's just gamma of v.
It's the same gamma.
But now it's associated with the velocity of a particle.
And it's the fourth.
So it's the whole velocity,
all three components of it squared.
So now we know the relationship between the four velocities,
or these are the three components of space
of the four velocity and the ordinary velocity.
Let's just write down what it is.
There's a 1 divided by square
root of 1 minus v squared.
And let's put in c squared now.
C squared would go over here.
And then we have the...
Question.
Yeah, that second part there,
the dx square of dt squared.
This is not second derivative.
This is the square of the first derivative.
OK, because when I do velocity squared,
I get all sorts of cross terms.
You do velocity squared.
No, no, no, no, no, no.
Wait.
What are we doing?
We calculated...
No, no.
Let's do it again.
This is definition.
d tau squared.
Definition of d tau squared is d t squared
minus dx squared minus dy squared minus dz squared.
That's definition of d tau squared.
OK.
Now we're just dividing it.
It's a square of something.
It's not the second derivative of anything.
It's just a square of d tau squared.
We divide that by dt squared.
dt squared by dt squared is just 1.
dx squared by dt squared is
the x component of velocity squared.
So this is minus vx squared.
OK.
So you're saying that when you use
a vector, you mean dot product of it.
Well, that was definition.
Actually, I didn't even...
Yes.
But I didn't even really use it.
I just used the definition of
what I meant by d tau squared.
But it just was, as
you said, the dot product squared.
Yeah.
OK.
So there we are.
We have...
This is the space components of the four velocity.
And all you do is multiply the ordinary velocity,
which by a number which
is very, very close to 1,
if the velocity is much smaller than c.
So I'm a little confused at this point.
Yeah.
Because I was not thinking of that v
as the relative velocity between two coordinates.
It's not now.
It's just the velocity of
a particle in some particular frame.
So it kind of looks...
It's the same...
It's a similar mathematical expression.
But...
Yeah.
I tried to steer you out of that
by saying it's not the velocity of another frame.
Yeah.
Right.
But no, let's...
OK.
Let's say it even again.
Right.
This gamma of v here is a
particular function of the magnitude of a velocity,
any velocity.
If it happens to be the velocity of a particle,
it's velocity of a particle.
If it's the velocity of a moving frame,
it's the velocity of a moving frame.
But its definition is 1 divided by
the square root of 1 minus v squared.
That's its definition.
Where v squared here means the
square of the magnitude of the velocity.
Ordinary velocity squared.
The same velocity that if you
were to write the kinetic energy,
it would be 1 half mv squared.
Same velocity squared here.
OK.
So if it's a particle, we put in its velocity.
All three components, we sum them and square them.
And that defines this quantity here.
It also happens to be the same mathematical expression
that goes into the Lorentz transformation.
That...
It's not completely accidental,
but at this point it's just
a notation for a particular function.
OK.
So this is the first three components of u.
What about the fourth component of u?
The fourth component of u is
by definition dt by d tau.
Well, it's dx naught by d tau,
which is the same as dt by d tau.
And that is just 1 divided by square
root of 1 minus v squared over c squared.
That's what dt by d tau was.
All right.
So we now know what
the four components of u are
in terms of the ordinary velocities.
OK.
First of all, they're bigger than the ordinary velocities.
1 minus v squared over c
squared is always less than 1.
1 over it is greater than 1 and so forth.
So the space components of the velocity are always bigger
than the component of ordinary velocity.
Notice something very strange happens
when the velocity gets to be
up near the speed of light,
ordinary velocity.
When ordinary velocity approaches the speed of light,
u grows enormous.
So, 4-velocity gets hugely big
when the ordinary three-dimensional velocity
gets near the speed of light.
What about the fourth component?
The fourth component, if the velocity is small,
is essentially 1.
The fourth component is just the number 1
in the limit that the velocity is small.
When the velocity gets big,
or gets up near the speed of light,
then u-naught also gets big.
Doesn't u-naught mean the units of velocity?
What's that?
Well, don't forget that we set
the speed of light equal to 1.
So,
we've lost that particular fact.
We could multiply it by velocity,
the speed of light,
and give it components of the velocity.
If we wanted it to have units of velocity,
when the speed of light was not equal to 1,
we would multiply it by c.
And that's fine, you can do that if you like.
You just have to remember what you're talking about.
It's more usual to think of
the fourth component of the velocity
as something near 1.
But you can think of it as being near c.
Now, that brings us to the four components of momentum.
Let's talk about particle.
Any object that has a certain rest mass,
we call the rest mass m,
then it has four components.
It's also a four vector.
Momentum is, standard notation for
it is to call it p.
That's true in Newtonian mechanics,
it's true in relativistic mechanics.
Momentum, the symbol is p.
Now, in non-relativistic physics,
it's just m times v.
Mass times velocity.
But that's not a very good four vector.
Mass times ordinary velocity, it's not a four vector.
If we want to make
a four vector out of it,
because we're going to want to write equations
which make sense in every reference frame,
then we want to take it
to be mass times u mu.
That's, of course, mass,
times v mu,
divided by square root of one minus v squared,
over c squared,
but I won't bother writing the c squared now.
So, that's a definition, if you like.
This is the definition of the momentum of an object
of mass m,
moving with velocity u,
moving with four velocity u.
And it has four components.
The first three components are very close
to the ordinary momentum.
When the velocity is small.
The last component is the energy.
I showed you that last time.
It's essentially m c squared
plus one half m v squared.
And I'll come back to that.
We'll come back to that.
But, um,
let's just note that this is the definition
of the four components of velocity,
uh, momentum.
Alright, the law of physics that we're going to study,
I think we may actually get to it tonight.
In fact, I think we might actually be there.
About to start it anyway.
Um...
No, v is not a four vector.
Right.
I did.
It does have four components though,
one of which is just one.
Uh, let's just get rid
of this side of the equation.
Not get ourselves confused.
Alright, what we're gonna do now
is we're gonna take a
bit of a vacation from relativity,
and we're gonna write law of motion,
the ordinary laws of motion,
even before relativity.
Think about it from the point of view pre-Einstein,
and then try to figure out how we would um,
redesign it.
Change it, modify it,
so that it would become a relativistically invariant
law of motion.
It's a law of motion of charged particles
in electric and magnetic fields.
Now I'll tell you right now, the decomposition
into electric and magnetic is not an invariant decomposition.
What in one frame of reference is a magnetic field may become
a combination of electric and magnetic in another frame and vice versa.
So I want to write down first
the pre-Einstein law of motion of a particle,
a charged particle, in an electromagnetic field, and then
we can try to think how do we modify this
in order to make it a legitimate relativistic equation
that will be the same in every reference frame.
As I write it, it will not
be the same in every reference frame,
because it will be based on pre-Einstein physics.
And the fact is that the pre-Einstein law of
motion is not the same in every reference frame.
is one of the things that really led
Einstein to say something's wrong with ordinary kinematics,
with ordinary space, time, and motion.
All right.
Here's our law.
First of all, F equals mA.
Force is mass times acceleration.
Now we haven't even talked about acceleration, but
I think we can guess the
rule for what relativistic acceleration is.
If ordinary acceleration is the
time rate of change of velocity,
then I don't think it would surprise you very
much at this point if I told you that the
four-dimensional acceleration is the proper time
rate of change of the four-dimensional acceleration.
is the proper time rate
of change of the four-dimensional acceleration.
So you can see that the three components
of u are very close to the ordinary velocity.
And tau is very close to
the ordinary time for slowly moving objects.
So for slowly moving objects, the first
three components are very close to the acceleration,
ordinary acceleration.
But we'll come back to this.
For the time rate of change of velocity,
we're going to have to do
something called the four-dimensional velocity vector.
Okay?
So for the time being,
let's just think about ordinary acceleration,
the old-fashioned kind.
F equals mA.
All we need to know in order to write
down Newton's equations for the motion of a particle
is what the force on it is.
The force of an electric
particle, of an electrically charged particle,
the force on an electrically charged particle,
is made up out of the electric field,
which is a three vector,
which we were going to
get ourselves in 4-dimensional acceleration.
Okay?
The force in a magnetic field
on something that's aqueous to F.
That's the cost of an electric poison,
of a back-aremission,
which is a big request even to me
if my students have got an sentence that says
that would be easy to Seung for the next class,
of course,
but really
that's another section of the decentralization cycle.
Okay?
Okay it did work,
it did work.
the relation between electric and magnetic fields. But
for the time being, let's just write down
the force law, and here it is.
This is Lorentz's force law, discovered by
Lorentz sometime around, I don't know, 1895. Of
course, it was always known that it was
proportional to the electric charge. It was known that
this is acceleration. Everything is
an ordinary three-dimensional vector here.
There was charge times electric field. That goes back
to who? Who was the first one who wrote down
charge times electric field? Faraday. Faraday first had
the idea of electric fields. If you put charges
into electric fields, forces are exerted on them.
And then plus, also charge, times the velocity
cross the magnetic field.
Okay, now I have to tell you what the cross
product is. Anybody not know what the cross product is?
In a moment, anyway. This piece of the force
is called velocity independent. There's no velocity
in here. There is a velocity in here.
But remember velocity, what in one frame
of reference a particle may have. Let's suppose
there was no electric field altogether, okay? But
because the particle is moving with a velocity
in a magnetic field, there's a force on
it. That's interesting because in some other frame of
reference, the velocity may be zero. If the velocity is
zero, then there would be no contribution to the force.
Okay?
And then you have the idea of velocity independent.
So, let's just write down velocity independent.
In a moment, anyway.
Okay.
Let's just write down the force on the particle.
Okay?
That's interesting.
Okay.
If the velocity is zero, then there
would be no contribution to the force.
Okay?
to the force from here, but there's a force
on it. We've just seen there's a force on it.
The force on it makes it accelerate. If it
accelerates in one frame, it accelerates in every frame.
Or another way to say it is if it doesn't
accelerate in one frame, it doesn't accelerate in another frame.
And so something's funny here. If
there was only a magnetic field,
if there was only a magnetic field,
then in some other frame of reference
there would have to be an electric field. In a frame
of reference in which the velocity of the particle was zero,
a frame moving with a particle, that
force could only come from the electric field.
So that immediately tells us that electric and
magnetic fields have to mix up with each other
when you do Lorentz transformations. What is
the connection between electric and magnetic fields?
And the connection is that the two of
them together form a new kind of object,
which we have here, and
that's called the Lorentz transformation.
And the connection is that the two of
them together form a new kind of object,
which we have here, and
that's called the Lorentz transformation.
Here's an object which has six components all together.
It's surely not a scalar. It's
got components x, y, and z.
b also has components x, y, and z.
It doesn't have four components.
It has six components all together.
So it's not a four vector. It's something new.
It's got to be something new, and moreover,
These things transform into each other
under various kinds of Lorentz transformations.
That's what we know.
So the next question is, what kind of
other objects are there that we can define besides
scalars and vectors?
And the next class of objects is called tensors.
In order to write down what the electromagnetic
field is, from the point of view of relativity,
we have to understand tensors.
Tensors are the new ingredient.
Well, let me tell you, first of all,
the simplest way to think about a tensor.
I'm going to call tensors T.
Capital T. A scalar is a tensor.
It's called a tensor of zero rank.
It has no indices.
Why does it have no indices?
Because a scalar has no indices.
A scalar doesn't have any components.
So a scalar is the simplest kind of tensor.
A vector, a four vector, a
four vector is also a tensor.
Okay?
But it's a tensor of rank one, which
means it's an object which has only, well, let's
call it A. A mu.
It has only one index.
It has four components, but it has only one index.
That index can run over four different values.
A tensor is a thing which has two indices.
The simplest tensor is to take two vectors.
Let's call them A and B, and B
does not stand for the magnetic field now.
Okay?
Maybe I should call it C. I'll call it B.
All right?
Take another four vector and
put them next to each other.
There's an object.
It's an object which has how many components altogether?
It's got 16 components altogether, right?
Okay?
So it's got 16 components because A
has four components, B has four components.
Mu and nu, each can be anything from
one to four or from zero to three.
And so altogether, there are 16 components.
We could display these 16 components as
a matrix, as a four by four matrix.
In the first place, we would put A zero.
Let's say A1B1.
Then I think it's A1B2, A1B3,
A1B0, and then A2B1, and so forth.
We could display them, all 16 components, just lay them
out on a grid and draw a matrix for them.
That's the simplest form of tensor.
Just take two vectors.
And juxtapose them together.
Take all 16 components.
And those 16 components form an
object which is called a second-rank tensor.
You could take three vectors.
Take a third vector.
Now we would have to
make a cube to represent it.
Let's take a...
First of all, this is a second-rank vector.
Sorry.
This is a second-rank tensor.
Don't worry about why it's called a tensor.
I mean, is it nervous?
It's not nervous.
Actually, it does come from
the word tense, but not the...
It's not nervous.
It just has two indices.
Second-rank tensor.
Of course, we can construct third-rank tensors.
A third-rank tensor would be made out of three vectors.
Mu, nu, sigma, let's say.
Okay?
That would be a third-rank tensor.
How many components does it have?
Four times four is 16.
64 components.
And if we wanted to display them, we
might display them as cells in a cube.
And thus it goes.
We could have fourth-rank tensors, fifth-rank tensors.
Now what is it that characterizes a tensor?
Is it just a product of two vectors?
No.
It's any object which transforms the same
way as a product of two vectors.
So let's ask how a product of two vectors transforms.
The product, all 16 components.
Supposing we know the components of A,
then the components of A
prime, in another frame of reference,
are L mu, nu.
A, nu.
That's the transformation property of A.
It's also the transformation property of B.
B prime, mu.
Let's use a different variable.
Sigma is equal to L sigma tau A tau.
All right?
Remember, it doesn't matter what
you call the summation index.
I call this one nu
and I call this one tau.
But on the left-hand side,
I have an open sigma index,
which means this really does
correspond to some particular component.
And we have a sigma on this side.
All right.
What's the transformation property of A prime mu,
B prime sigma?
That's the primed component, the mu
sigma component of the primed tensor.
Prime means its components in the primed reference frame.
Well, it's very easy.
Just L mu, nu.
L?
A tau mu mu mu mu tau.
Yes.
A nu.
B tau.
All right.
So whatever a tensor is,
it transforms with an object
which has two L's in it.
One for each index.
Here's the mu index.
Here's the sigma index.
Notice that the lower component
of this L goes with A.
The upper component of this L also goes with A.
The lower component tau goes with B.
The upper component sigma also goes with B.
B prime in this case.
Now I can tell you what the
general law of a second-rank tensor transformation is.
The general law is take a
tensor in the primed reference frame,
is given by exactly the
same kind of structure, L mu.
L sigma tau.
T nu tau.
Okay, so here's the rule.
If you know the components of
T in one frame, the unprimed frame,
then you take the L's, the Lorentz transformation matrices,
and you simply apply them.
The nu index transforms into the mu index.
And you simply apply them.
The mu index transforms into the mu index.
By the mu nu matrix.
The sigma, the tau index becomes
the sigma index by L sigma tau.
So you see the pattern.
This pattern repeats itself.
If there's a third-rank tensor,
then there's just one more L,
making it transform just as if
it were the product of three vectors.
This is what is called the tensor.
You can't ask me why that's called a tensor,
and you can't ask me why I wrote it down.
Or you can say, is it useful?
Is it useful to define it?
It is very useful to define it.
But here's its definition.
It's a thing which transforms as
if it were the 16 components
of the product of two vectors.
Now, there are other things.
It doesn't have to be the product of two vectors.
For example, here's something.
Take a mu b sigma.
That's not the same as a sigma b mu.
It's not the same thing.
If, for example, I take the 1, 3 matrix element,
the 1, 3 matrix element
of this will be a1 b3.
The 1, 3 matrix element of this,
or the 1, 3 component of this,
will be a1 b3.
So it's not the same thing.
a mu b sigma and a sigma b mu.
But both of them transform as tensors.
You could add them.
The result is still a tensor,
but it is not an object which
is just the product of two vectors.
You could do other things.
You could take some third vector,
and you could add some third and fourth vector,
and add it.
c mu d sigma.
c mu d sigma is a tensor.
If you add it to some previous tensor,
it is still a tensor.
It still transforms the same way.
So not every tensor is
just a product of two vectors,
but every tensor transforms the same way
as a product of two vectors.
Now, there are two special
kinds of tensors of rank 2.
Rank 2.
The two special kinds
are called antisymmetric and symmetric.
An antisymmetric tensor is one that has the property
t mu nu equals t nu mu.
This is symmetric, sorry.
That's symmetric.
That says that t1 2 equals t2 1.
Symmetric, it doesn't, in this case,
it doesn't matter which order you put the index.
That's called a symmetric tensor of rank 2.
An antisymmetric tensor of rank 2
is one which changes sign when you change,
when you flip it.
In terms of matrices,
they correspond to symmetric and antisymmetric matrices.
So if we take a symmetric tensor,
and we display its all 16 components,
then it will have the property
that it will be symmetric.
The 1 2 element over here
will be the same as the t,
the 2 1 element over here.
The 1 1 element will be whatever it is.
The 2 2 element will be whatever it is.
But then t1 3 will equal t3 1.
t1 3 will be the same.
So the matrix will have a symmetry.
It'll be a symmetric matrix,
which means that the components off the diagonal
will reflect into each other.
That's a symmetric matrix.
But more interesting for us
today and the next time
is going to be the antisymmetric matrix.
What about the antisymmetric matrix?
That has the property,
when you reflect it, it changes sign.
t1 3 is minus t3 1.
What about t1 1?
It's got to be minus t1 1.
t1 1 must be minus t1 1.
Well, if t1 1 is minus t1 1,
then the antisymmetric matrix
must have zeros on the diagonal.
Zeros on the diagonal.
And then off diagonal it has t1 2,
t1 3,
t1 0.
Let's do it nicely.
I'm going to make a nice big matrix.
And I'm going to subdivide it into 4.
And then put its components.
This is an antisymmetric tensor.
Its diagonal elements all have to be 0.
That's because t1 1 must equal minus t1 1.
On the other hand,
t2 has to equal minus t2 1.
So t1 2 up here
and minus t1 2 over here.
This is minus this.
t1 3 minus t1 3.
And finally t1 0 minus t1 0.
What about over here?
Here we have t2 1.
And over here it must be minus t2 1.
Here's t2 0.
This is minus t2 0.
And finally down here, what do we have?
t3 0 minus t3 0.
So it's antisymmetric,
which means that when you reflect it about the diagonal,
it changes sign.
And antisymmetric also means that it changes sign
when you interchange the two indices.
Those are called symmetric and antisymmetric tensors.
How many interesting components
does a symmetric tensor have?
Let's count them.
A symmetric tensor has four diagonal components.
And then how many off-diagonal components?
Let's...
There are of course 16 components altogether.
But the component over here
is not independent of the component over here.
So really the independent components,
the number of numbers that you need to know,
is 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9.
9? No. 10.
Ten independent components determine a symmetric tensor.
Okay?
So what? So nothing.
But how many an antisymmetric tensor?
Well, for an antisymmetric tensor,
there are zeros on the diagonal.
So we can subtract four of them.
Only this, this, this.
This, this, and this.
Zeros on the diagonal.
And the other ones off on
the other half of the matrix here
are determined in terms of these.
How many is that?
Six.
That's the number of components
of the electric and magnetic field.
Okay?
That's the number of components
of electric and magnetic fields.
This is the only object that you can construct.
The antisymmetric tensor is in fact the only object
that has six components and which transforms,
well, you could take six scalars.
Six scalars or a four vector and two scalars,
would also have six components.
But none of those correspond
to the electric and magnetic field.
The electric and magnetic
field form an antisymmetric tensor.
They form an antisymmetric tensor.
And out of that antisymmetric tensor,
we want to understand this equation here
and how it transforms under Lorentz transformation.
Now,
it does transform in a complicated way.
And that means that the electric and magnetic fields
are going to transform into each other.
I'm going to write down, we're going to finish now,
I'm going to write down for next time,
I'm going to write down the precise relationship,
but we're going to derive this.
We're going to derive this,
but I'm going to write down
the precise relationship between the antisymmetric tensor
and the components of the electric and magnetic field.
How do the components of the electric and magnetic field
combine themselves together to make an antisymmetric tensor?
So,
we take our
four by four matrix,
which I'll draw some guidelines so
that I know where the elements are.
The zeros on the diagonal,
the off diagonal,
I don't need to specify both above and below.
Once I specify above,
you can read off what's
below just by changing the sign.
And here I'm going to tell you what they are.
This is one, two, three, zero.
One, two, three, zero.
X, Y, Z, T.
This is the one, two component.
In the one, two component,
we put minus the third
component of the magnetic field, BZ.
Let's see.
Did I?
We put the third component of the magnet.
In the one, two place,
we put the third component of the magnetic field.
In the one, three place,
we put the second component of the magnetic field,
the Y component of the magnetic field.
And you get a whole inventory of that.
What is it?
magnetic field. And guess what goes down here?
Down here goes minus the first component of
the magnetic field. So if we didn't have time,
suppose we didn't have time, we only had one,
two, and three, then the anti-symmetric tensor
would only have three components. And those
three components would be identified with
the three components of the magnetic field.
We're going to discuss this further, but for
the time being, this is the setup for the
way that the magnetic field
enters into an anti-symmetric tensor. Now...
Are those all minuses?
No. Minus, plus, minus. We'll see why.
Are those supposed to be thought
of as coordinates? Like x, y, z?
Yeah. This could be the z component, this
could be the y component, or would be.
This would be the x component. And then
we would write x, y, z, time. Okay?
Is that what you meant?
Yeah.
Yeah. Okay. All right. Now we have
three entries over here, three more entries. Obviously
those three entries must have something to do
with the electric field, and of course they do.
Ex, ey, ez. Do I have the sign right? Yeah. Let's
just put in what goes down here just to fill it out.
We have plus bz here, minus by here, minus ex
here, plus bx here, let's see, minus ey, and minus ez.
So it's now got six independent components,
and it fills out a four by four
component.
So we have a four by four matrix, anti-symmetric four
by four matrix, with electric fields in the time slot here,
and magnetic fields in the space-space slots.
The space-space components are magnetic fields,
the space-time components are electric fields.
Now why is this? How did I
know this? How did anybody know it?
We'll come to that next time.
They know it by fiddling around
trying to find a sensible
relativistic generalization of this formula here.
So the next time we'll work that out. We'll work out
f equals ma for a particle in an electric and magnetic field
except in relativistic notation.
Incidentally, this four by four matrix here is not
usually called t mu nu, it's called f mu nu.
I don't know the history of
what f, why f is called f.
But I suspect it's faraday.
I suspect f stood for the faraday tensor.
And it's anti-symmetric, and it's composed
of the magnetic and electric fields.
So each of those elements is
the strength of the field, the xy?
It's the components of the field.
The components of the field.
Yeah.
So, here, let's just concentrate on
the magnetic part of it here.
Let's put a little fence around the time
stuff and get rid of it for a moment.
This now just constitutes
a three-dimensional tensor, anti-symmetric tensor.
And let's write down the equation.
This equation says that f is
equal to minus bz, or minus b3.
Three is z.
Next, f is equal to plus by.
And finally, f is equal to minus bz.
And finally, f, what's the last one down here?
The last one is 2, 3.
f2, 3 is equal to bx.
In fact, 3, this is 3.
Minus b8.
Yes, minus.
Minus b1, b2.
Okay, now I can write this in a nicer form.
in a nicer form where you'll see the pattern.
Let's write this one not as f
, but rather as minus f .
If I write this as minus f , then I
have that f is b2, and f is minus b1.
What do I see in that
form that I like about it?
Let me show you how it works.
Let's start with the equation f equals minus b3.
And let's cycle from 1 to
2 to 3 in each spot.
In each spot, the next equation, you go
1 to 2, 2 to 3, 3 to 1.
Make a clock, a clock
that goes around in a circle.
And let's proceed.
Clockwise.
The next equation down, everything would cycle forward.
So what would happen to the 1?
Become 2.
What would happen to the 2?
What would happen to the 3?
Minus b1.
What's the next one?
1, 2, the next one would be 3.
f , 2, 3, 1 equals minus 3, 1, 2.
Well, with any luck at all, that
would be exactly what we wrote here.
Let's see, f is minus b3.
f is minus b2.
Don't worry about whether they're upstairs or downstairs.
Forget that.
f is minus b1.
So this has a very nice structure to it.
The 1, 2 component of the tensor
is the third component of the magnetic field.
The 2, 3 component of the tensor
is the 1 component, and it cycles.
So you can always remember, all you
have to remember is one of them,
and the others will follow just by cycling
the numbers from 1 to 2 to 3.
Now, the electric field is different.
The electric fields,
e1 is equal to f10.
e2 is f20, and e3 is f30.
So the electric fields are vectors where
you just ignore the time component here.
And you see what the index structure is.
e1 is f10, e2 is f20, e3 is f30.
The magnetic field, a little more complicated.
There's something you might notice.
The magnetic field seems to have two identities.
It has an identity as an
anti-symmetric tensor whose components are called f,
and it has another identity as
a kind of vector, ordinary three-dimensional vectors.
When I speak of vectors
now, I'm speaking of three-dimensional vectors.
It has an identity as an anti-symmetric tensor,
in three dimensions,
minus b, b, b, minus sign here.
And it has a second identity as a vector.
That connection between anti-symmetric tensors and
vectors is only true in three dimensions.
It is not something which is true in other dimensions.
It's just an accident.
Well, it's not exactly an accident,
but think of it as roughly accidental.
That if you take a 3 by 3 anti-symmetric matrix,
it happens to have three independent components.
Those three independent components also happen
to form an ordinary three-dimensional vector.
But if you have a 4 by 4 matrix, anti-symmetric,
it cannot be identified with a 4 vector.
So, we see that the magnetic
field sort of has two identities.
In one identity, it has two indices,
and in the other identity, it has only one index.
So, we're going to build, next time,
out of this anti-symmetric tensor,
and four velocities and four accelerations,
four-dimensional accelerations,
we're going to build an equation
which we'll recognize as having transformation properties
that make certain that it's
the same in every reference frame.
That's our goal, to rewrite this
so that it's the same in every reference frame.
We'll have to modify it a bit.
This is not quite right as it is.
And when we modify it,
it will form an equation
which is the same in every reference frame.
Yeah?
So, was Einstein looking for this,
the Lorentz invariant formulation of work from minuses
on conceptual grounds, or did he have any other questions?
Was he doing that just on conceptual grounds?
Yeah.
He had a suspicion that the laws of nature
ought to be the same in every reference frame.
This was a matter of intuition to him,
or a matter of conviction.
It, of course, also had
a good deal of experimental support,
the fact that the speed of light was the same
in every reference frame, as far as we measured,
that nobody could detect using light
the motion of the Earth through space.
But I don't even know if that's true.
I don't even think he knew that.
I don't know if he knew it.
He said he didn't know it.
I don't know if he knew it or not.
But he himself, according to his own description,
was more influenced by the principle of relativity,
and he could not make these equations
be the same in every reference frame,
not without doing something to mix E and B up,
and even that wasn't enough.
He had to mix up the components of the velocity.
Eventually, he had to figure out special relativity.
He did not actually write
his equations in four-vector notation.
He just put in all the various extra gammas
and functions of velocity,
but what he was doing was basically making sure
that the equations were the same in every reference frame
by making them into four-vector equations.
It was Minkowski who really
put together the four-vector idea,
and rewrote the equations in a four-vector notation.
But Einstein was more or less clumsily, somewhat clumsy,
clumsily going about writing these equations
in a way that they would
go from one frame to the next
by some systematic transformation properties,
and they would always be
the same in all reference frames.
So, yeah, it was essentially
a conceptual guess on his part
that Maxwell's equations, together
with the Lorentz force law,
should be the same in every reference frame.
So you get to learn tensors for general relativity.
Did you feel silly about special relativity then?
No.
Probably not.
At first, I don't know a hell
of a lot about the history of it.
And, you know, history is always
in the eye of the beholder,
and what people say is not always exactly what happened,
so I don't really know.
But...
I think according to his own writings,
he at first did not like Minkowski's ideas.
He didn't like the idea
of four-dimensional geometry at first.
It didn't take him long to catch on,
but at first he simply wrote everything out
in sort of clumsy, brutal form,
and had a hard time adjusting to the Nieder notation.
That's what he said anyway.
Did Minkowski come up with this idea?
I think it was two years.
I think it was 1907, if I remember.
Yeah.
Things move slower at that time than they do now.
That's pretty fast.
That's pretty fast, yeah.
Yeah.
Well, I think if it was
today, it would have happened much faster.
Has Minkowski been a mathematician or a physicist?
Well, I'm not sure that
people necessarily distinguished at that time.
And I don't know that he contributed
much to the theory of the universe.
I don't think he contributed much else to physics.
Not that this wasn't enough.
I mean, this was a huge amount to contribute.
But I don't know what else he did.
There was no long history of famous papers by Minkowski.
This was essentially his...
...high point.
That's not correct.
I don't know.
Was he affected by Lorentz?
Don't know.
I think probably yes.
Was he affected by Fitzgerald?
Who knows?
I don't know.
The one thing I know is you don't
trust people when they give answers to those questions.
They don't remember.
So do you know if the tensor transformation of
E and B was in his first paper in 1907?
No.
It was in Einstein's paper in 1905.
Yeah.
But he just had it written out by hand.
When Maxwell wrote his equations, he wrote
every single equation, the X component, the
Y component, the Z component.
How many of them are there altogether?
Let's see.
The dot, there's one equation
for E dot, that's three equations.
Six equations.
Seven...
Eight equations?
I think eight equations altogether.
No, no, no, no.
There's more than that.
But...
Sorry.
The vectorization is today.
I don't know.
So this was three, six, eight equations, and
I think he wrote down all the x component
of this, the x component of
this, one, two, three, four, five, six.
Yeah, he wrote down all eight equations and
never put them together into some nice symbolic
form.
Well, Einstein was doing essentially
exactly the same thing in space-time.
He was just writing everything out and
sort of doing it by trial and error.
You get the feeling when you read the paper
that he did it by trial and error rather than
anything as systematic as four vectors.
It was Minkowski who understood the four vector idea.
So it was a hit and miss
for Einstein with some good intuition about the...
Yeah.
Next time we'll come back and we will
work out the Lorentz force law as modified by
Einstein and Minkowski.
The preceding program is copyrighted by Stanford University.
Please visit us at stanford.edu.
Thank you.