This program is brought to you by Stanford University.
Please visit us at stanford.edu.
Last time we had started to
discuss charged particles moving in electric and
magnetic fields and how relativity impacts
the laws of charged particles in
electric and magnetic fields. How the
Lorenz force law, which is basically the
law of how electric and magnetic
fields influence charged particles, how that law
and if that law is really
consistent with the principles of relativity.
Are the rules the same in every
reference frame? And what are those rules?
How do we have to modify the non-relativistic laws of
relativity?
of motion in order to make
them the same in every reference frame
and we do have to modify
them, there's no question of that
F equals m a
makes good sense
in a world where acceleration
is an invariant
and in Galileo's world or Newton's world
everybody would agree about the acceleration of an object
everybody would agree about the force on an object
everybody would agree about the mass
and so F equals m a was an
invariant equation that all observers would agree on
but there are kinematic changes, what we mean by
velocity, what we mean by acceleration and so forth
and so it's not surprising
that the Newtonian laws of
motion will have to be modified
now in particular
we're going to have to understand the concept of force
and where forces, well not so
much where forces come from but
uh...
but the deeper concept of force
there are many different kinds of forces in nature
and they tend to have different extensions
from non-relativistic to relativistic physics, for example
the laws of motion of charged particles
look off in, if you ignore completely
magnetic effects, magnetic effects incidentally
are themselves relativistic effects
if the speed of light were infinite
there would be no magnetic force on charged particles
that's because the force on charged
particles is proportional to the velocity
and whenever you see a velocity
you'll always know
really it's a velocity divided by the speed of light
uh... there would be no magnetic forces
if the speed of light were infinite
there would only be electric forces
and the force laws
F equals m a together with uh...
the newton law of force, the newton law
of force looks suspiciously like the coulomb law
instead of products of charges we have products of masses
they're both inverse square laws
the laws of motion for gravitation and for uh... electricity
electric uh... forces look very very similar
you might expect
that perhaps the generalization to the special
theory of relativity would also look very
similar
and you'd be wrong
they're very very different
in fact as i'm sure
you know the laws of gravitation
don't naturally lend themselves to a extension
in the special theory of relativity
it was necessary to go
on to a more thorough uh...
modification of space time for
gravitation
but not so for electrical forces
so today we're going to go through the basic
uh... laws of electrical forces
and the equations of motion
let me just write down what they are
what uh... as uh... lorenz would have written them down
just before
a few years before the discovery
of the special theory of relativity
he of course would have used newton's forces
and he would have said mass times acceleration
this is when he wasn't thinking
so hard about the speed of light
when he was trying to
be fairly conventional about electrical forces
and he was trying to be
fairly conventional about the speed of light
and he was trying to
be fairly conventional about electrical forces
without about the electrodynamics
what he said of course
was force equals mass times acceleration
by acceleration he meant exactly what
newton meant by acceleration
the time derivative of velocity by
the velocity he meant the time derivative
of the position
let's uh... let's work on the left-hand
side of this equation just for a moment
mass uh... mass
acceleration is the time derivative of the
velocity. So let's write time derivative of
velocity. Both are vectors, ordinary three-dimensional
vectors. I won't bother indicating that. They're
both three-dimensional vectors. And the mass of
every object is time independent. The mass
is simply a parameter that's identified with an
object once and for all. It doesn't change
with time. In relativity theory, the mass
doesn't change with time because by definition
it's the mass when the object is at
rest. In Newtonian physics, it's a deeper principle
in Newtonian physics that mass doesn't change.
But in any case, mass doesn't change with
time. And so you can bring it inside the
derivative, and you can write the right-hand side here
as the time derivative of the mass times the velocity.
And the mass times velocity is known as momentum.
Always carries the symbol p. It's also a vector.
And so we always write the right-hand side
here as the time rate of change. I'll put
a little vector symbol on it now, dp by
dt. And that's equal to force. That's a fairly
general definition of force.
It actually transcends a little bit simple
Newtonian physics. As we'll see, there's a
version of it in general relativity. Sorry,
in special relativity, even in general relativity,
that the time rate of change is the
force. But there's a slight difference in the definition
or the connection between momentum and velocity
in the special theory of relativity and in
Newtonian physics.
I'll just remind you, in both cases, the momentum is
mass times velocity, but in the special theory of relativity,
it's not ordinary velocity, but the time rate of
change of position with respect to proper time, proper velocity.
We'll come back to that. We'll come back to that. That's
the left-hand side. Actually, it's the right-hand side of this equation.
But now I'm going to put another right-hand side to the
right of this. I'm going to write down the Lorentz force law.
So we're going to work. Here's your homework. Your homework is
to put all the speeds of light back into the equations
by doing dimensional analysis. We are
going to set c equal to one.
The non-relativistic limit, in this case, will not be the
limit in which c goes to infinity. c is just one.
It's the limit in which
the velocity gets very, very small.
So you want to think about what
non-relativistic physics means. It means very small velocity.
All right. What's the right-hand side here? Well, according to
Lorentz, the right-hand side is proportional to the electric charge.
Now, we're talking about electric and magnetic forces.
Proportional to the electric charge, which
I'll call q of an object.
And then there's one term, which is electric field.
The electric field is a vector. In general,
it depends on position as well as time.
It has a set of components. The
components are three-dimensional components, x, y, and z.
And then Lorentz discovered another term.
It was actually implicit in Maxwell's work.
It was implicit in Faraday's work.
But Lorentz really spelled it out.
And it's the velocity. . .
The velocity, the ordinary velocity, cross-product, and I'm going
to explain that in a minute, cross-product with the momentum.
Oh, sorry. Not momentum. B. Thank
you. B. Cross-product with the magnetic field.
The magnetic field also being an object
with components. It's also a vector in space.
Very much like the electric field, but
it influences objects in a different way.
Of also position and time.
fields are time dependent and position
dependent. Now the magnetic field I've
written, I've told you that it's a vector.
First of all I haven't told you what
cross product means. So let's, and most
of course most of you know what cross
product is, but I want to think about
it in a slightly different way than the
usual concept of cross product. The
cross product of two vectors you normally
think of as another vector, and that
other vector is perpendicular to both, to
the vectors which are being multiplied
and proportional to the product of their
magnitudes times the sine of the angle
between them. That's not the way I'm
going to think about the cross product.
I'm going to use a definition of the
cross product in which the cross product
is really a tensor. It's an anti-symmetric
tensor that you make up out of two
vectors. Now it's very easy to make up a
tensor out of two vectors if I have
two vectors a and b, and right now
b is not the magnetic field. I just need
two letters, so I'm going to call them a
and b. If we have two vectors,
I guess I should indicate that they are
three-dimensional vectors by a
little arrow over them, ordinary
three-dimensional vectors. There's a notion
of cross product which itself is
another vector which I can call c.
There's another concept, as I said, of
cross product which makes it
an anti-symmetric tensor. Here's the idea.
You take any two vectors and you can
make a tensor out of it. A tensor is
simply an object with two indices
instead of one. Now I'm thinking now
about three-dimensional space. So a vector
has three components. A tensor in
this case has nine components, three times
three. It's a matrix built up out
of the components of the vector.
So if the vector a has
three components, incidentally I will freely
interchange between 1, 2, and 3
and x, y, and z. So x is 1, y is
2, z is 3. A has three components, b has three
components. The cross product also has three
components, but as we'll see in a
moment, that leaves a little bit of
an ambiguity. There are two objects in
three dimensions which have three
components. One of them, or three
independent components, is a vector. And the other
is a vector. And the other is a
independent component. One of them is
a vector and the other is an
anti-symmetric tensor. So given two vectors,
we can always make a tensor. For
example, we can make the tensor a, m. m and
n, remember mu and nu, go from 0 to 3,
time and space. That's the notation I
will use, I've been using. Things from the
rear end of the Greek
alphabet represents space-time indices. M's and
N's, Latin letters, just go from
1 to 3. Ordinary space, ordinary spatial
indices. Alright, so if you like, a 4
vector has an index M, 1, 2, and 3,
and also a fourth index 0. Okay, so AM, we're
working now strictly in three
dimensions, trying to get three-dimensional space
and ordinary vectors right. AM, we can take
AM times BN. That is a matrix whose
components, if we wanted to work out
the components, the 1, 1 component would be
A1B1. The 1, 2 component over here
would be A1B2, and then A1B3. I won't
write them all out, but here would be A2B1,
A2B2,
A2B1,
B2,
and so forth. Nine components altogether,
nine independent components. Now, as it stands,
this is not an anti-symmetric tensor. It's
got no particular symmetry. There's no particular
symmetry. A2B1 is not, there's no particular reason
why A2B1 should be the same as A1B2.
They're two quite different things. But,
if we subtract
ANBM,
in other words, we consider the
tensor made by interchanging A and B.
AM, BN, and ANBM.
If we subtract them, then that
gets rid of all the diagonal elements,
A1B1 minus A1B1,
and it's anti-symmetric because,
it'll contain things like A1B2 minus A2B1.
In the 1, 2 element,
you can see that it's anti-symmetric.
If you interchange N and M,
if you interchange rows and columns,
the two terms will interchange, and so,
what we'll get
is an anti-symmetric tensor.
The anti-symmetric tensor has zeros off the diagonal,
and then,
we'll get,
a 1B2.
It has, for example, in place over here, not A1B2,
but A1B2 minus A2B1.
Let's make it a little bigger.
A1B2 minus A2B1.
And then, A1B3 minus A3B1.
Zero.
We'll come back to that over there.
Then,
down,
down here, let's see, that's
A1, what do we have here?
A2B3 minus A3B2.
And then, zero.
The diagonal elements are zero.
There's off-diagonal elements here.
And what about the elements below the diagonal?
The elements below the diagonal,
are, the same.
Same as the elements above the diagonal,
except opposite in sign.
So over here,
you'll have A2B1 minus A1B2,
which is simply the negative of its reflection
about the diagonal.
That means there are three,
and only three, independent components
of this anti-symmetric tensor.
Well, you can always put three components,
and you can line them up, and
call them the components of a vector.
That doesn't mean that they transform properly as a vector.
But, these three objects do transform properly as a vector,
if we make the right identifications.
In particular,
those who know what a cross product is,
will already see the pattern that these are the
components of the cross product of a cross product.
So, we have a cross product, and we have
a cross product, and we have a cross product.
So, we have a cross product,
and we have a cross product.
But in particular, I'll tell you which components they are.
They are the components
A1B2, that's C3.
Let's write it over here.
No, let's do it over here.
C3.
This one is C3.
One, two, three.
What about this one?
What would you put here?
Temporarily, let's put C2 there.
Okay.
And this one, of course, would be C1.
In other words, these three objects
can be placed in one-to-one correspondence
with the components of this anti-symmetric tensor here.
The anti-symmetric tensor is one form of the cross product,
which in fact generalizes to other dimensions.
In other dimensions, an anti-symmetric tensor
will not have the same
number of components as a vector.
So this is special to three dimensions.
In higher dimensions, there's no such thing
as the cross product of two vectors giving another vector.
But there always is the
cross product giving an anti-symmetric tensor.
So the generalization of the
cross product to other dimensions
is the anti-symmetric tensor.
For three dimensions, it's fine to
think of it as a vector.
Now, it's actually C2 here.
Let's...
Let's write it out here.
C3 is equal to A1B2 minus A2B1.
Now, if we start cycling this equation,
the trick is always to cycle through it,
one to two, two to
three, and three back to one.
C3, the next one, what comes after three?
One.
C1 equals A2B3.
Minus A3B2.
And one, two, one, sorry, three,
the next one is two, of course.
There's only one left.
All right, and this is
one, two, this will be A3,
two, three, B1, minus two, three, A1B3, I think, right?
Okay, now let's check.
All right, what do we have?
We have over here A1B2 minus A2B2.
That's C3, I got that one right.
Okay.
C1 down here, that's A2B3 minus A3B2.
But C2, my temporary, my temporary identification,
C2 as A1B3, that's wrong.
It's minus C2.
Okay, you can see there that
C2 is not A1B3 minus A3B1.
Okay?
It's minus C2.
So, in fact, what goes here is minus C2.
So the components of a vector
can always be displayed as an
anti-symmetric tensor, or the
anti-symmetric tensor can always be
displayed as a vector.
Now, what's going on here?
What's the geometry of this?
An anti-symmetric tensor has two indices.
Every component of it is associated with two axes.
An x-axis and a y-axis.
Okay.
Well, the xy-axis, the xy component
of the anti-symmetric tensor is simply
identified with the z component of the vector.
It's clear that it's ambiguous.
Do you describe a vector by
describing the plane that it's perpendicular to,
in which case you're describing it
by a pair of vectors, namely the,
the pair of vectors that defines a
plane, or do you describe it by the
arrow that's sticking out of the plane?
The two ways of describing the vector,
one, by just an arrow sticking out,
is describing it by its vector components.
The other way of describing it is
in terms of the planes that are
perpendicular to those vector components,
and that's the description in
terms of the anti-symmetric tensor.
Now, the difficult thing, it's not
very difficult, it's rather easy, but
it's not very difficult.
The first thing that I want to do
is to prove that the components of the
anti-symmetric tensor transform under rotations
according to the same rule
as the transformation properties of a vector, and they do.
They do.
So these are two different aspects,
or two different ways of thinking about
the three components of a
vector in three, in three dimensions.
The cross product, and for many
reasons, or for many purposes, it's smarter
to think about the cross product as
a tensor rather than a vector, but then
again, in visualizing it and trying to get
a picture of it in your head, you
might want to flip back and
forth between vector and anti-symmetric tensor.
Okay, that's the idea of a cross product.
Now, let me do one more little exercise for you.
Yeah, no, not an exercise yet.
Let's come to the magnetic field.
Now, the magnetic field is a vector,
but it is also an anti-symmetric tensor.
0, b12, b13, b21, which is minus
b12, of course, 0, I won't bother writing
the things below the diagonal here.
It just gets us confused.
0, and then b23 over here.
The other ones are simply minus these.
For reasons that are historical,
the components of the anti-symmetric tensor
are related to the vector
components by an extra minus sign.
This is not a cross product,
but it is just a definition.
This is equal to 0, 0, 0.
Instead of b12 being b3, it's minus b3.
Then plus b2 over here and minus b1 over here.
It's just a semi-historical glitch.
There's actually some better reason for it.
But, of course, if a thing is
a vector, so is the minus of it.
And so the connection between the anti-symmetric
tensor and the vector that describes it
is, of course, ambiguous.
Though I described this plane here as
that vector or that vector, there's an ambiguity.
Once I fix that vector, we
usually fix it with a right-hand rule.
a cross b, c by making right-handed coordinates.
But there was always an ambiguity whether
we identify the tensor with the vector components
or with minus the vector components.
And for the magnetic field, as I
said, just as a matter of history,
they were identified with minus
the components of the tensor.
In other words,
they were identified with minus
the components of the tensor.
So that's the magnetic field.
It can be represented either as
a vector or an anti-symmetric tensor.
What I want to show
you is an interesting little theorem.
The force on a charged particle is v cross b.
Now, we can write v cross b.
We can write the components of the cross product,
v cross b,
either by thinking of b
as a vector or a tensor.
Let me show you what happens in the two cases.
Let's work out the components of v cross b.
I'm only going to work
out the x component of it.
What's the x component of v cross...
Let's take the z component.
Let's take the third component of v cross b.
The third component of v cross b
is, by the definition of the cross product,
where is it?
The definition of the cross product, the third component,
is v1 b2 minus v2 b1.
That's the third component.
We could write down the others just by cycling through.
I'm not going to cycle through.
But now, let's use that identification up at
the top of the blackboard to rewrite this.
Notice what b2 is.
It's also b1 3.
So this is also v1 b1 3.
What about...
Now there's minus v2.
And what is b1?
v1 is minus b2 3.
Minus b2 3, so that'll change a sign here,
and it'll multiply it by b2 3.
So the component of v
cross b in the third direction
is v1 b1 3 plus v2 b2 3.
And I'm going to add in another term.
v3 b3 3.
Why am I allowed to add that in?
Because b3 3 is 0.
b3 3 is 0.
It's a diagonal term here.
And now we have another way of expressing,
a very pretty nice way of expressing,
the component,
the components of v cross b.
Alright, we can cycle through it as I said,
but we can also write it in the following way.
v cross b,
the mth component of it,
m is 1, 2, or 3,
notice the 3 here
goes with the second component of b.
In each case here,
look at the structure of it,
in each term you have
the third component of the vector
being identified with the last component of b.
Alright, so that suggests that we should write down here
something b, something m.
We should write a velocity,
but notice that the velocity components
match with the first component of b.
The velocity component matches with
the first component of b,
and so that suggests that the answer is
nm vn.
Now, this means summed over n.
So this means v1 b1m
plus v2 b2m plus v3 b3m.
Repeated indices get summed over.
That's kind of a nice easy
way to write v cross b.
That's what it is.
That's another way of writing
the Lorentz force law here.
If I write it out in terms of components,
then at least let's concentrate
on the magnetic piece of it.
The mth component of the force
evidently then is
electric charge
vn bnm.
Okay.
Keep that in mind.
Let me show you another little mathematical fact
about particles moving in magnetic fields.
Let's forget the electric field.
No electric field for the moment.
Just pure magnetic field.
Then there's a fact about particles moving in magnetic field
that their speed doesn't change.
Speed is the magnitude of the velocity.
Magnitude of velocity doesn't change
in a magnetic field.
That's because the force is perpendicular to the velocity.
Let's see if we can prove that.
Let's see if we can prove that the velocity,
not the velocity,
the speed.
Velocity means direction and magnitude,
but that the magnitude of the velocity doesn't change.
In fact, as a consequence of that...
If the field varies in time...
Oh, if the field varies in
time, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes.
A static magnetic field.
Yes, that's correct.
Yeah.
The m subscript on f over there
corresponds to the m subscript on e, right?
But you also want a second subscript to denote
it's only the magnetic component?
We're talking about this?
Yeah.
Everything is three-dimensional.
There's no electric component in here now,
but I've set the electric field equal to zero.
Yeah.
I've set the electric field equal to zero.
If there's a time-dependent magnetic field,
the reason that the velocity, the speed changes
is because the time-dependent magnetic field
makes an electric field.
But let's just concentrate on a time-dependent
simplest situation,
time-independent magnetic field.
We'll see.
I don't know.
As we go along, we'll
find out if it was important
that it was time-independent.
All right.
So among other things,
that means that the kinetic energy of the particle
doesn't change if it's only in a static magnetic field.
That means that the square of the velocity,
we can write that as vmvm.
The square of the velocity,
this is v1 squared plus v2 squared plus v3 squared,
or better yet, vx squared
plus vy squared plus vz squared.
This is the square of the magnitude of the velocity.
And I'm interested in finding out
whether that changes with time.
So what I want to do,
I want to differentiate it with respect to time.
Remember that I sum over repeated index.
All right. Well, what is this?
This is just twice
the time derivative of v,
vm,
times vm.
This is vm squared.
The time derivative is twice v,
is twice v times the time derivative of v.
All right.
Which is
twice the acceleration.
Twice the acceleration
dotted with the velocity.
Now let's write the fact that the acceleration,
we know what the acceleration is.
The acceleration is just the force divided by the mass.
Let's see, what do we want to do?
Um,
yeah.
We want to substitute for the acceleration.
I want to substitute, um,
the force divided by the mass.
But in particular,
I don't care about the numerical coefficients.
This is going to be proportional to
twice,
now,
velocity
cross b,
the mth component,
times vm.
The acceleration in a magnetic
field is proportional to the velocity
cross the magnetic field,
the mth component of it,
times vm.
But now let's use the formula that we have.
Where is it?
Uh, the formula that we have for v cross b,
did I erase that?
Darn it, I erased it.
Uh,
twice b,
what is it?
b n,
m,
anybody have it written down?
v cross b, the mth component of it.
What is it?
Isn't it, uh, v n b n m?
v n,
b n m, right?
Right, that's v cross b in the m direction,
but now, let's multiply it by vm.
So what do we have?
We have the components of the tensor b
bracketed by the components of
the vector v on both sides.
Now the trick is to realize
that any expression like this is
always zero if b is anti-symmetric.
For example, there's going to
be a term which will be,
well, let's see what terms there are.
There could be a term with
v1 over here and v1 over here.
That will have to multiply b11.
That's zero.
Let's try another term.
There'll be a term v1
over here and v2 over here.
That will multiply b12.
But then there will be a partner,
a twin term that goes with it,
in which this is 2,
in which n is 2 and m is 1.
So that will be plus v2 b21 v1.
And now we use the fact
that b21 and b21 are the same.
So that's b11.
And b12 are opposite in sign,
equal and opposite.
And this is also zero.
So if we take an anti-symmetric tensor
and we multiply it from both sides
on both of its indices by the same vector,
we always get zero.
The consequence is that we've
proved that for a magnetic field,
that d by dt
of the square of the velocity is equal to zero.
In other words,
that the square of the velocity is constant in time.
Anybody want me to go over that again?
Alright, I'll just go over it very briefly again.
The MVM, we differentiated it and we got it
proportional to the product of the acceleration times the velocity.
Then I used for the acceleration the Lorentz force law,
the magnetic piece of it.
Of course, this would not be
true, incidentally, if there was electric field.
Only because if there's only magnetic field,
then the acceleration is proportional to v cross b.
I then used that v cross
b was vnm, vn, bnm, vm.
And then immediately from that it follows.
Immediately the symmetry of vnm is,
combines together with the anti-symmetry of bnm
to give zero.
Now why do I do it this way?
I could use elementary theorems
about cross products and so forth.
I do it this way because we
want to generalize it to four dimensions,
where the simple theorems don't generalize.
Okay.
So now we know some things.
Oh, incidentally,
we have a very interesting problem.
Well, it's just true that of course
that an electric field will violate this.
If a particle is at rest and starts at rest,
the electric field will start to accelerate it.
And of course the velocity will not remain,
the speed won't remain constant.
It's only because the velocity appears in here
in a particular special way that it has this property
that it doesn't change the magnitude of the velocity.
I don't think in any place here that I used
the fact that the magnetic field was constant in time.
I don't think I did.
What is true is a time-dependent
magnetic field will create an electric field,
and the electric field will do some work.
All right, now it's more or
less obvious that the electric field
and the magnetic field will
get mixed up with each other
when you go from frame to frame,
which are moving with relative velocity.
It's fairly easy to see.
This is under the assumption that the laws of physics
are the same in every reference frame.
It's more or less obvious that if you
have a pure magnetic field in one frame,
then in other frames you
will also have an electric field.
In other words, if there's a
pure magnetic field along some axis,
and you're moving in some direction,
depending on the direction you're moving in,
you will see also an electric field.
The way to see that...
Let's take a case.
Let's suppose there's a magnetic field in the up direction
that I have a particle...
Let's see.
Let's...
I have a particle which is moving with velocity v.
We'll call this the y direction, the x direction,
and this is the third direction, the z direction.
One, two, and three.
We have a magnetic field in the y direction.
We have a particle moving along the x direction.
And of course in that case we
will have a force along the z axis.
v cross b will be along the z axis,
and there will be a force
on that particle along the z axis.
Now, let's imagine slow velocities.
Newtonian physics.
We're not interested in relativity yet.
Everything is moving very slowly by
comparison with the speed of light.
Acceleration in Newtonian kinematics is invariant.
So if one observer sees an acceleration,
a second observer will also see an acceleration,
and the acceleration will be identical,
as long as we're talking about observers
who are moving slowly relative to each other.
Alright, now I haven't introduced a second observer yet.
I've only introduced the fact that my
particle is moving along with velocity v.
But now I'm going to introduce a second observer.
The second observer also happens to
be moving along with velocity v,
and therefore sees the particle at rest.
For that observer, the particle has no velocity,
but because acceleration is an
invariant under usual Newtonian physics,
that observer must also see
an acceleration for this particle.
There's no velocity, therefore the
b field cannot create any acceleration.
Momentarily, momentarily at that instant of time,
the acceleration is zero.
It's zero in one frame, it's zero in every frame.
So, as I move along with the particle,
I have to blame the acceleration on something else.
It cannot be blamed on the cross
product of the velocity and the magnetic field.
In fact, we know there's
a force along the z axis.
There's only one place that that could be coming from,
assuming that the Lorentz force law
is the same in every reference frame.
If it's not coming from v cross b,
because in my new frame v is zero,
it must be coming from an electric field,
and so there must be an
electric field sticking out of the blackboard
in the frame of reference moving with the particle,
in this particular case.
So, in the original frame of
reference, I started with no electric field,
but a particle moving with velocity v.
In the second frame of reference,
I have a particle at rest,
I must have an electric
field sticking out of the blackboard.
So the consequence is,
that electric and magnetic fields
must mix up with each other
under velocity transformations.
But, in order to get
the equations really relativistically correct,
we're going to have to work with four vectors.
So, let's remind ourselves about four vectors,
and how the electric and magnetic
fields fit into four vector notation,
and then see if we can
derive a set of equations of motion,
which will be the same in every reference frame.
And as I said,
we will have to mix up electric and magnetic fields,
they will have to transform,
we'll work out some of their transformation properties,
I mean, here we did a little bit of it,
but we'll work it out mathematically,
and see, for example, that this really does happen.
Okay, we have two fields, electric and magnetic,
that's six components all together,
a second object which has six components,
in fact, the only object which has,
I say this all the time,
the only object in four
dimensional space which has six components,
is an anti-symmetric tensor.
Now it's simply false.
You could have six scalars,
you could have a vector and two scalars,
I think that's all,
a vector and two scalars,
six scalars,
but neither of those are interesting.
The other object which has six independent components
is the anti-symmetric tensor.
So it's natural,
it's natural, since electric and magnetic fields
will transform into each other,
to guess that they fill out an anti-symmetric tensor
in four dimensions.
So let's,
here's the matrix associated with it,
let's,
just to guide my eye,
I'm going to divide it into four by four.
And now, my notation,
my notation seems to differ from a lot of books.
My notation is always
zero, one, two, three.
No, one, two, three, zero.
That's because I'm not sure,
that's because I,
in my youth I used to call zero four.
Now it's called zero.
Well, I'm not that old that,
but one, two, three, zero.
So, one, two, three, zero.
One, two, three, zero.
Let's fill it in with electric and magnetic fields.
And some of this, of course, is convention.
Some of this is rather arbitrary convention.
What the invariant fact is,
is that there's an anti-symmetric tensor
that describes all of this.
Exactly how we fill in the components
is a little bit arbitrary, not very, but
we fill in the one, two, three,
the three by three matrix, exactly as we did
with the magnetic field before.
Zero, zero, zero.
Minus b, z, or b three.
I think this is plus b two,
minus b one.
So this part of it, let me block it out.
The three by three part of it, one, two, three,
is exactly just the magnetic field tensor.
On the off-diagonal places over here,
we have the electric field.
We have room for the components of an electric field.
I think it's e one, e two, e three.
The three components of the electric field.
And of course, in the lower spots here,
we simply reverse the sign.
Plus b three, for example,
down here we would have minus e three,
et cetera.
Anti-symmetric tensor, six independent components,
constituting the electromagnetic field tensor.
When do you use superscripts?
Oh, as long as I'm only
interested in components one, two, and three.
As long as I'm labeling
things with one, two, and three,
it doesn't matter if they're all the same.
I'm just going to go with the upper or lower.
Here I simply mean, you're right,
I switch notation up and down.
Pay no attention to it.
Let's see, what would be consistent?
I guess it would be consistent
to leave them as upper components.
But it doesn't matter.
It's the three components of the electric field
and the three components of the magnetic field
exactly as Maxwell and Faraday would have defined them.
That's what goes into those places there.
So we needn't pay much attention
to where the indices are.
This is the object made up
out of exactly the same fields
that Maxwell and Faraday would have defined.
And this whole object is called F mu nu.
It's an anti-symmetric four by four tensor.
Mu and nu run from zero to four to three,
or three to zero.
And it is a four by four tensor.
It's called F.
I'm not sure why it's called F.
I think maybe for Faraday, but I'm not sure.
I don't think it was called F until...
maybe Minkowski, I'm not sure.
Einstein did not have that notation.
He actually didn't think about four by four tensors.
What he simply worked out in detail
was the transformation properties
of the electric and magnetic field.
I think it was Minkowski
who first put them together into a tensor.
All right, let's come now...
That's our object.
That's our electric and magnetic tensor.
It's the thing that has to be responsible
one way or another for the force on charged particles.
Now what we want to do is study possible...
Excuse me.
Possible force laws
that would be appropriate in
the special theory of relativity.
So let's begin with the idea of acceleration.
We've already defined four velocity.
Four velocity, u mu,
is equal to dx mu
by, not by dt, but by d tau.
Okay.
It has four components.
What are those four components?
They are the four components of ordinary velocity
times gamma.
Gamma equals one divided by the square root
of one minus v squared.
vx, vy, and vz
times gamma.
And then the last component is just gamma.
Another way to write them is
dx by dt, dt by d tau.
That's where the gamma comes from.
The gamma is just dt by d tau.
Okay, so those are the four components of four velocity.
The momentum is M times u mu.
That's p mu.
And the first three components
of it are the ordinary momentum.
They are the momentum, but notice that they're
made up out of mass times proper velocity.
That's what goes into
the generalization of Newton's equations.
And it goes in, not in the form
dp by dt, but dp by d tau.
Why?
Because we want to make a four vector.
If x is a four
vector and tau is a scalar,
and tau is a scalar, or an invariant,
then dx by d tau is also a four vector,
p is a four vector, and dp
by d tau is a four vector.
That's the left-hand side.
In other words, it's entirely analogous to
what we place in Newton's equations here,
except that it's d by d
tau instead of d by dt.
Okay?
We can write that if we like.
Well, let's leave it this way for the moment.
Let's leave it this way.
We'll write it slightly different in a little while.
If the left-hand side is a four vector,
the right-hand side must also be a four vector.
It's got to have the
electric charge in front of it.
It is going to have the
electric and magnetic fields in it.
Let's see what kind of thing we can invent.
We can invent something with...
No, let's for the moment
just call the right-hand side f,
script f mu.
f mu.
Okay.
Now let me prove a little theorem.
The theorem is that f mu...
Here's the statement.
f mu u mu is equal to zero.
Now this is analogous, but not identical to.
It's analogous to the statement that
the force due to a magnetic field
is perpendicular to the velocity.
That the force due to the magnetic field
It's analogous to that.
It's a four-dimensional version of it.
And we're going to see now how it works.
How do we prove this?
We prove it not by
using any special form for f,
but by using the fact,
which I probably mentioned last time.
If I haven't, I'll review it.
Well, I won't review it. I'll do it.
u mu u mu is equal to one.
Did we do that?
I think we did.
It's...
Let me just briefly remind you.
It just says that the x mu by d tau...
The x mu by d tau is equal to one.
And all it really says is that...
Well, this one...one of these should be lower.
The x mu.
All it really says is
that the sum of the squares
of these differentials is just d tau squared.
Okay.
I think we did that.
I think we may have done it twice already.
u mu...u sub mu times mu
super mu is equal to one.
Now let me differentiate that with respect to tau.
If it's equal to one, that means it doesn't change
along the trajectory of the particle.
It's very much or very analogous to the statement
that the speed doesn't change in a magnetic field.
Not the same thing, because there's four components here.
But it's mathematically analogous.
Let's differentiate it with respect to tau.
All right.
We're going to get two terms.
When I differentiate a product, I get one term
from the derivative of the first factor
times the second factor and so forth.
So there will be, for example,
du mu times u super mu.
And there will also be plus u sub mu.
My mu's and u's look the same, don't they?
I don't want them to.
u sub mu times du super
mu by dt, by d tau.
But these are the same thing.
It doesn't matter if you have...
When you put two vectors together like this
and sum over the indices, it doesn't matter
which one has the upper index
and which one has the lower index.
That's entirely...
No content in that.
So this is really just twice this.
What is this object?
This is twice the proper
acceleration times the proper velocity.
Okay.
This is the proper acceleration here.
And this is the proper velocity.
The proper acceleration...
of course, is proportional,
apart from the factor of mass,
it's equal to dp mu by d tau.
So this is just m times the proper acceleration.
Alright?
So what's on the left here,
apart from the factor of m,
is d mu du by d tau.
And if I multiply it by
u mu on the right-hand side,
it must be equal to zero.
So it follows...
It follows that...
f mu times u sub mu must equal zero.
Oh, we didn't finish this.
I should have said this is equal to zero.
It's equal to zero because
the right-hand side is just one,
and when you differentiate one, you just get zero.
The right-hand side is a constant.
When you differentiate a constant, you get zero.
And what is the expression here?
It's just proportional to the force times the velocity,
what I wrote up here.
So you can see that f
mu times u mu must equal zero.
This is a kinematic fact.
This doesn't depend on anything.
It just depends on the definition of four velocity,
four momentum, sorry, four acceleration,
four-dimensional acceleration, and so forth.
And so it tells us that in a four-dimensional sense,
the force on an object
must be plus or minus zero.
The force on an object must be perpendicular or orthogonal
to the four velocity in this sense,
that that has to be equal to zero.
That means we can't just stick
in any old thing for force.
It's got to satisfy this relationship here.
How do we satisfy it?
Well, it's, as I said, quite similar to the fact
that the magnetic force
is perpendicular to ordinary velocity.
We satisfy that
by a trick.
We made the trick of making
the magnetic field into a tensor,
m n,
and multiplying it by v n.
This is v cross b.
Then when I dotted it into v m,
it was automatically zero.
Exactly the same trick.
We take f mu
to be f mu nu,
the anti-symmetric tensor,
times the four velocity.
Everybody know what I mean
when I put a lower index on the four velocity.
It just means lowering the index
by changing the sign of the space components.
Alright?
So, if I invent
an anti-symmetric tensor to put here,
and I multiply it by u nu,
guess what?
If I now multiply it
by u mu,
the answer will be zero.
Because f is anti-symmetric.
Let's just write it out explicitly.
If I now multiply it by u mu,
if the force is proportional to f mu nu
times u nu,
and I dot it into u mu,
the answer will be zero,
because f is anti-symmetric.
So this is one way,
it's only one way,
of satisfying the criteria
that the force is perpen-
that the force, when multiplied by the velocity,
is equal to zero,
is to build the force out of an anti-symmetric tensor.
In fact, it's the simplest way.
Well, we have an anti-symmetric tensor,
in fact, we even call it f mu nu,
and it's built up out
of the electric and magnetic fields.
So let's see, let's take this apart.
Here is our equation.
Let's get rid of the intermediate step here.
This is q times f mu nu
times u nu.
And let's look at this for slow velocities first.
Let's first look at it for slow velocities.
We can study it for larger velocities later.
But let's check that for low velocities,
this really is the Lorentz force law.
Let's see how it's related to the Lorentz force law.
First of all, q, that just goes for free,
that's just the electric charge.
f mu nu is going to involve two terms,
electric and magnetic,
and u has two kinds of terms,
the time component and the force.
And the space components of u.
So let's work out some examples.
Let's work out dp,
which one did I work out?
Yeah.
Let's work out dpx by d tau.
Now the first thing is,
as long as we're moving slow,
I'm going to come back in a little while
and discuss what happens when we're moving faster.
As long as we're moving slowly,
dp and tau are the same.
For slow motion, dp and d tau are the same.
So in the non-relativistic limit,
we can just take this to be dp by dt.
As I said, we'll do better in a moment.
I just want to make sure that for slow motion,
we have all the right things.
That's equal to q.
Okay, now let's see what we have.
Mu and mu match here and here.
So this has to be fx,
and then mu can be any one of four terms,
any one of four entries there.
There's first of all ffx, xx, ux.
That's not there because fxx is zero.
So this is gone.
Then there's fxy, uy,
plus fx, y,
xz, uz,
plus fx0, or time, u0.
Okay, let's pull them apart.
What is fx0?
fx0 is electric field.
If one of the indices is zero
and the other one is space,
then this is just the electric field.
So this here is,
we first of all have a term which is q
times the electric field.
They're both x components,
so this is the x component of the electric field.
But what are these?
xy and the xz components,
those are magnetic fields.
So let's see what we have.
fxy, that's f12.
What is f12?
f12 is minus b3.
So this will be q
times uy, b3
with a minus sign.
And then from here,
what is fxz?
That's b2.
No, that's, yes, that's b2.
So this will be plus
u,
u3, b2.
You see what we're getting?
We're getting the cross product
of the velocity with the magnetic field.
To the extent that we can say
that u is the same as v,
we've reproduced the force law of Lorentz.
v cross b plus q times e.
You see where they come from.
Let's be a little more careful.
Let's write it more carefully
and not do the nonrelativistic limit.
Let's do it more carefully.
First of all, we have dp mu
by d tau.
That is dp mu by dt
times gamma.
Times dt by d tau.
dt by d tau, let me
just write down what gamma is.
Gamma is
the square root of 1 minus v squared.
Where v is the velocity of the particle.
Ordinary, ordinary velocity.
So this is dp by dt times gamma.
Let's see what's on the right hand side.
On the right hand side, we have things like,
let's take this term here,
q fxy uy.
But uy is the same as vy times gamma.
Likewise,
for all the terms,
uy, uz, and u0,
let's see,
we have q fxy vy.
In other words, this is going to be
v cross b times gamma.
And the last term
is just electric field
times u0,
and u0 is just gamma.
From the u's here.
The u's are v's times gamma.
And the last one here is just gamma.
Alright?
Okay, so the gamma's cancel.
And guess what?
We get exactly what, uh,
what Lorentz had.
Except there's something slightly different.
And that's that p is not m times v,
but it's m times u.
So there is a hidden gamma in here.
The relativity is hidden in the definition of gamma.
We can really write this as d by dt,
not of mv,
but of mv times u0.
So it's m times gamma.
Gamma changes along the trajectory.
And so,
gamma is not a constant.
But,
it is dp by dt.
So it looks exactly like Lorentz,
with the exception that we have to calculate p
in the right way,
as proper, uh,
in terms of proper velocity.
So we've, we've
reproduced...
In the first line,
the bottom board,
isn't that the q times e?
Yeah.
Good.
Absolutely.
Okay, that's the,
that is the Lorentz force law
as derived by,
and the logic was nice,
the logic was nice.
We first proved
that
the acceleration
and the velocity are orthogonal
in the four-dimensional sense.
That told us that the force
is orthogonal to the velocity.
The only,
the only simple way to do that
is to build the force out of an anti-symmetric tensor
so that when we dot it back into the velocity,
we get zero.
And then, we just worked it out.
We just worked it out,
making the identifications
with an older-fashioned kind of notation.
This is just purely notation.
The definition's here.
This is b, this is e.
When it's all put together,
it simply has the simple form
of a, uh, of a four-vector equation.
Because it's an equation between four vectors
on both sides,
it will be the same in every reference frame.
Okay.
Would you call it,
would you call it,
that derivation math or physics?
Uh, look, once,
that's a bit of a buffer for me.
Is there physics in there,
or is it just...
Yeah, there's, look,
there's, there's, there's,
there's heavyweight physics in there.
The heavyweight physics is that the laws of nature
are the same in every reference frame.
Uh,
that went in,
and the other thing that went in,
I mean, if we're doing it, you know,
we wouldn't really derive it from nothing.
There are other force laws,
other kinds of force laws.
Uh,
we certainly had,
or I certainly had in the back of my mind
that we were talking about things with electric
and magnetic fields,
but, um,
on the other hand,
not very much was used.
We used the idea that if
an equation is a four-vector equation,
it's the same in every reference frame.
That was the most important thing.
Uh, other pieces, other things we used?
We used, for example,
the fact that it's a,
that it's a second-order differential equation.
This is dx by d tau,
so this is d second x by d tau squared.
Why isn't it d third x by d tau squared,
or d fourth x?
Physics goes into that.
Uh, there's plenty of physics that goes into that,
that the equations of motion are second-order,
which is equivalent to the statement,
but it's a physical statement,
it's not a mathematical statement,
that in order to predict the future,
you need to know the
position and velocity of every particle.
You don't need to know the acceleration.
The equation gives you the acceleration.
Uh, the equation could have been
that the derivative of the acceleration
is equal to the force,
and then you would also need to know the acceleration
at the, in the beginning.
But, uh, physics tells you that that's not,
uh, experimental physics tells you that's,
that's not, uh, correct.
So it's a bit of both, I mean, uh...
So, if someone thought of this from scratch,
just by analogy,
potentially they'd have gotten
to check it experimentally,
because it's physics.
Well, you can call it what you want,
I mean, it is what it is.
It is what it is.
Let's talk about the transformation properties
of the electromagnetic field tensor.
How it transforms.
Uh, again, as a homework assignment,
I can assign you to work out
the transformation properties
of all of the components,
of the electric and magnetic fields.
In particular, the transformation properties
when you do a Lorentz transformation
along the x-axis.
When you have two observers moving relative
to each other along the x-axis.
I could have taken the y-axis,
but, uh, it would be no different.
Except that x would become y.
Okay.
The way to think about it,
is to first write down the transformation law
for the product of two vectors.
The simplest tensor,
we want to work out the transformation laws
for a tensor.
All tensors transform the same way.
So if we work out the transformation law
for a simple tensor composed of a product
of two vectors,
you'll see, as I'll show,
that that tells us everything we need to know.
So, for example, supposing we want to know,
in the primed reference frame,
the primed reference frame is the one moving,
let's say, to the right, with velocity v.
I'm prime, you're unprimed.
Okay? And I move to the right.
Uh, let me just write down for you,
to remind you,
the transformation laws of the coordinates.
And let's call them x1,
x1, which is what I usually call,
x prime,
is equal to x,
which is x1,
minus vt, which is
minus vx0,
divided by square root of 1 minus v squared,
x0 prime,
this is t prime,
oops,
is equal to v,
no, is equal to 1,
which is equal to x0,
minus vx1,
divided by square root of 1 minus v squared,
and what about x2 and x3?
x2, x2 prime is equal to x2,
is a y and z.
This is the transformation property for all vectors.
All vectors transform the same way.
Alright? So now let's work out
the transformation property of a tensor.
Let's, for example, take two vectors,
let's make a tensor out of two vectors,
a and b.
Alright?
In other words, a mu b nu.
Let's concentrate on the first
component of the electric field,
sorry, the second component of the electric field,
which one do I want?
No.
The first component of the electric field,
in the primed reference frame.
Now, what is ex?
Ex is really f0,1 prime.
I'm trying to find the prime.
I'm trying to find f0,1 prime,
assuming that I know things in the unprimed frame.
Now, f0 prime is like,
I'm going to write not
equal, but is sort of like,
the product of two vectors,
a0, b1.
This would also be a component of a tensor.
In fact, it would be
the 0,1 component of a tensor.
1 does not mean prime here.
Let's calculate a0, b1 prime.
How do we do that?
Well, we know what a0 prime is.
Here's how the 0 component of a vector changes.
We know what the 1 component
of a vector, how it changes.
So all we have to do is substitute.
Let's substitute.
What is a0 prime?
a0 prime is built out of a0 and a1,
the same way that x0 prime is
built out of the components x0 and x1.
Let's see if we can guess what it is.
a0 prime is going to be a0 minus v a1,
sorry, a, I better put
the indices in the right place,
a0 v a1,
divided by square root of 1 minus v squared.
That's a0 prime.
Now what about b1 prime?
b1 prime, we have to see
how the first components of vectors change.
That's going to be b1 minus v b0,
divided by square root of 1 minus v squared.
Does everybody see what I've done?
I've said that e x
is a component of a tensor,
the 0 1 component of a tensor.
Just as an exercise, I'm going
to calculate how a similar tensor,
namely a mu b nu transforms.
I'm going to see what happens to the
0 1 component of it in the primed frame.
To do that, all I have to
do is substitute in the 0 component,
the prime 0 component,
that I get from this equation over here.
The 1 component of the primed b,
That's these two factors.
Is that clear? Anybody not follow it?
Good.
Alright, now let's multiply them
together and see what we get.
First of all, we're going to get
1 divided by 1 minus v squared.
That's the easy thing.
Just multiply these two together.
Now, next we get,
a 0 b 1.
That's a component of the corresponding
tensor in the unprimed reference frame.
We'll use that.
Now we get minus v,
a 1 b 1,
minus v, a 0 b 0.
That comes from the a 0 b 0 term here,
and the a 1 b 1 term here.
And finally,
plus v squared,
a 1 b 0.
Now, the only unusual thing
about f is that it's anti-symmetric.
We could guess, we could guess now what
the transformation property of f 0 1 is.
Let's make the guess.
f 0 1 prime,
is equal,
to f 0 1,
that's from here,
from here,
minus v,
f 1 1,
this is f 1 1,
minus v, f 0 0,
plus v squared,
f 1 0.
That's this.
All divided,
by 1 minus v squared.
Okay.
I've said,
a times b transforms as a tensor.
Here's its transformation properties.
I know it just straightforwardly from
the transformation properties of the two vectors.
And now I identify the components of a b,
with the components of a tensor.
This is how a tensor transforms.
But an anti-symmetric tensor is especially simple.
f 1 1 and f 0 0 aren't there.
So we can erase them.
What about f 0 1 and f 1 0?
They're the minus of each other.
So this becomes f 0
1 times 1 minus v squared.
And the whole thing is just f 0 1.
Oh my goodness,
it looks like f 0 1 prime
is the same as f 0 1.
So this is f 0 1,
and this is f 0 1.
So f 0 1 prime is
the same as f 0 1.
And that's correct.
What does that say?
That says that if two
observers are moving down the axis,
and there's an electric field along the axis,
okay,
we're doing a Lorentz transformation along the one axis,
and we're looking at the component
of the field along the one axis.
It says that the component of the field
along the direction
of motion is unchanged.
It's the same.
And that's a true fact.
That the component of the electric field,
and it's also true of the magnetic field,
maybe we'll do it.
It's also true of the magnetic field.
In fact, the electric and magnetic
field transform very similar to each other.
But now let's do a case which is less trivial,
where there is an interesting
transformation law.
Let's work out the transformation property
of a component of the electric
field perpendicular to the direction of motion.
Well, what's the transformation of a 0?
We had it worked out over here.
The transformation of
prime.
The transformation of a 0
is
unprimed a 0 minus v a 1
again, divided by square root of 1 minus v squared.
That's a 0 prime.
And then b 2
This is, incidentally, this b
here is not the magnetic field.
Don't get confused.
This is just two vectors, any two vectors.
What is the transformation property of
the second component of a vector?
The y component in this case,
when I transform along the x-axis.
Nothing changes.
So this is just b 2.
Let's see what we have.
We have a 0 b 2 divided
by square root of 1 minus v squared.
a 0 b 2
over square root of 1 minus v squared.
Well, that suggests that
we replace this
by f 0 2
divided by square root of 1 minus v squared.
That's the first term.
And then minus v
times a 1 b 2.
That's f 1 2.
f 1 2
divided by square root of 1 minus v squared.
Okay, let's see what this says.
This
was the primed component
e 2 prime.
e 2 prime
is equal
this is e 2
minus v
now what is f 1 2?
f 1 2 is plus or minus b 3.
Which is it?
I think it's b 3 minus b 3.
I forgot.
minus b 3
so it must be plus v b 3
divided by square root of 1 minus v squared.
So we see that
this is
e 2
e 2 prime
does change
and it's equal to e 2 plus v b 3.
times gamma.
If the velocity is slow
then gamma is close to 1.
And it just says
that the electric field
mixes in a little bit
the second component of the electric field
mixes in with a little bit of
the third component of the magnetic field.
This was for a transformation along the x axis.
Along the 1 axis.
You can work out in the same way
the details of all of the transformation properties
of all the components of the magnetic field.
So you can see
all of the transformation properties
of all of the components
of the electric and magnetic field
and find out if you know them in one frame
the stationary frame
what they are in the other frame.
In particular you can check
that if you have
only a magnetic field in one frame
that if you move relative to it
you see an electric and a magnetic field.
And you can work out the directions
that the electric and the magnetic field will point in.
And these transformation properties
for the electric and magnetic field
will always be such
that the equations of motion
in any frame of reference
for the charged particle are the same.
Okay.
Okay, any questions about the charged particle
in the electric and magnetic field?
If you have a current flowing through a wire
and you've got a magnetic field
what sort of velocity do you have to go at
in order to make that magnetic field equal to zero?
Sure.
Why?
To go along with that charge?
If you have current in a wire
and you've got Q's going at some V
through the wire
what velocity do you have to go at
in order to make the V feel...
Sounds like you want to keep up with the electrons.
Yeah, but is it...
Is it low velocity or is it fast velocity?
Well, it's not a relativistic velocity.
I mean, it's not...
It's a medium velocity.
Yeah, but we can work it out.
We can work it out, but...
It seems to be very slow.
Very slow?
No, it's not that slow.
To get rid of the magnetic field?
No.
The velocity of electrons in a wire is slow.
Yeah, the current velocity.
What is it?
It's meters per second.
That's not the right velocity.
I'm not sure why, but...
Electrons wouldn't be a wire.
Well, wait, wait, wait, wait.
You've got to be careful.
Because there's positive charges there.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Yeah, there's positive charges there too.
It doesn't transform that simply.
No, it doesn't transform that simply.
I think we just have to work
out the magnetic field and do it.
That's something I don't know the answer to offhand.
I suspect it's sort of intermediate,
not too slow, not too fast.
It's not very slow.
Can you ever get rid of the magnetic field?
Uh...
That doesn't sound right.
Yeah, I think you can get...
No.
Not if there's only a magnetic field.
Not if there's only a magnetic
field you can't get rid of it.
Right, that's...
You can't.
But if there's an electric
field and a large electric field,
you might be able to
get rid of the magnetic field.
In other words, the transformation
property of the electric field
will produce a little bit of magnetic field
which could cancel the original magnetic field.
If all you have is a magnetic
field to begin with, no, you can't.
Right.
But for example, I mean, all
right, so what I was thinking,
which was inappropriate for the problem,
but if I had a moving collection of charges,
and the moving collection of charges makes a magnetic field,
it also makes an electric field,
you know, just a lump of charge.
It's moving, it makes an electric
field, and it makes a magnetic field.
Then I can answer very quickly,
what velocity do I have to move
with to get rid of the magnetic field?
I just have to move with
the object and there's no magnetic field.
That, uh...
The current in the wire is trickier.
And the electric field cancels out
from the protons and the electrons
and there's no way to get rid of it.
There's no way to get rid of it.
Um...
Okay.
Does the electric potential and the
vector potential form a four vector?
Yeah.
Very similar to this?
Yeah, form a four vector.
Yeah.
Uh...
We will also study Maxwell's equations,
but before we do,
we want to think a little bit about waves,
scalar waves,
scalar wave equations.
The main point being
that we haven't talked about derivatives of fields.
We've talked about the object dx,
which might be a little displacement along a world line.
Now let's come to an entirely,
what apparently is an entirely different subject,
a theory of fields.
Let's forget now particles,
let's concentrate on fields.
Fields are things which vary in space-time.
So they depend in general
on all four components of position.
Let's call phi.
Phi is a field.
Phi for field.
It's a scalar field,
which means it has only one component.
The simplest possible thing we can make.
And now we can differentiate it.
We can differentiate it
to create d phi
by dx mu.
This consists of
four terms,
or four components,
d phi by dx,
d phi by dy,
d phi by dz,
and finally d phi by dt.
Or d phi by dx1,
d phi by dx2,
d phi by dx3,
and d phi by dx0.
They form a four vector.
But,
they form the covariant components of a four vector.
They transform slightly differently
than the components dx mu.
How do they transform?
They transform the same way,
not as dx mu,
but as dx mu with a lower component.
Let me remind you what the lower component means.
The lower component simply means
you change the sign of the time components.
No,
the sign of the space components.
If d super x mu
is a set of four numbers
which form the contravariant components of a vector,
then this object here
is just minus
dx1 dot dot dot dx3,
minus,
also dx2,
and then dx0.
You change the space components
and those things define
the covariant components of a vector.
It's the same geometric object,
just being described differently.
Just being described in a different notation.
It's useful
because we can make scalars
by contracting lower and upper indices.
Contracting means,
you take a lower index and an upper index,
you identify them in sum,
and that makes
scalars.
So it's a useful device.
It takes into account this extra sign
in things like
t squared minus x squared
minus y squared minus z squared.
Okay.
If you were to work out
the transformation properties of the derivatives,
now how do you do that?
You know how the x's themselves transform.
You know what the coordinate transformations are.
x1 prime is equal to whatever it is,
all that Lorentz transformation stuff.
You know how they transform.
You know what combinations of the old coordinates,
the new coordinates are.
And you can work out,
you can work out
the derivatives of the same field phi
with respect to x prime mu.
I'm not going to do that on the blackboard,
it's a little bit tedious.
We can work it out and see what the connection
between the derivatives with respect to the prime variables,
the moving coordinates,
and the coordinates of the unprimed coordinate frame are.
And the answer is that they transform the same way,
not as the dx mu is here,
but the dx mu is with a lower index.
That's fairly easy to prove.
And so this object is a four vector,
but it forms the covariant components of a four vector.
These are the four co-
the, um,
the co-
the covariant components of a four vector.
Is it clear what that means to everybody?
Just that it transforms in that way.
It forms a complex of four things.
Can we make an object with upper components?
Sure, we can make an object with upper components.
We just change the sign of the space components
and leave the sign of the time component alone.
Alright, so we have two sets of objects.
We have d phi by dx,
let's call it one, two, and three,
together with d phi by dx naught.
And that's what we call d phi by dx mu.
Now, we can also consider,
and this is a definition now,
d phi by dx with an upper index.
Instead of the lower index,
it now has an upper index,
and that's just the same thing here,
let's cross this out,
with a minus sign here.
In other words,
the object with the lower index and the upper index
are related in the same way that all four vectors
with upper and lower components are related.
In fact, every time you differentiate an object,
if you have any tensor,
or any vector,
or any scalar,
and you differentiate it,
let's suppose you take a vector field.
Here's some vector field
that depends on x.
Let's suppose it has an upper index, for simplicity,
and you differentiate it
with respect to x nu.
That makes a tensor,
but it makes a tensor with one upper index
and one lower index.
Every time the derivative operator acts,
it simply puts another index on the object.
So if v is a vector and you differentiate it,
you get a tensor.
If v is a tensor and you differentiate it,
you get an object with yet another index,
and so forth.
The differentiation always puts the index downstairs.
So differentiation is another rule
that allows you to form vectors.
Vectors, tensors, and so forth.
Now what I want to
discuss for the remaining time today
is wave equations
and the invariance of wave equations.
The invariance of wave equations follows
if the wave equation has the form
that some scalar is equal to zero.
Scalars are the same in every reference frame.
And so if we can
write the equation for some wave
in the form a scalar is equal to zero,
then we can be sure it's
the same in every reference frame.
In other words,
we can coordinate transform things.
Let's try to do that.
Wave equations by their very nature, incidentally,
always have two derivatives,
not one derivative.
They correspond to second derivatives acting on fields.
Of course, we could imagine
wave equations with six derivatives,
but the simplest wave equations, Maxwell's equations,
other wave equations,
have second derivatives in them.
That means that we're going to have a derivative
and another derivative acting on some field
that's equal to zero.
This is a typical example of a wave equation.
There are other wave equations,
but let's look for one like that.
We want it to be
the same in every reference frame.
So that means we want it to be
the left-hand side to be a scalar.
Left-hand side to be a scalar would be
one way of going to make a wave equation,
a single wave equation.
There's only one way to do it.
There's really only one way to do it,
and that's to say,
we've got to begin by differentiating,
so let's put mu there.
The only way to make a scalar out of this
is to differentiate again
and to put the index here upstairs.
What does it mean that the index here is upstairs?
It means that the space components of the derivative
are treated with a negative sign.
This is the simplest wave equation.
It's invariant because whenever you contract
a lower index with an upper index,
it automatically gives you something
which is invariant under Lorentz transformations.
So this is the simplest example of a wave equation,
and let's write out what it actually means.
Let's write out what it actually means in detail.
Let's take first the time component.
The time component is just d0 phi,
and now the time components don't change sign
when you raise the index.
So this is just the second derivative,
the second derivative with respect to time.
The first derivatives do change sign
when you raise an index,
and so this is minus d second,
sorry, d second phi by dx squared,
same thing for y squared,
same thing for z squared.
This equation,
well this is d by dt squared.
This equation has the virtue
of being the same in every reference frame.
How do you check it?
You write it in a form
in which it's manifestly just a scalar.
One index upstairs, one index downstairs.
That always gives you a scalar.
That's the simplest wave equation.
The reason I'm writing it down now
is because we want to get to Maxwell's equations.
This is an example of a simple wave equation.
Maxwell's wave equations are more complicated,
but we want to get to Maxwell's equations,
and we want to write them in a form
which is equally manifestly Lorentz invariant.
That's our goal.
We're not going to do that tonight.
I think we're going to quit now.
Next time we'll come back and work out Maxwell's equations.
In a covariant notation,
they're equations which mix up electric and magnetic fields
in a somewhat intricate way,
but they have the virtue of being written,
or the way we'll write them has
the virtue of being explicitly Lorentz invariant.
I'm getting tired, so I think we'll quit.
Any questions?
What's that?
Oh, it could be.
No, it could be a constant.
In fact, it could be any number of things.
It could be any scalar on the right-hand side.
This is one particular example of a wave equation.
Another one which is interesting is
to write a constant here times phi.
What's on the right-hand side?
You could have constant times phi squared.
You could have all kinds of things.
The simplest equation is just to have zero.
And we're going to discuss those equations.
We're going to work them out, study their solutions,
understand how they behave,
but this is just the
simplest example of a wave equation.
And next time, we'll study them in some detail.
The preceding program is copyrighted by Stanford University.
Please visit us at stanford.edu.